[Music]
[Applause]
so today what I want to talk about is
the beginning just pick up on the stuff
we didn't discuss last time so I think
the I think mistake I did this this
semester was I trying to cram what was
the three lectures now into two lectures
so normally we would discuss b-trees B
plus trees and lashes separately but now
I'm trying to include them in discussion
of the tries here
so first we'll discuss how to actually
implement latches or what kind of
lectures we could use our data system
then I was talking about how to do
latching in a B+ tree and of course this
would be now contrasting with the BW
tree which is meant to be a tree here's
one you know people ask you you have to
have latches and then we'll focus on the
what you guys read about and today's
assigned reading on the Judy ray are
indexed in the mastery or they're all
variants of tries okay all right so
again recall from the introduction class
when we discussed the different locks
and latches that locks were this logical
concept in a database system meant to
protect entities within the database
itself like we take locks on tables take
lock on tuples take locks on blocks of
tuples we're in the entire database and
then the latches we're gonna be these
low-level primitives you would use to
protect the critical sections of any
kind of current data structure and
anything that needs to have multiple
threads accessing or modifying at the
same time and so this can get confusing
if you're coming from the OS world where
there's no notion of a latch there is
now in C++ but it means something
completely different
in the OS world they referred these
things as locks so for today's lecture
we're mostly only talking about latches
and it's sort of confusing because the
way you would implement a latch is a
spin lock so when every time I say lock
in this lecture I really mean latch but
let me go read out you know read things
that aren't in the database
literature community they'll refer to
things as locks but they really mean
latches when you're in two databases
which is began a confusing sorry
all right so if you want to have a latch
in our system right again we are the
database system developers we are the
people actually building the system so
we need to make a decision about what
kind of latch you want to use I would
say we're not in the business of writing
latches ourselves and I do not encourage
you to do that although you can build
them as simple as one will show in a few
more slides but the general conventional
wisdom is do not write your own latching
library there's a ton of ones already
out there and just pick one of those so
we want to talk about what we're gonna
want to have in our latch that we could
apply to our database system to sort of
get have to be most efficient in terms
of storage capacity of how much space it
takes to occupy the latch in memory and
also the efficiency of sort of the
latching mechanism itself so obviously
we want to we want a small memory
footprint right think about now in your
B+ tree or in your own your radix tree
that will talk about today like every
node is gonna have a latch so if your
latch is like you know a couple hundred
kilobytes that's stupid that's wrong but
even then if it's if it's a couple
couple bytes that can start to add up
because you don't have one for every
single data structure or every single
node so like in the pthread mutex they
are gonna be 64 bytes which is actually
a lot right and the reason why it's so
big is because they have to for
historical reasons they have backwards
compatibility with some older CPU
architecture that required the latches
to be 64 bytes but there's other
implementations that we could use
that'll be much smaller we obviously
want in the best-case scenario when
there's no contention on whatever it is
we're trying to access that we can
acquire the latch very efficiently so
this is right we want a fast execution
path when there's no contention we just
go ahead and choir the latch and it
doesn't take a lot of work a lot of
instructions for us to do that and then
when the if we can't acquire the latch
then we want to be able to be scheduled
our thread with the operating system so
that we're not just spinning their
burning cycles in a spin latch which
I'll show in the next slide right
because this is just burning cycles and
wasting the CPU and the OS is gonna have
trouble scheduling you because they're
gonna think you're actually doing work
and sheep keep trying to schedule to
execute you when actually out
you not if now we have to maintain any
metadata also - about what threads are
waiting for us or what threads are
waiting to acquire latch we don't want
to have to have each of our latch
instances allocate and maintain their
own queue data structure to keep track
of what threads are waiting so if we use
less blocking mutex the OS does that for
us
but if we're using something in
userspace right above the kernel then we
don't want have to have every single
latch you know maintain its own queue
because that's gonna blow up the size of
the thing so this is question is going
to us and saying I can't run anymore
don't and I'm here's the here's the oh s
lock that I'm waiting to get notified on
so that I can run right so yeah sorry
we'll get there his question is does
that means every single latch
implication has to wrap it or lock no
but it's actually your question is
actually very pointy because this is
actually in the been in the news if you
want to call it that on like hacker news
and a limits mailing list because some
guy that was working at Google on their
new gaming console vast attea thing it's
like that it's the streaming gaming
console they had this long blog post
about how the OS kernel locks are a
mistake and you would be really wouldn't
be using spin locks so then of course
Linus didn't like that and he had a long
post where he was saying like about how
this is wrong they were you know why
user lands spin locks are a bad idea
so I'm like I was gonna read the whole
thing the only thing I'll point out
though is he has this one comment here
that I'll highlight where he says do not
use spin box and out world spin latch in
user space unless you actually know what
you're doing and the likelihood that you
know what you're doing is very very low
right so prior to this every semester
when I taught I taught latches I'd
always say oh yeah never used an OS
latch a few texts for pthread mutex
because the going down into the the
kernel was always really expensive right
to tell the OS hey I can't run anymore
that's now going into the
to the OS you have to update the the the
data structure that the scheduler is
maintaining to keep track of what
threads are running what they're waiting
for
and I always thought okay yeah there's
better off to do everything in user
space so he's claiming that you know his
mind the OS is always can do a better
job than what anything else could
possibly because it has least a global
view of everything that's going on and
can make decisions about whether the
scheduler or not right we can't control
that in our database system entirely if
we do green threads and manage our own
threading stuff up above we could do
that but that's usually an overkill for
from those systems all right so again
the point I'm talking about make here is
that prior to this this blog post I
would always say use a test spin latch
and I think the current understanding in
the state of the art is that you don't
want to do this alright so let's talk
about how we connect with the different
end of latches we can implement so the
test and spin lock or the spin latch
it's the most basic one and this is one
you can implement yourself without
necessarily going back and yielding to
the OS then there's a blocking OS mutex
which is what Linus was referring to and
then I think the right thing to choose
actually is this one the adaptive spin
lock which is a combination of these
twos and a little bit smarter than what
the OS blocking one can do and then
we'll look at more sophisticated
implementations the cubase one and the
reader/writer locks but you can build
these on top of these these other ones
here these are like the basic primitives
and then you can do more sophisticated
things on top of this so the most
simplest way to implement a latch is the
test and set spin Locker the test set
spin latch all right and all it is is
that we just have some chunk of memory
look like a single byte or there are 64
bits that we're just gonna test to see
whether it's set to zero and if it is
then in a single compare and swap
instruction we'll set it to one meaning
we've acquired the latch and so you can
get this in C++ they now in the STL
standard they provide you with this
atomic template type and then you can
put whatever like you know primitive you
want boolean integers and things of that
in them so late you basically use it as
like this so I have I define my my latch
and this is just a syntactic sugar to
declare an atomic boolean and then I
this while loop where I try to set the
latch if it's if it's zero and my single
parent swap instruction sets
the one I hold the latch if not then I
fall down to this wild loop make some
decision about what to do and then come
back and try it again from spinning and
burning executing burning cycles trying
to get this thing over and over again so
the tricky part is obviously in the
middle here and this is what Linus is
standing like that the decision of what
to do here is non-trivial and you may
end up doing the wrong thing that could
cause the OS to big bad skeleton
decisions like you could is yield
immediately but then that's you know and
that's now going down to the West and
more syscalls and getting slower in a
database system like in the case of the
like in the the BtoB tree he was asking
like isn't the mapping table caprile
swap operation isn't that the same thing
as a latch sort of yes right because if
I tried to update the the location
mapping table don't get it then that's
all abort the operation and restart over
again or I can retry and go over again
all right so again this is the most
simplest way to do do this we use a in
our system now we actually use a spin
latch that does essentially the same
thing
written by from from Intel called the
thread building blocks so if you ever
see like there's a spin latch in our
system now it's it's essentially doing
best but one of the downsides of this is
that it is not very cash friendly so
what I mean by bad is like say I have
two two threads running on separate
sockets and there's some latch they both
want to acquire here so what's gonna
happen is say this thing is held by
another even another thread then these
guys are just going to spin and keep
trying to call test and set open over
again trying to acquire this for this
guy
the memory is local to him we'll talk
about new marva textures let it later on
but like this thing of this dim is is
it's closer to this socket and it can
access it more quickly than this other
guy here so he can do this efficiently
but this guy over here has to now go
over the interconnect and say you know
over and over again is this thing set is
this thing set and then whenever
somebody else quire's the latch then we
have to do a cache invalidation message
because we know this guy is trying to
read it alright so so the most the most
simplest spin latch is not efficient
from from the cpu standpoint it's not
scalable and the OS is not gonna be
doesn't not go know anything that we're
doing so what what he was then referring
to
about the the OS lock right this is
sometimes called the basic OS mutex and
the basic idea is here is that I declare
in under ela plus a standard mutex and
then it's just like the other code I had
before where but instead of having this
the spin explicit while loop where I'm
spinning trying to choir the lock I just
say hey try to lock this and then in
this case here my thread will get
blocked if I can't get it otherwise then
I fall into the critical section do
whatever I need to do then anybody knows
what what you have to get when you
declare a standard template mutex what's
that you have a before underneath a few
texts like before you - yes but like
there's an alias in front of that -
Peter mutex right and the PAF mutex is
just a few texts there anybody other
than handled a few Tex stands for fast
fast user space mutex so what it is it's
basically a spin lock plus an OS lock
combined together so what will happen is
I have a begin the user space latch the
spin lock and then the OS latch down in
the kernel so if I have two threads come
along and they both want to access this
by they people won't acquire this lock
right say this whole thing represents a
single single lock this first guy gets
it the second guy doesn't so then he
goes down now and waits on the on the
the kernel lock of the kernel latch and
now he gets D schedule the schedule
knows that he's waiting for this thing
to get released and once that happens it
can then he can then start running again
so this right so this part is cheap
because this is just a test and set and
then and again under a when there's no
contention this is super fast because
this is just hanging out in userspace
memory I can test to see whether I
require it without having to get this
call if I can't get it now I got to go
down and block on this thing that's
expensive cuz that's a cisco get and in
some measurements we take roughly around
95 nanoseconds which which is a lot
right think of that like in the test set
case it's a single instruction which
could be depending whether it's in cash
or not it could be one cycle tool
to acquire that patch in this case here
because we're going down the kernel the
kernel has its own protective primitives
then that gets expensive so what a
better approaches sort of combines the
two of these and still it looks like a
few texts because there is still that
fast user user part is called an
adaptive spin lock and the idea here is
that unlike in a spin lock where we spin
and user space over never again trying
to acquire and unlike in the fast user
mutex where we we immediate try to get
the the latch we can't get it then we
fall down to the OS kernel which you can
actually do is allow a thread to kind of
spin on the user space lock for a little
bit and then at some point you give up
and then you fall back into the the OS
kernel alright and try to lock on that
thing and we're going to call this is
now a user space is this parking lot
where you can have in user space keep
track of like all the threads that are
waiting for this you're sort of
replicating what the OS is doing but
because it's up in user space and not
assist call you can potentially be it's
much more faster in some ways and then
what will happen is if a new thread
comes along tries to acquire a latch we
see that the user space latches already
is held and we see people in our parking
lot getting or that they're that are
blocked then we meet Lee's go park
ourselves and say we're waiting on this
as well and we don't have to go down and
block on the OS kernel right well in the
parking lot there is that there is a lot
that will get us down to do scheduled so
Apple has this thing called the WTF
parking lot lock or the deputy of lock
it stands for like the WebKit template
framework or something but this is seems
to be the if you're not gonna use a you
know a blind spin lock in you're not to
use oh it's blocking mutex this might be
the better way this supposedly is better
to use although Linus disagrees so this
exactly what the hyper guys are using
our for Umbra in Germany and somebody
else is using this but the name excuse
me now there's another data system as
looked into using this as well and they
claim it it's much better than the OS
blocking mutex yes
I think I think it's supposed to adapt
itself that's the idea okay so alright
actually going back to quickly the other
thing to point out too is like in the OS
blocking you text when you allocate the
lock it has like when you allocate the
mutex it allocates the the user space
one and the LS lock in this case here
you don't actually allocate the OS lock
until you actually need to block on it
till you get put into the parking lot
and in Apple's Warford WebKit this they
wanted this because I think they're
requiring a latch for every single
JavaScript object that gets instantiated
right in the Java Runtime or start a
JavaScript runtime and so in there well
they have a lot of latches in a database
system yeah we have a lot of nodes and
RB plus G potentially but not at the
level of like that maybe they're facing
alright so now let's talk about some
some better implementations that we can
build on top of our basic latch
primitives so the exam I show with the
spin box where there's this cache
coherency issue where if two sockets are
trying to access the same latch we have
traffic going over to interconnect all
right where the one guy's trying to
everyone trying to spin on this one
location and we have to send
invalidation messages to every single
thread you can do a cube a spin lock
where instead of having every thread
blocking on the same memory location you
sort of daisy chain them together so
that one thread blocks on one location
and the next thread blocks on the next
location and then when you start
releasing them right sort of propagates
through the queue and so when you really
start at least one of them it's only one
sort of cache invalidation message
because only one thread is actually
blocked on one location at a time so let
me show what I mean by this all right so
so this is sometimes called MCS so the
Linux kernel actually uses this for
other aspects of internally other other
system Melora crumby and scott's the
name of the guy that meant to this so if
you google best googoo whom MCS spin
lock you'll find information about it so
we had his base latch again this could
be a they always blocking mutex the
parking lot one it doesn't matter and
then we have now our CPU comes along
alright and then when they want to
acquire this latch assuming this thing
is already being held by somebody else
we're gonna go ahead now and update our
pointer to keep track of that this is
the next one we wanted this is the next
one to release right okay sorry bad
mistake let me sort of this guy wants to
quiet this latch it's not being held
right so he's gonna stand she ate this
new latch place holder in this cue goes
ahead now and acquires the lash by
setting the pointer to now this new
location here right and once that's done
I'm gonna compare and swap we hold we
hold this latch now when another threat
comes along they're gonna try to acquire
this latch see this pointer is set and
realized they can't send they can't
acquire it so instead of spinning on
this and trying to do test and set to
see whether I can acquire it right they
are going to then follow the pointer
here see that this thing is now unset
update its pointer which is prepare and
swaps it now it's it's sort of claiming
this place position in the queue and
then it spins on this right same thing
and so forth like that all right so then
now what will happen is if this guy ends
up releasing the latch right it would
then get notified that this thing got
released and then this guy could get get
you know take the latch next all right
so this is nice because again like this
could be in one see me
this could be one region of memory on
one socket this could be in another
region and they're just potentially
spinning locally not going over to some
remote memory location yes if I released
this I and four shows up where do they
follow yes I think the lines are kind of
bad this thing is actually spinning on
this because it's waiting for this thing
to get released right there for this
pointer to get set back to zero so this
is everyone always has to start here in
traversal aw yeah the tricky thing now
too is also like say in in my example
here everyone just waiting to acquire
the latched you always want to want to
do it but if I have like I bought my
operation if I try to spin too many
times and like and like this guy goes
away now I need to sort of reconnect
them because I have this hole and that
that starts to get tricky right if you
always know that I'm gonna block forever
and in some parts of the David ISM you
will
block forever - TV makes you do
something then this is fine but if you
need to pull things out at different
positions then it gets harder
yes like is it like what is that what am
I actually doing here right and I'm
waiting what I'm actually doing it could
spin or - could like could be swapped
out do you do signals for this you could
it depends on position I actually I
don't know right you could just like
increase the amount of time you're to
let you're waiting because it takes
longer you could do a signal yeah I
think it ends on April edition I don't
know what you'll do I don't know what
the colonel does alright so then the
last one that's off to probably the
super important for databases as well
reader/writer latches and the basic idea
here is like just like we want to have
under two phase locking we have multiple
readers one a tuple and a single writer
we want the the same thing in in our
slashes right so basically you need to
maintain now two latches and then a cue
of what threads are waiting for the to
acquire the latch and is then we can
make decisions now about who should
actually acquire the latch if we have
cues in both side so say that thread
shows up he wants to read latch the
number of writer threads is zero the
number of reader frets is zero so this
means we're able to acquire the latch
and we just do a compare and swap to
increment this counter by one next guy
shows up same thing wants quite a read
latch we already have a thread that they
will that holds the read latch so this
can be shared so we allow him to go
ahead and and and acquired as well he's
update the counter now our writing
thread shows up tries to acquire the
right latch can't do that because the
read latch is currently being held by
two threads so we go ahead and just
queue ourself up as waiting another
thing that comes along was to do a read
we could just let it acquire the read
latch right away and let it run but of
course this might starve the writer so
we'll block
sky update its counter to be to be one
once these guys go away then this guy
can acquire the law the latch right I
just useful for all different parts of
the data system yes so today's question
is with the spin latch does it make
sense to put a sleep in there like a
nano sleep or something that makes it so
I'm not burning cycles and that could
let potential that they always do other
things yes but there's this trade-off
right like if I if I put some amount of
sleep in there is it the fact you get to
the line at this point it's hard to get
this right if I put a sleep in there
then yes I could I'm releasing the CPU
to do other things but now that means
that when it's when they latch is
actually available to me I could
potentially be waiting longer before I
can go ahead and pick it up and run but
now if I go the other direction I'd make
my sleep time super small now I'm
burning cycles and the CPU looks busy
but it's not doing anything useful so I
think again for project one the CPU when
you run out on a lot for that take a
benchmark we gave you guys the cores are
spiked at 100% why because they're all
spinning or trying to choir that latch
because the Intel one Idol thing yields
the Intel latch we're using doesn't
yield okay alright so now I want to
briefly talk about how to do latch
traveling and coupling in a B+ tree so
in the intro class we describe what it
B+ tree is same thing and in memory
database right we have key values arrays
in our nodes and only the leaf nodes
contain the actual pointers to tuples
and then everything else above that are
just guide posts right so why do you
want to use a B+ tree it's the same
reason why we want you to be double tree
or any other order preserving data
structure because now we do lookups in
in log n alright so the we discussed
latch crabbing coupling last semester
but I want to go over in more detail now
that we understand power actually could
potentially implement latching or our
latches and then we'll talk about a
variant of latching from the hyper guys
for art that is not necessarily specific
to a B+ tree they actually do use the
same technique in art but I'm going to
show it in the context of a
of a the people s tree so the idea here
is that because everyone allow
concurrent access to our data structure
we have to protect it and there's
obvious thing to do is protect it with a
single latch for the entire tree of
course that would be stupid because now
becomes single threaded so we're gonna
do is an as now as threads start
traversing into the tree we want to
acquire latches as we go down and we
only want to release them the latches
that are above us when we know that the
node we're at is safe and we're defining
safety meaning based on the operation
we're doing we know that won't be any
split or merge below us or at the node
that we're at that would cause us to
have to make changes up above us in the
tree so once we know that we're at
everywhere to say I know that is safe we
release any latches that we've required
on the way down and then now although
threats can come behind us and start
doing lookups or modifications as well
because they may be going down a
different path in the tree right so
first for the most basic protocol for
search because we're not modifying the
database we just take latches one by one
going down and then once we reach a node
we can release the latch on our pin on
our parent node because we don't need to
go back for insert and delete again once
we know that a latch were add is
considered safe we can release all the
right latches we've acquired on the way
down so for the search again basic basic
operation is I want to do look up on key
23 down here so at this first node
acquire to read latch then I traverse
down to this certain this node here and
at this point here because I'm doing and
just just look up I'm never gonna go
back to the root node a so it's safe for
me to go release that latch and this is
why it's called sort of crabbing because
it's just be helical like a crab walks
like with one one leg forward then the
next one and back and forth so then we
get down now to here same thing we can
release the latch on see because we
don't remember to go back to it and then
we go down here to FM do our read on
read on 23 now I didn't do a delete
start with start with a we take a write
latch on a come down here take a write
latch on C and now at this point here
because we're gonna do a delete we don't
know what's below us in the tree so if
we do a delete down here that causes us
to have to do a merge we may end up
losing our key here
and now this note would be empty but
because it's a P plus tree has to be at
least half full so there may be a change
below us that causes this thing to get
merged and which means what the update
pointers up here so therefore it's not
safe for us to release the the latch on
on on a at this point so then we come
down to W our started to G we're
deleting 44 at this point here we know
we're not going to have to do a merge
because if we delete 44 then our note is
still half full so everything above us
is safe and we go ahead and release
those latches and then now at this point
we can go ahead and delete our key see
the idea is we will release our lashes
as soon as possible when we know that we
don't need to go we will never make any
changes up above us right so we want to
do release the latches before we
actually do our delete all right because
I'm releasing latches sooner rather
later allows other threads to make
forward progress all right so insert 40
right take the right latch on a take the
right flap Chauncey now this case here
we know that if we have to do a split
below us see has an extra space for
another key so we don't have to we don't
have to split this guy so it's safe for
us to release the latch or name then we
come down here to no G in this case here
where we wanted to start a key we don't
have any more space we're gonna have to
split it so therefore we have to
maintain the right latch on won't see
above it so that we can then update it
with our new or their new pointer here
all right and then when one's that
that's done you then release the latch
on C and then release the latch on G all
right we always recently release latches
from from the top to the bottom okay all
right so that's the basic latching
protocol there's obviously it's it's
inefficient because in all my examples
when I did an insert or delete the very
first thing I did was take a right latch
on the root and then go to the next
child so that means that F every every
thread is trying to update the data is
updated index actually any threat also
trying to read the index will get
blocked anytime I have a writer because
they're always taking the right latch on
the root so a better approach is to be
optimistic and assume that when I get to
my leaf node
it's not gonna through to a split or
merge and therefore I can take real a
ch's all the way down and then right
before I get to my leaf node or at the
leaf node I take a right latch check to
see whether I my assumption was
incorrect if if it was not like if I if
my something that I'm not gonna do a
splitter merge was correct then I take
the right latch to do my change and I'm
done if I am incorrect then I can come
back again and now take the more
heavyweight right latches all the way
down all right so let's look at our two
examples late 44 and then the insert so
I'm gonna delete 44 again under
optimistic approach I take take a read
latch take a read latch again at this
point here I don't go back to the root
so it's okay to release the latch on a
now I get here and then I can release of
latch on see it's my assumption that I
was not gonna have to do a merge when I
do my delete was correct so I can go
ahead now and just do this leap so
instead of hagun right latches all the
way down I took a read latch right and
then you do the same thing for the for
the insert so is this clear so there's
even better approach where we can avoid
having a block the the readers on the
writers or sorry block the writers on
the readers by doing by not having a
right latch at all
sorry latch at all and the idea here is
that on allow threads to read anything
they want as they go down but then after
they after they complete their visit at
a node you check to see whether it's
modified since when you started reading
it if no then you know no writer came in
and modified it and you just proceed
down the tree if you do see a
modification then you realize someone
else got in before you parole you
finished and then you just restart so
there's no more there's no more read
latches anymore there's a write latch
present to prevent to write latches from
modifying the same note at the same time
but anybody that's reading the whole to
read that that won't block any right any
of those right latches right
and so the because now we have that we
have the issue of like what we could be
doing splits and merges and now then
since there's no real
we don't know whether somebody is
reading something when we start deleting
things we do that scene same epoch
garbage collection we did last time in
the BW tree so that we know that there
could be a thread hanging out in our
index when we don't know where they're
at
within our epoch so it's not safe to go
ahead and clean up the nodes just yet
and then once everyone leaves the epoch
we can go ahead and clean it up so let's
look at an example here so right every
now nodes gonna have this virgin counter
just 16 bits or 32 bits in the header
that says this is this is the version of
this node and anytime you modify it will
just increase that back counter by one
right so say we want to do a search on
44 right so we start at node a the very
first thing to do we're gonna mean what
the version number is for this node
right so we can keep track that we read
node a at version three then we examine
the node do whatever we need to do in
this case here we're searching over 44
so 44 is greater than 20 so we're gonna
know we're gonna go down this side of
the tree here so we go ahead and do that
now we're at node beep and what we need
to do is get read our version here but
then go back and read the version that
we know of the node we just came from I
maintain a stack of pointers of the
nodes as we Traverse down so we just go
back and look where do we come from and
then we check to see whether this
version has changed since since when we
started initially when we read it if not
then we know that nobody modified it if
it was changed then we have to border
operation because somebody did something
here that we missed that we should have
seen and want to go back and start over
again right because somebody could have
modified this index of this node here
and the correct pointer to the right
side of this key is now some other
memory location here and we followed the
old down the old path and there may be
garbage below us so what does a abort
ourselves and restart yes
question why don't go all the way the
leaf and indeed what sorry his question
is why don't go all the way the leaf
don't essentially don't do this recheck
here to go all the way the bottom the
pointers will be ballad I think he is
that true yes the pointers are valid cuz
there you can't clean anything up before
you switch the epoch so I get to the
bottom and now I say alright well what
did I read all all the virgins or any
diversions change if know that I'm fine
if yes then restart so in that case I
mean it's sort of like an OCC like we
talked about cicada if you're if there's
gonna be a conflict and your apt about
bored maybe you want to abort sooner
rather than later so that you're not
doing much a work that is end up wasted
right but in doing this recheck is cheap
it's just reading that memory location
to see whether it's change it's not like
I'm it's in memory not like I'm fetching
a page and bringing it back in yeah
someone modifies C or a yes on say so I
think you're saying if someone notes
let's go get example and we'll come back
to the right right I think you're I
don't you you don't have to modify if
you modify this guy you don't the
modified this guy unless you did a split
merge that caused this thing to get
changed alright so now I do my exam in
my node find Phi McHugh I'm looking for
say they now I get down here on C read
benign check v5 still valid if if that's
that if yes then I'm fine then do
whatever need to do and I'm done so
let's rewind and go have the thread come
back be we just finish checking our
reading node see we Traverse down sorry
reversed down to G I bet should be this
should be a at a
at CES gee sorry so say now another
thread writer that comes along and he
modifies this this note here so he
choirs the right latch on it which
implicitly acquires the right latch on
this and then when they complete their
modification right they modified the
increment the version counter by one so
now when this guy's down here and he
rechecks
hey is note C still set to v5 if no then
he knows that somebody else had come to
modified this and therefore he shouldn't
have gone down here and he just
restarted so in this case here like what
did i do i did a delete I didn't say
right I did some modification here but
it didn't have to get propagated up into
the questions say this guy modifies it
but then by here when I'm down here
I went checked and still b5 and I'm done
and then I'm back here and then like
like connects complete yes correct yes
yes okay so one thing about this that
this potential problematic is if you
have really big nodes like if you if you
have a lot of keys in a single node then
these versions are very coarse-grained
right they're saying for the entire node
like say I modified something that was
this side of the tree and and this
pointer is still valid and everything
over here is still fine then I'm not
gonna be able to catch that I'm saying
oh the whole node change the meas go
ahead restart all right and then so
again the sort of this trade-off you
could have more fine-grained versioning
per per key for element in the node but
the way they did in the hyper that has
had for a single the node itself yes
especially restart from C so again it's
like the B to B tree I think you always
restart from the root yes
inserting by 40-mile and reading it one
day we won't read like somebody's
inserting like moving 44
sir someone's inserting what sorry all
right so what what is being torn there
sorry like like the I insert 40 here
right because like because the reader
can come down and they don't get blocked
on on this on the right latch could be
the case like in the memory
representation of the of the node could
be the case that I you know I update the
the the the key list but not the the
pointless actually I think the readers
blocked the readers do get blocked on
the right latch I take that back they
have to be in otherwise have this
problem yeah but I like the writers
don't block on the readers that's the
difference yeah the coarse grain issue
yeah like you get a cache invalidation
your entire note it gets shot out or
brought back in your entire notes
actually
yes yes the statement is I said if you
make the note too long then you have
these course rating blocks but if you
make it be a cache line size which is 64
bytes then you can't atomically update
it but like at least it's being moved in
and out of memory atomically that
depends on like the memory model it OS
and also the CPU and what it guarantees
in terms of writes like the organ writes
that'll make it more efficient but I
still think you need the latches to
protect things yeah yes well we're 45
minutes let's let's take this offline
cuz yeah I just realized we're 45
minutes in we haven't got to the tries
yet you have a quick question order okay
yeah sorry yeah databases okay all right
so let's get to what would you guys
actually read about so we'll cover bi if
you want I discussed P plus trees when
I'm a bit more when we just talked about
project two when we release that all
right so the in the B plus tree and like
a B every tree I call them whole key
indexes the idea again you have this
entire key being represented at all the
various nodes in the in the tree you can
do prefix or suffix compression but we
can ignore that for now but in the case
that B plus tree because the inner nodes
only contain guideposts if I want to
know whether a key exists in my in my in
my table I always have to go to the
bottom the leaf nodes and then see
whether that key exists if I see that
key in an inner inner node it may
actually not be in the in the table
because if I delete a key I don't
necessarily remove it from all the
Internet's as only through the split and
merge process where it could get pruned
out right so now if now it sort of his
comment if I have if I make my node be
the size of a single cache line then in
the worst case scenario in order for me
to figure out does the key exist in my
table I have to pay one cache cache miss
for every single level of the tree right
just to see whether something exists so
this is sort of the motivation of the
choice right the idea is that instead of
storing the the whole
at every single node we could store a
digit of the key at a node and that way
if we determine we can determine
potentially more quickly whether the
thing we're looking for is is not there
or not so tries are really old I think
they're from like the 1950s like some
French dude amend it and then he didn't
have a name for it and then there's this
other guy Edward Franken who supposedly
is at CMU he came up the name of of
tribes right shore for retrieval tree
but again the basic idea is that for all
our keys we're gonna break them up into
digits and then store them down you know
one digit at a time so in the case of
this this data set here I have hello hat
and have so at the first level
I'll have H because that's being shared
by all the keys and then I have I can
have a path down just for just for hello
and then just like in a B+ tree down
below at the bottom will be the pointer
to the actual tuple that you know that's
represented by this key right so
sometimes you'll see these referred to
as digital search trees or prefix trees
they're also radix trees and Patricia
trees those are compressed versions of a
try the sort of original try data
structure has the full P represented
like this
so tries are actually really interesting
because the unlike a B+ tree words login
for for the the the search time on
average in a try it's ok where K is the
length of the tree or a lot of sorry
length length of the key like if I have
a key of ABC then to do if I'm not doing
any compression to look to see whether
ABC exists and I try assuming I'm
storing one character at per level then
it's just three right we're in a B+ tree
I could be mixing with a bunch of other
stuff and it could be it could be longer
the all that you think about them is
that the data structure is deterministic
meaning if we have the same set of keys
and we can shuffle them in any order and
insert them in any order we will always
end up with the same try data structure
I just could the nature of how we're
doing the the doing the combining
overlapping digits right in a B+ tree
it's totally not the case
if I shuffle the the the keys in random
order
I could end up a completely different
data structure from one time to the next
right
so the keys will never be actually
stored in their entirety and so we have
to recreate them by by taking the path
down we get to the bottom and we keep
track of every digit we see along the
way so then then we can put the key back
into its original form so the language
we're gonna use to describe the
properties of a try the key the key
concept is called the span and this is
just the number of possible paths we can
have coming out of a given node right
essentially it's the number digits that
could exist and so what will happen is
if a digit exists in one of the keys
that we're trying to represent at our
node then we'll have a pointer now to
the next node in our try going down
otherwise you store null you need a way
to represent that so the spans
representing the fan-out which also
represents the physical height of the
tree so anyway try would say we have a
fan-out of n so let's look at actually a
real example I actually wouldn't how you
actually could represent a real try in
memory so let's say that we'd have the
most simplest try as a 1-bit try all
right so that means at every single node
we're going to represent a one bit digit
it's either 0 or 1 so say we wanted to
store the keys 1025 and 31 so we would
represent them and binding a binary form
like this so in actuality they'd
probably be 32-bit Kesey or 64-bit keys
we'll keep it simple and we'll say it's
16-bit so we have 2 2 bytes representing
each each key so our track it looks like
this so at the first level here right
it's representing the what the value is
for the first digit position right so in
this case here there are all 0 right
so in our node we have for the the digit
0 we have a pointer down to the next
next level and then for the digit 1 we
have a null pointer all right so now if
anybody looks up and say well is there a
is there a key where the first digit is
1 we would look at this first node see
that this thing is null I'd know that
the key could not exist
now for the next one here I it's the
same one as the one above it zero has a
pointer one is null and I'm just gonna
repeat its a repeat ten times because
the next ten digits are all the same
thing otherwise we've run out of space
now we get to this position here now we
see there is actually a difference
between the keys right this first one
here the digit is 0 the second to the
digit is 1 so I have now a pointer over
here for the 0 path and a pointer over
here for the 1 path and then going down
for this key here right there's nothing
the Reg actually no I mean there's only
only one key of my corpus has a 0 at
this position so this one here only has
one pointer down to one one level to the
next over here for the other two keys
they are the same here but then then
they split 0 1 like that and then we
traverse down for both of them right so
what's like what's one easy optimization
we could do to compress the size of a
node okay let's boil all right yeah
what's one easy cop what's the one easy
optimization we can do to compress the
size of a single node here what's that
don't start every pointer for the ones
that don't have anything we don't do we
don't do that anyway right that's that's
null we're not storing any but that's
not gonna compress the size of a node
that's how decrease the size a single
node exactly yes
yeah so he says take out the zero one so
I don't need to store 0 and then the
pointer and then one and then the
pointer I implicitly know that well if I
want to know whether there's a is there
a pointer for the position zero digits
zero in my array a pointer so to say all
right here's here's you know here's a
pointer and if it's null then I know
that the value of the digit 1 doesn't
exist right so this is horizontal
compression this is compressing the size
of a node what you're referring to is
vertical compression where if I now have
in this case here and over here once I
get down to this path there's no there's
no alternatives it's always go
from one level of the next there's no
branching out so instead of storing
every every single level and there's you
know these pointers essentially always
take you to the bottom I can then just
compress it down to only store too short
nothing right in this case here this
path here has nothing else going down so
I just replace that now a pointer to the
actual tuple and then for this one here
the same thing at this level here I just
have the tuple pointers going out to the
to the actual tuples themselves yes
squishes how do you differentiate
between a point or another node and
pouring two extra tuple sort a bit yeah
yes yes oh yeah that would be yes that
would be can you do that you would need
need a way to record that this thing was
repeated ten times
yeah yeah yes yes yes right so that
there's another way to do vertical
pressure yes so the one thing point
thing to point out here though is that
if I do this kind of compression in a B+
tree again I have the whole key in in
the leaf node so if I want to see
whether that key exists I'm you know I'm
guaranteed to get an answer from the
from that the B+ tree because it's
either there or not there in this case
here I could have a key that had 0 0 0
and then had a 1 here I'm gonna look up
to see whether I have a key like that
but I don't know this because I hated it
here so I know I have to follow this
pointer and go actually look at the
tuple like I did in the tea tree to see
whether this thing that actually is
matching me or not so although I can
compress the size like this reduce the
height I may still have to go look in
the in the look at the tuple a actually
get the original key this also prevents
you from doing like covering indexes are
covering the queries where you want to
be able to answer a query entirely based
on the index right and a B+ tree you can
do that like if you if my index is on a
and I do a lookup it looks you know
select a from from the table where a
equals
I can just only have to access the index
to answer that query in this case here I
still have to follow the pointer to get
to the original tuple okay so this is
sort of crash course or tries because we
covered this in the intro class but now
I want to talk about more sophisticated
variants implementations of the tries
that people are actually using
so Judy arrays were came out first and
they were developed by HP the art index
was was in the paper and you guys read
right from the hyper guys and the
mastery is a variant of a try where it's
it's a try of trees and every node will
be a B+ tree and so by understanding why
what they do here they'll see what why
they have to do it the way they did in
mastery
okay so the the Judy array and your
index will be both 62-56 wait rise so
that means the span or the number of
digits they're storing per node will be
256 but the goal is now store them in a
compressed way so we don't have to
allocate all that memory to store the
tour 206-999-9251 ailing let's post
where the authors of the Judy race
like and 8hp doesn't care about this go
ahead and use it any way you want right
but as far as you know although like it
you know it does solve a lot of problems
and can do you know very succinct
representation of large key sets the
best my knowledge nobody actually uses
them right because whether or not
because of the patent I don't know okay
so the important thing that's going to
happen in the Judy right that's can be
different than the b-plus dream and the
BJP treaty is that they're not gonna
store any metadata about the node in the
node itself I think again think of like
MVCC and the header of the tuple we
would store like the time stamps in the
B+ tree you restore information about
what keys are havelet's what offsets I
have we're not gonna do any of that
we're only gonna store information about
a node in the pointer to that node and
so in a red X tree you're not gonna have
any sibling pointers that you have in a
B+ tree but you can't scan along the
leaf nodes you always have potentially
backtrack so that means that for any
given node because we know there's only
one pointer to it so we don't have to
worry about keeping that synchronized a
bunch of pointer synchronized if we
modify the layout of that node so the
what's gonna happen is they'll have to
store a pointer a memory pointer that
there's as we normally would to get to
the location of of the node but they're
actually stored double the size of a
pointer to actually pack in all this
additional metadata like the node type
the number of keys the population at the
at the node what the prefix value could
be if there's only one child below and
then the secret try pointer so if my I
have a 64-bit child pointer
I need another 64 bits to store all this
extra metadata in the original duty
array implementation they're back you
know on x86 32-bit so they had 32-bit
child pointers and then 32-bit metadata
but now in in in modern systems it has
to be 64-bit corner so it takes a
hundred twenty 8-bit pointers so they're
going to call these Judy arrays or
Judique sorry Judy pointers in the paper
you guys read that evaluated them
against the radix tree I think they call
them fat pointers it's the same idea
so the they're gonna have three node
types again so it's a 256 way try
so that means that you can store up to
260 jets per node the idea is that not
every node is gonna have exactly two
hundred six digits
so rather than storing you know two
hundred six pointers they're gonna have
a more compressed form to represent
these things so we're going to talk
about the the linear node and the bitmap
node the uncompressed node will be the
same thing that will what they do in
sorry I take back what's talked about
talk about the Lina node and the the
bitmap node the uncompressed node will
be similar to what hyper does but hyper
also have the linear node it's the
bitmap node that they're they're gonna
be different the idea here is like say
if you have like a you know if you're
storing like strings and you're storing
URLs a lot of URLs are gonna start with
dub dub dub dot and then whatever the
domain name is so I could in that upper
node those digits are always be the same
so I could pack them into like a linear
node so I can represent a large you know
a large number keys below me in a small
amount of space at that at that new
level alright again the idea is like
going from the top to the bottom this is
when you have a small number of digits a
little bit larger number of digits and
this is when you have at most or more
than you can sort this but you know out
most 206 because it's a 256 away try
alright so let's look at the linear
linear nodes again the reason why it's
called linear node because you're just
going to linear scan to find the key and
find the digit you're looking for so you
just have two arrays so the first array
are the sort of digits and then the
second array are the child pointers and
so whatever offset you are when you scan
along to find the digit you're looking
for you keep track of how far you went
and then you can jump to an offset in
the in the child pointers alright so in
the original implementation of the the
judy array
this thing was sized to be a single
cache line now in in in the 64-bit
architectures this is going to be to to
cache lines so the total size is Nell's
to be is that these things are going to
be each one byte right because it's a
but you store a source six of these and
then so each and then that'll be total
six bytes and then these are gonna be
128 pointers so 16 bits because again
the Judy pointers are
the size of regular pointer so I have
six of these so these would be 96 bytes
so in total a single node would be 102
bytes but now we need to be word aligned
to our cap cache lines and so we'll Pat
it out and make this 128 bytes so again
now 2 cache lines is all it takes to
fetch this one thing all right so the
next node type is the bitmap nodes and
this one's a little bit more tricky so
the idea here is that we're going to
break up our digits into that we're
representing in this node into 8-bit
chunks and so think of this is like
these parts here are all the offsets
within our all the offsets that
represent the you know the particular
digit value for this node right so going
down here at offset zero that's when you
have nothing but zeros then an offset
one is when you have a 1 at this
location 2 is when you have a one at
listed location and so forth right and I
just do this all the way up to 256 so
now what will happen is when I want to
do a look up here I have these sub array
pointers are actually different pointers
down down to an array that tells me that
that is my child pointers so now when I
want to do a lookup right in this case
here say I want to look up for look up
for the digit 1 so that seven zeros
followed by a single one so I know that
would be in the first position here so I
would see a 1 meaning I know that there
there is a child below me and I need to
follow the pointer to that so I then
follow this chunks sub you know sub
array pointer down to here and then now
I count the number of ones that preceded
me in my position in my chunk map here
and that would tell me at what offset I
want to be in the surrett so in this
case here for this one the position that
at one there's there's no other one to
the left of it so I know when I come
down here I met position 0 and this one
here right he is there to the left of
him there's one one so when I follow my
pointer down I want to jump over by 1 is
that clear yes
now so the question is interview 8 to 15
range do I need to come no but come
before you know because the pointer here
is only for this chunk so if I'm looking
in here I follow this pointer down which
is now offset it by the the number
elements yes the question is I can its
insert into in this one here so
questions it yeah could I inserted here
and not mess with these pointers no
because there because now I gotta resize
this array contiguous in memory yeah so
the Chuck like yeah think of this is
like a beat there to B teamers regions
of memory within the node right so this
is saying you take 8 bits that
represents the position offset 0 to 7
and then after that you have now a sub
array pointer in the subarray pointer I
think is like you're just jumping to an
offset in the same node so it plugins B
16 bits right and then after that now
you have the next 8 bits for the next
the next offset region and then it has a
sub array pointer so the tank which you
were getting as by now insert into like
this position here that screws up the
offset everybody else and I gotta resize
this so inserting it's expensive in my
example here I use 3 but like I could
insert all ones and then the the first 8
child pointers would represent the key
there the keys here the digits here
right but the idea is that like it's not
always me all ones right if you have a
sparse population of the digits on this
node right
the pointers at all if you are going to
you can just own the ones and I can
watch what yeah a certain question
question is statement is if I'm just
gonna count the bunch of ones that came
before me then why even bother with
these right cuz it could night cuz these
things are always the same size can I
just count the ones come before me and
jump to where I need to go I we're not
gonna be too much but like because this
this is like a fixed size I can do like
Cindy instructions on it very
efficiently and count the number ones to
come before me right don't think of
living this as a for loop counting along
I can implement like a single seeing the
instruction alright well where's my ones
how many ones are to the left of me and
then offset could be that offset very
quickly you could still do that yeah
yeah yeah yeah I don't know the answer
yeah yeah okay yes if you hash if you
hash or digit and then you jump like
then you're basically treating this like
like a like a hash table yeah I think
the hashing would be too expensive like
this can be all don't like bit flipping
and jump very efficient we've done
pretty quickly where you need to go I
think a hash table isn't over killer
this yeah
you can't a cannot Craig yes you can
know you can hat you the hash can be
some bead but yeah right depends on the
hash you can yes you internachi will be
an overkill although the B+ tree that
they're using it in the in the radix
tree are sorry in the mastery sort of is
the same thing but they're they're
trying
pack in as much data as you can in a
single note I think hash it will be an
overkill right the idea here is that
like when you think about like the in a
in a radix tree like depending on what
what your keys are based on the upper
level nodes might not change that often
right it's the ones below me that could
be changing because things are getting a
certain delete it like again going back
to my you are example if I have a bunch
of URLs that start with dub dub dub
then the upper nose and the tree could
be packed in tightly like this I'm
almost never got to modify them at all
so therefore the the indirection of a
hash table would would be wasteful and
this could just be some bit manipulation
a bit shifting to jump to where I need
to go but his question in his point I
don't know the answer to it was why
bother having this why can't you just
count all the ones below you and jump to
where you need to go I don't answer yes
yes his statement is I think for
efficiency reasons if I know that I'm
looking for like position 248 I can just
jump here I think that's the answer if I
know the digit position 248 I just jump
here and I don't have to scan everything
else came before me to figure out how
many ones there are but there I think
there I think there are Cindi operations
that can count the number ones very
efficiently so you could do that the
babies didn't do that way yeah okay so
yeah so we covered there's three know
types we covered the the linear nodes
and the bitmap nodes and then the
uncompressed nodes will see the same
thing in in hyper there's not just just
storing pointers to everything all right
so hyper now is or sorry art is a
variant of a radix tree that you're
going to do the same kind of adaptation
that that Judy does but it specifically
designed for database systems meaning
like it's meant to be an index that
points to tuples whereas the judy array
is meant to be like a general-purpose
array that's that's the final resting
space or of like data
so it doesn't have pointers to tuples it
is after the tuples themselves so again
we're going to do the same thing to Judy
Ray we're store metadata about every
node and the pointer and then there is
no way to easily do actually at all to
do a lat tree right X tree or art index
they're going to do that version
latching that I mentioned earlier in
that today so the main difference is
that the judy ray is gonna have three
node types or different organizations
arts can have four node types that are
mostly gonna vary in the number of
elements you can store a number digit
you can store per node and then as I
said the the judy array was meant to be
this general-purpose associate array
whereas the art is a table index so the
the first node type is gonna be the same
thing as the linear node in Judea ray
just they have two different size sizes
and all you have is just a list of
swords digits and then follow followed
by a list of of child pointers and you
can either have one that's stores for
keys or sixteen keys right same thing so
then now for the node 48
instead of having the bitmap node that
we saw in the in Judy ray they're gonna
actually now store just an array of of
the keys that have pointers but the
pointers are gonna be to all sets to
another array of the child pointers
right and so in this case it just
pointers so forth right so in this case
here the size of this will be each of
these are a one byte pointer to some
offset and then so I have 206 fixes
though so that's 256 bytes and then
these are gonna be up to 48 pointers and
those gonna be eight bytes all right
because they're not they're not doing
the fat pointer thing as you do it and
in duty and then be 384 bytes so put
this together this node is total is 640
so the no 48 means that at most I can
have 48 child pointers so a bunch of
these are gonna be null I put all have
at least 48 digits right in this array
the last one is the uncompressed one and
this again this is the same thing as an
Judy ray this is just one giant array
where the position in this array for the
child pointer represents if it's if it's
null then it's not there the digits not
there if it's a pointer to a child
pointer or if it's a child pointer than
it is there so the total size of this
would be 206 times 8 so 248 bytes
the idea is that as you're inserting
things and modifying the index the the
system keeps track of what the capacity
is or what the number elements you have
per per node and then if you go above
like the the max size of the node you're
looking at about and that no 48 and I
insert a 49th digit then I have to take
a latch on that node and convert it over
to this one here all right all right so
I'm gonna skip the binary compatible key
stuff again we covered this in the intro
class basically just saying like if you
store things in little-endian as you do
it in x86 like going from the from this
side to this side storing the way down
you'll have false comparisons for your
values so you they convert everything to
be big-endian and they have a recipe
book for how to do this for any possible
data type all right the last quickly
thing i want to mention is silo so in
the case of the art and the judy array
they would have different sized nodes
based on the population okay and then
the as I said once you go above the
threshold oh but the node can hold then
you had to go switch into the next node
type and they're doing this because like
well they don't support dynamic node no
sizes so to support dynamic sauce no
sizes you could use another data
structure like a hash table or a B+ tree
so this is what silo does or sorry it
was what master does so mastery is a
tree of tries now to try of trees sorry
and instead every single node again
instead of having that bit packed an
o-type there's gonna have a B+ tree and
in that B+ tree you could either have in
the leaf nodes pointers to the next
level in the Tri or actually pointer to
to a tuple so again just like
in a try you don't have to go all the
way at the bottom to get a pointer to a
tuple if you know that there's you know
the pet there's no path below that right
but inside that B+ tree at every node
the the pointers to the tuples are
always at the leaf nodes all right so
the mastery was built for this silo
project which is a in in the academia is
sort of a very influential system that a
lot of other systems are based upon it's
written by the guy that you ever used
hot crap to submit papers and
conferences it's the guy that wrote that
Eddie Koehler is insane he's awesome so
this this is a really interesting data
structure I don't know of any other
system that actually does this but it's
used a lot in academic evaluations all
right so now I just want to show back
bring this back to the same graph I
showed at the end of last class that we
sort of rushed it at the end but now you
have to understand what these art index
the master you're actually doing and
then just showing you that again that
the art the B double tree that we built
for our system is going to get blown
away for for you know against the B+
tree and the and the the art index but
you can see here that the art index
insertion is very very fast because as
soon as I insert something and I realize
there's nothing below me in my path I
don't have to keep inserting more digits
I can just stop but you can see that the
scan is really bad for it though because
you can't scan along the leaf nodes that
you can and a B+ tree right you have to
traverse back up and go back down all
right
so yes I so I fully admit I was wrong
about the veto tree I was wrong about
lat tree indexes I was wrong about never
using an OS mutex and always using spin
latches up in userspace so I'm wrong
right I can get that it's okay and then
the the radix free stuff I think the
reason why I had you guys focus on this
because that you know the B plus trees
is still sort of the go-to choice when
people build new systems but tries are
sort of now becoming more and more in
vogue let me partly due to mash tree and
the radix tree and I know with several
systems that are very interested in
incorporating it and in different facets
like the the data stash guys with could
you know they work on Cassandra
therefore Cassandra they want to replace
a lot of the internal data structures in
in their their data system with tries or
radix trees an art index is showing up
in a bunch of other places so I think
there's going forward I think things
like art will be more common then
alright so next class we'll talk about
up sort of more potpourri of other
things so it's all about system catalogs
data layout and then storage models I
deserve now that we know how to least
index some database index some tables
and run transactions on them what's out
building up the storage layer of the
system and actually start storing data
and keep track of what we're actually
storing okay all right and then I will
update will try to update the project
web page with more information about how
to complete you know what were the
different options you can choose for
implementation okay all right guys enjoy
your weekend see ya Bank it in the side
park what is this
[Music]
ain't with that gear called the
Hokey cuz I mochi ice you down with an
STI you look and it was go grab me a 40
just to get my buzz Oh cuz I need it
just a little more kick trucks a nice
hot dog and my heart won't be to say
I've nice cute they can say I said a
prayer