[Music]
so DJ's dropped cable his what he's
coming
his second girlfriend found out about
his third girlfriend so he went to Vegas
to hide out that's his problem he has to
deal with that so all right I've been
gone what what happened to me well my
wife had a kid and in theory yeah so
let's be honest here it doesn't look
like me and I'm not sure it's mine yet
so we're waiting for the paternity tests
come back so just hold off hold off your
all's okay um the other thing I want to
update for you guys is that at the
beginning this semester I said that I
only care about two things my life
number one was my wife number two was
databases so I have an updated version
for everyone now the new version is that
my wife is still number one databases
are still number two and again depending
on the paternity test the the baby is is
just you know sort of there okay uh I'll
say one thing to everyone here if do not
get pregnant or getting buddy else
pregnant before you graduate school it
is a nightmare I've done nothing for two
for the last two weeks except cleaning
like poop diapers and like vomit stuff
like that it's it's it's awful all right
sorry it's my my for wife is at home now
with the kid
all right so for you guys that that
don't have any newborn children take
care of here's what you have to do so
this is what's coming up you in in the
next month homework 4 is due two days
from now on Wednesday at midnight
project 3 what we do at the end of this
week on Sunday at midnight and then I'll
announce this on Piazza and post this on
the website we'll do the first
checkpoint for the extra credit will be
on will be on on Sunday November 24th
after the one week after the project 3
is due and so what the checkpoint means
basically is yo-yo
the URL to the article that you've been
working on the myself or the TAS will
look at it give you feedback give you
suggestions tell you what looks right
and doesn't look right and then that'll
give you guidance towards the final
submission
so I'll just say up front that you won't
get full credit for the extra credit
unless you submit the check point right
if you just Smith the check if you
submit the final thing at the very end
without giving you know that's giving
you feedback you won't get full credit
and I'll update the the document provide
information about all these things and
then after that there's one more
homework and that'll be due in December
and there's one more project and that'll
be due in December as well
okay so Roma's done any questions okay
so let's talk about logging so the idea
of logging and recovery is that we
obviously want to be able to persist any
changes we make to the database and
whenever there's a crash or a failure
so don't understand this problem let's
talk about the kind of system we've
talked about so far see if the problems
are and then we'll go back now and add
maldium recovery and we'll see how to
handle the issues with making sure
everything is durable and safe let's say
I have a simple transaction t1 was your
read on a write on AIM and it's a very
very beginning there's nothing in our
preferable like we haven't brought
anything into memory and we only have
one page that has the object a in it out
on disk so when our transaction starts
it does the read on a and then we go
fetch that page from disk and bring that
into our buffer pool that's good we know
how to do that we've talked about talked
about about that already
so now when I want to do the right o
name I modify the object as it exists in
the buffer pool right I make a flip that
make me of it and make the change then
now my transaction says I wants to
commit what has to happen here
what does it commit me the application
tells us we want to commit when did we
tell the outside world that your shows
actions actually committed well if we
immediately say they tell us commit we
immediately say well you don't there's
no deadlocks there's no time stamp
violations or validation issues with
your transaction if we merely tell now
the outside world yeah your transactions
committed what could happen well our
change is just hanging out here in
memory again we pass it all our
commercial checks that's all fine but
it's still sitting in memory so now if
like the most evil person for databases
comes along like the Hitler databases
it's just Hitler if he comes and that's
us
taps our data center or our machine and
we lose power then all the changes that
were sitting out in involved tool memory
are gone all right we never wrote
anything out the disk so if we tell the
outside world that when you know
immediately hey your thing committed and
nothing got persisted to disk we can
immediately you know we could lose power
right away and lose all our changes and
now we totally outside where we
committed but you come back and you're
your changes aren't there and that's bad
so this is at a high level is what the
problem trying to deal with today
all right called crash recovery and the
logging schemes it was a mechanism we're
gonna use to prevent these things so the
recovery algos were talked about today
are the techniques that the database
system is going to use to ensure that
all the changes make the changes that
transactions make will guarantee the
database is consistent all the changes
are atomic and all the changes are
durable right so we care about a C and D
in the asset acronym we don't care about
isolation for work talk might here today
cuz that's sort of handled by the
commercial protocols
okay that's worrying about you know who
can reuse writes this is really about
how can we make sure that our changes
are atomic consistent and durable so
every recovery protocol our mechanism is
gonna have two parts the first of all
the things we're gonna do at runtime
while the system is running while we're
executing transactions and queries that
will well set us up so that if we have
to recover after a failure we're able to
do that and not lose any any information
so the first part is all the things we
do at runtime the
second part is if after a restart or if
after a crash how do we use the
information that we collected from the
first part when you're running normally
to go back and put the database back to
the correct state so today's lecture is
focused on the first part what do we do
at run time to make sure that we can
collect the right information so that we
can restore the database correctly the
second part is on Wednesday if after we
crash we look in here and figure out
what the hell we actually did and put us
back to the correct state so for today
there's a bunch of stuff we need to talk
about before we actually talk about the
method we're gonna use so first we gotta
talk about what kind of failures we
could have in our system and how can we
you know which ones we can can recover
not recover from then we're started
talking about how we actually going to
manage memory and our buffer pool in a
slightly different way than we've talked
about so far so that we can assure that
we can again we can recover after a
crash then we'll talk about two
techniques to do database recovery the
first is shadow paging the second is
right ahead logging the spoiler would be
right ahead logging is the better way
this way what every single data system
actually uses but it's good to know what
shadow paging is just to see for stoical
reasons and see why this is superior
then we'll talk about how two different
types of logging and write ahead logging
like what's actually in the log record
itself and then we'll finish up talking
about checkpoints what - then we'll
segue into what we talked about on
Wednesday to do a recovery ok all right
so the the database system itself is
going to be divided so conceptually into
different components based on what the
underlying storage device they operate
on right the buffle manager keeps things
in memory the disk manager keep things
on disk right ones volatile ones
non-volatile and then so so based on
that we want to keep track of and
understand how can these different
components fail based on or have
problems based on the different types of
failures we can incur while we're
running transactions while we're running
queries and in the base of that we can
figure out what you know what do we
actually need to support in our recovery
protocol so there's three categories of
failures and we'll go through each of
these one by one transaction failure
system ferrars and storage media
failures so
the spoiler or the the heads-up for what
I'm talking about we care about the
first two the third one is impossible to
handle and we'll see why as we go along
so transaction fares over all the things
we talked about so far when we talk
about currency control these are things
like when like when the transaction has
a deadlock or transaction tries to
update something that it's not allowed
to update or update a value nor certain
way that's not update right these are
things that we can't allow the
transaction to continue and therefore we
have to abort it and roll back as
changes
so again logical errors would be the
transactions trying to violate some
internal integrity constraint that's
that's put upon the database or a
referential referential constraint like
if you try to insert something but
that's a foreign key preference and that
foreign key doesn't exist then the
database system says you can't complete
your transaction has to fail we're gonna
make sure all your your changes get
rolled back and never persist even
though if we you know we start multiple
times internal state errors are the
things we talked about under two-phase
locking and timestamp ordering right if
we have a developer to between two
transactions we got to kill one of them
and abort them rollback all its changes
and then you know make sure that then
they don't persist after a crash
so our database is logging protocol
needs to handle both of these I think
these are sort of obvious then we get to
actually the system failures the
hardware failures that we can count for
in our protocol as well so the first is
the software failure these are where the
the database system itself is buggy
right there's some crappy code in the
database system and like a divide by
zero and now the software it's system
itself the David system itself crashes
right gets a six set of boards and so we
need to be able to account for those
kind of failures in our database system
and make sure that you know any
transaction is still running they get
aboard and rollback correctly or any she
was actually that did commit before this
this error occurred all this changes are
persistent the hardware failure is when
the actual machine that our data system
is running on crashes or ceased ceases
to operate or runs okay this could be
someone like tripped over the power cord
or like there's a loose wire plugging
into the disk drive right the system has
a failure and they can't keep
the operating system you know crashes
the Davis system crashes and we need to
come back and recover the database state
so in order for us to make this you know
be it'll handle this we have to make
this fail stop assumption and that as we
assume that the harbor is not going to
suffer a unrecoverable damage if we have
a hardware failure meaning like if we
have a spin against hard drive and
there's the needle writing on the
platter if we pull the power and the the
the needle is not gonna like Kareem into
the platter and sort you know mess you
know messing up sectors we assume that
if we if we crash have a heart failure
then we can always come back and recover
the correct state so the last category
there is the ones that we can't handle
at all in our database system simply
because the database system although
it's you know as great piece of software
it is it can't been you know the the
pencil is a matter to its own will so a
harbor a non repairable heart affair
would be like the example of the needle
crashing into the platter or like find
like the machine on fire and melt all my
disks no database system can recover
from that right so we're not gonna
design our protocol to account for this
we can do other things like just
replicate the database to overcome this
or maintain archive backups that we can
recover if there's a crash but that's
not really recovery and the same we're
talking about today like if I had to
restore it from an archived version
that's just backup and restore that's
you notice me loading it in from from a
you know a separate copy that's not
doing anything extra special the kind of
things we're talking about today to
recover the database State so again we
only care about the first few failures
no database system can account for this
but through redundancy which we'll talk
about with distributed databases we can
we can try to avoid this and mitigate
the issue okay so the entire semester
we've been talking about discarding
database systems right and so we've
already covered this already but now we
need to sort of go over it again and see
how this is gonna be an issue when we
talk about logging and recovery so again
and it's what a database says what says
that the systems of design such that B
primary storage location is assumed to
be on disk
and at anytime you want to read a record
or manipulate a record you have to first
copy it into memory into your buffer
pool make your change and then
eventually write it back out the disk in
order to persist it this is the bond
omean Architecture from the 1950s it's
not specific to database systems but
it's it's the operating assumption we're
basing our tired discussion on and there
are some special newer hard drives that
can you know have CPU cores on the disk
itself and you can try to manipulate the
data down there but that's just sort of
moving the problem somewheres else for a
purposes we can ignore that and say you
know what we want to modify something we
bring into memory make the change then
write it back out to disk so the
question is gonna be when do we actually
write those changes out so when you guys
built the buffer pool stuff from before
all you're really doing is just saying
all right well this page should be
evicted it's dirty so therefore I have
to write it back out the disk and you
didn't worry about who actually made
that change and whether it was the right
time to actually write that change out
the disk so that's the thing we need to
account for in our logging protocols
today so the the basic guarantees we
need better to ensure in order to
provide the atomicity because it's the
in durability guarantees is that if we
tell the outside world that their
transaction is committed meaning we send
them an acknowledgment say you've
committed then all of those changes are
persisted and durable forever someone
may come and overwrite those changes and
update them that's fine but you know
before that you know those changes
should always persist forever and
likewise if any transaction makes
changes and those changes make it out
the disk but then that transaction
aborts or doesn't complete correctly
before the crash we need to make sure
that we can reverse those changes as
well so those are the two main
guarantees we need to have in our
logging protocol and the core principles
we're going to use to Nord provide these
guarantees or undo and redo which are
exactly as they sound
so with undo it's basically information
we're going to maintain to allow us to
reverse any changes to an object in the
database that a transaction has made so
it's like here's what the old guy used
to be for this attribute for this tuple
and
store that somewhere so that if I ever
need to reverse the change that someone
made to it I can go always go put put
the old value back in and then redo is
the opposite of that redo is the
information needed to reapply a change
that a transaction made to to a to an
object in the database right here's the
information on how to say you know
here's what the change here's the change
they made at this given time if I ever
need to go back and make that change
again I might redo information tells me
how to do this so based on these two
principal or primitives we can now build
on this and I'll have to build something
more complex a logging protocol that
allows us to generate this information
at the right time and in the right way
to allow us to restore the database
after a crash how we're actually gonna
use undo and redo and when this
information guide sheet gets written to
disk
it's gonna depend on how we're gonna
manage disks should I manage dirty pages
in our buffer pool so let's look at more
complex example here you have t1 t2 t1
does a read on a it right on a t2 does a
read on be right on B so in this case
here we're not worried about deadlocks
or concur to toll we just assume that
they're allowed to acquire these locks
into whatever they need to do we only
care about this point it like the low
level changes they're making to these
objects so we transaction t1 starts we
do a read or a there's only one page in
our database and so in order to do the
read on a we got to first bring into our
buffer pool and then the transaction is
allowed to read it then it does the
write on a and again it's already in our
buffer pool assuming we can get the
latch on it
we can go ahead and make our change
updated directly in place we were
ignoring multi versioning for now we
make our change right there and then our
operation finishes now we have a context
switch t2 starts running it does a read
on B the page is already in memory so
that's fine that happens right away then
it doesn't write on B again already in
memory we we assume you get the right
latch on it we can make our change and
we're fine so now we go ahead and t2
wants to commit what needs to happen
here well there's two decisions we have
to make
the first is in order to be able to tell
the outside world that our transaction
is committed should we force the the
buffer pool to flush out and write out
all the changes that it made for this
page out the disk yes or no yes right
because you have to do theirs otherwise
if I crash a Hitler comes along and it
takes to take this away all my changes
are gone well what's the issue
correct
t1 modified a in the same page so should
I be allowed to write out a page that's
been modified by a transaction that has
not committed yet out the disk he's
shaking her head no well what's the
problem right bees in here T two's made
that change but he wants to commit it's
allowed to but there's this other change
in here from an uncommitted transaction
so let's say that all right well I take
it's better for me to write out t choose
changes even though t1 has a committee
yet so I write write those out the desk
but now I you know I tell the outside
row tteyuu is committed I'll go back to
t1 but now t1 aborts so what needs to
happen here yes right so I need to roll
back the transaction so I need to roll
back the change it made on a I can do
that memory pretty fast right that's not
a big deal but I've wrote out the page
two you know that existed in with the
change that t1 made out the disk so now
I got to go make that change in here and
then write it out again to reverse the
change that I made what's the problem of
that exactly so he said by the time I
get my abort I maybe I've reversed the
change here before I overwrite my change
out the disk I crash now I come back I
don't have any of this I only have
what's on disk and now I have a change
from t1 that I that shouldn't be there
but I don't know it shouldn't be there
because I have no extra information to
tell me that T
t-1 did not actually commit so the two
things we talked about here where the
two decisions we had to make we're here
whether we should require to force the
the transaction and write out all its
dirty pages out the disk but fourth law
to commit and whether or not we're
allowed to copy out a page or a victim a
strimer buffer pool from a transaction
that has not committed yet so these two
policies are called steal and force so
the steal policy says whether
transaction they by their database
systems allows a uncommitted transaction
to overwrite the most recent committed
value of an object in the database ad on
disk before it's allowed to commit so if
you say if steal if you're using a steal
policy then you're allowed to do this if
you're using no steal then it's not
allowed the way to think about this is
if I'm running out of space my buffer
pool from one transaction is that
transaction allowed to steal a page in
the buffer pool or slot in the buffer
pool from another transaction that has
not committed yet right that's why it's
called steal the forest policy says
whether we require that all updates that
a transaction makes to any object in the
database have to be written to disk
first before it's allowed to commit so
if you say I'm using the forest policy
then it's required to do this if you're
using no force then it's not required so
forcing is gonna make it our life easier
because it's gonna allow us to recover
rather quickly because we just come back
and we see all our changes are there
right we don't have to you know look at
any other place to try to redo
information to redo the changes but the
steal policies would be problematic
because now we're clean writing out
changes or transactions that have not
committed so let's look at one way to do
this let's look at the no steal forest
policy right because they're sort of
they have a flippin goals and you know
you can only choose you know two
combinations of these two things so no
steal force means that no steal says
that any uncommitted changes any changes
made by Duncan
action cannot be written a disk and the
force says that any change all changes
ever turns actually may have to be
written to disk before the transactions
allowed to commit so t1 starts does a
read on a we bring that a buffer pool
that's fine
now we do the write on a update the the
the page and our buffer pool then we do
a context switch of t2 t2 does a read
then does the right we update the buffer
pool then now wants to go ahead and
commit again the forest policy says that
all the changes for this transaction
made have to even out the disk but we
have this this change from t1 hanging
out here as well so we need to get rid
of that so what do we need to do right
copy the page in memory right only apply
the change that we want or reverse this
other change we don't want and then we
can go ahead and write that out so now
when we when we come back over here and
we abort t1 now it's super trivial for
us to reverse the change that all the
change that t1 made because it's just
updating this this this page in memory
we don't have to go out the disk was you
know no dirty dirty change got written
out there so the database system is
going to maintain some extra metadata to
keep track of the right set over these
different transactions you guys already
solved this under two-phase locking and
and OCC under concur to your particles
so we already have that information
about what changes they made to what
objects so it's not that big of a deal
or extra work we have to do to be able
to reverse that change when you make
that copy all right and it's in memory
so that should be pretty fast so this
seemed like a good idea or a bad idea so
that's one what's one good thing about
this approach I've already said it
detector right there it's super trivial
to rollback after a crash there's
because there's nothing to rollback
because I know that anything is that
that's on add on disk should be out on
disk because they're all from committed
transactions
what's that sorry is there a deadlock
between two transactions so his question
is going back here in my example here I
have one thread or one transaction wants
to write out something disk it makes one
copy but then another transaction may be
committing at the same time and it
modified the same page you shouldn't
make another copy we can ignore that we
assume that I mean you have to have a
single latch protect these things
there's no way to get around that but we
can ignore all that here so there's
there's two problems actually three
problems yes so you're close these first
two he said the now and your processing
page to commit this copy here it's more
work it's on the critical path it's in
the critical section of the commit the
commit protocol for the commercial
mechanism that becomes more expensive
yes absolutely right yes but more than
just CPU cost it's actually the you have
to write this thing out multiple times
now like so say if you go back if we go
here if t1 didn't actually abort and
actually committed then in order to get
it's changed a out the disk I'll never
write it out again so for every
transaction that commits I potentially
have to write out the same page over and
over again yes exactly
he's actually right so one big issue
with this in my seabone example here I
have one page say it's four kilobytes
the harbor I can guarantee that I can do
a four atonic four kilobyte page right
but if I update multiple pages the
harbor can't guarantee
that for me so I could if I update four
pages I've read out the first two then I
crashed before I get the next two now I
come back and I don't have you know I
have a torn up dates so that see that's
right that's one big problem there's
another big one that's a more nuanced so
again I have one page of this this is
sort of trivial example but in this case
here for a given transaction since I
can't write out any dirty data from
uncommitted transaction to disk that
means I can my my right set all my
transaction has to fit entirely in main
memory so if I have a table has 1
billion tuples I have a single query
that wants to update all 1 billion
tuples but I can only store 1 million
tuples in my buffer pool then I can't
run that transaction in under this this
this this system cuz I'll hit the first
1 million update them that's fine then I
try to get the million plus one and then
I'm running on it I ran out of space so
he says can't you is there a workaround
can you write into a temporary spot yes
give me two slides that is that is that
is the solution yes it's not a good one
but it's one okay so no steal force is
the most easiest way to actually
implement a recoverable correct durable
buffer pool manager and a disscourn a
database system because I don't have to
do any redo after a crash I just come
back my database is guaranteeing the
correct state and I never have to go you
know undo anything from an aborted
transaction at run time because I know
none of us changes ever made it out the
disk but as we said already that you you
can't support transactions that have a
right set that exceed the amount of
memory that's available to you the
commit protocol is now more expensive
because you have to do all these extra
extra work to figure out what things
actually should be written to disk where
it's not written disk and the and you're
doing multiply out to disk you know for
everything that could have just been one
right now for every single transaction
you're writing the same page over and
over again and if you're an SSD those
things actually can't be written forever
right you can burn out the cells on the
SSD
you know it's in the hundreds and
thousands right Purcell but eventually
to keep doing this if you're just
running a lot you'll burn it out in a
short amount of time so nobody actually
does what I'm describing here right it
is the easiest way to implement it but
nobody actually does this the thing that
he alluded to that people have tried
before is to basically store the changes
you're making from uncommitted
transactions in a temporary space and
then at some point when the transaction
commits you somehow resolve the the
directory or the page table to now say
here are actually the correct the latest
versions of our of our pages and that
way if you crash you just ignore
anything that got modified in this can
those temporary buffers so this is what
shadow paging is we briefly touch about
this in the very beginning when we talk
about current control this is one way to
do a no steal force buffle management
system that avoids some of the
complications we talked about before so
lay shadow paging worships it's like
it's sort of like multi versioning but
at the page level instead of the tuple
level and there's only going to be two
copies at any given time there's always
the master copy that's the latest most
recently committed version of of the
database and then there's the the shadow
copy that all new transactions are going
to end up modifying so when a
transaction commits we want a way to
atomically switch the the shadow to
become the new master I mean we can do
this in such a way that we don't worry
about torn rights if we're updating
multiple pages so unlike in in Multi
versioning where we copy every single
thing we're going to modify actually
it's like multi burgeoning but instead
of doing a tuple of what you're doing at
a page level and you can organize the
the directory of your pages as a tree
structure so now you only need a cat
copy sort of portions of the tree and
then just do Pat copying to update them
in place or apply them to the the page
table without having to recreate the
entire hash table all over again
so at the root of this tree is gonna be
the database root that's always gonna
point to the latest master master
version so that means we can make a
bunch of changes to the low portion of
the tree but update the lease to point
into our new pages that we just created
and then when we're ready to apply the
changes to atomically across all these
pages we just swing this database root
pointer to now point to our shadow
portion of the tree and then all all our
changes get immediately become
immediately visible so a high level
looks like this again there's this
database root and it points to the
master page table and this master page
table points to our pages out on disk so
I'm gonna briefly go with this but goof
is sort of quickly but let me just get
this get to the example so say we have a
transaction comes along t1 any
transaction that's read-only can go
always go to this database root and go
to the the master copy and see a
consistent version but if we have an
updating transaction we have to create a
shadow page table that the the
transactions going to modify so the very
beginning the shadow page table it just
all its entries point to the same pages
that the master page points to the
master page table points to them so now
as this transaction starts modifying
pages we're going to make a copy of that
page into a new location in our
temporary space in on disk make all our
changes there right and we keep doing
this for all all the other all the other
pages we want to modify and then when
this transaction says I want to go ahead
and commit all we need to do is update
this database root which is stored in a
single page to now point to that the
this portion or this patient of the
shadow page table so we flush that
change out the disk and then now it
really becomes that becomes once that's
durable we then swing that pointer in
memory and then we now know that
everyone can can follow this one so if a
new transaction comes along and once it
wants to you know want to read what the
latest version is of the database it
just follows this route and finds the
shadow page table yes
questions wisely Davis root written the
desk right so they crash right so so I'm
here byte resident transaction says I
want to commit I want to tell the
outside world I commit it right so if I
don't update this database route I crash
and come back and now I look at my date
of his route and he's putting to the
master page table and all these changes
are gone correct yes it's Alama it's I
think it's a page number two page ID
right dad has to be durable cuz if I
crash to come back if I tell Fiats I'd
world I commit but then I crash I'm like
alright wall
I'll assume whatever this thing was
pointing out is the is the root of the
page table and that means I told the
house I weren't I committed but now all
my changes I made here in the shadow pic
table are gone they're still there on
disk it's just no one can see them there
you can't logically see them so it's as
if they didn't exist you quit your
question is can you be clever and figure
out a way to when you write out these
pages put a little mark in here to say
yeah you're the latest version yeah so
all right so this guy updated three
three pages so I need to now record that
okay you updated three three out of X
pages or n pages to make sure that if I
crash come back I see all those changes
yeah
essentially because you know essentially
I'm disc right now without the according
the data make sure you have some
something like out of some out-of-date
pages there right use except to keep
track of whichever the data major tells
you which ones are the most up-to-date
well yes essentially whatever
transaction commits lets you bring some
pages out to disk with those two pages
right now for this you may know the
timestamps or the transaction or
something sure my database is 100
petabytes that this is one page it has
everything I need always can always
think in extremes yes excellent so he
said and in my example here I have one
transaction what if I have a bunch of
transactions at the same time how does
this work
so you either have to have only one
transaction run out of time which sequel
light does or you you have to commit
them in a batch so I say I ignoring two
days locking because all that is
orthogonal to this assume that you don't
have a way to figure out who's allowed
to update what if I have multi Tunes
actions within the same batch updating
things I have to wait until they all
finish then they all get committed I
swing mop my database root pointer right
and then it get all Tom I can apply so
that's one way to do this if you assume
all transactions are going to finish in
a reason amount of time if you have one
transaction that takes an hour then you
either need to kill it if for a certain
amount of time or wait that one hour
before everybody goes it goes ahead and
commits some systems do this it is rare
it's most systems don't don't operate
this way but you most absorbing do
shadow paging all right IBM did this in
system or in the 1970s they abandoned it
in the 1980s when they did db2 because
you have fragmentation issues right so
now I blow a master page table I blow
away these pages here because they're no
longer visible right so this is all that
I have now but it doesn't match up the
ordering of pages here so now we do
sequential scan I you know I may not be
reading things in the right order so I
can't do clustering index is what they
were trying to do back in the day
so nobody actually does this but you
have to be right you're there you to
commit him to bat or have one
transaction from
a time yes you know so you're going back
to the previous table word t1 t2 would
that handle in this case yes if you
assume t1 t2 are committing together in
the same batch right so yes q this is
Hanna exactly in that case because again
I have the undo information I need to
reverse any changes that a transaction
made in memory so if as long as that
thing has been written out the disk then
I can just reverse it here and I'm fine
and if I crash before I flip the Davis
reporter then I'm fine okay so nobody
actually does this so let's jump through
more quickly and get to the good stuff
so the reason why this sucks it because
copying the entire page table is
expensive you even if you use a tree
structure it becomes it's not cheap and
the committe overhead is high because
you have to update flush every single
page that you modified the page table
and the route the date becomes
fragmented you need a background garbage
collector just like in a multi version
cartridge hole and you either have to
commit everything in a batch or only
have one writer out of time so as I said
the only systems I know that actually
does do this or a couchdb but I think
CouchDB is giving is going away from
that and doing their switching over to
Roxy ve l MV B is a tree based system
that uses M map so that's sort of hidden
from them and then against the system
are in the 1970s but they banded that
IBM abandoned that in 1980s it one
system you probably have heard about
that does something similar to this as
sequel Lite but this is what sequel I
did up until 2010 then they dished it to
and switched to over what we'll talk
about next
the write ahead logging approach so
what's eagle light would do is that
instead of copying the
instead of copying the page that you
would they're gonna modify and make a
modification in the copy they have a
copy original page write that out the
disk then make the modification to the
master version and then if you commit
you just blow away the the copy that you
had or if you crash before you commit
then you then you look back in that that
separate copy file and restore the
restore the change so they would call
this the Journal file so let's say that
my transaction was a month update page
two so before I modify page 2 in memory
I first make a copy to it persist it on
disk and a journal file and then when
that's done I can modify it
same thing with page 3 before I can
modify it I make a copy into separate
journal file then I go ahead and make my
change now let's say before this
transaction actually commits we end up
flushing out page 2 out the disk but
before we flush out page 3 and complete
and actually commit this thing we crash
alright so everything gets it gets blown
away in memory so when we come back we
would say alright well I have a journal
file so I need I need I made me make
sure that all my changes that are in
this journal Fog cuz these the original
versions they get written out back to
the the original disk file so again like
I said this is what this what sequel
light did up till 2010 and then they
abandon this for performance reasons to
use to write headlong okay so this
shadow paging approach it'll guarantee
correctness but it has some of some
performance issues and the main
performance issue is going to be that
it's we're gonna do a bunch of random
i/o so in my back going back here in the
sequel Lite example when I had to replay
the journal file I'm updating random
locations on disk to in order to restore
the database back to the correct state
and here's a shadow paging when I was
flushing out all my changes and say my
transaction actually committed again I'm
doing random i/o to different locations
to persist all the changes from this
from the shadow Shadow Copy so even then
with it fast SSDs that we had today
sequential i/o has always be faster than
random i/o so we need
way to convert all those random iOS into
fast sequential i/o and still have all
the durability guarantees that we'd want
in our logging protocol so this is what
right ahead logging is gonna is gonna
achieve for us so the idea was right
ahead logs that we're going to maintain
a separate log file on non-volatile
storage along with our table heap and as
transactions make changes to the
database we're gonna make entries into
this log file that record the changes
that were made and then when a
transaction go has goes at once and I
hope go ahead and commit
we just need to guarantee that we
flushed the log records that they
generated out the disk and not the
capital changes to the to the objects of
the pages in the buffer pool so for
owner for us right head log in to say
our transaction is committed and it's
durable we only need to flush the log we
don't need to flush anything else and so
now the log file is just switch why oh
because there's keep appending to this
this file you know would you know page
after page of the page that again that's
when try always to be much faster than
the random i/o of of writing out the the
random pages and again the reading
reason why it's call it right ahead log
is because we make sure that any log
record that corresponds to a change made
to an object in the database is written
a disk before that object can be written
a disk so that's that's the very
important most important thing to
understand about write ahead logging so
write ahead logging at his example of
steal and no forest because we're gonna
be allowed to write dirty pages out the
disk before transactions actually commit
as long as their log records have been
written out first and then it's no for
us because we don't require all the
changes that the transaction made two
objects we burn out the disk we only
require that the law of records be
written as a disk so again this is the
most important thing you need to
understand in order to understand the
protocol so the way anything about this
is like if I have a transaction that
updates a thousand tuples I potentially
have to create a thousand blog records
so let's say that thousand tubers are
stored in a thousand pages my log
records could just be stored in a single
page and therefore I'll need to want to
do write one one page out to flush the
log rather than all the pages that they
were modified so there's me a bunch of
performance advantages we're going to
get from this approach so the database
is going to stage all the changes that a
transaction makes in these log records
in volatile storage this is typically
bet also backed by the buffer pool and
then again this is we already talked
about everything gets flushed out and
they were not considered committed until
we know that all our log records have
been written out to disk as well so the
protocols don't work this way so when
our transaction starts we have to write
a begin record into our log that's gonna
tell us that hey there's this
transaction that started it exists
here's some metadata about it like
here's the identifier for an image
transaction commits we're gonna write a
commit record out to the log and when
you make sure that this commit record
appears in the log after any log record
that corresponds to changes of a bet
transaction made it's gonna be
interleaved potentially with other
changes that other transactions are
making but for our one transaction that
we care about at this point in time our
commit record needs to appear after all
its changes I think they because once we
see scenes come into law we know there's
no other change the transaction could
ever make so now in each log record
first in the very you know it's an
initial simplistic version of the
protocol I'm teaching right now we need
to need to record four things the unique
transaction identifier right like the
timestamp the transaction the sign when
it was started the object ID of the
thing that actually modified and then
the before value with the corresponds to
the undo and then the after value that
corresponds to the redo so this
information by itself it's enough for us
to be able that we need to in order to
recover the database and for all
possible errors that we talked about at
the very beginning so let's look at an
example here
so we just have t1 there's a write on a
write on beam and so now in memory we
have our right ahead log buffer as well
as our buffer pool so when we do the
transaction stars
begin we're going to add an entry into
our log record that says hey there's a
transaction that just started it's
usually not done exactly when you call
begin it's usually done unless you're
running with auto commit turned on it's
usually done at the first right but
different systems can do different
things so now I do write our name so the
first thing I need to do is add our
entry to my log buffer that says here's
that here's the change I'm making to a
right here's the Bears than before value
and here's the after value and once
that's in my log buffer now I go ahead
and make my change into my page in my
buffer pool all right we'll talk about
this more that next class the reason why
you have to do this before this because
there's gonna be this thing called a log
sequence number that's gonna get
assigned to the log record that we had
to use to figure out what was the what's
the log entry that course but that
changed this particular page so you may
think who cares into the muttering out
the disk can I just update this this
first then add this thing in here we'll
see next next next class why you have to
do this first followed by this so then
now I do the right on B same thing I add
my entry to my right hand a redhead log
buffer in memory then I go ahead and
make my change here so now when I go
ahead and do a commit
I add my commit record to my redhead log
buffer then at some point I'm gonna
flush it out the disk in this case here
since we need to tell the outside world
that a transaction is committed will
immediately flush this out do an F sync
and once we know that's durable and say
from disk at this point the transaction
is considered safe to now return back
the application and say that it's
committed so now who cares that Hitler
comes along and kills shows our buffer
pool because everything we need to do to
replay the changes that it made is now
safe on disk so if this page number got
written out we can just look in that log
and replay it to update the page as
needed to do exactly the same thing the
transaction did when it ran the first
time so again at a high level is this
clear
yes our question is what is instead of
storing the redhead log buffer as a
separate file what if I stored it in the
page itself
I said you told me like a log structure
storage we talked about earlier yeah so
in the log structure storage you don't
you don't have this on disk you only
have this yeah it's a Volks record yet
correct and the the what your what
you're giving up by hat not having this
is that reads are now more expensive
because you have to replay the log to
figure out what the page I should look
like when every read but it makes some
write super fast cuz now you don't do
extra writes to write out dirty pages
you only keep appending things to the
log so there's a trade-off so this will
be like rocks DB leveldb Cassandra bunch
of systems do these log structured merge
trees log structures storage yeah for us
we're time I here assume you have table
heaps we write everything we talked
about we have table heaps we have
override a head log we're not doing the
log structure stuff we talked about
before but the concept is still the same
you just you just don't have this you
don't have a table
[Music]
so his question is if I have to
transactions and they're updating the
database are there log records and are
mixed in the same log buffer or they
have separate log buffers they're
intermixed again this is this is this is
independent orthogonal to the commercial
stuff so some higher-level part of the
system that says set determines whether
one transactions allowed to update you
know what we know this object of that
object at this point we assume that
they're allowed to do that and they did
do that they're going to do it and
therefore we just we just add their law
records into the log file we don't eat
we don't maintain several log files for
different transactions because we have a
transaction B we know who did what
yes okay
so again if we crash there's everything
we need to restore the database is in
the log so to sort of implementation
questions one is when should the
database assumed write out the log
entries to disk
well the talks as we said it's whenever
the transaction commits before we tell
the outside world our transactions going
to go ahead you know is fully committed
we do make sure that those log records
and the buffer are now stored out at on
disk that's all we need to be able to
restore the database but my example here
I only showed one transaction and when
they said commit you know I just mean
did s sync and write it out but that's
actually gonna be super slow if I for
every single transaction I do an F sync
when they commit to write out it's a log
buffer that's not what I'm gonna want to
do because saying F sync takes five
milliseconds on a slower disk then I can
only commit one transaction every five
milliseconds and that bet that's gonna
be that's gonna be bad I can only do two
thousand transactions a second so what
every system actually implements instead
is what's called group commit where
you're gonna allow multiple actions to
buffer up a bunch of changes in the log
buffer and then at some point you make a
decision all right now I'm gonna go
ahead and write whatever's in the log
buffer out the disk and then may include
log records from transactions that have
not commit
yeah but that's fine because we know how
to undo their the undo their changes
because we have the undo information in
there in the log record so this is what
you're going to end up happening
implement in in project 4 so the way it
basically works is that in the simple
form you instead of having one log
buffer you have to log buffers it's sort
of like shadow paging there's the master
there's the master when everyone's
writing to and there's the background
one that you're eventually write to next
so when my transaction starts t1 here
doesn't write on a or you always go to
you go to the first one first add the
begin then do the write on a to write on
B now I do a contact switch here all
right
at t2 sentry-go right on C but now at
this point my log buffer is full so I
can't add anything and anything else in
here so I'm gonna go ahead and write
this out the disk all right and I have
to do F sync so that you know that's
gonna take some time so in the meantime
now I switch over to my second log
buffer and now any other changes that
transactions may get added to this thing
here the idea is start your wild ones
getting read out in a disk you fill up
the next one when that gets filled then
ideally the other ones been flushed out
so now then you write the write the
second one out and then fill up the
first one so just going back and forth
while ones getting flushed you fill up
the other one but let's say for this
transaction here it stalls right it does
something right it does additional
computation so neither transaction are
generating new log records so instead of
just waiting till it's filled up before
I write it out there's also a second
prop process where you you say well if
it's been a certain amount of time since
any since I've last flushed this thing
out let me go ahead and flush it out and
the idea is you should want to tune it
such a way that like if you know that
what the f sync time is write something
up the disk then you sort of set your
timeout to be to be that so like if if
it takes me five milliseconds to write
write the first page out or the first
blog buffer then I'll wait five
milliseconds for the second one and when
what five milliseconds is up if I'm not
full yet I go ahead and write that out
as well
so again group commit basically says
instead of one transaction F sinking the
log when it commits you back to bunch of
them together and then you amortize the
essent costs across multiple
transactions so if you're the first
transaction that gets added to the to
the log buffer and then you commit
you're kind of like you're screwed
because you have to wait the longest
before you're actually written out the
disk but if you're the last guy then
it's as if you get that you're getting
the disk exactly to yourself because
you're not waiting any time so on
average this works out to be much better
than everyone else inking immediately
all right so then the the last question
is when she'll be actually write the
dirty records out to disk
well this depends now so now that we
said that the law buffers everything we
need to do everything all the operations
we need to be able to redo the changes
that transaction is made and we say that
the log records that correspond to
changes to pages are written out to disk
before this page is written out to disk
it's not actually immediately urgent for
us to flush all those pages immediately
when the transaction commits because the
law workers have been flushed so now on
our replacement policy in our buffer
pool manager we can account for this we
can say all right well this thing is
dirty but I the law workers been written
out for it so maybe I don't want to Vic
this one right away Brian can evict it
right away where this other one here
although it's probably as a higher
priority for me getting removed or
getting evicted its log records haven't
haven't been flushed yet so maybe I
don't want to dick that one because I
have flush the buffer first before I can
write that out so this this idea of log
and recovery permeates throughout the
entire system and now we need to account
for the other parts of the system but
we've already talked about we can update
replacement policy to keep track of
these things yes all right so so this
question is well in these example we
don't recommit so let's say that I have
a commitment log buffer but before I
read up at this high crash who cares
ah no no the application said commit we
haven't told me you committed yet we
only tell them that they commit when
that log buffer that corresponds that
commit message is written to disk that's
the genius of this right because again
the the if we're doing OCC where we're
doing validation after after the
transaction commits we still might end
up getting aborted right at this point
here at the law buffer we assumed all
that's taken care of so we see a commit
message here we don't tell you know
there's no callback to say yeah you're
good everything's durable until the law
buffers we've written a disk his
question is is the application hanging
for a while yes correct but I mean like
what else would you do otherwise if you
don't want to wait to see what you
committed that's fine but you could lose
data right so if I don't run it a
transaction then then you know actually
even even if you do auto commit here's a
single state by transaction I think it's
still gonna write a write a log record
before it comes back and says your
things actually finished I don't some
systems lottery turn allow you to turn
off logging on a per transaction basis
so I can run a transaction that would
say I make a bunch of changes but when I
commit don't write anything out the log
you could do that some systems will
apply to do that by default they don't
yes
do we need to commit entries about
renewed transaction or we don't his
question is do we need to commit entries
for a retailing transaction what do you
think well what would you have to commit
what what would the log record beat
there's nothing there's nothing to log
this is what I'm saying like going back
here uh oh sorry guy Taemin hmm oh
that wasn't me that was PowerPoint sorry
so I showed the the right and this in
this case here I showed that when the
transaction started I had to begin entry
you don't have to do that right because
if it's if it's a read-only transaction
like if this thing called begin but then
did a bunch of reads then I'm storing
crap that I don't care about you could
do that you don't have to though right
in some systems you can actually declare
a turns actually read-only at the
beginning that you say begin as
read-only or something in sequel then
you just turn off all logging and all
control if you're doing snaps to
isolation because you just know that I'm
gonna see exactly what I should be seen
for simplicity's I'm showing that here
yes I so question is when you garbage
like the logs a few more slides will get
there yes actually is spoilers
checkpointing but we'll get to that
okay so just to recap everything we
talked about the way it is heard a thing
about the different methods for doing
bustable management and recovery is in
the context of the runtime performance
and the recovery performance so the
wrong time promise would be how fast is
it for you know to maintain all this
information while I run transactions so
in the case of no for steel which is
right ahead logging that's gonna be the
fastest during run time because when I
commit I'm just committing out those log
records I don't worry about those dirty
pages hanging my buffer pool I'll take
care of them at some later point whereas
with shadow paging it's more expensive
because I have to make sure I flush all
the page
that I modified and my shadow page table
then flush the database route to disk
before I can tell the outside world I
commit him but now the downside is if I
have to recover the database after a
crash shadow paging is the fastest
because I don't do anything extra I just
come back and my Davis root points to my
shadow page or the consistent
master the most recently committed
version and I'm done but under write
ahead logging that's actually slower
because I'm not the replay the logged up
to some some point which she was sort of
alluding to with garbage collection so
because of this trade-off between
performance and recovery time most
database system implementations choose
the the right head logging choose the no
for steal because they'd rather be
faster at runtime and assume failure
failures are gonna be rare which which
you know in the grand scheme of things
they are your data systems not crashing
every minute if you do we have other
problems so therefore they're willing to
trade off faster runtime performance in
exchange for slower recovery there's
only one system that I'm aware of except
for the ones that do shadow paging like
the old sequel light there's only one
system that I can make the trade-off for
having faster recovery time in exchange
for running slower at runtime and it was
this system I don't know the name of it
it was a database system built in the
1970s for the the Puerto Rican
electrical system because in Puerto Rico
in the 1970s they had power outages like
every hour so the DA's ism was crashing
literally every single hour so for them
it was much better to be slow at runtime
such that for every hour when you
crashed when you lose power you could
recover the database Amelia Edwards
right another were there anything like
this at the high level to is this is
with no undo no redo because there's
nothing to reverse and nothing to
reapply with with right ahead logging
you need undo and redo all right so I
showed sort of at a high level what
these long records are that there's an
object ID and then there's a for value
in the after value but what how this is
actually implemented so there's a couple
different approaches
so one but the one would be what it's
called physical logging which is
basically what I've talked about so far
is we're recording the low level byte
changes to a specific location as some
object in the database that you made -
you know and you know how to reverse it
so thinking this is like if you run
there for or get diff
it'sit'sit's but allows you to get out
the before and after advantage of of the
change but the downside of this is again
if I have to make if I update of you
know billion tuples in my transaction I
have to have a billion log records that
corresponds to all those low-level
physical changes another approach is do
logical logging where you just record
the high-level operation that which of
the change you made to the database and
that's enough for you to be able to
reapply it at run time undo is a lot
more tricky based if you have you know
based on what the actual query is but
let's ignore that for now so I think the
way thing like this is this is storing
like in the diff of the change you made
this is storing actually the sequel
query that of the change you made so the
advantage or disadvantage of each of
them are that logical blogging allows
you to record more changes with less
data I update a billion to post with a
single update statement I only know of
that one update statement the downsides
gonna be with logical logging though is
that it's gonna be tricky for me to
figure out what changes I potentially
may made to the database that I've got
written to disk before the crash because
I don't have that low-level information
I update a billion to blows over a
billion pages maybe half of them got
written out the disk how do I know which
ones I need to update and reapply the
other issues gonna be you'll see that
however long it took me update the
database the first time when I ran the
query with a logical logging scheme this
is gonna take that same amount of time
the second time so my query took an hour
to run during recovery to take an hour
to run again there's no magic because
I'm in recovery mode that's gonna make
that go faster so although the skins
storing I'm storing less information of
logical logging it's going to make
recovery more expensive and most systems
do not make that change
the hybrid approach that most people use
is call it physiological logon where
you're not going to store the low level
byte information about the changes
you're making to the database you'll
still you're still sort like it's a low
level enough to say here at this page
I'm modifying this object but you're not
you're not really taking a diff as you
would under physical logging you're just
saying here's this logical thing I want
you to make up make a change to so this
is what most systems actually implement
so let's say we have this update query
here so in a physical log it would be
like at this page of this offset here's
the before and after image and we
haven't talked about indexes as well but
indexes you basic at the log in the at
the same time you're making changes to
the database because if my of my index
doesn't fit memory then I don't want to
have to rebuild it from scratch upon
recovery so most data systems also
record the log the changes you makes it
indexes logical login of query again you
just store the Seigle statement physical
logical logging is you're saying at this
page at this slot number here's the
change I want you to make these these
low-level attributes and this allows you
to not have to but having these in this
extra indirection sort of like the
slotted pages
it doesn't allows you to reorder that
the the replay operations in such a way
that the the data it doesn't mean a byte
for byte copy yet before and after the
crash you have some wiggle room to
actually reapply these in different ways
and restored still restore back to the
correct state all right so the getting
to her question is the issue of anything
we talked about so far so far is that
these right ahead logs are gonna grow
forever if my database system is running
for a year I'm gonna her years worth of
logs so now if I have to crash if I
crash and come back into replay this log
I potentially have to replay the entire
year's worth of data so logical logging
that would be terrible right because if
the query takes the same amount of time
it took the first time as it does during
recovery so I have a year's worth of
data of logical log records if I crash
and come back I pretend to take a year
for me to recover the database
so that's bad so the way we can truncate
and the the log is to what are called
checkpoints and the idea of a checkpoint
is that we're gonna flush out all the
pages that are dirty in our buffer pull
out the disk and add a entry to our log
record to say at this point there's no
dirty pages that are not durable in
disks so therefore you don't need to
replay that far in the past potentially
from from from from my checkpoint
because I know all those changes have
been persistent again the idea here
again because we're doing the steal
policy or the no force policy we're not
requiring that the dirty pages that
transaction made has to be flushed out
the disk before the transaction is
committed so we don't know whether they
actually made it to disk or not if we
crash whereas with the checkpoint when
we know the checkpoint completes we know
that at that point everything has been
written a disk so look at really simple
example here so for this one I'm going
to use a very simplistic checkpoint
scheme that basically stops the world
stops all transactions from running and
flushes out all their changes all the
dirty pages out to disk and then once I
know all the dirty pages are written
then I let them to start running again
this is called consistent consistent
checkpointing or blocking checkpoints
most systems don't actually implement it
this way we'll see on Wednesday how to
do it better and how things can run at
the same time but just understand it
edit you know the very basic how the
basic protocol works assume that's the
case so I'm gonna add this checkpoint
entry here so what will happen is when I
take this checkpoint I stop all
transaction from running and I flush out
any dirty pages and so now if I have a
crash when I come back I know that I
don't need to look at net1 t1 s changes
because t1 committed before my
checkpoint so I know all the t1 changes
are written a disk so I don't need to
replay and look at it's long it's the
other two guys t2 and t3 those guys get
started and could potentially make
change before my checkpoint so I need to
go back in the log up to that point and
figure out what they actually did to
my Davis back in the correct state so in
the case here
t2 committed before the crash so I know
I want to reapply it changes to redo
their exchanges t3 did not commit before
the crash so I would know I want to
reverse its changes right so the
checkpoints basically if your skin is
telling us that we know that at this
point in time all dirty pages from any
transactions have been written to disk
and it's up for us to then figure out
well what came slightly before the
checkpoint and what came after the
checkpoint to decide who's allowed to
actually have their changes persisted so
well game will talk about checkpoints
more on Wednesday but in my simple
example here I stalled all the
transactions to make my life easier
because if I have a transaction that's
updating a bunch of pages I don't want
to have the case or it could be I had to
do some actual work to figure out well
I'm updating 20 pages and my checkpoint
flushed out the first 10 pages that
transaction modified but then while the
checkpoint was running it modified these
other ones I didn't flush those things
out so I don't want to figure out which
ones actually should be around the other
tricky thing is gonna be it's not clear
how often we should take a checkpoint
because these checkpoints aren't free
because we're writing out dirty pages
and that's slowing slowing the disk when
we could be running out to a log now in
a lot of systems they'll have the disks
the log we stored in separate discs and
the heat balls are sort of separate
discs so when you do a net syncs on both
of them you're not slowing down each
other but again now my checkpoint is
running out dirty pages when I could
have been you know evicting pages for
disk
to get new space in my buffer pool to
have other transactions keep on running
so how often you take a checkpoint can
vary based on the implementation so the
one approach is to say every after every
every Sura minutes or seconds take the
checkpoint if I do that then my recovery
time is much faster because now I don't
need to go as far back in the log debris
figure out what should be actually
persisted because my checkpoint is
occurring more frequently because now
the checkpoints are slowing me down so
I'm like my runtime performance suffers
another approach which I actually think
is better is that the checkpoint only
occurs after a certain amount of data
that ran out the law
like after I've written out 250
megabytes of data to the log then I take
a checkpoint and that that bounds the
amount of time you have to wait and you
don't worry about whether you're taking
checkpoints unnecessarily because it's
your I know that I only need to look at
me but I'd most join fifty megabytes of
the log before at the recover my
database again I'm going over this very
very very fast cuz we're running out of
time but we'll cover this more detail
i'm teletrac of ur e on on wednesday so
any any high-level questions about
checkpoints saying a checkpoint is like
garbage collection for for the right
ahead log but i know that at that at
that point of checkpoint
I don't potentially need to look at
anything it came before of course in the
extreme case if I have it if I would
chose action the runs for days and I'm
taking a check one every five minutes
and I need to go back to when that
transaction started to figure out what
all changes actually made okay so as I
said right ahead logging is is almost
always the preferable approach that the
better approach to handle avoiding data
loss or to make sure that our database
ism is durable on disk and the core idea
what's gonna how it works is that it's
gonna use steel no force buffer pool
management policy it's gonna flush all
changes that transactions made to their
log records to disk before we tell the
outside world that a transaction is
committed and then in the background of
some later point we can flush out
there's those dirty pages but we have to
write the log records first before we
can write out the dirty pages that they
modify and so on recovery we just undo
any changes from uncommitted
transactions and they redo the commit
changes the committed to redo the change
of any committed transactions to make
sure that they get applied yes this
question is we have to undo potentially
changes on recovery again we'll cover
that on Wednesday because changes from
uncommitted transactions could have
those dirty pages could read rid now the
disk because we're using the steal
policy
I'll never ever wore it actually right
now
his question is this question is other
scenarios where upon recovery we would
not have to undo because we can look at
data art changes actually make it out
the disc the know the the spoiler would
be for Wednesday you redo everything you
could riff through the law of multiple
times
you're gonna redo everything but then as
you redo you say oh I see this
transaction didn't commit then you go
back and reverse on the log and you undo
anything that is on so you you just you
play it safe and you always undo there
are some optimizations that I don't
think most people do them all right so
on Wednesdays class again it would be
the second part of what we talked about
for logging recovery is two things we do
after a crash right after a restart how
do we use the right head log how to use
the check points to put us back in the
correct State so this is probably the
third hardest part of database systems
so the thing we're talking about is
Aries Aries is the gold standard of how
you do database recovery I don't know
what the textbook calls it Aries
but and most systems that implement
right ahead of all are not gonna call
but they're doing Aries but everybody
that does red head logging it's me based
on the IBM's protocol from the 1990s
whether or not they know that they're
using their basically using Aries I'm
Graham all right I'm having office hours
now at 1:30 and see you guys on Monday
Oh
losing crushed up kids let the cows in
the demo I'll Drive he's with say knives
in my system I'm blessed
let's go get the next one get over good
there will be son ricochet jelly hit the
deli for a boat one naturally bless ya
what rap is like a laser beam the fools
in the bush say nothing like a king wrap
the bottle of us a nice sympathy go you
don't feel like drinking that boney to
you drunk you can't try and if the sake
don't know your phone can tap a thing
[Music]