[Music]
okay let's get started a lot to discuss
today
so again Thank You DJ drop tables for
having us out today so you're flying out
immediately after class right where are
you going
my boy Debbie Steve's got a hedge fund
your boy has a hedge party yeah Jenny
block King yeah
that's not sketchy yeah all right okay
all right so that's his problem all
right
your problems are these things so
homework three is into today at midnight
the midterm exam will be in class a week
from today
here again the the end of this lecture
we'll do a review of what the you know
the outline was expected of you for the
midterm and then project two will be due
on at midterm on Sunday October 20th
anyhow little questions about any of
these things okay
so let's jump into it so the last class
we started talking about query execution
and we said that we were gonna have
these operators for in our query plan
and then we showed different ways to
either move data from the top to the
bottom bottom to the top and then we
also showed that sometimes you could
send a single tuple you can send a batch
of cute wolves or all the tuples for one
opera to the next and so during this
discussion we've made this big
assumption or I didn't even talk about
you know how these operators are being
executed we just sort of set it at a
high level there's these functions that
call next to each other and they pass
data around so so now we're gonna talk
about today is how is the data system
actually gonna execute these things
right what are these you know we're
gonna have these workers they can take
these operators and and execute them and
produce some result and so for the most
part in last class we just you could
just assume that we were talking about
single threaded execution
meaning there was me one thread that was
gonna call next at the root
assuming you're doing the iterator model
going from top down and call next going
below until got some data and then just
you know one thread did everything but
as we spent a bunch of other lectures
talking about we know how to build
thread save concurrent data structures
where we could have multiple workers or
multiple threads or processes operating
or executing these tasks for us at
simultaneously and then at the end we
you know we put combine it all together
to put it into a a single result that we
hand back to the application or the
terminal whoever whoever invoked the
query so that's what we talked about
today talk about how do we actually
execute queries in in in parallel so it
showed us to be sort of obvious why you
would care about parallel execution
right in the modern era of what CPUs
look like today or GPUs for that matter
as well like we have a lot more cores
that are available to us and so we want
to be able take advantage of them and so
the benefit were to get in a database
system if we can support parallel
execution is that we're get honestly
better performance but not always but
usually is the case or you want this to
be the case and this could be in terms
of better throughput meaning we can run
more queries per second a process more
data per second will get better latency
meaning the time it takes for us to
execute a single query can be can be cut
cut down in time because we can get in
between one things in parallel the other
advantage of this is that we'll get also
better responsiveness or availability of
the system meaning you know the system
will feel more lively and what and
respond more quickly to our to our
requests again think about remember
we're talking about disk oriented
database systems hey remember I said
that anytime for all these data
structures that we talked about so far
or like the table heap anytime a query
could be accessing a page that's not in
memory it's not in the buffer pool and
therefore it has to stall while the you
know we go fetch it from disk and bring
it into our buffer pool so if we only
had one thread executing in our system
or one process for our entire system
every single time we had to touch the
data from disk it would to be this long
pause while we go and get the data we
need so this the system would look
unresponsive but so but allowing us to
have
operations our current execution we can
have one thread block because it's
gathering get some a disk but other
threads can keep running and hopefully
operate on what's already in memory and
and still make forward progress and at
the end of the day what this is all
gonna add up to is that it's gonna
reduce the total cost cost of ownership
or TCO of our database system so TCO is
usually how people in an enterprise
world think about the cost of a database
system right it's not just like the cost
of buying the machine or the cost of
paying for the software license it's the
total cost of actually running this
thing for you know for some period of
time so that includes the software
license includes the hardware it also
includes the the labor costs actually
set up the software set up the machine
the energy costs to actually run the
servers and so if we can do more work
with less Hardware then this is going to
cut this down significantly so this is
also a big win for us as well so it
means that if we buy a new machine that
has a lot more cores we want our data to
somebody would take advantage of it
so the thing we need also distinguish -
before we start talking about parallel
situation today is to be able to
distinguish it between distributed
execution or distributed databases so at
a high level but both trying to do the
same thing so in a parallel database an
distributed Avis the idea is that you
have a database that's spread across
multiple resources that allow you to
have improves different characteristics
of the database system again before most
cost latency things like that and so I'm
highlighting the word resources here
because I'm not necessarily saying that
this means another machine or multi
machines right it could be multiple CPUs
could be multiple disks alright all
these things are wouldn't call us a
distributed parallel database system so
the from the applications perspective
like for the from the person actually
you know opening the terminal and
writing a single query and sending it to
our database system they should know
shouldn't care whether we are a parallel
tribute database or a single node
database system ranked again is the
beauty of a declarative language of
sequel I write my select statement
I don't care where where my data is
actually being stored I don't care
whether it has to join you know move
data across the network or move data
across different sockets again the
sequel query is is agnostic to these
name
so if we have a single new database
system and then we start scaling it out
to make it parallel or distributed then
we shouldn't have to go tweet we should
have to go back and rewrite our
application rewrite all the sequel
statements everything should still just
work so that's the ultimate goal what
we're trying to do here again having the
disconnection or the abstraction layer
of the logical versus the physical we
can move the physical stuff around as
needed and the logical part doesn't
change and that's and it seems sort of
obvious right now to us but like that
was a big deal actually it's a big deal
with inner seagull systems a few years
ago as well but it's big deal in the
1970s all right so the difference
routine a distributed in a pair of
database is the following so this is my
definition I don't know what the
textbook says but to me this makes the
most sense and this sort of follows
along with what with what's in the
academic literature the term parallel
which distributed is usually the terms
are often mixed together but for the
most part people mean most people have
these kind of systems but a lot of
systems are still missed so parallel
database is one where the the resources
that are available to us in the system
are going to be physically close to each
other right think of like a single rack
unit machine that has two CPU sockets
right so the CPU sockets are have the
corsican XE queries for us those things
are really close together because
they're going over our really fast and
high bandwidth interconnect so that's
how the resources are gonna communicate
with each other again whether it's CPU
what's compute or storage it doesn't
matter for now and then the thing that
matters the most for this discussion
today is that we are going to assume
that the communication between these
different resources is gonna be not only
fast and cheap to do but also reliable I
mean if I send a message from one CPU
socket to another CPU socket it's not
gonna get dropped right because that
means like I'm losing cache traffic on
my interconnect and I have a whole bunch
of other problems than just losing
database messages like the whole system
is falling apart all right in a
distributed database the resources can
be far from each other so that could
either mean like different machines in
the same rack different machines in the
same data center or different machines
of different parts of the world right
East Coast versus West Coast data
centers in the in the US and therefore
the
in order to communicate you need of
resources we have to go through a slower
communication channel like the public
wide area network and where is this
thing can be like interconnects between
CPU sockets which is way faster and
therefore because we're going over this
unreliable interconnect we can't assume
that our old messages are gonna show up
really quickly and show up in the right
order that we expect them to or you show
up at all so there's a whole bunch of
other hard problems we have to deal with
when we talk about distributed databases
and then the semesters so we're gonna
ignore all that for now and we're going
to focus on parallel databases and for
this you can just assume that it's a
it's a machine that has a bunch of
sockets a bunch of cores that can all
operate at the same time I may be
talking also to the same disk that's
local bot that's local to it okay all
right so today we're first talk about
the the process model this is how we're
gonna organize the system to order to
actually have workers to execute our
queries and then we'll talk about how we
actually support parallel execution for
our query plans and then we'll talk
about - getting parallels in its view
Iowa parallelism I deserted the
distinction teen compute versus storage
between these two guys then as I said
we'll finish up at the end talking doing
a quick review on what's expected and
then in the midterm yeah right so the
database systems process model is how
we're gonna organize or architect the
system to have multiple workers running
concurrent requests and the reason we
have to do this is because we could
either have an application send really
big requests that we want to split up
across multiple workers or we could have
the map application to send multiple
requests at the same time that game we
want to divide up across the different
workers so in the case of OTP it's gonna
be a bunch of small requests so we want
to be run those in parallel in OLAP it's
it's traditionally you know a small
number of requests but those requests
then we want to break up and run in
parallel at the same time so we'll talk
about the distinction of this type of
parallelism later on that's the general
idea today we want to take requests and
run them across multiple workers and so
I'm using the term worker just a means
some component of the Syst
that's able to take tasks that some some
other part decision is telling to do
like the network layer gets a request we
run it through the query optimizer and
now we have a query plan and the query
plan is a task that we want to hand off
to a worker or workers and have them
execute this thing so the reason why I'm
using the term worker because it could
be a process it could be a thread I we
could be either in but I love the basic
idea is still the same and the workers
traditionally responsible for for for a
given task if there's something that
would hand it off back to the
application and say you know here's the
result of the query you executed so
there's three three row process models
we could have yes yes
you see question is can we say a workers
a thread yes workers gonna be either a
process or a thread dependent process
model you use yes this question to the
application necessarily mean you need
abilities or no could be but all OTP yes
I think of like I have a web page I have
multiple users accessing a web page
every single page load is gonna fire off
a bunch of code on the server side like
PHP JavaScript Python and that that code
is gonna do a bunch of requests to get
data from the database and then render
the HTML back to you so I'm having
multiple users accessing my web page
each of those are then flying off this
code that then fire off different
requests or it could be like a single
dashboard or analytical application
where it's one user submitting much of
queries you know at one at a time but
then we want to run those in parallel to
be either one so there's a theory
process models we could have in our in
our database system the first is that
we'll have a single process per worker
then we have could have a process pool
and then the spoiler be that the most
common one is the last one here at least
in newer systems we're actually a
multi-threaded system we have multiple
one thread per worker so we'll go
through each of these examples one by
one so the process per worker is sort of
the most basic one approach where we're
going to have a single worker be
represented by a single OS process so
what happens is your application sends a
request to say hey I want to execute a
query or open the connection to the
database system
some centralized coordinator a
dispatcher that gets that initial
request and then can fork off now a
worker which is gonna get as a separate
process that is gonna be responsible for
handling this connection so now the what
happens as the dispatcher says all right
I got you a worker here's the port
number where you can go communicate with
with and then now the the application
only communicates directly with the
worker and the worker is responsible for
doing whatever you know executing
whatever request that the query wants
all right so the issues gonna be is that
right have multiple workers there to be
separate processes and now they again
assuming we're a Discordian system now
that could be having in their own buffer
pool and going fetching pages from disk
and bringing them to memory but course
now we don't want to have multiple
copies of the same page in these
separate processes because now we have
to like court eight across them and
that's gonna be expensive if you're the
send messages back and forth and that's
just sort of wasting memory because
we're going up again we've done two
copies of things so the way to get
around there that issue is that every
you can use shared memory that it can
allow these different processes that
normally have their own separate address
spaces in memory a lot of them share
access to these global data structures
right and the OS is what facilitates
that so the the one advantage you can
also get from this approach if you are
worried about the resiliency of your
system is that if you have a blog in
your worker code and it crashes it
doesn't end up taking down the whole
system because just this one process
crashed like the OS knows it was forked
off from the dispatcher but it doesn't
take down the whole system if there's
one guy fails yes yes right so shared
memory is a do they cover that in five
13 to 13 or no yeah okay so shared
memory is a contract the operating
system provides that says here's some
region of memory so normally when I call
malloc in my process that is my that's
in my private address space only I can
lean right to that memory with shared
memory you tell the OS hey Malik me a
bunch of space and then anybody in that
shared memory group that has permissions
is allowed to also read and write to
as well right normally the OS would not
let you do that that's it's one of the
protections of the OS carbides but this
is allows you to now have a block of
memory to be shared across multiple
processes so if unless I have shared
memory then every single worker is gonna
have its own buffer pool and it's gonna
bring in pages that are just be copied
in other worker pools or other workers
that they are bringing in the same pages
so this approach is used in and pretty
much every old database system every
database in bed with made in the 1970s
1980s maybe early 1990s is using this
approach anybody take a guess why why
would you process these ever threads he
says maybe there's no thread yet very
close so there were threads back then
not as good as we have one tab now but
there was no standard thread API
discipline like this like 1980s before
POSIX before P threads right so they had
all these different variants of UNIX all
these different various of operating
systems so if I have my database system
and I wanted to have it run on alt you
know own backs and all these other os's
I had to rewrite my app my database
system to use the threading API for all
those different operating systems now
with P threads and sort of Linux being
the the dominant UNIX variant that
everyone uses that's good enough for
everyone so back in the day it wasn't
like we have now everyone had their own
threading package and it wasn't a
standard API and we have to rewrite
everything so but everyone had fork
enjoying right now was the basic
operating system primitives so if you
built a database system using this
process model then it would work pretty
much everywhere
so a extension of this it's called the
process pool so in this case here we're
still working our processes but the idea
is that instead of forking off a process
for every single connection that comes
along we just have a bunch of workers
that are sitting around and we are
dispatcher can sit can pick one of them
say all right now you're in charge of
executing this query and then what you
can now also do is because you have a
pool and you're aware that there's other
processes around they help you to do
work now you can actually do some get
some query parallelism because now you
can say well I need to actually this
query
and it's gonna take too much work for me
to do so maybe I'll give half of the
work to another process and let it let
it run right when the single process
think of process model for per worker in
the last slide you're not aware of what
else is running and you want to fork you
know a process while you're running as
well because that's gonna be expensive
whereas this guy has things around that
Niki reliably use so yes so his question
is like what is the database system data
system would be sort of everything over
here all of us this is the application
this is like this is like your website
this is whatever you know that's not
application that talks to the database
so this is sending sequel queries and
the dispatcher is the one we're handing
with Hannum all yes thinking that
there's a division line here that says
everything over the side of the database
system so the important thing about this
though in the case of this slide and the
previous slide these are getting these
are full fledge OS processes so we're
not doing any scheduling ourselves in
the database system the OS is
responsible for doing all that
scheduling now we can give it nice flag
two priority flags and try to say this
one is should get higher priority or
more runtime this other process but at
high level we can't control what gets
scheduled right so once we hand off the
work it just runs yes this question do
you have idea where you have more than
one worker pool no these have one quite
any question is you have a fix of our
processes in the work report yes so this
is something you would define when you
turn on the data set you say how many I
mean
worker processes mile-and-a-half cuz is
forked forever having connections and
then the system get overwhelmed and then
typically what you do is you always have
one in real systems you always have one
worker be like the special worker so
that if you get the system gets locked
up there's always one worker that can
take a incoming request from the
administrative account so they can start
killing things and clean things up he
says what does the process deal with
does M&E work to do
it sits and just waits right and
actually this is um
we actually talked about this in our
developer meeting yesterday for the
business and we're building in our ole
since we were building at CMU we had
this issue before we threw all the code
away in the old system if there was no
work to do our CT would still spin to
like 60% like this is doing useless
stuff it's pulling on something ideally
you want this like if there's no work to
do you want the the CP utilization to be
like 1% 2% and for my one system I use
for all the demos I'm running like
sequel server I'm running a MongoDB I'm
running per scraps my sequel Maurier DB
and you don't you know some of them like
the CPU spikes are like 10% when there's
doing nothing most of the ones are like
running at 1% so it's still doing
something just because it's checking say
hey is there work for me to do but you
don't want to burn run cycles yes yes
there's question is do some do some work
opposed to use work stealing in the
high-end systems typically what happens
is I should make us laugh at us at
high-end system like the dispatcher or
the coordinator it knows who's doing
what work so if it can on the fly
recognize oh this one worker is maybe
it's taking a long time to read a bunch
of data and it has a bunch of stuff in
the queue and he needs to process so
maybe I'll take it to work out and hand
it to somebody else
yeah the high-end systems can do that
all right so this is the approach that
use this use an IBM db2 Postgres switch
to this model in 2015 is going back to
previous slide here right again Postgres
oracle and and and tv2 these are all
older systems like from the 80s and 70s
I think Sybase and the formics might
also work this way again also from the
1980s most of the modern systems do the
last approach was the multi-threading
one and so the basic idea is now is that
we just instead of having a bunch of
processes that are all doing different
different tasks we just have one process
for the database system and inside it it
has its own threads and they can decide
how to dispatch things as needed like
again this is just using P threads or
whatever the
the same thing as in Windows so the in
this environment what's gonna happen now
is that because we now we have full
control over what is we know what the
tasks are we know what threads we have
we can now do a better job and have an
easier understanding or a global view of
what elder frets are different doing or
doing what are the tasks are available
to us and then we now make scheduling
decisions on individual threads run the
process model we're sort of giving stuff
up to the OS and let us figure things
out so in my opinion the the
multi-threaded model is the way to go it
just from an engineering standpoint this
is easier to handle because not you're
not dealing with this
all these OS semantics for shared memory
or dealing with process management the
overhead I'm also doing a context switch
in this in a multi-threaded environment
is much lower if you still pay a penalty
when the OS switches from one thread to
the next and then the same process but
it's not as heavyweight as in a in a gun
from one process to another process
because of all the security and
protection mechanisms they need to have
or for the memory in memory
representation or in memory storage of
the process so in a I can't prove this
scientifically but in general a
multi-threaded process will be where a
davison will be faster than a
multi-process one so the thing to point
out though is just because we're going
to a multi-threaded process model
approach does not mean we're gonna get
automatically parallel query execution
in particular we may not necessarily get
intra query parallelism which I'll talk
about that in a few more slides meaning
like there is no guarantee that even
though our data systems can run with
multiple threads if I give it a single
query it can't break that query up
across multiple threads that run all
those in parallel so my sequel 5.7 is a
multi-threaded database system but it
can't do intro query parallelism this
might been fixed in eight I forgot the
check before today alright and for me
like my understanding what's out there
in a database world there's no database
system that I'm aware of that's been
built in the last ten years either from
an academic standpoint or from a
commercial like a startup enterprise
system there's no system that I'm aware
of that's gone to the multi-process
model
and less they're using a fork up
Postgres which is up to a very common
approach that everyone does like there's
a lot of Devi systems but they'll take
Postgres to bsd license so you can do
whatever you want with it and it's
actually pretty well written
compared to my sequel but you can then
rewrite the parts of Postgres that are
slow for your particular application and
and have that be your new database
system like Vertica greenplum time scale
all these all these do this and so what
happens is that they inherit the legacy
process model architecture up Postgres
if you go down this route but anybody
that starting from scratch for the new
code base is gonna almost always end up
being multi-threaded all right so the
other thing we briefly talked about
which we don't have time to go into
today is scheduling we all talk we've
told us a little bit about the you have
a dispatcher a coordinator can
understand what the tasks are that I
need to execute what resources or
workers are available to me and then it
can decide you know how many tasks to
split up a query into where you know
what CB course we XE do those tasks what
thread should pause for another thread
right and then once it produces the
output of a task where does that output
actually go all right all these things
we have to worry about if we want to do
in a parallel database system but you
know in general there's not one way
that's better than another it depends on
the environment you're working in
depends on what kind of target workload
you you want to support but as I said
multiple times throughout the semester
the database systems always been no
better than the OS so we can always make
better decisions about all these things
yes Sadie on this question is isn't it
the case that the for a given thread the
OS decides what court runs on No
this is called neumann control in arrow
test set in Linux you can have complete
control to know say my threads gonna run
on this core or these cores right the OS
won't force that for you if you don't do
anything then the the OS will try to
figure out like well you're accessing
memory and this you know state somewhat
Multi multi socket CPU gives to CPU
sockets and in the modern like numerous
systems a CPU socket has local memory
right the dims that are close to it so
if your thread is running here and
you're accessing memory on this other
socket the OS or the CPU could
automatically migrate you over but in a
high-end system we know exactly what
data were going to touch we can pin
ourselves ahead of time or force
ourselves and say all right we know we
have this thread running this core it
can only read memory read data from this
memory location so all tasks that touch
that memory location go there we can do
all that ourselves and we can do a
better job than the OS can do all right
so let's talk about quick parallel
queries so there's Cupid a two type of
parallelize we're going to support
there's inner query parallelism and
intra query parallelism so I'll go
through both of these but we're gonna
spend most of our time today talking
about this one right so inner query
peril ISM is that we can actually
multiple queries that are doing distinct
things at the same time and again this
is going to improve our throughput and
latency of our system and then for intro
carry payloads over to take one query
and break it up to subtasks or fragments
and run those in parallel on different
resources at the same time so again
inner query payload is what I've already
said the idea is that we have multiple
requests coming in from our application
and instead of running them one after
another on a single thread we're to have
multiple workers or multiple threads run
them simultaneously and then that way we
get a response more quickly to the you
know to the application with the result
they were looking for so if all the
queries we need to execute are read-only
meaning they're not doing insert update
or deletes they're just just doing
select statements then this is super
easy to do because there's no not gonna
be any conflicts there's not gonna be
any issues of you know I'm trying to
update the same hash table while you're
reading it everything just sort of works
very nicely so this is super easy but
this isn't always that common the thing
that's gonna be super hard for us is
that if we have multiple threads
updating the database at the same time
and now we got to worry about all the
concurrent row stuff we talked about for
the the B+ tree and the hash table but
now I just have to worry about this for
the actual data itself like you have two
queries try to update the same tuple at
the same time what should happen so
they're good news for you guys we're
gonna punt on this until after the
midterm because this is a whole
you know ball of wax we got to deal with
which is super hard and super awesome
and so we're gonna spend basically two
weeks discussing this in exhaustion and
this is the thing I'm super excited
about this is like there's one my
favorite part about database systems is
that they can do these these concurrent
operations at the same time but it's
super hard to do so we'll cover this
after the midterm all right so for this
class like I said we're focused on intro
query parallelism so this is gonna be
useful for for analytical queries where
we have multiple resources or multiple
workers available to us and we're gonna
split it up with these the query into
fragments or subtasks and run them in
parallel at the same time so for this
discussion here we're gonna focus on
compute parallelism meaning I have
multiple workers that have multiple
cores that are available to me I'm gonna
I'm gonna use them for the same query so
a way to think about how we're gonna
organize this is it is that in our query
query plan we have these operators we've
already discussed how they have this
next function that can move data you
know you ask next and it gives you back
a chunk of data or single tuple and so
we can think of that in terms of a gap
producer-consumer paradigm where each
operator is a not only a producer of
data like if you call a next on it I'll
produce some data for you but it's also
consume data potentially from some
operator running below it and so we can
think about how we're going to organize
in our query plan in this prehistory
customer model and we see how we can
then run these things in parallel in
different ways so the first thing I'll
say - for all the operator algorithms
that we talked about there are parallel
versions of all of them but they're
gonna differ based on whether you are
having multiple threads updating some
centralized data structure at the same
time like if I'm doing a joint hash
joint in parallel I could have multiple
threads update and build out my hash
table and then multiple threads could
probe that hash table or I could split
it up a partition my input data that I'm
consuming from my the the operators
below me and have them each work on
siloed or individualized
chunks of data or partitions of data and
then now I don't need to coordinate
across all across these different
workers running at the same time so the
conceptually this is pretty easy to
think about right so this is the same
it's the same hash drawing we talked
about before the partition of grace hash
to him and before what I said was we
would have this hash function on both
sides on the build or the enter in the
outer table and they would hash into
these buckets at these different levels
so now we wanted to do a join to combine
these these buckets we would just have
to have this you know we'd only have
examined the tuples in this level with
the tuples in the same level on the
other side because we sort of partition
this so in a way to run this in parallel
now is super easy we just have a single
worker just take its own level and now
do the joint I produce the output so you
can sort of see how we can do is for all
the different things that we talked
about before the sort merge join any
kind of special scan we can break it up
and and and divide the work up and have
them run in parallel the tricky thing
though is now putting this this data
back together and the different ways to
do that so that's what we're going to
focus on so the three types of intra
query parallelism could have is intra
operator parallelism also known as
horizontal parallelism intra inter
interoperate apparels I'm a vertical
parallelism and then bushy parallelism
which I think is in the textbook it's
just an extension of these other ones
but I think it's worth this to to show
you quickly what it is in case you see
it again and I'll say too is that for
all these approaches they're not
mutually exclusive meaning if you want
to run queries in parallel you know you
don't pick one of these three you can
actually do a combination of all of them
and this is what the data students can
figure out for you say all right my
harbor looks like this my data looks
like this my query looks like this I can
use some different combinations of these
techniques to get the best performance
you know for my workload so again let's
go through the each of these one by one
so in intra operator parallelism is
where we're gonna decompose the
operators into independent fragments and
each fragment is gonna do whatever it is
that the operator wants us to do on some
portion of our input data alright so if
I have a scan operator on a table I
could have multiple instances of that
scan running a separate fragments on
separate threads and they're each going
to scan a different portion of the table
and they're all gonna sort of funnel the
data up so the way we're gonna combine
this data now is to what is called an
exchange operator thus change operator
is a location in the query plan that the
the data system sort of injects
artificially like as it produces the
query plan that says all right here's
the points where I can have parallel pay
law fragments and here's the exchange
operand I need to be able to combine
their results together because I'm gonna
need a single stream or single data data
flow going up to the next operator so
the exchange operator was actually
invented by a the same guy that came up
the volcano iterator model from we
talked about last class quartz graphy
the same guy who did the B plus tree
paper or B but B plus tree book that I
was I was raving about but he has a
paper in 1889 8 1990 that presents this
exchange operator and this is pretty
much the same this this approach here is
what every single Davis is doing
parallel execution or even distribute
execution is doing something like this
although they may not always call it
exactly the exchange operator so let's
look at real a simple example here so we
have a single select statement select a
from from select start from a where a
top value is greater than 99 or 99 so
the query plan is super simple
sequential scan on a and we feed that
into our filter operator so to run this
in parallel which we do is we would
divide up now the the query plan across
different fragments or the scan with a
scan and the end the filter and then
we'll split the database up now which is
already you know in general it already
is because it's a it's already divided
up into pages and so what we can have
now within a given plan fragment we can
have it operate on a side the distinct
page so the exchange operator up above
is has its own next function just like
any other operator so if we're doing the
volcano mod or iterator model or we're
calling next and going down the exchange
operators say I call next on my operator
here which then calls next on the scan
and then now I'm gonna start beating up
data that I'm gonna retrieve from a
particular page and we do this for all
the other other fragments as well right
it's going to operate on its separate
pages
right and then the exchange operators
can coalesce that the the data it's
getting from these three different
fragments these three different workers
and then combined them to into a single
result that we then spit out as the
output to the application right because
the end result of the query always needs
to be a you know a single result we
can't say your data's over here here and
here because they had three different
workers we have to always produce a
single result yes engineers question is
how is exchange calling next year it's
calling them in parallel it knows I have
three fragments below me and therefore I
need to call next on all of them and it
fires them off in different workers yes
yes so his question is like if I call
next once here how's that been
percolating down to these other ones you
could have a coordinator up above and
say like I know I need to get data from
all these other guys and keep calling
the next one until they produce nothing
right so think it like the fragment here
this is running sort of separately right
and it's like a producer consumer this
thing is a secret of saying hey give me
some data and then they stick fires off
and goes and produces the result and
then something else they'll have to come
back to I go get more data yeah yes yeah
think of these are like almost like
streams right that were producing
results shoving up to the next guy and
depending on how its implemented this
thing could no I'm gonna keep shoving up
data until someone tells me to stop or I
can do it whenever I'm invoked different
systems do different things yes
this question is the call the fragments
like this part here is this in parallel
yes could you want them to run in
parallel like this right so like again
like this is it they're all getting
fired off in parallel they're all doing
work at the same time simultaneously on
different cores oh yeah so this question
is how do I make sure that they're not
reading the same page so as part of this
query planning here where there's two
ways to do this one you could say here's
the cue a bunch of work I need to do so
let's say that in this case here the the
first and second thread finished up
these pages and they say all right let
me go to the queueing if the next pages
I read right and that you just keep
doing that until you run out of pages
then you stop or you can you actually do
pre partitioning which we'll talk about
later on you could say well the the
first guy is gonna operate on 1 2 & 3
the second guy operating 4 5 & 6 and so
forth and that's just sort of blindly
grabbing different pages or you can
understand the semantics so actually
what's in the table and say well I want
to look at this is a small table so say
like I want to have one thread process
all the data where the values are less
than a thousand and then one process all
that potato or values less than 2,000
right and then they could be reading the
same page but now that is processing
different portions of the data there's
different ways to do all these things
the main takeaway what you have is
understand is like this exchange
operator is a way to coalesce or break
up the data further yes guarantee
wording on what
we don't well if the sort order matters
and you're clustered index on your
Taylor cluster table if if this were at
the order of how you process data
matters then you wouldn't want to do
this parallel stuff right because if I
can't like I can't process page two
until process page one is processed well
that's 0 threaded execution anyway so I
don't do any of this set up all these
threads cuz that's this waste of time
wait you know wasting resources to do
something you know I have one thing
block on another alright so the exchange
operator do was the basic one called the
gather and the basic idea is that we're
combining results from different from
different worker threads different
outputs that these operators are
generating and then we're going to
produce a single output stream that up
that we Hannah up above so again in my
last example here like this is the
output that we send to to the client
whoever invoked that query so that
always needs to be combined together
into a single output there are other
times where maybe you want to take a
bunch of output streams and then
reshuffle them based on what the data
looks like and then hand them out to
other worker threads now so let's say if
I'm doing the scan in parallel and I'm
going to divide about based on the range
of the values I can run the scan in
parallel and then put it through a
repartition exchange and then now had
that then be what's splitted up based on
the actual values that I'm seeing and
then the last one is to do distribute
where we have a single input stream that
then going to divide up and hand out two
different output streams so that could
be what we did for the the grace hash
join right when we started off with a
single input stream from our table we
built the hash table and now that spread
out the different levels of the hash
buckets to two different threads so for
there's parlance I'm using here so this
nomenclature this is actually what
sequel server uses because sequel server
explicitly shows you the exchange
operator in the query plan and their
documentation so for me this is the
easiest way to reason about it
Oracle db2 Postgres all the high end you
know
that support payal execution they all
have something that looks like exchange
and just may not use exactly this this
terminology but it hi another all it
works the same way yes right the
question is what is repartition so say
like say I had something about this in
my query plan that wanted to now do a
group by based on the values and so if I
if I this exchange pulls out a single
single stream then I'm gonna have one
worker thread do that group by but maybe
what instead what I could do is I could
then split up and say well if the value
is is is even go go this direction if
value is odd go that direction and now I
have a separate worker threads that can
do group eyes or those things I don't
need a coordinate because I'm doing
group by and then I have another
exchange above them that combines the
result to a single output it's a way I
take multiple streams and produce some
new other multiple screens but split up
in different ways
alright so let's look a little slightly
more complicated example here so now
we're doing a two way join between a and
B and so the first thing we want to do
is do this a scan and parallel so we'll
sign these two three different Brooker
threads and then inside our plan
fragment will actually do the you know
will do the scan do the filter and then
they'll build the hash table and this
hash table could either be a in this
case here it has to be a global hash
table because I don't know what values
are gonna be in the in the table as I'm
scanning them so if I put if I have
different hash tables for each for each
fragment then when I do a joint I gotta
check all the hash tables and that's
gonna be expensive that's gonna be slow
so these are all building the same hash
table but then I have exchange operator
that basically says why wait until they
all update my hash a when I'm done then
now to do the scan on B I can run that
maybe on two cores or took two worker
threads they just do the filter and now
they're going to partition and split up
the data and now they have their own
exchange operator and then now I have I
do the join and
could be a this could be either
single-threaded or I could do it
multi-threaded in this his carrot let's
make it multi-threaded so now I can
split up inside this after the join I
can have their different threads now do
the probe for the partitions over here
alright so you can see how you can
compose these things together we can
have these different workers generate
these these outputs that are then split
across multiple threads and then you can
find them together and split them back
up and you can compose them to this news
giant you know tree structure that can
now run in parallel all right so this is
intra operator parallelism again the
idea is that within a single operator
like a single scan on a I can have that
run in parallel in different fragments
in tour operator parallelism is where
we're going to have different operators
run in separate threads at the same time
right and this is also called vertical
parallelism because the idea is that we
can sort of for every single operator a
tree we could have them run as a
separate worker and there is feeding
data you know the output of one is fed
into the input of the other so basically
works like this so instead for the for
the join part here I could have one
Corps one worker just do the join right
it's just getting data from from its
from its children operators and then it
does the join and then as soon as it
doesn't join it emits it up into another
worker that just takes whatever this guy
sends it and then does the predicate or
does does the projection and then sends
that up further up in the query plan so
now these guys are just spinning alright
and digging this is the producer
consumer model this guy's spinning on
the input it's getting from guys below
it and then it hands off any tuple that
matches up to this guy we then spin the
waits for that so this is again this is
where the coordination stuff actually
matters a lot because if now if you know
if the number of tuples other things
gonna spit out it's gonna be really low
then this thing's basically gonna sit
for a long time and do nothing so now
I've assigned a task to a core it's not
gonna waste cycles because it comes to
block on whatever incoming queue is but
it's no it's taking up you know taking
up a task if you resources
would've been better just to combine
these two together and into a single
pipeline again I they're not new chicken
skewers I can do the horizontal and
vertical together I could have this join
be combined with you know be broken up
with vertical parallelism with with this
with the projection here but I could
have multiple workers all doing this at
the same time as well all right the last
one I'm talking about is bushy
parallelism again in my opinion this is
just an extension of inter operator
parallelism it's not something distinct
but again I think the textbook and other
other guys online talk about this so the
basic idea is that we just had different
workers operating on different portions
of the query plan at the same time and
we're still using exchange operators to
- as an interchange to move data between
them let's say I'm doing a really stupid
four-way join on three three tables so
what I could have is if I'm composed my
joint Algrim like this I could have this
portion of the query plan as a fragment
X you don't want on one worker and then
this these two joins over here execute
on another worker and they're just
running in parallel shoving data up into
our exchange operators all above and
then we have other workers operating on
that again this is why I'm saying it's
to me this is just an extension of the
inner operator parallelism because it's
just different portions of the the query
plan running at the same time yeah yes
question is do you that the third and
fourth words all workers up here do they
stop there is a weight to the result of
one or two yes in this case yes
it depends on gate well depends how the
exchange is set up right so any after
you do the join anything that this
generates out then it gets shoved up to
this guy it could start building the
hash table with people's a as it gets
out you could wait you don't need to be
don't have to depends how it's set up
yes
this one so this is one so the question
is where does the parallel where's the
parallelism here so I have one worker
that's running this the join have
another worker that's running the
projection so this thing's spinning and
doing doing the join and everything
they'll find it find the matches it
hands off the tuple as it as its output
hands it off to this guy who can then
now start doing the projection now
projections like super simple operations
so it's not that expensive but the idea
is that instead of having this thing do
to join then do the projection then go
back and do the next join while this
thing hands off to do the projection up
here it can go back and do the next one
question is like coming back here with
this hash there he says only one thread
can update hashing about the same time
no right because they're talking they're
accessing different pages I can do that
in parallel right so good so you can
either do every one upstate same hash
table or you can do the partition one
right and now like now you're doing
multiple stages so now I could have the
the first pass I mean it still you're
still accessing the same page though
like in the first pass it's alright
still accessing the same hash table but
like the first pass you have the
different threads update the different
buckets right but as you hash it but
then you may end up hashing you know two
threads might hash into the same bucket
then you have to deal with that that's
unavoidable then the next phase though
you can run a parallel but not have the
corn across any of them or alternatively
you could just do the you know one for I
could take a pass build out that the
hash buckets then you paralyze that
different systems do different things
if you assume your disk is super slow
and that not everything fits in memory
then having a single thread build the
hash-table
doing that first scan is probably the
better approach because that way the
you're just doing as much sequential i/o
as possible and the the disk head isn't
jumping around with an SSD you can do
multiple simultaneous requests so
therefore you could you do want to do
build a hash table mate in parallel yes
so I said is there any reason we're not
building the hash table and be here like
that's what sort of partition is like
partition is sort of breaking this up
dividing up and then multiple streams
now can do the probe so this is like
this is just breaking the data up didn't
different different save for partitions
it's like this is like the race hashed
one but we're still accessing a single
hash table yes which is what's in it
between the inner operator and the bush
you join so that's what I'm saying it to
me it's the same thing the definition of
bushi operator pushy parallelism is that
there's one part of the tree right since
turn bushy because it's so complete tree
this will make more sense when we talk
about joins next class but if there's
right deep left eat trees right but this
is like a bushy tree because I'm doing
joint joining two tables over here and
joining two tables over here so I can
have one thread do this joint over here
and another thought I do this joint over
there and I don't need a corner between
the two of them at this point up until
we get after the exchange so yes to me
this is the same thing as what I showed
here of the intraoperative parallelism
but figure is calling it bushy parallels
correct yeah yeah we're having one
operator be its own and worker this
approach you see a lot like this kind of
like every operator is its own worker
you see this a lot in like streaming
systems like spark streaming Apache
knife I've flank I bit or storm or Kafka
they have this is the architecture they
typically use but you can do it in
database systems are probably gonna be
do something more bushy because you want
to have a you know single
tasks you much work with the two boys
not just possible going up Friday as far
as you can up into the tree yes correct
yes this question is in this exchange
operator here for this one exchange it
could either be shoving data up into
this operator or into this operator how
do I decide so this is something that we
baked into the query plan you would say
you know here's I want to partition my
database on this attribute just do
round-robin just do hashing we'll talk a
little bit about this at the in the
class but there's some logic in here to
decide just they help you decide where
to wrap the data easy thing to do is
just round-robin
but actually for this particular example
you wouldn't want to do round-robin
because you need to know that there's
some tuple over here that's coming on
this side if it's gonna match for the
tube over here you want them to go to
the same partition not you know not not
different ones cause otherwise you'll
have false negatives yeah I should put
next I'll fix the slide to make that
more clear later okay so the right so
that that's it for compute parallelism
again at a high level the everyday
system that supports query parallelism
in different manners is going to support
exchange operator and in some some form
of it in how sophisticated they are
depends on how complex the system is the
the finger though that I mentioned is
that if we're running on slow disk and
all our threads are getting blocked
because the things they need aren't in
the buffer pool and we have to go to
disk and get them then all these extra
cores and all this extra exchange
operators we're doing is not going to
help us at all
because we're always going to be
bottleneck on doing that doing that
request and so the way to get around
this is through IO parallelism the basic
idea here is that we're going to break
up the database systems files and data
across different locations on own
storage devices and we can do this a
bunch of our ways we could have multiple
disparate database you can do it one day
to is per disk
we do 1-1 relation for discourse
ablation across multiple discs again
from the sequel standpoint from the
application standpoint we don't know we
don't care how this is all being set up
the Danny's doesn't hides all of us for
us it's quite discussed is this like
raid yes so who here is hurt has heard a
raid most of you okay so ray stands for
a redundant array of so I know what it
used to be call it I don't know what
it's called now it's redundant raid of
independent disks it used to be called
we're done a rate of inexpensive disks
and then the disk manufacturers one of
the use ray but didn't like Devine
calling in expensive because they wanted
to I think their products for being
cheap so they went back and had a change
to be independent you see the idea here
is that we can configure the system such
that multiple storage devices are going
to appear as a single logical device to
to the database system and we can do
this either through a special harbor
controller that's on our motherboard we
can do this through software itself like
the Linux kernel supports raid
configurations or we have like a storage
appliance that just provides this
functionality for us and we have a fast
interconnect direct to our system but
the main takeaway is that for the most
part for for the raid setup this is
gonna be completely independent to the
database system it doesn't know doesn't
care that the distance broke up to
multiple devices or the my storage is
broken all cross-multiply slits in this
case over here this is something that
database system manages and therefore it
can be smart and make decisions about
how its gonna plan its queries because
it knows how the data is actually being
laid out on different devices and it
notice the speed of those devices so
let's say we have a really simple
example here we have a database that has
six pages so this is an example of raid
zero it's just it's just called striping
so what happens is that as the data
system creates these pages and write to
them there's some RAID controller up in
here that then decides or you go here
you go there I decide them as a
round-robin approach which device to
write it to and it knows internally it
has its own metadata to say oh I need
page 1 I know it's on this disk let me
let me go get it
but again the data's in does it doesn't
know these things another most common
approach is to do
Mearing and basically that now every
single device has a complete copy of
every single page and do you have some a
racial coding or other other methods to
make sure that you know if one disk goes
goes down you can recreate it by it from
the other pages yes this question is is
Rea one end up being a bit slow for
writes yes for reads no cuz for reads I
can say alright well I assume I hover is
okay so I can go to any one of these and
now I could have one one thread reading
page one no threat reading page two on
separate devices and that's all fine for
the right I need to make sure that that
it's propagated across all of them that
makes that more expensive there's way
more this is like the most basic thing
you need about raid there's way more
complicated setups like raid 5 raid 1-0
but they can do you know combinations of
these different things yes round-robin
is just like like you're dealing cards
you just everybody gets one and then
when you reach the end you go back round
and do it all over again right I don't
know what the round rock I don't know
what the Robin stands for this like let
me play like kids growing up we play
games you round robin just you know hand
out things and in that order
yeah I really that's an American
colloquialism okay so the raid stuff we
just talked about that's all transparent
to the daily system the thing that we
can be smart about though is is the
partitioning stuff that we talk about a
little bit so far so the idea with
database partitioning is that we going
to be able to split the database up into
disjoint subsets that can then be
assigned to discrete disks and then what
happens is now the data systems buffer
pool manager knows that if I need to
read a page it knows what partition or
what disk location is going to have that
the data that is looking for so the
easiest way to do this kind of
partitioning if your database system
supports you know one database per one
file per database one directory for
database is that you're going to set ups
in links to to have the these different
directories point to different disks the
high end systems actually can know about
those different devices that can do that
mapping for you and you know and within
like a centralized location as
as an administrator but a quick and
dirty thing like for my Segal for
example is just move data around and
puts in links Get Set set up the law
file though is the tricky part
well talk about what a log file is later
on but that's basically the record of
all the changes we made
and that usually needs to be stored in
the centralized location but if you're
now if you have different devices and
you need to shard your log file that's
something a data system has to do for
you it's not something you can fake out
with a file system so let's quickly talk
about partitioning a little bit that'll
help understand how we're dividing up
the work for exchange operators and then
we'll spend more time talking about this
in distributed databases because this is
the key idea that they take advantage of
so the idea of partitioning is that we
want to take a single logical table and
then split up to disjoint subsets that
can then be stored and managed
separately on our different storage
devices and ideally we want our
partition to be transparent to the
application substances we'll let you
tell it how you want to partition things
all the systems will do it for you
automatically and we don't want to have
to have somebody be cognizant of when
they write a single query of where their
data is actually being located it's not
always the case in distributed databases
because you it's good it's good to be
it's good to know that if I'm running
during join between two tables and that
table one another's tables is in a
remote location maybe I don't want to
write that sequel query because that's
going to take me a long time to get the
data that I need to process it but in
general we don't want our end users to
have to be know anything about where the
data is actually being stored so there's
two approaches to partitioning there's
vertical partitioning and horizontal
partitioning horizontal partitioning is
what people are most familiar of if you
know about distributed databases you
know about sharding that's what
horizontal partitioning is vertical
partitioning is just the column store
stuff that we've already talked about
before so I have a table it has four
attributes so I could take this
attribute here and just store that in a
separate partition all right and a
separate file on a separate disk and
separate storage device and so what will
happen is if most of my queries only
need touch data over here and these
between three attributes things are
super fast because I'm just reading
exactly data than I need but anytime I
have a query that wants to combine these
two things just like in a column store I
got to go do fetches of these separate
locations
and stitch it back together to its
original form so some systems support
vertical partitioning as a way to sort
of approximate what a column store is
but it's not exactly the same because
the the systems that do this don't take
advantage of like you know these columns
are all the same values and give you
compression and have a you know the
query execution approach is can be
optimized or do operating on columns for
but this is sort of a halfway point to
get you some of the benefits of a column
store but not entirely the same thing
there again as I said the most common
approach is to do horizontal
partitioning and this is where we're
going to split up the table based on
some accurate sum value and so that all
the data for a single tuple will be
located together within a single
partition so now f f/a query says go get
me tuple one I go just this partition
and get it if I have another query says
go give me partition or tuple 3 I go to
this partition to get it and now I could
have multiple workers running in
parallel and both operating on these
different partitions at the same time so
now how you do this horizontal
partitioning can vary across these
different systems again we'll cover more
about this in when we talk about it
should be two databases right just to
finish up quickly so parallel execution
is important it's everywhere every
single major system is going to support
some variants of parallel execution and
whether that means running multiple
queries at the same time or taking one
query and dividing it up and how you
divide it up could be the entry operator
parallelism interoperate parallels and
the bushy stuff the things that are
super hard to get right are things that
we've covered out we covered so far in
the semester and we'll cover more later
on and going forward is how do we
coordinate multiple threads doing you
know operating on the same thing at the
same time without in any other two
incorrect results again we'll focus this
way more when we talk about transactions
to control but for read-only stuff this
is not that not that big of a deal all
right any high-level questions for the
parallel execution
this question is what is it between the
calm sort and vertical partition it's
like it's like a yeah but you still can
do that in a column store it's it's just
at a high level it's the same thing but
usually what happens is vertical
partitioning will be you can do this in
a row store system but you'll do this
but like when you actually process the
queries you're not doing it in a way
that's efficient for for a column store
like you may be still doing the iterator
model going one tuple at a time or you
don't compress this data because you
know it's all the same value it just
says I just tears my attributes you go
here you go there and then everything
else I'm a Bob still looks the same
your question is to partition so Nikki's
question is how do I figure out where to
buy this thing up you know this you know
that you know the schema is you know
that oh I want to partition I three four
I know for every tuple here's the offset
for it so I know exactly how to split it
up and move it over there you're not
gonna split this thing up in half
accidentally right you're doing this on
a per tubule basis you're not blind
knees taking a chunk of data I think of
this as continuous memory returns page
so I know how to jump to this offset for
tuple one we we stayed over here and do
the same thing for all the other ones
yes
it's question is is this user define or
is it something a date system can
automatically do this is typically user
defined there's no reason it couldn't be
automatic and so the high end systems
have tools to help with this but in
general this is user defined same thing
for this one here this is usually a user
defined but doesn't have to be alright
the midterm let's talk about that that's
fun right um so who needs to take it you
what are your to take midterm exam
when next Wednesday 12 o'clock in this
room and why this video will answer all
the questions in life okay so the exam
will cover everything up to and
including everything we talked about
today query execution part two it will
not include anything on query
optimization that we talk on Monday okay
if you need special accommodations
please contact me as soon as possible
some of you already done this and what
will take care of you and then there's a
if you go to this URL here this will
take you to the sort of it's the same
information I'm showing here a study
guide it'll also include a practice exam
aid with the solutions that I'll upload
later today later tonight I haven't done
that yet okay all right so what do you
need to bring your CMU ID you need to
bring a calculator right because if
you've done the homework so you know
that you have to do some basic logs to
compute the math and then you're allowed
to have a one eight by you know standard
eight and a half by eleven sheet of
paper handwritten notes double-sided no
taking the the slides you're cooking
with Alan super small everything has to
be handwritten and again you can use
both sides put anything you want on it
okay so this list keeps expanding every
year here's what not to bring first year
20 brought a live animal did you not do
that last year somebody brought their
wet laundry or two years ago there's a
wet laundry it was kind of weird he's
like oh oh you have laundry why you
bring this oh because I wash my clothes
I didn't time put the dryer I didn't
leave it there before the exam and so he
starts spreading out his clothes on
don't do that
last year this kid brought uh I knew
this existed it's like a it's like a
holy candle but it has Jennifer Lopez on
it
don't bring that he was internal AC like
I like the smell don't do that okay all
right so what do you need to know for
you need to understand the basis of the
relational model relational algebra we
focus on the integrity constraints what
does it mean for peb a foreign key what
does it mean to have a you know primary
key secondary key I some basic things
for sequel reality not going to ask you
to write raw sequel on on the exam
because that's the paymaster grade but
if we show you a sequel statement you
should understand what it does and what
it means right so the the more complex
operations were going to care about will
be the joins the aggregations and the
common table expressions you don't need
to worry about window functions CTE sub
queries and things like that for storage
we talked about different replacement
policies for for the buffer pool
management LRU mru and clock we talked
about different ways to represent the
the heap file or so the the disk file
this is you can either gonna be table
heaps or the linked list and then for
the page layout it can be either the
slotted pages or the log structured and
again this would be like high-level
questions about the implications of one
versus the other not like you know draw
me a diagram of what a log structure
page looks like or what I want a slotted
page looks like for our hash demos we
talked about with static hashing and
dynamic hashing schemes so we talked
about the linear program hashing with
the Robinhood hashing and the cuckoo
hashing what are the what are the
implications of these why is one better
than other what problem they trying to
solve right are they better for reads or
writes dynamic hashing schemes
extendable hashing linear hashing and
then bucket hashing should be in there
as well I'll fix that right look if why
would you want to use one of these
versus another when would you want to
use one and then join when when would
you want to use one for an index like
high level questions about these things
we talked a lot about tree indexes in
particularly the B+ tree how to do
insertions deletions and we'll split
some merges the difference between a B+
tree and a B tree again what are the
performance implications of that in a
disk or in a database system where
everything may not fit in memory how did
you latch crabbing and coupling and how
to do
reversal or scans along leaf nodes right
how to deal with deadlocks and we talked
a little bit about radix trees or suffix
trees again will ask you high-level
questions not like you know draw me an
exact diagram of something for sorting
we talked about different algorithms
that the external to external merge sort
and the general merge sort so understand
the cost if I give you a bunch of buffer
pages that give you a bunch of data
pages what is the cost of doing that
sort for the joins the different
variants of them abnesti loop join the
submarine hash join again what are the
cost of doing these joins one is one
better than other one of extreme cases
like if everything is all the same value
which one would be better than another
right how do we do multiple keys or
composite keys and who joins in these
things and then the thing we finished up
today would be the processing models
what are the advantages and
disadvantages of the iterator model
versus the mid-tier lights model versus
the vectorized model top-down versus
bottom-up and what the different
advantages are different approaches of
doing parallel query execution
interoperate or parallelism inter
operator parallelism and the pusher
parallelism
ok any questions about the midterm yes
this question is it this question is
what do you think this question is are
we responsible or any signal C++ code
what do you think the answer is right
because I how am I gonna grade that
right run for it like 90-something kids
run that through a compiler I'm not
doing that not that cruel okay any other
questions yes do I write in person
that's what moms do you read it No yes
I'll try to put the sample up later
tonight yeah okay and what do you need
to bring CMU IDE calculator if you need
it not your phone like a regular
standalone calculator and a one in a pie
lab mashite of handwritten notes you can
use both sides what not to bring live
animals candles wet laundry you can
bring food if you want I don't care all
right next class we're talk about query
plan according opposition now
so we're putting it all together and
we'll see how to do that okay guys see
you on Monday
[Music]
ricochet jelly hit the deli for one
naturally bless the bottle of I don't
drink it only to you can't say don't
know your phone can a pain