Oh guys let's start it what the
president again Thank You DJ drop tables
or keeps keeping everything for us
alright so before we get into today's
lecture just go through real quickly
what's on the schedule for you guys
coming up in the next two weeks so
homework three is out today it should be
on the website well we'll set up great
scripts so you can submit later today
and so that'll be due next week on
Wednesday the 9th in two weeks we will
have the the midterm exam project tubes
going out today
so I'll talk about a little I'll talk
about that at the end of this miss
lecture but that'll be due after the
midterm the midterm will be on Wednesday
the 16th in this room at the normal
class time it'll be you know an hour and
20 minute exam so this will cover
everything up to and including next
week's lectures so on Wednesday the 9th
the midterm will cover that lecture and
everything prior to that ok any
questions about any of these
expectations so homework number three
knock that out before the midterm and
then this thing project two it'll
encompass some of the material that we
talked about that'll be relevant to the
midterm but it won't we do officially
until after after the midterm so you
space space things out for you guys okay
okay so where we're at now in the
semester is that we've again going up to
this architecture layers we know how to
store things on disk in pages we know
how to then copy them into memory into
our buffer pool manager as needed then
we talked about how we actually access
them so we can build indexes on top of
them or we can do sequential scans and
so now where we're at is up above now we
actually want to start executing queries
we actually want to be able to take
sequel queries generate query plans for
them and then have them use the access
methods to get access to the data that
we need okay so for the next two weeks
we're going to first talk about how what
how we actually implement the algorithms
for our operators and our
then we'll talk about different ways to
process queries themselves like it's the
how to remove data from one operator to
the next and then we'll talk about also
to the more system architecture was the
runtime architecture of the system for
threads or processes and how do we
organize them to run you know queries in
parallel so I'm not gonna go into detail
what a query plan looks like just yet I
just want to show you what one
potentially looks like just to frame
that a conversation where we're going
today and the next class and then we'll
go into way more detail about what query
plan and execution looks like next week
and then when we talk about query
optimization query planning further so a
query planet is essentially the the
instructions or the high-level direction
of how the database system is going to
execute a given query and we're gonna
organize the query plan into an in a
tree tree structure or an acyclic
directed graph so we take the sequel
query like this or doing a join with a
filter on table a and B we can represent
it as a query plan like this where at
the leaf nodes we're doing our scans or
accessing the the tables and then we
were moving tuples up to the next
operator to do whatever it wants to do
so in this case here we scan a and since
we don't have any filter on it we just
feed it right into our joint operator
and then for the scan on B well first
apply the filter to limit out any values
less than F at 100 and then we feed that
into our join operator and then this now
produces some output that's then fed
into the projection operator so what I'm
showing here is what what we call it as
a logical plan meaning I'm not saying
anything about how we're what albs are
we're gonna use to implement all these
different operators I'm just saying this
is at a high low what I want to do is
the most like a direct translation of
the relational algebra I want to do a
join I'm not telling you how I want what
to do to join us I just want to do one
on a and B I want to get to pull some a
I didn't tell you whether to do scruncho
scan or index scan I'm just saying just
get tuples from a so what we're focusing
on today is now to talk about what these
algorithms actually are and then we'll
put it all together when we talk about
query planning query optimization to say
now we need to make a decision of here
the different choices of algorithms I
could use or different access methods I
could use for my query which
is gonna be the best for me so today's
lecture is really focusing on
and-and-and and for Wednesday's lecture
as well for this week what are the
different algorithms we can implement
for the physical operators in our query
plan but at a high level we're assuming
that it's in this tree structure where
we're moving two bulls one Operator to
the next so this Clara hi this is
essentially what what you know what any
any query engine is going to do right
they're gonna represent as a treat as a
dataflow tree and they moving tuples
between them so the tricky thing though
now that for us when we start deciding
what we know how do we actually
implement the algorithms for these
operators is that again we this entire
semester is focusing on the system
that's assuming that data doesn't fit
entirely in memory so just like within
our disk or new database system just
like we can't assume that tables fit
entirely memory where indexes can't fit
tiredly memory we now need to be worried
about that the intermediate results
between those operators cannot actually
fit entirely in main memory so therefore
when we design the algorithms we're
going to use to execute you know the
operator we need we need to pick ones
that actually know how to write data at
the disk and be mindful that we may have
to read and write data from disk and
therefore we'll make certain design
decision in those algorithms to to
accommodate them right so just as a
quick example I'm doing a joint here on
a and B the hash table or depending what
you know what what joint album I'm going
to use I may have to spill the disk like
a doesn't fit in memory B doesn't fit in
memory so I need to join algorithm that
can handle you know inputs where the
entire data set may not fit in memory
furthermore the output also may not fit
entirely main memory so again we're
gonna use our buffer pool manager that
we built in the first project we talked
about before that's how we're gonna be
able to accommodate algorithms that need
more memory than is actually available
so we're not using for tables not using
it for for for indexes we can use it for
intermediate results and this again goes
back to why I was saying before this is
why the you know if the database system
ends just a memory instead of letting
the OS do it the OS can oh oh this page
is for an ephemeral data structure to do
whatever my query is and I'm gonna throw
immediately after the queries over and
maybe I want to do different things or
have different replacement policies or
different strategies for those kind of
pages and those kind of data versus the
data coming from from the underlying
tables whereas the OS doesn't see that
it always doesn't know anything about
what's inside these pages or how they're
being used so again we're gonna use our
puffle manager Bureau of scope Islands a
disk and therefore we're gonna design
algorithms of prefer algorithms they're
gonna maximize the amount of sequential
i/o that we can do and this is gonna be
different than any algorithms course
you've taken potentially before where
you assume that you're just reading
writing into memory and everything has
uniform access and now we need be
mindful of what's actually in memory
when we design these approaches so we're
gonna first start off talking about the
external merge sort algorithm and what
will come out of this discussion you
will see some high-level strategies for
essentially doing divide and conquer
that allow us to then that we can apply
to other methods or other operators we
want to implement and then we'll finish
up talking about how to do aggregations
which can rely on sorting algorithm but
then it also sort of Segway and into the
joint album stuff we talked about next
week about hash joins so there's sort of
this trade-off between sorting versus
hashing as the two different methods you
can used to exude algorithms in your
database system we're going to first
talk about sorting and then we'll add in
hashing at the end okay all right so
it's sort of obvious that you know why
we need to sort but just make sure that
everyone puts this in the correct
context the in relational model the
tuples in our relations are inherently
unsorted right it's set algebra there's
no sort order so we can't assume that
the the data as we read them is gonna in
any one particular order now there's
clustering indexes that we talked about
before it was talked about again today
which then you know provide you a
enforces of sort order based on some
index but in general we can't assume
that's always gonna be the case and
furthermore we could have an index our
table could be clustered on one
particular key but now we need to sort
it on another key so that you know being
pre-sorted doesn't actually help us in
that scenario
so in addition to also now being able to
you know someone calls an order by and
we want to sort the output we if our
data is sorted there's a bunch of other
optimizations we can do for other
utility things we want to do or queries
we want to execute in our database
system so if our table is sorted or
outputs or keys are sorted then it's
really easy to do duplicate elimination
because now I just scan through the
table once and if I see that's the thing
I'm looking at is the same as when I saw
the last thing I looked at that I know
is a duplicate and I just throw it away
for group eyes this is the same thing I
can if everything is pre-sorted then I
can generate the aggregations by just
scanning through the table once and
computing the running totals as needed
and then we talked about optimization of
doing bulk so bulk loading in a P plus
tree where you pre sort all the data
along the leaf nodes and then you build
the index from the from the bottom up
rather than top down and that's way more
efficient so again sorting is a as a as
a useful utility operation grid need in
our database system but we need to be
able to accommodate one where we doesn't
fit entirely in memory because it fits
in memory then we just pick whatever
your favorite sorting algorithm that you
you know and love from your intro
classes and that works just fine for us
quicksort heapsort
if you crazy bubble sort right but we
don't care it's in memory so all the
things that we learned before in intro
to albums class work just fine but then
the issues now if it doesn't fit in
memory quick sorts can be terrible for
us because what does quicksort doing
quicksort is doing bunch of random
pivots jumping around to memory in
different locations that's random i/o
and our role because those pages we're
jumping into may not actually fit in
memory and the worst case scenario we're
having one IO cost per you know per
change to the the data set so instead we
want an algorithm that is mindful of the
potential cost of reading writing dated
disk and therefore make certain the
design decisions that try to maximize
the amount of squinch IO sequential i/o
even on faster SSDs is to be more
efficient than than random i/o because
you can bring a lot more data in with a
single and there's no seek in an SSD but
within a single you know
with a single read operation or write
operation down into the device you can
get more data coming back right so the
I'm going to use and and at a high level
this is what every is what every single
database and does that supports atom
memory sorting is a called the external
merge sort alright sometimes it's a you
seek external sort merge and it be
really confusing because they'll be
there's the external merge sort
algorithm and then we'll see a sort
merge join which could use the merge
sort algorithm right but I'll try to
make it more clear when we talk about
joins what we're actually doing so as I
said this is a divide and conquer
approach where we're gonna basically
split the data set that we want to sort
up into these smaller chunks called runs
and then we're going to sort those runs
individually write all the keys within a
given run or are sorted and this the
runs are disjoint subsets of the entire
Keys that we want to sort and so then
we're gonna sort these little these
little runs and then we're gonna start
combining them together to create create
larger sorted runs and we keep doing
this and doing this until we get the
full data set the full key set that we
want sorted so there's two phases for
this so the first phase again we're
gonna take as many blocks as we can fit
in memory sort them and then write them
back out the disk then in the second
phase again that's when you go combine
these sub sort sorted runs into larger
sort of runs and then write them out and
you keep doing this over and over until
you have the entire things sorted so
this is gonna end to end up taking
potentially multiple passes through the
data set that we're trying to sort but
in the end we end up with a complete
sort of run so let's start with a simple
example called a 2-way merge sort it's a
2-way means that were where the number
two is that it's the number of sort of
runs we're gonna merge together for
every single pass alright so within a
pass we're gonna go grab two runs merge
them together and produce a new path a
new run that's that's the combination of
the two smaller ones that were our input
so our data set is gonna be broken up
into n pages and then what's now
important for us when we consider what
how algorithms going to work is that we
need to know how much memory is
available
to us to buffer things in memory to do
our sorting because again if everything
fits in memory then we don't need to do
any of this we just do quicksort but we
need to be told ahead of time how much
memory we're allowed to use for sorting
and this is actually something you can
configure in database systems so in
Postgres it's called working memory
you basically say how much memory the
one particularly is allowed to use for
whatever kind of intermediate operation
wants to do building a hash table doing
sorting and other things like that so
we're told this we're always told this
be ahead of time so let's look at sort
of visual examples so in past 0 you're
gonna read every B pages from the table
into memory and then you're gonna sort
them in place in memory and then write
them out so let's really say for example
I have a disk on disk I have my data set
I have two pages so let's say this case
here I can only have I can I can bring
in the first page sort that in place and
now that's a sort of run and then I
write that sort of run out the disk and
I'm gonna do this one at a time assuming
I must have a single thread I'm gonna do
this one at a time for all my other
pages right so now so this is sort of
step one and then now we're here I'm
reading the other page I bring that into
memory sort it and then I write that out
so now that's the end of past zero that
I've taken all the the my sort of runs
sorry all my my I grab a run that's the
size of B pages I sort that in memory
because IB pages I'm allowed to use a
memory so I'm sorting that in place and
then I'm writing it back out and then I
go to the next run once after that's
done so now in the subsequent passes
we're going to recur submerges of all
the runs we sorted so far and we're
gonna combine them together to produce
runs that are double the size of my
input right and so for this approach I
need I need at least three buffer pages
because I need to have one to buffer
pages for each of the two runs that I'm
bringing into memory and then another
buffer page for the output that I'm
writing out so in this case here I could
say I want to sort these these that you
sorta guys so I bring those in memory
and now I have one other page where I
can write out the the combination of
these two guys but I you know this is
two pages long but I only have one page
so I'm just gonna scan through each of
these and compare them one by one to see
which one is greater than the other
sorry which was less than the other
depending what order you're going and
then I just write that out into a sorted
page like this and then once that's full
then I write that out the disk and then
my merging continues where I keep going
down think of leagues - cursors are
scanning through these guys comparing
them one by one then I continue down
with the other data set and I write that
write that page out and then once I've
reached the end then I have then I'm
done this is this clip yes so her
question is if if the memory in this
case here memory can hold three pages
why not is do exactly what I just did
here first
yeah you could think of like and then
this is sort of simple example you can
think of like I could bring I could
bring the two sort of pages unsorted
pages in memory sort them in place then
do the combination without having to
write them back out of the disk yes but
in general that's like that
this is a trilogy upon general that's
not you can't do that this is also sort
of oversimplification to because think
of these are like the data pages of the
tuple or the table right there these up
tuples in them you're actually really
can't kind of do this the the in-place
sorting like this because that would be
modifying the actual table itself and
you don't want to do that so in general
usually like you're not going to do this
one step here where I was sorting them
in place
you'd make another copy and then write
that out so in that case that wouldn't
work because you would need you would
need at most four pages in memory okay
so so this is sort again this is a sort
of a simplification but looks like you
work through the math now see what
actually what happens so let's go
through a more a more fine-grain example
here so the way the math works out is
the number of passes we need for this
two-way merge sort is 1 plus the ceiling
of log 2n right and the first one here
the one that's 4
that's for the first pass and then the
log 2n is is as you as you keep dividing
up the in each pass you're sort of
getting a larger and larger runs until
you reach the total size of the data set
right the last pass the two runs that
you're sorting will will be you know at
most half the size of the total data
data set so the total ioio calls to
joining sure number sword is 2m times
the number of passes and this is 2n
because I always have to read it in and
write it out right for every pass it's
one read in and then one right out so
and means also in every pass at most I'm
reading I'm reading and writing every
record every key that I'm trying to sort
exactly once once in and once back out
so let's look at an example like this
alright so we have a bunch of pages and
each page we have two keys in them so
yeah and then this little marker to say
here's the end of file so in the first
pass we're just gonna read in every page
sort it and then write it back out so
we're not examining data across
different pages or these are actually
runs but it's it's a one page run then
in the next pass I'm gonna go grab two
to two sort of runs that are next to
each other bring them to memory sort
them globally within within the two
pages and then write those guys out so
in this case here the output of the
second pass will be runs of size two
pages
and then I do this keep is going down
second page now I have four rot four
page runs and the last one I have an
eight page run and then here point I'm
done because now my output run is the
total size of of the number of keys that
I have okay so what I've shown you so
far all right for the two a merge sort
as I said it only requires three buffer
pages two for the input one for the
output so back going back here when I
was creating this this you know now
creating a run that's two pages actually
use this example so now I'm creating a
run that has four pages I can only have
three pages in memory all right so I
have I'm gonna have one for the the
right side or the left side one for the
right side so again you think I'll just
have a cursor I'm just scanning through
each of the pages on the two sides and
then compare to see whether one is
greater than the other and if the one is
less than the other then that's what I
write out to my output and then move
that cursor down and then I do the same
comparison right so I keep going
step by step until I reach the end the
cursor reach to the ends of both of them
yes a question is and what is my what am
i showing here are these numbers
consider tuples yes
I'm showing the simplification their
keys but in actuality in a real system
you'd have like the key you trying to
sort on and then the record idea where
it came from
yes in this example here each square is
a page right but I'm there's only two
keys in the page for simplicity yeah
okay so again for this example here we
only have we only need two pages but the
problem is say I said I'll give you more
pages and what I'm showing so far you're
not actually gonna get any better right
why he's right the i/o remains the same
because what am i doing I'm going
fetching two pages and then I have this
cursor it's gonna walk through them and
then whatever one has the you has the
lower key that gets written out to the
third page having more pages in memory
doesn't really help us because you know
eventually I'm only can doing comparison
you know two pages at a time so a really
simple optimization to to minimize this
this this i/o cost is to do prefetching
so this technique is called double
buffering the idea is that when you go
and start merging say two other pages
you have a bunch of shadow pages or
shadow buffers where you start fetching
in the the next runs you need to sort or
the next pages you need to sort so it
requires you to have deuce asynchronous
i/o to have something in the background
go and fetch the the next pages you're
going to need so that when the cursor
reads that reaches the end of the
current page that's operating on the
next page that it needs is there if it's
single threaded and every everything
synchronous then you have this ping-pong
effect where I'm gonna be CPU bound and
disk bound and CPU bound the disk bound
because I'm gonna bring the page in and
wait for that then do my sorting that's
all CPU then I'm done that doing that
sorting or done doing the merging and
now I have to get to the next page and
I'm I'm blocked on that right so really
simple example here I want to sort one
and then while I'm doing that in the
background I go fetch page two and then
by the time I'm sorting this one then
when that's done then when this guy's
ready to go for me
okay right so this is this you know the
to a merge sort is a sort of most simple
way to consider this we need to consider
that what how this works with a general
you know general anyway sort or k way
sort yes sorry so this question is how
do you how do you do this optimization
here how do you can have the thread
student sorting while on the background
there's it's going fetching data well
this is actually the operating system
helps us right so we make a request from
the operating system go read this for us
and then there has another thread that's
called any synchronous i/o in the
background it goes fetch the data we
need we tell it where we're to put it
and then that way I through I can do all
the computation as well actually the
data says we can do this well you
actually don't need the OS in a real
system you would have like a IO
dispatcher thread so you say I want this
request get me this page and then give
me you know here's a call up to tell me
when it's actually ready then it goes
and does that your thread can do
whatever computation at once and then
when it's done it's available for you
yeah yeah they have two threads yeah
okay so let's quickly go over how to
generalize this algorithm beyond just
having just do two you know standard two
ways sort so with the general K way sort
it's still the same we're to use remai
be buffer pools and then in the first
pass we're gonna produce and divide it
be the ceiling of that sort of runs of
size B because that's what we're doing
the in-place sorting and then in the
subsequent passes we're gonna do we're
gonna generate B minus one runs at a
time right and it's always minus one
because we always need one buffer for
the output having additional output
buffers doesn't help us because you
really only write to one with one thread
but only write the one output buffer at
a time so that's why it's B minus one so
the way the math works out is just an
extension of what we showed before we're
set up now saying log 2n or law to it's
log B minus one and then you take the
ceiling of n divided by B but still the
the i/o cost is two n times the number
passes
so this is very plugging chuggy you'll
see this when you do the homework right
you fill in the bees fill in the ends
and the numbers work out so let's just
walk through a really quick example here
so we're gonna sort 108 pages with with
five five buffers pages we can use 2n
equals 108 P equals five so in the first
pass write the the amount of i/o that
we're going to do is we're trying to
compute how many runs we're going to
generate so it's the ceiling of 108
divided by five so that's gonna generate
two twenty three sort of runs of five
pages each right and then the last page
the last run is only three pages so
that's why you have to take the ceiling
right because you don't want a
fractional cost and then going down in
the subsequent passes now you're taking
the the number of runs you want you
generate at the previous pass and
dividing that by the number of the size
of the run you're going to generate
before right so now it was two now it's
four so this generates six sort of runs
of twenty pages where the last page is
the last run is only eight pages and
then just sort of going down just keep
applying over and over again until you
reach the very end where you have now a
the data set is exactly the same size as
the original one yes these questions are
assuming here this sort of done in place
for the first pass yes for the
subsequent passes now but as if this is
what the textbook does in a real system
you wouldn't do that because again the
the depending on how where you're
reading the data from it could if it's
coming directly from the table itself
then you can't modify that if it's
coming from another operator then you
can do that yes yeah the -1 close it
because you always have the one one
buffer page for the output yeah so yeah
indeed in the general case it was three
right good one whatever it's two for the
input one for the upload yeah
this question is why am I using five
here so you're sorting yes sorry it
makes it so before I was sorting two
runs at a time this is now sorting
multiple runs at a time right so I'm so
say with B equals five I bought five
buffer pages so for each of the sort of
runs I'm gonna five sort of runs I'm
gonna try to merge at the same time and
again all I need to do is just have a
cursor sit at each one and walk through
them one by one and just do a comparison
across all that and say which one is the
which one is the smallest write that out
and then now we have four cursors and
one applet yes yeah I should visualize
that sorry again this wife record Excel
remember to do that next year or is this
clear okay so that's external merge sort
they said this is this is the exact
details of how you actually implement
this will vary from system to system
there's obviously some other
optimizations we can think about like
some hints to say oh I know the min
value of the max value if my sort of run
is is this an that and my min max value
for this other sort of run is that so
therefore if I know that the the min
value is is greater than the max value
this other sort of run I don't need to
do the merge I disappear on top of Java
right so there's some optimizations you
can do like that but in general what
I've shown here today is works you know
works well for for for most data sets
assuming uniform distribution of the
values there's no sort of there's no
locality to enter the data it's just
completely random this works fine if you
know that something more about my your
data like it's skewed in a certain way
then you can apply some simple
techniques to speed this thing up but
this is what I've shown today is just
like the pickup truck version of it a
general-purpose version of it so
instead of actually just doing the sort
of brute first brute force mergesort
that I showed here sure now
there may be some cases where we can
actually use the B plus tree to speed up
our sorting operation so in general the
sorting and joint algorithms those are
actually the most expensive things to do
oh so if there's any way we can speed
these things up this is always gonna be
a good choice for us so what did the B
plus tree essentially doing well it's
maintaining the sort order for our keys
in the data structure so we're paying
you know the penalty to maintain update
do splits emerges as needed on our B
plus tree as the table gets modified but
now we can then possibly piggyback off
of that work we've already done to speed
up by sorting but not having to do
sorting at all so if our sorting
operation that we need if the keys we
want to sort on are the same keys that
are B plus tree is indexed on then we
can potentially just reuse the B plus
tree and not go through that whole looks
from merge sort and with multiple passes
that I just showed but it only works if
we have a cluster B plus tree again we
showed an example of that I think two
classes ago but now we showed it more
visual cable what actually is going on
and you'll see why this makes sense for
sorting but not for the uncluttered one
so the clustered B plus tree a clustered
index just means that the the sort order
or the physical location of the tuples
on our pages will match the sort order
defined in the index so if I have a
index on key foo then along my pages
will be the the the tuples we sorted in
pages based based on that order of foo
so now if I want to do a sort on that
key I don't need to do external merge
sort because all I need to do is is get
down to my leaf pages and IB plus tree
because now the the sort order of the
key will match the sort order of the of
how the data is B is found
so I don't need you any extra
computation to to go sort it it's
already sorted for me
so this again this is another example
where the database system the query
planner that we'll talk about after the
midterm or the class before the midterm
the the query optimizer can figure out
oh you want to do a sort on this key I
already have a clustered index on that
key let me go use that to generate the
corrects whole order and not even bother
running external merge sort but as we
saw in the case of Postgres they can't
they don't enforce this you tell me I
want a complete cluster on an index on a
given key they're not gonna maintain
that's what ordering other systems will
do this so now if you have an
uncluttered index on custom P plus
trading this is actually the worst
possible thing to use for trying to
generate a sort order and we think I
guess why it should be obvious what's
that
great you have one eye open record so
again I traverse the index to be gentle
to the left side of the tree and I want
scan across and because that's how my my
keys are sorted but the data has no
connection to how it's being sorted in
the index so for every single record I
got to go get and generate as my output
I may be doing another disk i/o because
the page I need is not in memory I go to
disco get it bring my brother poll and
then now that very next key it I look at
is in another page and it's a victim one
I just brought in and bring him the next
one yes the question is what does it
mean for tree to be you wouldn't say it
is a you don't say the trees clustered
the tables clustered again I wouldn't
call it that like if I was writing you
know coming with those terms I would
call it oh it's a sorted table for
whatever reason they call it a cluster
table right because it's basically the
the tuples that are that are similar to
each other
are clustered together on the page right
so again back here this the sort order
of the how the two was actually being
stored matches the sort order the key so
this is this would be a clustered index
all right all right
in this case here we just call create
index this is what you normally get the
or just you know the actual where the
records actually being sword has no
relation to how they're being sorted
questions what is the information in the
tree it's just the B+ tree we talked
about before right so create index on on
on key foo so to build that index I'm
doing special scan looking at every
single tuple getting their value of foo
inserting that into my tree and the key
value pair is the value of fee of foo
and then the the value is the record I
need a pointer to the tuple all right
this is different than the index
organized indexes or any index organized
tables we talked about where the two
will pages are actually in the leaf
nodes themselves in that case that is a
clustered index but it's also in its
organized table this is like if there's
they're not you're not storing the data
in the leaf nodes themselves if it's
disconnected then it's either cluster
yeah so David is instead of actually
every single time I encounter a key
immediately go fetch it what if I get
all the keys that I need and their
record IDs and then now do combine the
lookup so that I get all the ones from
page 101 first and all the ones on page
one or two yes there we'll talk about
two weeks or next week right
four scans that's a common optimization
but that assumes that you can fit like
the yeah the key set and there are some
algorithms where you actually can start
producing outputs sooner rather than
later
this is like an all-or-nothing this is
like what I've shown so far is I'm gonna
get all you know this operator asked me
to get this data in sort of order so I'm
gonna get it all now and then I don't
move on to the next operator until I get
everything there are some streaming
operators where you could say all right
to start streaming data out as you get
it because I'd rather have it sooner
rather than
like there's other optimizations that I
can do up in the tree so in that case
you're you know your best approach won't
work won't work in that environment but
that that is a common opposition we'll
see this in like next week okay all
right so again the main takeaway of this
is if it's a cluster index and and the
query needs it to be sorted on the key
that the index is based on then you just
you just use the clustered index if it's
not a clustered index then you just
almost never want to use it all right so
that's basically it for discussing
sorting so let's talk about do some
other operations so imitator we're now
going to focus on aggregations because
for aggregations is another good is
another good example of or it is an
example of a type of operator where we
can make you a choice between sorting
versus hashing as our for our algorithm
and then have different trade-offs and
have different performance
characteristics because one is
essentially you know trying to do a lot
of switch will access someone's trying
to do random access so maybe certain
scenarios where one might be better than
another in general as a spoiler what
I'll say is that and no one was always
in the case no matter how fast the disk
is oftentimes the the hashing approach
will work better and we'll see an
example of how we can actually make the
hashing aggregation do more sequential
i/o rather than random i/o all right so
if you take the advanced class in the
spring this is another big thing too is
like hashing always works super fast
because everything is in memory all
right so how would you use sorting do an
aggregation well again what does an
aggregation doing you're basically
taking a bunch of values and you're
coalescing them to produce a single
scalar value so with sorting the nice
thing about it is that because the data
is sorted as I said when we take a pass
now through the sorted output we don't
have to backtrack to computer
aggregation and we only do one pass to
find to compute whatever the answer it
is that we want so let's see a real
simple query here we want to do it we're
doing we're doing a scan on the enrolled
table all right
students rolled in the classes the
database classes at CMU and we would we
always want to get the all the distinct
course IDs from any class where a
student either got a B or C in it and we
want the output to be sorted based on
the course ID so the very first thing
we're going to do in our query plan tree
is do the filter so we're gonna first
filter out all the tuples where the
grade is not B or C then the next step
we're going to do is remove all the
columns we don't need in our output
right we only need the course ID we only
need the course ID to do the order by
and for the stink clause because for our
filter it access the grade table at that
point we know in our query plan we don't
need to ever look at the great the great
column anymore we don't need to look up
a student ID anymore so if we can strip
all that out before we move on to the
next operator and then we finish off now
by sorting on sample column here and
because we're doing a distinct
aggregation or distinct clause we want
to remove any duplicate values so all we
need to do is just have our cursor scan
through this and any time it finds a
value where that was same same as the
one I just looked at that knows it can
throw it away and strip that out and
that's our final output so we'll go into
this more next week when we talk about
query planning but just one obvious
thing during this in this pipeline we
make students query that I did was I try
to strip out as much useless data as
possible sooner in my in my pipeline
rather than later so the very first
thing I did was the filter so say you
know say this table had a billion
records in it but only five of them
match or for them match for my predicate
so rather than me sorting a billion
records first then going back and
filtering it it was better for me to
filter it first then move that movie to
move the data on to the next operators
same thing for the projection right this
is a row stored it's not a column store
in my example so in order for me to go
get the data I need to do you know
whatever the sorting I want to do I
gotta go get the entire I mean the
entire record because that's gonna be
packed together in a single page but if
I can do a projection
you strip out all the columns I don't
need or the attributes they don't need
and then now when I'm doing my sorting
I'm not copying around a bunch of extra
data so my sort of sort of simple
examples and was related to her question
the you know what a might be actually
passing around it could be the record ID
it could actually be the entire tuple
itself depending on how I want to
materialize things so the projection
here allows me to throw away coms I
don't need so now when I'm when I'm
doing my sorting I'm I'm only you know
I'm copying things that just related to
what's needed for the rest of the query
plan yes so his question is I mean it's
not really this query you're talking
like a count query so this question is
the the grey column is has a fixed
domain meaning it's a B C D or E I don't
think see me as s does it you have an
completes right but it's fixed oh
there's another one that's whatever tom
is when I go putting your grades I can't
tell whether you're an undergrad or
graduate student so I'm like oh this
student got you know did awesome to get
an a-plus but then it throws an error
because they're an undergrad undergrads
can get a pluses unless you're ECE which
I think you can
it's a nightmare but anyway so his
question is all right so couldn't I have
some kind of side table that has a tally
that keeps track of every single time I
inserted a tuple with one of these
values and I'm trying to maintain an
accountant I increment that counter by
one
[Music]
within a page all right so what he's
saying is say this was stored in a page
this this little example here is in one
page and then for the grade column I
could keep track of the min and Max
value so this case B or C so now if I'm
say I'm looking for all people that have
the grade A if I get to that page and I
look say oh why it's only between B and
C because nobody has an A in that page I
don't mean even bother looking at the
column that's what you're saying right
okay I I think we are - I want the same
thing what you're describing called zone
maps right well we will talk about this
I think next week or this week I forget
when but basically there's a way to keep
track of yourself on auxiliary data
structure on the side that he looked at
that first and then you then you check
the page yes so that's a zone map you
can you could or could not be in the
same page you could have a separate page
but within the page but it's basically a
precomputed information to say the data
you here's the range of data that could
possibly exist for each attribute and
you refer to that first and make
decisions whether you didn't even go
further
yes so those are called zone maps
they're called pre oracles and zone maps
tremendous a call a pre computed
pre-computer materialized aggregation
sometimes different systems do different
things
but that does exist we'll cover that
later yes that's an index right that's
what it index does here's how my
something more fine like like not an in
Excel I think right yeah that's a zone
map when you're ascribing is in index
and again the the beauty of a
declarative language like sequel is that
I write my sequel query like this I
don't know whether I'm using zone maps I
don't know whether I'm using an index I
don't care the databases won't figure
out what's the best strategy for me to
go find the data that I want right so
just trying to try never move is
is crap quickly as possible that's the
whole goal of all this alright so that
was a change about zone maps we'll cover
that later the main point I want the
main takeaway from this was if I'm
sorted I do one pass and I can eliminate
the duplicates all right in this example
here this worked out great for us
because the output need to be sorted on
a course ID so I was it was two for one
I did my sorting because that's the
output I needed but then I'm also in the
sort order I need for my output right so
in this case here doing a sorting based
aggregation is a definite win for us but
in many cases we don't actually need the
output to be sorted right so again you
still can use sorting for this like you
can do foregrip eyes and and and doing
distinct stuff but if you don't need to
be sorted then this actually might be
more expensive because again the sorting
process itself is not cheap so this is
where hashing can help us so hashing is
a way for us to be able to sort of again
another divide and conquer approach
where we can split up the data set and
guide our the the tuples or the keys
that were examining to particular pages
and then do our processing and memory on
those pages but again hashing removes
all all locality all any sort ordering
because it's taking any key and do you
know doing some hash function on it and
now it's going to jump to some random
location so we this works great if we
don't need sorting we don't think don't
need things to be ordered so the way we
can do a hashing aggregate is we're
gonna populate at a femoral hash table
as the date of some scans the table or
scans whatever our input is hey and then
say we you know when we do our lookup
depending on what kind of aggregation
we're doing if we do an insert and the
key is not there then we populate it if
it is there then we may want to modify
it or modify its value to compute
whatever the aggregation that it is that
we want right for distinct it just a
hash see whether it's in there if it's
is then I know it's already I it's a
duplicate so I don't bother inserting it
for the group like queries for the
others other aggregations you may have
to update a running total and what we'll
see an example of this so this approach
is fantastic if everything fits in
memory so the key thing I'm saying up
above I'm saying it's an ephemeral hash
table not an emery hash table so
ephemeral or transient means that this
is a hash table I'm gonna build through
my one query and then when that query is
done I throw it all away I'm gonna do
this for every single query I said that
we said in the very beginning we use
data structures and different ways of
the database system so there's the
example of a transy data structure I
need it for just my one query I do
whatever I want then I throw it away so
if everything is in memory the hash
tables fantastic because it's oh one
book UPS to go update things right in
this case you're also not doing deletes
right it's just inserting things or
updating things if we need to spill a
disk though now we're screwed because
now that this random randomness is gonna
hurt us because now I'm jumping around
to different different pages or blocks
in my hash table and each one could be
incurring an i/o so we want to be a bit
smarter about this and trying to
maximize the amount of work we can do
for every single page we bring into
memory so this is what external hash me
aggregate does and it's again the high
level is the same way as the same
technique that we did for external merge
sort it's a divide and conquer approach
so the first thing we're to go through
to take a pass through our data and
we're to split it up into a partition
into buckets where so that all the
tuples that are either the same that all
tubes that are the same had the same key
will land in the same same partition and
then we go back through in the second
phase and now for each partition we're
gonna build an in-memory hash table that
we can then do whatever it is that the
aggregation that we want to do then we
produce our final output throw that that
a memory hash table way and then move on
to the next partition ok we're
maximizing the amount of sequential i/o
that we're doing and for every single
page we every single i/o we have to do
to bring something into memory then we
do all
the work we need to do on that one page
before we move on to the to the next
ones so we never again never we never
have to backtrack so let's go through
these two phases so in the first phase
again what we're trying to do is we're
going to split the tuples up into
partitions that we can then write out
the disk as needed so we're gonna use
our first hash function it's just to
split things up and again we use member
hash city hash xx - 3 whatever it
doesn't matter and so the reason why
we're doing this is that because our
hash table hash function is
deterministic meaning the same key will
always be given the same hashed value
output that means that tuples that have
the same key will land in the same
partition and we don't need to hunt
around for other parts of the the
tablespace at the table to find the same
key they're always gonna be in our one
partition our partitions can just build
a disk using the buffer manager when
they when they get full so so we have a
page that we're storing the the current
partition data and when that gets full
we just write that out to disk and start
filling in the next page so in this case
here we're gonna assume we have B
buffers and we're gonna use B - buffers
for the partitions and at least one
buffer for the input so I'm gonna bring
in one page from my table and I'm going
to ask winchell scan on that page look
at every single tuple and then it's
gonna write it out to be minus 1
partitions alright because you need to
have at least one buffer in memory for
each partition yes so so if if say I'm
doing I'm gonna doing a group I on the
course ID here next like I'm doing a
group I on the course ID I'm doing
aggregation so I'm gonna hash this
course ID for every single tuple if I
had the same course ID it's gonna Lane
that in the same partition so it's gonna
live there right reside live stored and
then that way when I want to go now do
that in this case the duplicate
elimination when I come back the second
time I know that the the tuples that go
have the same key has to be in the same
partition there's not gonna be some
other random place
this question it's partition to page no
partition would be like a it's a little
logical thing take the hash value Matta
by the number of partitions and that
were you write into and these partition
can have multiple pages alright so again
we do our filter do as we did before we
remove our projection columns and then
now we take our all the output of here
we're gonna run it through our hash
function and we write it out to the
partition pages so in this case here I'd
be -1 so say there's like four or five
I'm showing three here so all the 15 for
45 keys land here all the 1588 26 land
here at 15 7 21 lens here so again you
could be smart about this and say
alright well I know I'm doing doing
distinct so within my page if I see the
same thing then don't bother putting it
into it but for simplicity reasons we're
just we're just we're blindly just
putting it in yes question is what is it
what is it partition you can think of
like a partition is thinking like it's
like the the bucket chain and the chain
hash table you just have within a within
a chain you could have multiple pages
but I only have one page in memory as
I'm populating this because again for
everything every single time I'm gonna
catch something and insert it into this
I'm only inserting into one page and
when this gets full I guess again
written out to disk and I now allocate
another one that I start filling up so
within memory why I'm doing this first
days I only need B minus 1 pages because
I'd be minus 1 partitions
so this question is what if the number
of distinct course IDs you do because
you're hashing it right you're dating -
mod to take this hash value mont by b
minus 1 so in this example here I'm only
showing three distinct keys but like I
have another class 15 for ten back at
land in the same bucket as 15 for 45 I
don't need to have a partition for every
sting every stinky the hashing allows
them to go into the same thing your face
looks like you'd like this confused by
this right again so I have 15 for 10 I'm
gonna hash it I'm on it by B minus 1 it
lands in partition 0 and so I just
append it to this to this page right and
then the main thing is that 15 for 10
can't exist in any other page because
the hash function always guarantee that
it's always gonna point to this one if
the partition the current page with this
partition overflows I write it out the
disk and I allocate a new page and start
filling that up yeah you first plus the
page allocate a new one yes and again
like at this phase all we're doing is
this partitioning so I don't care like I
can be smart and say oh I'm doing
duplicate elimination I know I already
have 1545 over here I don't put it in
ignore that for now right
it's just I'm blindly putting things
into this to the pages and writing them
out yes yes so so this question is it's
getting written out the disk where am i
storing the metadata that says oh
partition 0 has these pages you had that
in memory data structure you keep track
of like partition 0 here's the pages for
our partition 1 here's the pages for it
but that's small right that's like
that's nothing
this question is are we not considering
collisions we don't care at this point
right
it's in actually maybe use another table
than indistinct maybe that's following
people but if I'm doing a you know a
count again you can do that more
efficiently as well but like like I
don't care putting in inside of this I
don't care this collision scope because
I'm gonna resolve that in the second
phase when I rehash things your question
is where is this number coming from B
minus one so that's the database system
telling this query that's whatever
thread or worker that's exiting these
queries you have this amount of memory
to use for query processing yeah so like
the data system says you're allowed to
have B equals 100 pages to do whatever
you want to do for next to the query to
execute this algorithm I I'm gonna use B
minus 1 to store my part I'll be minus 1
partitions because these partition will
have one page yeah it sucks yeah your
question is if B is really small
you're yes right there's nothing you can
do it's not it's not like you might you
know you can't magically just add more
memory right justifying that resource
the database system you know is the is
is doing resource management it's
deciding oh I have a lot of queries that
need to execute at the same time so
therefore I can't let them all have a
lot of memory so this gets into the
tuning side of things which is actually
very difficult as well yes ok so he says
and I don't have slides with this we'll
do it next class he said that you're
screwed let me rephrase what you said
you're screwed are you better if
everything hashes is this bucket so say
this is this is most popular course
McAmis everyone's taking 1545 right then
as I hash
everyone lands there then I'm screwed
right but again this gets into the query
planning side of things the database
system could look at and say oh I know
what the distribution of values are for
for this column and everyone is taken 15
40 45 so therefore if I do this
technique then I'm it's not gonna get
any benefit because everything's gonna
hash to this and it's always to work I
might as well just do ask Winchell scan
this question is you always don't know
about the data like you know a good
decision will know something it won't be
entirely accurate but it'll know
something so this table is like with the
full data set
these can be this be unskilled but then
this is skewed again this is this is
next week or two weeks the daily ISM can
maintain metadata about every single
column histogram sketches I do an
approximation of what the dish being
about looked like again for skewed
workloads that's harder you got a call
all right he's got a call yeah all right
sorry
he's out on parole says what he's got a
call his parole officer all right so for
simplicity I'm just saying assume
uniform distribution okay for skewed
work again they'll be assert up to a
certain point where this technique won't
work in a squinter scam will be the
better approach yes this question is
what is the overhead of removing columns
so in in this example here I'm showing
this as like discrete steps like filter
and then remove you can inline a combine
these together but again this is another
great example there's a trade-off so if
my table is massive and I know that I
don't need all the columns up up above
an entry then it's totally worth it to
me to pay the penalty to do this
projection because there
copping datum but if I only have one
tuple then I'll delay that that may be
the projection as late as possible
because that's gonna be it's just
cheaper to do at the very end all right
there's a trip how wide and how tall the
table is and again the data system can
figure this out
attempt to ok so what we're doing here
in the first phase where we're taking
the course ID we're hashing it we're
putting into these these pages for the
partitions so now in the second phase we
rehash for every single partition now
we're gonna bring them bring bring the
the pages in right and then we're gonna
build a named memory hash table that we
can then use to find that the same keys
so we don't have to do this we could
just bring in every single partition and
do scratch or scan on them but because
we're doing aggregations we know that we
don't need we don't need to have all of
the duplicate keys in memory at the same
time so we're using a hash table to
summarize it and could condense it down
to just the bare minimum information
that we need to compute our result and
again the reason why we did the
partitioning first is that when we go
back in the second phase and we do
rehashing we know that all the keys that
are the same will exist in the same
partition so once we go through all the
pages within that partition we compute
whatever the answer that is that we want
we can we can potentially throw it at
that hash table away because we know
that there's or at least produce it as
an output there's no that it's the keys
that we've updated so far through that
one partition will never get updated
again from any other partition because
the hashing guarantees locality for us
all right so back here right these are
all the buckets we generated in the
first phase so let's say now that we can
bring in you know we can bring in you
know these two pages or all the
partitions for well we can process these
two partitions in memory at the same
time so all we're gonna do is just have
a cursor that can just scan through them
and every single key you're gonna hash
it and populate the hash table
and I keep the scanning down and do the
same thing for everything else and then
now I produce this as my final result
again for some realize that may be
confusing the final result of this hash
table or the is the same as this one but
you know and the main takeaway is that
we're gonna throw this away when we move
on to the next the next partitions right
and this one we keep around distinct is
like a little bit too simple but like I
was trying to pick something I just
distill down the core ideas alright so
now we got this other partition here so
again we blow away that the hash table
from the first the first set of
partitions we do the same thing build a
Ameri hash table for this guy and then
we just when it's done with minutes
populate this thing yes a question her
statement is assuming we're not gonna
have collisions in the second hash
function you yes that we can write her
so her statement is question is what
does that mean you be overriding this
but it so that that does the collision
handling schemes that we talked about we
talked about hash tables so it's either
linear probing cuckoo hash whatever the
Robin Hood stuff right that's all the
internal to the hash table we're sort of
above it now we're saying your hash
table I can write things into key value
pairs and it'll it'll store them for me
I don't know and I don't really care at
this point how it handles collisions
okay again distinctive is a really
stupid simple example but you know going
through those processes is it was main
thing I what you guys get okay a
statement is the question is how is this
faster than then sorting for this
particular query probably not it depends
on the turns on the size of the data
I'll cover those let me leave really
punt on that question until next week
and be more clear when you start seeing
like the different joint algorithms yes
yeah so again because this is these
question is why do we need this when
it's just this one is right into this
and that example yes but like I was
trying to show that you look you have an
ephemeral hash table as you bill and
populate and then when you're done then
you shove it into this thing four
distinct it's stupid doesn't make sense
for aggregations fraud aggregations you
could potentially do that as well right
because again this like this may not fit
in memory yes oh so yes so I should be
clear this is this is a different seed
same so you know remember half of the
difference seat this question is like
say I built this first hash table and I
use that one C for the hash function now
down here do I need to use can I use a
different seed I don't think it matters
right
if you're writing into this if you're
writing into the same hash table you
have to be have to use the same seed if
you're just gonna merge that in later on
it doesn't matter now
yeah yes yes the final result farmers on
the database
I've sent a final result of an operator
is always gonna be a relation so this is
it could be a hash table it could be
just a buffer of pages depends on
implementation I realized that like it's
the same shapes yeah sorry
alright so finish up
let's talk about it do something more
complicated it's actually had to do you
know a grens were you know the actual
producing a real result so for this one
they the intermediate hash-table after
ever using for the the second phase
we're actually going to use that to
maintain the running total of whatever
it is the competition we're trying to do
in our aggregate from aggregate function
right and so this running value would
depend on what the aggregation you're
actually trying to do so it's going back
here so saying all of these guys now I'm
doing a I'm getting the the course ID
and I'm doing the average GPA so in the
hash table that I could be generating
for all of these I'm gonna have the the
key map to this like topple value that's
going to keep the running count of the
number of keys that I've seen with there
sorry number two was I've seen with the
same key and then just the summation of
of their GPAs right and then I just take
this thing and then when I went to
compute its produced a final output I
take the running total divided by the
number of tuples and that's how I get my
average so for all the different hash
different aggregation functions and
generally just keep track of you know a
single scalar value account you're just
adding one every single time you see
your new key or key of the same value
and then for some you just keep adding
values together for the average you you
can compute that with with the number of
the count plus the sum standard
deviation or other other aggregation
functions you you maintain a little more
information so now basically what
happens in our hash table when we want
when we want to update the hash table we
do an insert if it's not there we just
add it if it is there then we need to be
able to modify this in place or do a
delete followed by an insert to update
it so this time and again if you were
doing this with sorting you could do the
same thing you would have this on the
side and then as your scan through and
in the final sort of output you wouldn't
you could update these totals and
produce the final output
all right so I'm gonna skip this for now
this will this will make more sense for
next week we do hash trends essentially
a hash joins would be essentially do the
same thing that we're gonna build this
ephemeral hash table with on on the keys
we want to do a join one and then we
probe in that and see whether we have a
match and we produce our final output or
the operator okay so let's let's get
this and then we'll focus well we'll
discuss this again next week when we or
next to next Wednesday we do hash lines
okay all right
so in conclusion so what I show today is
this sort of the trade-offs between
sorting and hashing and again we'll go
to more details about which one is
better than the other when we talk about
joins next week the high level
techniques that we talked about here are
we applicable for all the parts of the
database system so this partitioning
approach this divide and conquer
approach all that is useful for other
algorithms other methods we have we we
care about in our system so we'll see
this recurring theme throughout the rest
of semester that splitting things up
into smaller units of work and trying to
operate on that small small chunk of
data or small problem is gonna be very
very useful technique okay all right so
let's know what project two so project
two you are going to be building a
thread safe linear probing hash table so
this is me built on top of a buffer pool
you built in the first project so it's
not an in-memory hash table it has we
backed by disk pages so we're not gonna
do anything that we talked about here in
this class we're doing trying to
maximize crunch why oh it's just you do
random i/o and you go grab pages and
from your buffle manager as needed right
to do to do inserts and deletes so your
are going to support resizing so again
linear probing hash table assumes it's a
static hash table but when it gets full
then you need to take a latch on it and
then resize the entire thing so you need
to support resizing as well and you need
to support doing this resizing when
multiple threads could be accessing the
the hash table at the same time so the
the website is up the it's not announced
yet on Piazza
what will remain there's some final
adjustments we're doing for the source
code before release to you guys but we
hope to
this will be later today I don't know
let's our animations alright so there's
four tests you're gonna have to do the
first is that you're responsible for
designing the page layout of the
hash-table blocks so this is the header
page and then the actual block page is
where the actual key values are stored
so this is a useful exercise to get you
to understand what it means to take a
you know a page from the buffer pool
manager and then be able to interpret it
in such a way that stores the data
exactly that you want all right it's not
your just malloc in some space you're
going to bump Amanda he says give me a
page and you say oh this is a this is a
hash table block page here's the offsets
to find the data that I'm looking for
how do you do a reinterpret cast on that
data
so your first implement those two
classes they do the header page and then
the block pages then you want to
implement the basic hash table itself
right to do inserts and deletes and they
get also support concurrent operations
using a reader writer latch which we
provide you and then also support
resizing you take a latch in the entire
table double the size of it and then
rehash everything so you need you need
to be able to support that so you should
follow the the textbook semantics and
algorithms for how they do you know do
the various operations
I think the lecture I gave on milena
hash table follows the textbook pretty
closely and the later hash table doesn't
have that many you know different design
decisions you have to make it's just
sort of going through these X steps I
advise you to first obviously work on
the page layout because you know you
can't have a hash table that you can
stored in pages anyway but you should
make sure that your pages work perfectly
before you move on to actually building
the hash table itself so we'll provide
you some basic tests test cases again to
do some rudimentary checks for your page
layouts but it's up for you to guys to
make sure that it's actually you know do
you simply more rigorous because if your
page layout gets up and then now
you start doing your hash table on that
it's like building a house on sand
because now you're like my hash table is
not working and it could it could
because the your pages aren't working
correctly so get this down solid before
moving to the next thing then when you
when you actually build the hash table
itself don't worry about making it
thread safe
focus on the honest single-threaded
support first this is a common design
approach in database systems this is the
approach I take with my own research and
in practice I think this is not every
company follows this he's wearing the
shirt for the company that does not
follow this the focus on correctness
first don't worry about it being slow so
make it you know make sure that it works
exactly what you think it should work
then go back and now start doing up the
optimizations that some of the things he
suggested some things we talked about in
class to be you know to do optimistic
latching be more more crafty on how you
release latches right make sure it works
correct force have test cases to prove
that it works correctly for you then
when you go start trying to make it go
faster because we'll have a leaderboard
to see who has the fastest hash-table
then you know then you know that you're
working with a again a solid
implementation okay all right so just
like before you don't need to change any
other files in the system other than the
ones that you have to spit on great
scope this is what we're working on now
so Wilson announced on Piazza that you
want to rebase your existing code on top
of the latest master because that I'll
bring in the new the sample header files
and the sample test cases before you
will provide instruction exactly what
you need to need to do the rebase
obviously makes you know since you can
blow away your source code on github
very easily with a Porsche push force
make sure you make a backup of your if
your copy but first before you start
doing the rebase and then as always post
your questions on Piazza and and come to
come to office hours yes this question
is if we assume if you get a hundred
cent score on the first project and you
assume that you're your buff elimination
is solid to support hashable yes I could
be wrong but we we think we tested
right but I would say like there was a
blog last year that that exact problem
showed up that's all the unresolved so I
think if you've passed our test it
should be solid this question is coming
now releases a skirt I cannot do that
because there's some people that are
still haven't submitted yet let's take
that all fine in the back yes for the
sorry for the first project you can
submit as much as you want
yeah yeah what is the whatever whenever
whatever the highest score you got from
the last I see great scope of let you
activate what you scored you want try it
I think but it's whatever the highest
score up into the deadline is what we'll
use
yeah yeah you submitted is all you want
you like if you get if you had an eighty
before and have a hunter after the
deadline you have an eighty score you
play the game with it like the late days
but that you know yeah again your
question is what if you change your
invitation after the fact for from
project one the it would still be you so
people Schmitt on great scope the old
project for project one we could just
have it throw in the first test as well
if you want to that make it easier like
it'll run all the tests from the first
project you won't get a score for that
but it does be there we could do that
well fix that okay what's that you know
make it slower that's the only thing
[Music]
yeah but you can still be able to submit
for the first one okay do not plagiarize
we won that we're gonna run this emboss
this is we're doing that this week for
your first project if you plagiarize
well ever worn a hole you'd be
kicked out okay
don't do that next class we're doing
joints next live joining partners
joining to hash coins okay alright he's
got a call here guys ricochet jelly hit
the deli put one naturally rap is like
the bottle don't fill out drink it only
to you can't and if the sink don't know
you for can't pay
[Music]