[Music]
all right class and it's snowing
did you drop tables thank you so I
noticed you don't have your deck today
what happened yes you had to buy her a
gift now yeah so what'd you do
you sold your deck yeah how you gonna
how you to drop the beats now but this
is getting interfere with your album now
right how long you don't have anything
all right well he's got his problems we
we have database problems but this is
the last class and as I said it's just
gonna be the final review and then a
system top Arif what you guys voted on
for what you want to be talked about so
just real quickly the remaining things
for the semester project for is due next
week on the 10th and it's way off when's
the 10th is that Monday Wednesday it's
not even close right so Tuesday December
10th with the the final project and the
and the extra credit will be due we
promised you feedback we found people
plagiarizing so we have to deal with
that first and then we'll hopefully be
able to put out the reviews for the
feedback for everyone else within like
the next day or so okay
so apologize for the delay overall they
were pretty good some are better than
others obviously but the feedback will
help guide you to finish it up yes so
you remember how when you filled out the
form you know click the check box yes I
agree I'm not gonna play dries big they
still plagiarize
yes well the very least zero where I go
talk to the Provos or not that's another
story
yeah again Seema does around they take
this seriously and the fact that I made
you check click that check box and it's
on video saying me saying don't
plagiarize you don't have any evidence
if
not you understand whoever did it yeah
yeah
and then the final exam is due on a
monday december not after you going back
to X credit this is why we have it's
like a wiki stylus we have revisions so
the person could go back and try to
remove the the plagiarized e-text but
it's still in the Davis we can go see
always go see it anyway again not you
but in general all right final exam is
on Monday at 5:30 p.m. in posner hall i
which i think is over there the old
business school yeah so that so we'll
cover that first okay so any questions
about the extra credit or project for
and then for homework five we will have
that graded and released by Friday
whatever I think he was due yesterday so
four days after that unless everyone has
already turned them in we'll send it out
okay all right
the final exam all right so you have to
take it uh or you don't have to but you
should this is not Bob yet but I'll post
this after class this will be basically
a summary of everything that I've talked
about like it's the the same thing I did
for the midterm it's like the sheet of
everything you need to know what
chapters in the book what homeworks
matter and things like that
again posner hall 100 at 5:30 p.m. don't
come to this room and then if you're
curious why you should take this other
than you want to pass the class you can
watch that video all right so what do
you need to bring you should bring your
CMU ID because it's Class of 95 people
or 96 people I don't know I know
everyone so I need to check your ID this
like the midterm it's one page of
handwritten notes double-sided no
shrinking down the slides no copy and
pasting attacks if you write it by hand
on your iPad won't print that that's
okay but again just know like text text
right from a word processor and then if
you were in the class last night on
Monday bring your extra credit coupon
and you have to turn that in when you
when you turn in your exam so the thing
is you optional if you want to change
your clothes halfway through somebody
did that two years ago I'm fine with
that because also it's at 5:30 uh you
could bring food I think there's will
give up candy I'll try to do something
better than that but don't you know I
can't can't promise anything right it's
not gonna be a full four-course meal
before the exam
what not to bring again I think we
talked about all the problems on the
midterm everyone brought weird stuff in
previous years two years ago again so
when you brought the roommate just to
hang out don't do that okay all right
before we get into the the course
material for that for the for the exam
yes sorry go ahead
is that what pH means all right then
yeah I did whatever that is yes hey
where's Porter Hall oh that's the one
over there yeah if it's not gates I
don't know where it is right I'll be
honest that this is my seventh year okay
so right so the announcer some Piazza as
well I need everyone to fill out the
course evaluations I don't care whether
you say I'm an awful person I have bad
hygiene or you hate the class that
actually is useful to me I you know I
actually read these things so the things
that I mentioned in getting feedback
from or like was the particular mark
assignment you thought was unnecessary
or stupid anything about the projects
you've seen my announcement of Piazza
that we're looking for people to help
with expanding bust hub further you know
fixing all the things and maybe went
wrong this semester but if there's again
something about the project that you
thought was too hard the pacing was not
right you wanted more documentation less
documentation into that was too easy too
hard again that feedback is actually
super useful to me all right so
undergrads are awesome at at filling out
course evaluations like if your stinks
they'll tell you the master students you
guys you guys to click five five five
five on everything and he's the great
professor I don't want any that the
right just like I actually read this the
university apparently reads it to I
don't care about them but I actually
make the course better based on your
feedback right one year a kids
psychoanalyze me with a Myer Briggs test
in the feedback that was useful so again
please go for the cell and I'll send a
reminder on Piazza all right so I didn't
have office hours on Monday but I'll
have office hours extra office hours
this Friday at 3:30 in my office and
then I'll have my regular office hours
at 1:30 on the day of the exam if you
can't make either of these and you're
dying to talk to me please send me an
email and I'll try to make arrangements
I may have to like do it over Skype or
hangouts because because of the thing
the baby and then all the TAS will have
the regular office
hours up until and including September
December 14th right so the due date for
the project for is on the 10th they're
gonna get for late days so it'll go out
into the 14th ok any questions about
office hour stuff alright so this always
comes up every year what do you need to
know from before the midterm so the exam
is not cumulative meaning like I'm not
gonna ask you questions specifically
about like buffer pools right you know
what how does this eviction policy work
but you obviously didn't know you know
it's a part of a database system we've
covered through the full stack you need
to know how all these different pieces
work together so the things that you
have to know about from the previous
prior to the term would be the buffer
management hash tables B plus trees
short models and then enter a query
parallelism which is again running
multiple queries at the same time and
you obviously didn't know how that works
because you have to do transactions I
could be updating the database at the
same time ok so this is clear we're not
asking you separate questions like in
the earlier homeworks before the midterm
but this is background knowledge that
you just you know if you forgot this
already you have other problems ok all
right so the main thing we spent time
talking about was about transactions
right you should be aware of what the
basic concept of acid were the different
properties that are combined in the
acronym and what the data's meant is
supposed to provide then we did a we
talked about the difference between
conflicts their lives be and view sort
of eyes ability number of you sterilized
ability nobody can actually do so
there's no way to actually check this
it's just a higher level concept but for
conflicts their lives ability you want
to know how to check this and how the
data system can ensure that it generates
a schedule for you know that's
guaranteed we conflict serializable what
it means to have a recoverable schedule
right amazing basically means no
cascading aborts and then isolation
levels and the anomalies write dirty
reads on repeatable reads and phantoms
then we talk about concurrent protocols
to actually generate schedules on the
fly for arbitrary transactions that are
conflicts are reliable so we spent a
whole class talking about two things
locking shows you know what the basic
protocol is but the difference between
the non rigorous and rigorous one is
what's the difference what is rigorous
two phase locking mean in the back yes
thanks Matt yeah so rigorous is you've
released all the locks at the end there
is no shrinking phase regular two-phase
locking
soon as you release one block then
you're now in the shrinking phase and
you can't acquire any new locks then we
talked about multiple granite multiple
mostly granularity in locking right and
the big thing there was the intention
box right how do I notify or how do I
post information about what I'm gonna do
at the lower levels of the lock
hierarchy in the upper level so I don't
have to take me locks on everything
right if I have to take a lock on if I
want a go and update a billion tuples
and my tables at billion turbos I better
up just taking a single lock on the
table rather than locking every single
individual tuple and then important to
know how you release these locks like in
what order is it top down or bottom up
then we spent a lecture on talking about
timestamp order and concurrency control
alright so you know what the Thomas
Wright rule is the base of protocol that
we talked about then we spent time
talking my optimistic a country toll
what are the three phases read phase
validation phase and write phase when do
we actually acquire a timestamp for
transaction in these different protocols
in the basic time stamp ordering what
when you get a timestamp when the
transaction starts in optimistic control
when you get a timestamp with that when
you validate yes when you finish the
write the read phase then we talk about
multi-version concurrency toll I'm not
gonna worry so much about the again the
the commercial protocol of that you
would use in MVCC like either you know
mb to PL or MV OCC I'm more care about
the virgin storage and the ordering of
the Delta records are doing the pen only
or you're doing the time travel tables
and then how you want to do garbage
collection
then we spend all the time talking about
crash recovery question yes right so the
isolation levels again it's uh it's it's
sort of a the very top you have
serializable isolation and then below
that you have repeatable read below that
you have read committed and below that
you have uncommitted read and so
basically as you go down that hierarchy
the the database system is not enforcing
or protecting you from different
entities certain kind of all not
anomalies so if your see reliable
isolation then you don't have phantoms
you don't have dirty reads and you don't
have unrepeatable reads but then if you
go down to repeatable read then you're
not gonna do phantom checking if you go
down to be committed now you're not
doing now you're not doing on repeatable
reads and then read uncommitted read or
read uncommitted is is no protections
yes so session is it's not actually when
we love us snapshot isolation is a weird
one it is it's almost a throg '''l to
some answers no it's not in that main
hierarchy if you take the advanced class
we'll discuss a bit further but
basically in 1992 when they invented
when they came up the ANSI standard for
these isolation levels the guy that was
supposed to double check the other guy
didn't double check that they missed
snapshot isolation so there's an anomaly
that can occur on our staffs isolation
that the that cannot occur the other
ones and but the ANSI standard doesn't
support it you don't the worry about
that just go with the ANSI standards so
serializable repeat or read read
committed uncommitted reads read
uncommitted
yes natural isolation is a it's not a
straight hierarchy the tree actually way
more complicated but we'll cover that
meet in the advanced class if you take
that the auntie ones are fine for the
for the final exam alright so we talked
about crash recovery we talked about the
different puffer hole policies steel
versus no steel what a steel mean
yes she said so with this new policy
means that a the data says was allowed
to write dirty records or dirty pages
out the disk from uncommitted
transaction under no steal you're not
allowed to do that and enforces no force
somebody other than Paulina correct so
she said you have to write all you have
to write all dirty records out to disk
before transactions allowed to be saying
that it's committed and then under no
force you don't have to do that
so with write ahead logging is it using
steal versus versus no steal just no
steal no it's already using steal wrong
right because the words right ahead
logging I have to make sure that the log
records that correspond to the changes
to the data the data pages the log
records have to be written to disk but
for my transactions a lot of commits but
I'm allowed to at some later point write
out the the dirty records you know after
the transactions already committed which
means that it's also no force we talked
about different logging schemes the main
distinction I care about is logical
versus physical my physical is where
you're actually writing out the the the
low-level bits or bytes that got changed
to the database system in your log
records and then logical log and you're
just writing a high-level command that
made the change so like the sequel query
and so there's trade-offs are these
things right so if my query is gonna
update a billion tuples with logical
logging all I have to have is that
update query in a single log record and
that'll battle that's enough information
for me to record what change that made
under physical logging I have to have a
billion log records that correspond all
the change I made to every single tuple
then we talked about how do you check
points so you should know about the sort
of the difference between the fuzzy
versus non fuzzy right
fuzzy means that I'm allowed to write
out inconsistent data to the database
system or to the disk when I'm taking
the check point but I need to know what
was going on at the time in my system
when I when I'm taking the check point
that I can reconcile after recovery what
pages may or may not gotten written
during the checkpoint or may have been
modified while I was taking the
checkpoint right in the in the non fuzzy
checkpoint case they're basically
stopping the world for a brief period
while you write everything out so that
way you're guaranteed to have a
consistent check line and then we talked
about her new areas recovery for a
lecture right what are the three phases
like the analyze the redo and the undo
shows you know how far back in the log
you need to look at for each of those
phases potentially right it should know
about the conversation log records when
you write them when you read them right
if I have a compensation log record in
my log and I apply it but then I crash
before I you know finish my recovery
when I come back around the second time
do I need to make another CLR for that
first one no right because you've
already done it the CLR has information
to tell you how to how to undo the
original update all right and then we
briefly talked about distributed
databases you know that we can't
obviously go real deep into this beyond
what was what was covered in homework 5
so this you know about the different
system architectures we talked about
shared everything share discs shared
memory shared nothing what are the
trade-offs for these or when would one
be better than another how did we
actually gonna do replication and in
these different environments at the ship
an environment how do we make sure that
the the database system is fault
tolerant how to make sure that database
system if we're making updates is
consistent across all the copies of the
data how we do partitioning again high
level things you know we talk about hash
partitioning what are the benefits of
them how to actually find the data you
need and then two-phase commit you know
under what circumstances you know at
what steps would you do at different
phases of the protocol don't worry about
Paxos that's too hard for for final exam
in gay basis okay so any questions about
the fire
to sweeten the deal I forgot to announce
this earlier if you take the final exam
when you turn it in I will give you a
bust tub sticker you can put on your
laptop okay we have enough for everyone
yes this question is what is the
duration of the exam it will be the same
as the midterm but you have three hours
and there's always somebody who takes
three hours yeah yes yes yes who
questions question is will they be
present yes when I post the review guide
I will post a same way I did in the
midterm I post the practical exam yes
these will be my own choice yes it's
easier to grade yes all right so this
question is I made the distinction
between force versus no force or
Gilbertson no steel would there be a
case where you would have won like women
you won't want to use one so no I think
you have to be one you have to be sort
of like steel no force or no steel force
right we talked about shadow paging
shadow paging was an example of no steel
force because I wasn't allowed to over
write dirty pages from uncommitted
transactions because I had this shadow
copy on the side I was making all my
updates there right so that's that's
that's the no steal part and then the
fourth part is when my transaction went
to kokum it with shadow paging I had to
make sure all those dirty pages were
flush to disk and then I flipped the
pointer the root pointer to now you know
point to the the old the new the shadow
becomes the new master when I do that I
make sure I have to make sure
everything's all have already flushed so
again write ahead logging is steel no
force shadow paging is no steel force
and then the the the main takeaway was
that the red head logging it is almost
always I can't think of maybe some cases
I haven't thought of it it's almost
always better and it's what every system
uses most systems
any other questions yes yes so this
question is unlike the midterm do I not
need a calculator
I forgot to highlight that yes you do
not you don't need it I can think of
what we did in the homeworks we didn't
estimate joins we didn't yeah I don't
think it like it live is that there we
no questions on like query optimization
stuff that's the only thing I can think
of may need a calculator right say don't
worry about that you know the questions
yes like two phase locking stuff or
about the hierarchy yes sir so her
question is are there more questions
about like multi granular granularity
locking so so in in the in the textbook
all the odd problems the solutions are
online I haven't looked at I haven't
looked at the newer version but like
there might be some questions are there
you can look at and then we do the odd
ones and you go to the DB like DB the
links on the web on the course websites
are DB book calm they'll have the
solutions to our problems you can just
follow those I'll put a link on the the
final review web page yes especially can
you bring a notes on midterm one cheap
one cheap copy whatever you need okay
all right so this is my one this this is
pie my favorite one of the favorite
lectures well they're all good but cuz
he talked about more databases alright
so again I asked everyone in the class
to vote on what systems they were most
interested in learning about so here's
the tally from last year for the top 10
cockroach TV spanner and manga DVD and
here's what we ended up with this year
which is very surprising scuba came up
first followed by manga fought like
cockroach and surprisingly this is my I
think fifth or sixth year teaching like
this puppy thing
spanners always been in the top three
right and so the only thing I could
think of that people why people didn't
vote for this as much is because the
name got changed a cloud spanner right
and maybe people didn't think it was the
same thing so that's okay
but scuba is a really interesting system
so we'll start that for that first okay
all right so Facebook's Cuba now so I
also noticed that people vote for the
ones or has like if has a name of a
company in front of it like Amazon
Aurora Baidu ocean base then people vote
for those things more so all right all
right Facebook's Qi
so what the you know what we're trying
to do here in the system potpourri is to
show you that we can now look at real
world systems and start using the
vernacular that we've discussed all
through it an entire semester to sort of
start to understand what this thing is
actually doing right so now I could say
this things out to shared nothing to
shoot the system and you know what that
means you know what the implications of
that are you know what the performance
characteristic performance challenges
you would have in a system like this so
scuba is an internal database system
that Facebook isn't working on for
several years now was first announced in
vldb in 2013 and they've been still
working on it it's it's not open source
right there's it's only till very
recently is there now some public
information about the newer version and
actually turns out because the guy that
that's actually leading the project is
CMU database alum like he got his PhD
here before I showed up and he's now
running that whole the the running the
the development of this data system and
then his boss is actually a his boss's
is the mother of another CS student here
in the department who actually worked on
bust table over the summer all right so
it's all to all one giant simi family
all right so scuba is a it's a it's MIT
it's designed for having low latency
queries and ingestion of internal metric
data generated from from Facebook's
different services all right so this is
not running an ode to the application
this is not running it's not a good ient
warehouse think of like every single
time you click something on Facebook
right on the website that causes a bunch
of functions are going to vote on the
servers and you can they can have their
developers instrument those function
calls
to keep track of the performance metrics
right throughout the entire stack and
then all that data then gets shoved over
to scuba now they can use that and then
run queries on that data to try to
figure out you know why does this
function take you know run it slower
what are some problems I'm seeing and my
giant fleet so the newer version of
scuba is now a column store it's a
distributed shared nothing system it's
using a tiered store just means that
this just means that like you can have a
you know you can have a in-memory cache
flash cache and then may be slower discs
below that and then it's gonna be using
a heterogeneous hierarchical distributed
architecture and so one interesting
about the system as well is that since
they are trying to have this thing be
really fast but you want to run your
queries very quickly over a lot of data
they are not a lot that can support
sequel they're not going to support
joins I'm not going to support global
sorting so you can only write queries
that access one single table and you
have a where clause that do you know yes
simple filtering and then you can
aggregate aggregations another
interesting about it that's gonna be
different than everything we talked
about before is that they're gonna have
to have replication to have or done a
deployment of an entire Scooba cluster
so you would think about like you have a
bunch of machines I send all my data to
this this this cluster but I'm also
going to send it to other clusters
running in different data centers or
different regions but they're gonna
allow for lossy fault tolerance in this
environment because the data that
they're collecting it's valuable would
not like bank account invaluable right
so like say you know you go click on
something in your time on a Facebook
that generates a bunch of performance
metric data if that data gets lost
yeah right it's not that not the end of
the world you know actually I want to
lose everything but they're an allow
they're gonna tolerate queries to end a
you know may have false negatives false
positives cuz they're gonna end up
missing data that just end up again
getting missing and so the way they're
gonna try to avoid that is to running
multiple points they'll run the query in
different regions at the same time and
then when they get back the result they
see which query actually read them had
the the fewer number the fewest number
of missing data and then they use that
as the CREP result but if they lose some
data it's not a big deal
and actually going to be they're gonna
have
retention policy where you can say any
data stored in this table after after
you know seven days just thrown away and
who cares all right so here's here's the
high-level pipeline of what they're
trying to do so you have your different
application servers right these are all
running the the you know the running the
website running all the back-end stuff
you need to support the website so these
guys can be generating structure debug
logs so think of this as like a JSON
document that the application server
spits out to say you know here's how
much time I spent in the CPU for this
function in that function so then
they're gonna load this into this
internal tool that they develop called
scribe I think of this it's sort of like
a Kafka kind of thing we have a bunch of
log records coming in and then you can
have the pub sub system to say here's
how to categorize the data I've
collected and here's in other systems
get notified when new information
arrives to it so this is an older thing
that since over ten years old there's an
open-source version that they have on
github but that was like abandon a
decade ago so that supposedly the the
internal version it's much better than
what's on online now all right so the
scribe is now gonna take the structured
logs look at some tag to say you know
it's it's generated for you know this
particular application type or this
service and it's gonna combine them and
get together based on that category and
then it's gonna send them to this
streaming platform or they call it the
tailor service because they're just
tailing the log and this is just gonna
bash together a bunch of these log
records they've gotten from scribe and
then when they have a large enough batch
they're gonna convert that into a
columnar data file think of like park'
or orc that we talked about last week
all right this thing's like a standalone
file almost like a CSV but it's actually
a binary column store and so if they
have a larger batch they're gonna
generate these these column store files
and then now they're gonna feed this
into the leaf nodes in scuba and so
we're talking to 16 aggregation notes
and leaf nodes but this is basically the
storage nodes think of this as like the
the shared disk architecture but you can
actually have you know run queries down
here or the the last class when Shashank
talked about Oracle Exadata but they had
the storage nodes at the bottom could
actually do filtering and predicate
evaluation down there
same same idea here so now one
additional thing they're going to do is
that they're gonna each of these leaf
nodes are going to update this
validation service with information
about the number of tuples that they've
inserted for each table and we'll see it
in a second this is how they're gonna
determine which which when they run the
query on multiple deployments or
multiple clusters you'll check that
thing to say well how much data is
actually missing so I know I sorted a
million tuples but I only read maybe
500,000 so half of my data went missing
again they're not they're not gonna go
freak out that's okay in their
environment but just they keep track of
this and they know that which query is
producing the most accurate result so
now it's again it's a seagull system so
they have a vistas sequel interface or
these dashboards that people can use
internally at Facebook that sends sequel
queries to this execution layer which
then is gonna send it to these
aggregators who then are gonna farm it
down to these leaf nodes so I'll discuss
this hierarchy and a few more slides but
this is an important distinction between
all the distributed databases we talked
about because it's a heterogeneous
environment so the leaf nodes are doing
things that are separate or different
than what the aggregator notes are doing
right and you obviously have more of
these because you're have more data yes
the question is the categories name is
accurate yes think of like it's some
internal tag that that Facebook is
ascribing to a particular class of log
records right so again say it's like I
don't know the facebook inbox or
messenger right so you'd say that would
be one category so all the the log
records from the messenger app go to get
combined together okay so again all
right it's a header juice architecture
and we have leaf nodes aggregator nodes
so the leaf nodes are going to store the
column our data that we're getting out
from the the record batchers in a
columnar format and the for each query
every query is gonna go to every single
leaf node so the may not be data that
the query needs on that leaf node but
they're not going to store any
additional metadata or maintain any
indexes on these leaf
give me it'll figure out whether I need
to touch data at them so they're trying
to make this thing be as fast as
possible to trying to make this both in
terms of how fast the query can execute
but also how fast you can ingest new
data so if I don't have to maintain any
metadata or catalog information about
which data is that what leaf node then I
can ingest new data very quickly and
then every query shows up and just scans
everything and then that determines
whether the you know you have data that
you actually need that makes sense right
so like when we talk about partitioning
before we talk about how there's and
we'll see this a and cockroach
there to maintain this this state table
that says if you want data within this
range or this hash value go to these
nodes they're not gonna have any of that
they just blast everything to everything
every query goes everywhere so the
aggregator nodes when they get a query
they're going to dispatch plan fragments
to the leaf it's shown in leaf nodes
there Dan gonna do on the leaf nodes
they're gonna do the scan and some some
basic computation but I'm gonna send the
result up to the aggregator nodes we're
then going to combine the results from
multiple leaf nodes to produce a single
result and then send that up to a root
node who combines combines the final
result so this is an allow them to scale
out the system very easily because I
know if my aggregators are running slow
I can add those nodes because they don't
have any state right that's not where
the data is actually stored or if I need
to scale out my leaf nodes I just add
more of those and keep my a Grenadiers
but the same but it's a very interesting
architecture that shows up in a lot of
other Facebook system design the mem
seagull guys when they before they
started mem sequel they spend their time
at Facebook and they saw this kind of
architecture and then they sort of
copied it or inspired by it when they
went off them psychosom em sequel works
the same way okay so again we talked
about this this tolerating lost aid or
missing data so if a leaf node either
has no data or that it's down and it
can't produce any results within a time
out then they just ignore it and that's
okay and they use the validation service
to figure out well how much data was
this thing actually have and that'll
determine the quality of the query a
query result so let's see what the end
the full pipeline looks like so
again this is this is be considered one
scoop of cluster they're gonna they're
gonna have multiple instances of the
same kind of cluster running in
different data centers different regions
and they're gonna vote a query on all
than at the same time and they all get
back the same result and you pick out
which one is the best one so my query
shows up I want to do a an aggregation
of the number of vents that crashed on
there was a crash on a Monday again so I
can only do single table queries I can
do aggregations I can do group bys I can
do filtering under scans but I can't do
global global sorting on I can do joins
so the routes gonna get the query and
that's going to break it up to query
plan fragments that's can then
distribute down to the aggregators and
the aggregators are gonna tribute them
down to their delete nodes all the leaf
nodes are now going to do a scan and
then send results back up but let's say
while we're executing this query this
node goes down which happens right if
you have a large large cluster so
everybody else I'm still wrong everybody
else is still gonna be able to do the
computation for this query and then they
send the results back up to the
aggregators prepend just can't combine
it together right so I'm doing accounts
I want to know the number of events that
occurred so this guy says has I have ten
events he has 20 events so this guy just
takes 10 plus 20 and produces 30 and
then sends it up to the root and the
root does the same thing just adds all
the results at different aggregators and
then produces the final result so this
is clear yes yes so this query is to
scan everything right so there is no
again there's no metadata there's no
catalog to tell me anything about
whether or not these leaf nodes had the
data in my that I have my where clause
so I don't know but I don't know where
type is I don't know where time is so I
send it everyone so everyone essentially
he's gonna in this example here
everyone's gonna do the exact same query
run it on the leaf nodes alright so he's
doing a count star work type II type
equals crash time he goes Monday he has
10 he just shoves that up and this guy
knows well I'm doing this count thing so
I just added some up
numbers together please the result yes
ah is it true that for every single
query you would always copy the same
query down to the leaf nodes no because
like for averages the way you do that is
account on the sum and then you can put
the average up at the top so that that
would be different yeah so there really
isn't like since there's no joins the
cook there's not really a query
optimizer here it's just I need to know
what the I just convert the seco to a
query plan and to shut that down
and there's some basic heuristic they
probably do to figure out like you know
how to actually break it up and send it
down huitnids yes so this question is
why was it why was it decided to have a
root node here and how all the clients
go to this versus having everyone can
penally go to any aggregator and then
any aggregator can talk to anybody else
so the my understanding is that there's
actually a there's a layer above this as
well the root were they're doing a
mission control so they can do some
things like oh if a query if a node is
sending too many queries a client
sending too many queries maybe want to
throttle them or like if I know I'm
getting bad data from some some set of
these nodes then I can have someone to
make a decision about what to exclude or
not include them in my query execution
so it's allows them to have a single
location to have a global view of what's
going on in the cluster doesn't know
about what's in the database right
because that's that would be to
extensive maintain and keep keep it
fresh all the time it just knows that
like these nodes are performing and well
they're not well yes his question is say
that this node had a ton of results ton
of that would match my predicate
I wouldn't be better for me just abort
this query cuz that because I'm my
counts me way off how do you know that
this node has all the date has a lot of
data that matters for your clearing you
don't know yeah so again think about
what this is design for this is design
for logs being generated by machines
right it's not like hey here's my bank
account I want that to be you know you
know to the penny so if you get
loosey-goosey results that still was
probably okay and then the way they sort
of overcome that again is by having that
validation service they can determine
how much data did they actually not read
so then also again then they have a
bunch of a Dunant copies of the system
running at the same time they're all
gonna produce the same query so the
likelihood that every single every
single cluster that's running Scooba for
a single query is gonna have this node
fail exactly you know exactly this node
has this data fail is pretty low so at
least one of those clusters will have a
more active result and that's the one
they'll use that's way different we talk
about entire semester that's why I like
the system because it's like we talked
about never losing data now I'm saying
it's okay to lose data because and it's
like if the tree falls in the woods and
no one's around to hear it who cares if
this node goes down and no you know no
one knows and it cares about what data
is actually on it does it matter and
because they're not in you know running
wrap or patos every single time or
they're updating data this thing can run
really fast all right so this is
summarizes our whatever I already said
before right so for every scuba
deployment there's me multiple there's a
really multiple scuba deployments
running in their regions we run the
query at the same time on all the
regions and then they come back with a
result and then the result is annotated
with information from the validation
service that says how many how much data
did I end up not reading I picked the
one that has the that has the most the
read the most data and time
again so we know the guy Stavros that
runs us he got his PhD from CMU in
[Music]
2007-2008 and now he's in charge of us
so hi any questions all right good step
all right number two was is
always always picked every year so let
me ask you guys I asked this every year
why did you guys pick I assumed
you picked Facebook cause some of you
want to get jobs at Facebook because you
think like I go in the job interview I
could talk intelligently about scuba
same thing for do you want to work
at or do you want to use
some people already done internships
some people are going to new internships
there I guess he says it's much
different than what we normally do ok so
I've known the MongoDB guys for a long
time the one of the co-founders actually
went to brown before I did he so he like
we've known Elliot since like 2009 when
he first started assessment can you come
give talks at this year's Sparta they're
all the time and I actually was there in
August they have a new office building
they used to be right around the corner
from Times Square which is awful they're
still in Midtown but they have a nice
office building so you know they're a
big deal if you have the sign for your
company outside the building right above
that says Warner Music Group they have
the money is doing pretty well
it's all for the databases so this is
their Lobby the lobbies nice looks
familiar right yeah um the view is
amazing so this is from the kitchen I
mean it was a cloudy day the view is
absolutely stellar uh and again all paid
for by databases it's amazing all right
so what is is a distributed
document model data spirit system so
when I say document think of JSON like a
JSON object and in the MongoDB world the
language for when we talked about the
entire semester has been slightly
different so again instead of saying to
bold to say document instead of saying
table they or a relation they say
collection but the high-level concepts
are still the same so it's one of the
earliest of our original no sequel
systems it was open source
it used to be GPL but now they switch to
the server side
license and this is basically to protect
them from Amazon like MongoDB got so
popular they were worried about Amazon
coming along and just running MongoDB in
a hosted environment and selling it for
cheaper than what mom could be could so
they switched their license now Amazon
did come out with a system that does
clone the mummy protocol called document
e-beam but my understanding of how it
works is that underneath the coverage is
just Postgres so the wire protocol looks
and smells like looks like looks like
MongoDB but underneath it is just post
groceries so it's going to very
centralized shared nothing architecture
with a heterogeneous configuration and
originally they you know as this no
sequel system they didn't do
transactions and they need new joins in
a new sequel so right now the latest
versions the that will they do
transactions they brought in
transactions and they also do joins the
only thing they haven't brought in is
sequel now there are some hacky tools
that can convert sequel into mom-to-be
queries as far as I know I've never run
across anybody that runs this and those
things in production alright so they're
among enemies gonna have their own API
which I'll show in a second that is
basically you write JSON queries to read
JSON data so one important concept about
the document data model which is quitly
different that we talked about the
entire semester is this concept of
denormalization so in the relational
model we would define our tables or
define our relations and we would use
foreign keys to say there's a reference
from this table to another table right
so if gain if I'm by modeling Amazon is
my store information so I have customers
customers orders and orders have order
items so in a relational database system
I would define these as separate
relations and then if I want to say for
a given customer give me all the items
that they bought I would have to do a
three-way join between these three
tables and the no sequel guys argue that
that would that was expensive to do to
do these joins you know because it's now
you got to run your hash join a nested
loop join right so what they would argue
you'd want to do in a document data
model is to denormalize what basically
says combined together the the related
information about a single entity in
your application into
single JSON document alright so setup in
this getting this environment here
instead of having a three different
tables you would have one table called
customer and then inside each customer
record you would embed their orders and
then which eaten within each order you
would embed their order items so now if
I want to go get all the order items
that Andy bought I go get my customer
record from the database system and then
I just reversed now inside the JSON
document to get what I want now
nummy did not invent that idea
that's an old idea from the 70s XML
databases did it in the early 2000s late
nineteen nineties the object-oriented
guys did this in the 1980s so MongoDB
did not invent that what Mongi was sort
of famous for was having a you know fast
distributed JSON database system right
when sort of web bill and and JavaScript
was becoming prominent so again we just
look like this and your your JSON
document would have inside of it and
array called orders and with inside that
you have additional JSON documents for
every single order and decide every
single order you have an array for order
items and then all the items that they
bought right so again we've talked to us
and they're actually the first class
some a performance standpoint this is we
really fast
again it's one read to go get you know
all Andy's order items the bad thing is
going to be obviously now we're gonna
duplicate a bunch of information about
these different order items over and
over again and now I need to write my
application code to make sure that
everything is is is the I maintain the
integrity of all of this information so
if I change the name of item I have to
write code to go through all my inside
all my customer records and make sure I
update everything so the way you panic
reacts to you queries is through a JSON
only query API they don't have a query
optimizer at least not in a call space
one that we talked about before and I
think a briefly talked about us when we
talk about query optimization so they
basically do is do your query shows up
and they're gonna generate sort of every
possible combination for that given
query and then there's gonna blast every
node with different different
combinations of that query and then
whatever one comes back first then they
learn that that's the better one to use
because it came back more quickly
so the next time you actually that same
query or similar query they'll just
reuse the query plan that they generated
before and they'll do this maybe like a
thousand times and then just after the
thousand query invocation they'll do
that sort of blast them all out first or
blast them all out and see which one
comes back first thing so you may think
is kind of hacky right I spent two
lectures talk about how hard it is to do
a query cost based scoring optimization
and and how hard the problem at you addy
and they chose this cuz back in the day
they didn't do joint so you didn't have
to worry about joint owner he's just
basically was picking what index to use
so the random walk approach would
actually work I don't think they do
anything sophisticated for the joins now
they might just use basic heuristic this
table or this collection is smaller than
this one so it's one versus the aunt
once the inner versus the outer they
support JavaScript UDS we'd actually
didn't talk about UDS for this semester
it's basically like a function you can
write in your query that gets invoked on
the data server side they do now support
joins and they now support also multi
document transactions though the early
benchmark numbers for MongoDB were
amazing like you could write data into
it very quickly because what they were
doing is one they weren't doing
transactions and they weren't actually
guaranteeing anything was actually
written to disk when you got response
back that you're right succeeded was
actually even worse of that if the
database ever got the packet for your
right they'd immediately come back when
to acknowledge and say yeah we got it
then at some later point would act to
the right would actually be executed and
in log to disk so if you wanted to see
whether you're right actually made it to
disk yet when you got back the response
you had to go back again and say hey did
my right make it alright she had to do
two round-trips to see whether your
right was actually successful
that used to be default for a long time
so if you look at the early benchmark
numbers for MongoDB they're amazing
then 2013 or 2012 they actually turned
that off it's known only by default all
right now they're actually doing right
had log and we'll talk about a second
and they support multi dublin
transactions across multiple machines
which is impressive it's not not easy to
do alright so the system architecture I
think we've already talked about before
it's a heterogeneous distributed
components shared-nothing
the centralized query router they're
doing master slave applications you can
have your rights from from
when masternode a master partitioner
shard will go off to other shards so
part of reason I think manga Dini was
very successful in the early days was
they actually supported Auto sharding so
the idea was here that like you just
start shoving data into your database
and you know it'll be distribute across
multiple nodes but then if one of those
nodes gets too full mahogany will
automatically move your data around to
balance things out it didn't always work
the way people thought it was going to
work but you know back in like 2010 when
I would go out to Silicon Valley and you
ask people like you know oh they're
doing a startup and they're basing it on
MongoDB you ask him why and maybe say oh
because this auto sharding thing was a
big deal for them because you know at
the very beginning most people don't
have much data because you're you know
you're start-up you have a stupid
Twitter app no one's using it you can
run on single machine but of course no
one doesn't start out thinking that
they're gonna fail everything everyone
thinks they're gonna be big so of course
I'm gonna need you know 20 machines in
the future so I wanna make sure MongoDB
can scale it with me right with with my
sequel and Postgres and other relation
databases at the time you couldn't do
that so that I think this was a big deal
but there's a famous Foursquare outage
51 it was super Foursquare is think of
like how to describe this
it was app you could check in what
location you were in it's still around
but it's not not sort of the not not a
phone app everyone uses but they were
using MongoDB and there was a famous
like you know multi-day outage because
the auto sharding stuff got stuck
alright so here's the architecture again
we talked about this before and we have
different type node types we have
routers we have config server and we
have a shards so every query from the
application always goes to the router
and the router says oh I know I want to
look up ID 101 but I don't know
information about where that is so I go
to the config server to config server
tells me and it looks in the chart table
it says the data you want is that it's
located it's node so then now the router
knows how to send the query to the right
location or it could blast it out to all
of them so again this is important
distinction between the scuba stuff and
we're talking about here scuba doesn't
haunt have it this partition or sharding
table it blasts the query to everyone in
MongoDB
since you don't want to waste resources
because you're trying to run you know
update query ISM for your website real
quickly you you maintain this
information to figure out exactly where
the query needs to go so you only touch
them the data you only touch you can do
that has the exact data you need yes
so a question is it sort of catching on
the router yes so like you wouldn't
always have to do this but this would be
the this would consider to be stateless
so if I crash I come back I just I get
my cache version from this again but any
update to like if I say I'm doing the
auto shouting stuff and I add a new node
right move some of data to another thing
I update this thing and that's done as a
transaction yes what is the origin of
this what do you mean oh the naming oh I
think just means humungous I
thought it is right so and so this is
like actually the s I don't know that is
but like maith backwards I don't know no
yeah it's this demon or data is PI just
demon and asks I don't know what
that means yeah I don't know the ask
means so another thing I said during
this semester was that never use MF for
your Davis
well when month when MongoDB first came
out they were using em after their Davis
and we actually did a little study on MF
database systems in my in our opinion we
haven't published us yet the MongoDB
implementation of using MF is probably
the most sophisticated one that we've
ever seen it's probably the best one but
it still sucks it's still bad alright so
basically what happened is the way they
would use a map is they would have
they'd basically maintain multiple
copies of the database in memory and you
would do your updates to this like sort
of private copy that would then get read
to disk and then you had to replay the
log to update the sort of the master
copy and so the OS could swap things out
anytime it wanted it was a big big pace
for them the other big problem they had
was they had a single lock for the
database now there's a not in time
because they were using M map but I
think it's sort of probably probably
helped make things easier using M map so
that means that in the entire database
system even though you may be split
across multiple machines in the earlier
versions as a MongoDB you could only
have one writer in the entire cluster at
a time so if I have 20 machines I have
one query that comes along I basic
Lock all 20 machines to do update on one
of them and then in the newer versions
of since version 3 they got rid of
this so what they end up doing was they
bought this this storage engine startup
called wire tiger which was founded by
the guy that one of the guys that
invented Berkeley DB Berkeley DB is an
embedded database wire targeted at a
Davis we're gonna talk about this too
much but post best my sequel these are
all database systems that like run as a
standalone demon or standalone system
and you have multiple clients connecting
them Seco light is typically used as an
embedded database you embed it inside
your application and it provides you the
database functionality but when your
application closes the database closes
so why are Tiger is sort of like sequel
light but it doesn't support sequel it
supports like a key value store API so
probably one of the best acquisitions in
a long time they bought why are tiger
and they replace the end map stuff with
with the wire tiger engine so when you
run when you run MongoDB now you get the
wire type engine by default and it's
amazing questions are yes this question
is if you think MF is so complex why
would you use this so again I can't I
want to prove it scientifically I can't
yet so just take everything what I say
like this is my opinion M map is like a
seductress right it's like it's this
sexy thing that looks like gives you
what you want for a buffer pool manager
right without having to do it cuz the OS
does it for you
you don't need an eviction policy the OS
does that you don't need to worry about
paging you know keeping track of dirty
pages and things I think oh that doesn't
that so it's this thing that looks like
it's gonna give you everything you want
but it's like it's the extra 5% you
actually need to actually make it be
durable and safe that's when all the
problems come in so like it's sort of
like the query optimizer it's a Tibetan
query optimizer let's do something
really simple and just blast everything
out and see what comes back first so set
it bearing a buffer pool manager I'll
just use the os's
profitable cache or the man map cache
let's take that one off line hey me
Elliot I mean L is a really smart guy
the co-founder and I've wildly
successful right like it's a public
company right I think you know by using
M map although it causes problems in it
can cause problems when you really start
to try to scale up and scale and Hammer
the system it allows you to build a
system pretty quickly
so instead of spending six months having
to develop a buffer manager that's you
know safe and transactional and things
like that
use these OS you know and map and then
when they got enough customers they got
enough money they bought wire tiger and
did it right my secret was the same way
right Mike well he didn't use em map
please I don't think like my Siegel with
nodb is amazing inner DB is fantastic
it's a solid database engine storage
engine but the original engine they use
was my ISAM that thing sucks that thing
lost data all the time right you it
would you have corruption and so but it
got my C go up and running pretty
quickly a lot of people are using it and
then eventually in a DVD came along and
my sequel bought them out and started
using it that's a not a very uncommon
strategy for Davis business all right
let's do a demo so when we have to tell
you is semi semi illegal
alright anybody is about yes this
question is why would you want to maybe
use for others so the I think that
being in a stupid architecture is
matters a lot
the the document model is actually
better for application development right
think about you when you write Python
code you write Java code you're writing
an object it is object oriented
programming languages and so it kind of
if you can have now your object just be
written out as a JSON document and then
putting the Davis and fetch it back in
and we instantiate in your application
code that could potentially be faster
but the thing I would stress though
there's nothing about what MongoDB is
doing because it's document database
system that is different than anything
we talked about this entire semester why
are tired doesn't know that it's
actually being used for a document
database system it's doing right ahead
logging it's doing all the crash
recovery stuff we're doing it's doing
transactions underneath our covers in
the same way that we talked about so
there's nothing about in the document
that invalidates or changes anything we
talked about here today it's all at the
application level hey it's all sort of
client level to quit what the query
looks like what the query is actually
gonna do everything else below is
everything we talked about the entire
semester yes the question is do they use
special compression enemies so that
would be wire tiger I think it's just
snappy yeah yes again the the the older
versions the user name the default
username passwords test test it's not
that way anymore yes ok all right so the
last one we have 10 minutes left is
cockroach DB actually I was there in the
summer as well so when I went DB
and cockroach DB their headquarters are
in in New York City so when I was out
visiting cockroach or whatever I visited
both of them at the same time this is
their old office they had this nice
little pixel art thing for the cockroach
house and this is their newer office
though I was actually surprised how big
it actually is
I gave a game I gave a talk there they
just raised 55 million dollars as a
Series C round which is a little money
for a database company so that's
actually very impressive how do I assume
that means they're doing well so that's
good right so Krakow HDB started in 2015
by some X kugel employees they were I
think incorrectly characterized as the
open-source version a spanner from
Google spanner I don't think they ever
said that people sort of tributed that
to them I would not say that's true at
all cockroach TV is sort of a core
architecture is fundamentally different
than spanner and spanner has one magic
piece that nobody else has that
cockroach doesn't do and nobody else
does so is a decentralized
shared-nothing homogeneous database ISM
architecture and they're going to be
doing range partitioning the internal
storage engine they're gonna use is Rox
TB so the same question is why would
anyone want to use em map right well my
answer was because so you don't have to
build that piece yourself so cockroach
GP they then wouldn't spend time writing
a storage manager right the same way
that you know the wire tiger piece from
MongoDB so a lot of these newer database
system startups they're using rocks TV
or leveldb these embedded storage
engines so they don't have to worry
about right reading writing data from
disk and they worry about the high level
parts of like you know managing
transactions in a trivet environment so
they're going to be doing multi virtual
but optimistic you know optimistic a
commercial protocol and I know but this
is still true but they're only going to
support serializable snapshot isolation
so I I don't think they support the
other assistant isolation levels they
also speak the Postgres wire protocol so
that means that if you have an existing
post test application you can just in
theory point it to cockroach DB it's
pointing at progress now you migrate
your data bit over to cockroach DB and
you don't have to change potentially any
of the sequel it's not entirely true for
everything like there's some things that
are different like Auto increment keys
but in general it's migrating to a
cockroach even Postgres is a should not
be an owner snek so at its core
cockroach GB is a distributed key-value
store transaction attributed key value
store so that means that the lower
storage engine of the system
at rocks TB is a key value system but
then the way they're doing transactions
or the way they're managing the the
database across multiple machines is
essentially just going to be a key value
store and so so using that now they can
build layers above that to provide the
full sort of sequel compatibility that
you would want all right so once you get
past like the sequel query shows up they
can then convert that sequel query the
query plan is essentially going to be a
bunch of key value API calls that can
then read and write data from from
different nodes so the way they're going
to coordinate the updates throughout the
system is using raft raft is essentially
at a high level which same thing as
paxos it's a consensus protocol that
allows me to say when I make an update
and I want to commit a transaction
across multiple Sheen's everyone's gonna
agree or quorum has to agree that the
updates allowed to proceed or to occur
in order for that transaction to be able
to commit so the way they're going to do
OCC is through using timestamps it's
using what are called hybrid clocks so I
think I talked about this a little bit
or Prashant Agra this one we talked
about times not conjectural we need a
way to have a clock that we can you
nuclei identify every transaction and
that clock needs to always be always
increasing so we know what transaction
in the serialize will order as their
neck solution what transaction came
before the other so you could just use
the physical clock which is you know
from from the actual CPU like I'm a
machine itself what's the system time
but the problem in that one is that's
not going to be guaranteed to be highly
synchronized across multiple machines
right there's every computer has a clock
that clock is not super super accurate
it's not like an atomic clock right this
can mean you know counting electrons
coming off of an atom it's gonna be some
kind of quartz crystal thing that it has
to approximate so now you can have a
bunch of skew and your clocks and so now
what could happen is you know
transaction rise on one node it thinks
it's time stamp 1 another transaction
Rises another node it thinks it's time
stamp 1 and now I have a conflict I have
pie of a yeah complicated that I've
resolved so the way they're going to
handle that is through a hybrid clock
where you'll still use the system clock
to try to get what the current time is
but then you also used a logical clock
that allows you to have globally ordered
transactions without having to
synchronize every single time so
basically took a little calendar that
says here's my current timestamp and I
just my machine would add one to a disk
illogical counter to increase it so
what's gonna happen is under OCC
transactions gonna stage all those
rights and the system says these are the
modifications I want to make yes
question his question is how's a hybrid
clock different than the Google spender
clock the Google spanner clock is not
the Google spent to the treatment I
don't get too much into spanner
Google spanner is relying on the the
harbour clocks to have super accurate
times that are synchronized across all
the machines and the true time API gives
you a bound of how long we have to wait
for someone to show up with a lower
timestamp it's a way to basically is
like this is like true time but using
only software so if you have really bad
clock drift like this one machines one
hour behind another machine no
transaction could potentially have a
complete because you yeah every
transaction think they're gonna in the
past in the future get messed up so you
have to make sure that you try to keep
the clocks in the sink using like NTP
spanner doesn't do that spanner does
that you know the GPS satellites plus
the atomic locks they have super fine
granularity all right so again different
than scuba all the metadata about where
the data exists what the transaction
state is that's when the Vista exists in
their own key value store as well and
that's all considered transaction so
let's look at a simple example here so
we have our application comes along and
what may be update data and this
Klosterman so again different from scuba
we maintain a partition table just like
a MongoDB to keep track of what node is
responsible for what range of data so
when my query shows up the first thing
like the consult is my is this partition
table which actually would be replicated
on every single machine and say well I
want to access key or ID equals 50 what
machine what what node is the leader for
that
and then in this case here it's this guy
so now my right has to go here did you
my update and then the update has to get
propagated to the other nodes and then
we use raft to to get everyone to agree
that we're gonna go ahead and commit
this transaction
all right so instead of using two phase
commit they're just using raft so now if
I want to do now I read say for this
this ID goes 150 well I'm always going
to go to the leader where this guy is
located even though I have multiple
copies of the data on different notes
and I in theory I could read at these
other nodes but I always want to do my
read on the leader to make sure that I'm
reading the most you know the most
consistent or up-to-date version of it
because maybe these other nodes have not
seen the latest update yet because you
and a raft you only need a quorum you
don't need to have a every node agree
which is different you know to Bayes
committee everyone this one you always
need a quorum so some node could be
behind but you were still allowed of
committed transaction so to handle that
all the reads are always going to go to
whatever the leader node is for an ID
and to avoid having every query go to
just a one node that's why we have this
table appeared to tell us which one's
the leader and we're going to distribute
that across multiple nodes so the guest
so the reads can then be scattered
across multiple machines again it's just
doing the consensus protocol the
replicated replicated rights that we
talked about in the semester the hard so
the core concepts aren't any error arm
aren't mind blowing aren't dramatically
different than what we've already talked
about the hard part is the engineering
making this actually work and that's
what you know that that's what they're
spending all their time to make happen
so that you don't have you know lost
rights or missing updates and things
like that okay all right so let's finish
up so hopefully I've conveyed throughout
the entire semester that I love
databases they're awesome
Joran hit him you're gonna hit him
throughout the rest your life and so
what hopefully this course has provided
for you is the ability to say you know
something's running slow in our
application because it's the database
what kind of database system am i
running on what is my data look like
what does my query look like it allows
you to now make an informed decision
about
how these systems work and whether
you're you know you're choosing the
right database system for your given
application or workload environment
right because not everyone's gonna go
off and build a database system but I
guarantee you no matter what you do
especially you mean even if you don't
stay in the tech field
you're gonna chrome across databases
like Excel is a database I said we're
using Excel you're using a database so
and the other thing I would say also to
that's super-important is I would avoid
premature optimizations in deciding what
data system to use always start with
something that is is maybe it's just
good enough of what you need right now
and don't worry about you know
potentially scaling up to you know
millions of users in the future all
right that was sort of my mom gonna be
example everyone said oh my startup is
gonna be huge I don't have a million
customers of course I wanted to show you
a database that can scale out well know
in the very beginning you probably just
use Postgres or my sequel on a single
box and that'll get you you know maybe
for the next two years that'll be good
enough but maybe you buy some better
hardware and scale up a little bit more
as your domain increases but don't worry
about bringing in distributed system
because that's gonna bring more
complexities that you maybe need right
now you should focus on what makes your
app you know what you need for your
application to succeed so people often
ask me what database system should I
start with if I'm building an
application my interest progress or my
sequel for you know 99% of applications
that's gonna be good enough because what
will happen is if your application does
blow up and you do have a lot of
customers what are you gonna have money
so now you can go pay me to come tell
you how to scale out your database all
right or one of my students right so a
avoid you know introducing new
complexity by bringing in a you know
going overboard with with a database
system you don't need like maybe
starting with Amazon RDS would be a good
choice and then you just scale up and
buy a bigger instant size and you add
Azure as your as your data size crows or
your need grows okay all right any
questions yes
boom okay all right so
yes so uh I did get a my test results
came back last week right this is it
it's mine isn't it there's no house so
the probability that I am the father of
my child is 99.999999 8% so there is a
point zero zero zero zero zero through
two percent chance that it's not mine
but at this point I've accepted my feet
and it's definitely my kid okay
yeah no it's yeah all right yeah it's
mine all right all right guys so I'll
see you at the final exam on Monday and
then the I'll have office hours on
Friday and then again this is the last
class with DJ drop table so again
rattleballs for him staying with his
time Spencer okay
all right guys take care
witzy nights in my system racking up I'm
blessed
let's go get the next one get over there
will be Sun ricochet jelly hit the deli
for a boat one naturally bless ya my rap
is like the laser beam the pores in the
bushes say not even like a chain wrap
the bottle of us a nice sympathy go
don't feel like drinking at boney to
drunk you can't drop cross he was alive
and if the sake don't know your phone
can tap a pain