[Music]
okay jump right into it so the schedule
for you guys
the major thing obviously two days from
now on Wednesday in this classroom we
will have the midterm exam study guy
who's been online since last week but
also the practice exam
I've also uploaded all the lectures all
the lecture notes and all the slides
from everything that's covered in exam
over this weekend and then there's
additional problems in the textbook
solutions for the odd ones are available
online so any high-level questions about
the midterm you need to bring your CMU
ID because it's a class of a hundred
people I don't know everyone I should
bring a calculator if you can't do logs
in your head and you're not have a one
one eight half I let me sheet of paper
double-sided with handwritten notes no
shrunk it down slideshows hunker down
let your notes know slowly shrunken down
textbook everything I'll be written by
hand you'll get more out of that way so
any question about any of these things
okay good and then project two will be
due on on Sunday at midnight as well I'd
like you I posted on Piazza what
questions things like that right and
then the tears are helping as needed
okay all right so we have a lot to
discuss today I don't think I'm gonna
get through all of it
so it might spill over to next week
after the exam
plot there and see what happens so today
we're talkin and query planning so the
high-level idea what we're trying to do
today is that given that sequel was
declarative meaning the the application
that sent us the query the query says
what answer they want us to compute
right select this from this table
produce all the employees that have this
particular attribute I and they and it's
not telling us how we actually supposed
to compute this right doesn't say do a
hash join
let's look join although you can do
hints like that but we can ignore that
for now right it's it's just them
telling us what answer they want and so
it's up for us now inside the database
system people actually building but they
have a system software it's our
responsibility to take that simple query
and figure out the the best way the most
efficient way to execute it and so if we
saw from from last week or the previous
weeks when we talked about joint
algorithms but they can be quite a big
difference in performance depending on
what album you choose
we had stupid mess of loop join would
take one point three hours for a table
of six megabytes but if you do it in the
hash join worst case scenario was 0.5
seconds so you know eight spits for this
one it's pretty obvious right we don't
wanna do the stupid thing we can figure
this out when we start getting more
complex queries more complex joining
these then figuring out how exactly go
from this to this it's not always
obvious and that's why in this new this
is what's going to separate the the high
end database systems that are very
expensive the oracles the db2 the
Teradata is the sequel servers versus
like the source ones are the free ones
Postgres is still very good but it's no
where the query optimizer is nowhere as
sophisticated as sequel servers report
example so the idea about query
optimizer goes back to the 1970s so I
don't think I've talked about system are
in this class a little bit but I said
why but back in you know in the 1970s
when Ted Cod and wrote the first paper
on the relational model there was
basically two people or two groups that
picked it up and try to actually
implement it because getting Ted Cod was
a theoretician it was a mathematician so
he didn't have to have it in software he
just proposed an idea
Haagen place the model said this is the
right way to actually build software and
then there was a group at IBM in San
Jose and then a group at UC Berkeley who
ended up taking that payment actually
built the you know the first two
relational data has been assessed at
least most famous ones no one at
Berkeley was called ingress that was you
know my post course is called Postgres
the same guy that made arrests also be
post-grad
because it's post immigrants that's what
the name comes from I think he was my
advisor when I was in graduate school
and then be the IBM guys they build this
thing called system art and the project
is actually fascinating because they got
like eight or nine people that all had
PhDs in math and computer science again
this is early computer science but there
wasn't many people that had graduate
degrees in computer science they put
them out of room says we're gonna build
a relational database system and then
every person of the P sheets are carved
off the room and part of the problem one
person who worked on the storage layer
one person worked on the execution
engine one person worked on concurrency
control and there was one people person
pass cylinder she kept query
optimization Krita curry optimizer and
so back then the idea that you could
have a database minute system take a
query a declarative language like sequel
get Ted Cod never actually proposed a
language initially with relational model
sequel came later on because it was
embedded by IBM the Berkeley guys had
this other thing called quelle which
looks a lot like sequel but the syntax
is different
Mike Stonebraker the guy wouldn't be
dressed would he claims Quayle was
superior to sequel I disagree but you
know nobody writes it well now so but in
the back then people argued that there's
no way of Dan basement systems gonna
take a high-level language like a sequel
or quell and generate a query plant as
efficient and what a human could do
right in my hand cuz that's what people
were doing before the rational model if
you were writing this these query plans
by hand like writing the for loops and
do joins and scans by hand and so in the
same way that he will argued when the
the C C language came out ATT he was
saying oh C's to high-level it's the
compiler is never gonna generate machine
code as efficient than what humans can
write today or a human humans could
write an assembly and of course now we
know nobody writes for the most part
assembly by hand everyone writes in
higher-level languages even higher than
C and compilers do a pretty good job in
those cases they can do even better than
what the average human can do this is
what I be improved back in the 1970s
that you could take a declared language
life sequel and have the query optimizer
or the planner generate a quit plan that
was
as good if not better than what a human
can actually do or at least the average
human right so well Tom's not about how
the system optimizer works but what I'll
say as we go along and talk about
different leading up to it actually how
we do the cost based search that IBM
demented invented back in the 1970s a
lot of the designing decisions and
assumptions that they made about what
the data looks like and what the query
plans look like to simplify the problem
to make it tractable are still actually
used in practice today all right and
I'll go through what those are as we go
along
so with query optimization there's
essentially two Pro approaches to doing
this and again this is also gets into
like what distinguishes the good up my
bad optimizers so the first approach is
use static rules or heuristics so the
idea here is that we can look at our
query plan and that matches a certain
pattern like a portion of the query time
matches a pattern that we know about
then we fire off a rule that I do some
kind of transformation or rewriting of
the query plan took to make it more
often more right maybe like an Eevee if
you defy stupid things where one equals
zero right then you can have a rule can
strip that out very easily so the
important thing I'm saying on these
rules that we may need to look at the
catalog the system kalam that tells us
what our database looks like what our
tables were packets that the catalog an
is the metadata about the data what
tables do I have what columns do they
have what attributes that they have so
forth so for these rules you may have
look at a catalog consult enough to
understand what you know what our
underlying tables that should look like
but we never actually have a woman
actual data itself right we can fire off
these rules without actually going to
the table say well what did what did it
put to be what am I to was actually
contained right be the alternative is
new costly search which is instead of
you know you don't look at the data this
one you are gonna have to look at the
data in some way see the idea what the
cost base search is that
gonna do a we're going to enumerate a
bunch of different plans and different
ways and ideally intelligent manner
around looking at redundant or stupid
things or with a numerator a bunch of
her plans for us that we could choose to
execute our single query and then we're
going to use some kind of cost model to
approximate
which one is the execution cost all
these different plans of course the idea
is that we want to always pick the one
that has the lowest cost so obviously
getting the bat that cost minor if you
have accurate estimations is super hard
we'll see why as we go along and then
also in the way you enumerate the plans
is difficult to it because as I said you
don't want to look at you have a finite
amount of time to look at about
different options and you don't want to
spend you know hours and hours doing a
branch of bound search or a query that
may take one second to run who it's
actually quite amazing how how how fast
these things can actually be like every
time in this class and we'll show some
demos later on every single time I open
up the quickly in the terminal I never
wrote a single query I hit enter
it was doing both of these things in
milliseconds now again for our queries
we look at they're pretty simple so it's
not that
mind blowing but even still you know you
you can't run anything forever and find
it you know the best possible plan are
you try to approximate it so the
pipeline for our query optimization path
it was looking at the following so the
very beginning we have an application
the application is connected to the
database system and then it's going to
send us a sequel query so the first
stage would go through our optimization
pipeline is called the sequel rewriter
so the idea here is that we're given
sequel we can have some some some some
transformation rules that allow us to
rewrite the sequel in certain ways so
sometimes this occurs for distributing
databases or if you have views like The
Hobbit ale is for a table name and this
thing can say oh I see this team when a
believer you write it to be something
else
let me annotate it with additional
information to say this particular table
can be found on this node over here or
this disk over here so this is optional
right this is not that common I don't
think most David students don't want to
operate directly on sequel but you know
this is something you could do to do so
traditional opposition here then we take
the sequel query that comes out of this
if we have it otherwise you go back
through the application and they passed
it through our Seco parser and this is
just getting the lexer token stuff you
can you read a pilot class there's
nothing there's no fancy stuff we're
doing here we're just converting a
sequel string into the activities syntax
tree so then now we see the syntax tree
into our binder and a binder is
responsible for converting the named
objects referenced in our sequel query
to some kind of internal identifier so
really dude is like consulting the
catalog so the sale I require it select
star from table food I don't want to
have the rest of my query plan and have
to operate on the string foo I go to the
catalog and say hey do you have a table
called foo if yes give me some internal
identify or to allow me to find it later
on or if it doesn't have it like it says
you know people who doesn't exist at
this point we could throw in air and say
you know you looking up a table we don't
have common we don't have so now that
the buyer is gonna admit is a logical
plan well explain look where do you tell
what this is in a second but the hyoid I
think what this is there's a logical
plan in the physical plan a logical plan
could say at a high level what the query
wants to do I want to scan this table
I'm our mediator from this table I'm
gonna join these two tables it doesn't
say how all you're actually going to do
that that's the physical plan actually
specification with the Oliver you're
using comes later on so the binders
without a logical plan it's basically a
conversion the converted form of the
Signet reading now of internal IDs and
we have someone in a relational algebra
approximation and then we can feed this
now into a tree grade item again this is
optional this actually is more common
than the sequel provider this one
actually most of some purpose because
these are the static rules so to do the
tree right rewriting we have to go to
the Cal attentively and ask them hey
what does our tables look like what are
our attributes look like um but yeah we
don't have to go to the cost Monica we
can do this as use your static world
that you want to do for every query no
matter what the actual data looks like
so then the tree writers gets picked up
still the same logical plan that
finder spit out so then now we feed this
into our first night I mean this is like
the black magic part this is where we're
actually gonna do the search to try to
use a cost model to figure out what the
best plan for us is so they've been
using a combination of schema
information that the Cal provides us as
well as some of these s these estimates
that our cost model could provide us all
right this query plan is going to take X
amount of times other party plans meant
a Y amount of time X is less than Y I
want to pick this other one well we'll
see as we go along this this cost model
is going to be a typically it's a
synthetic number that the database
hasn't computes internally it has no
need to be outside world
you can't take a cost not an expert say
oh that's really 27 that's me you know
20 minutes
it's just internal thing that solves
this 8 this query plan is better than
another so just used to compare
relatively inside big data system
between different plans and has no
bearing to the outside world so if you
think Postgres this cost model it spits
out a number my sequels cost I don't
spit out a number
you can't apples and oranges you can't
compare them some systems will try to
have the class amount of estimates B
term to the actual time but that that's
tricky and usually not reliable because
hardware changes and the environment
changes and so forth all right - now the
optimizer is going to spit out a
physical plan and the physical plan is
what our data system can actually
execute so when we talk about very
execution I show these plans like it's
the hash join that you know yeah doing
torrential scans right index scans
feeding the hash drawing their choppers
drawings do my hash aggregation or
sorting aggregation that specification
happens here so once we get outside the
optimizer then there's not really
anything else we have to do until none
of them is executed create fun so again
and a high level of this is how every
single database managed system
implements it some things like a super
driver which we write every writer you
don't necessarily have to have but the
parts of binder and optimizer is this
the standard package so just to
reiterate between the logic versus
physical again the the the way to think
about is that the
I'm gonna generate a logical plan that
is roughly equivalent to the the
relational algebra expressions within
our within our query it's not always a
one-to-one mapping but at a high level
you can think of it that way I want to
do a selection on this table I'm gonna
do a filter I wanna do a projection I
would do a join right those are all be
contained in a logical plan and all
those query plan trees that I showed
before way I sort of just had the
relational algebra symbols it didn't
annotate it and say what album I was
using and those have we considered
logical plans the physical operators the
physical plan that's where we actually
specifically define what execution
strategy we're going to use for those
different operators in our query plan
I'm gonna do an index scan using this
index in this order we're gonna feed my
output an index scan into a hash story
operator right it's all the low-level
details of how we actually execute it
and so that the bunch of different
metadata we have maintain attention a
physical plan that we don't be care
about at this point or this class but
like if I know I have a order by Apple
Bob and I give you a short version on
the same join key the same by the or by
key then I can annotate my physical
operators and my query plan to say this
data that I'm spitting out is o my way
is sorted based on this key so then you
can reason and that you can drop the
order by up a ball low V it's probably a
1:1 mapping from the relational algebra
to the to the logical plan not always
true but title it is but for the visual
plan we can't assume it's a 1:1 mapping
from the logic which is the physical
right again if I could have a join plus
an order by but if I do assert merge
join in my physical operator then I can
get rid of the order by operator up
above so the the way to think about this
is that the rewriting stuff we'll talk
about and then we get to the cost cost
based search those are all operating on
logical plans but the final is always e
needs to be a physical plan okay so
before we get into the nitty-gritty
details I mean to say that this is super
hard this is the hardest part about
database systems this is actually the
part I know the least amount this is why
I'm so fascinated and I always want to
try to do more because like I don't know
it I don't understand it if you can do
this if you if you're good at doing
query optimization you can get a job
immediately move people pay you some
money to do this because like as I said
IBM meta stuff in the 1970s there was a
lot of query optimization worked under
late eighties early early nineties but
now it's all like crusty old people
right we're all like retiring or moving
on you know what 21 year 21 year old
knows about per diem ization other than
my students right so that's the one
email I always get I should share that I
should show screenshots of this the
email I always get from from people
friends at Davis companies I'm not
wearing a mic maybe I pick up most of it
right right so if you can if you can do
this you'll get paid a lot of money
because it's like super hard and it's
hard to hire people to do this kind of
stuff
one day based company told me that if
they can find people that have a PL
background they can they can do this
another Davis company told me that they
have people that have backgrounds in
high energy physics can can do query
optimization so this is joke and
databases that says like people always
say Oh query optimization is as hard as
rocket science and the joke is that no
if you fail at doing query optimization
your backup career plan could do rocket
science because there's so even harder
than that right and this is what's gonna
separate the high end guys versus the
the open-source guys or the the the
smaller systems Oracle sequel server and
IBM and teradata and all the the the
enterprise systems around for a long
time they have spent millions and
millions of dollars have hired hundreds
to hundreds of people to work on these
things and they're quite sophisticated
and so if you know if you can do this
kind of stuff you'll you in demand so
another way you talk we're not gonna
talk about this
class is that you may say all right well
this is like super hard K machine
learning solve this so can a AI solve it
no but yes right so people have tried
applying machine learning PR try apply
machine learning now more recently and
seeing some promising results but it's
still not not no anywhere near what the
you know the commercial systems can do
IBM actually tried something similar
back in the early 2000s this thing
called leo the learning optimizer turns
out it was it sucked and everybody you
know they shifted in production but
every db2 DBA I've ever talked to says
the first thing they do when they
install db2 is turn off that learning
crap cuz it never worked make things
worse so just machine learning is is a
potential way to improve things but it's
not going to be you know a magic bullet
to solve everything so as I said this is
the one thing about data systems that
I'm most excited about and know the
least about last semester we covered in
the advanced class we did three lectures
on this I think I'm expanding that to
make four or five necks semester just
because like we build our own query
optimizer at CMU it's super hard for me
to get students come work on it but they
all get jobs immediately but like this
is this is something we'll call a cover
more in the advanced class so yeah I
don't know bad-mouthing any other
systems some systems are they'll create
optimized areas total crap you know
cover that later at all fine okay all
right so we have a lot to cover today
and like I said I don't think we're to
get through all of it so what this might
spill over into next week I don't know
why I just didn't break it up to two
semesters or to two lectures before this
but it is what it is so first we'll talk
about relational algebra equivalencies
the core underlying concept that's an
allow us to do manipulation and
transformations of our query plans to
find better alternatives then we'll talk
about how we do at cost estimation how
do we take a query plan and and in our
cost model and estimator we have to do
to execute it and then won't spend more
time talk about enumeration this is like
the search strategy define different
options for the cost base search model
and then we'll talk about how to handle
sub queries we oh we probably want to
get through half of this but that's okay
all right so as I said the core
underlying concept that we're going to
take
take advantage of when we do query
optimization is the fact that we
understand the high-level properties of
a relational algebra and therefore can
permute or transform the relational
algebra or a plan that's equivalent to
some relation Auto statement in
different ways and still produce the
same result so we're gonna say we have
two relational algebra expressions or
two query plans so to speak that if they
produce the same set of tuples then we
know that they're equivalent and
therefore it's it's it's it's valid for
me to transform my original relation
algebra expression into a new expression
so notice I'm here again I'm saying a
set of tuples because remember
relational algebra or the relational
model is unordered so I don't care and
let's have an order by statement or
order by clause I don't care that one
query plan produces tuples ordered this
way and another query plan produces
troopas order in this way
they're still equivalent and that means
there's me more options available to us
to figure out what is the wouldn't you
know what's a better query plan for us
to use so we can apply these sensitivity
of the Trinity and the committed hippedy
properties of relational algebra right
standard you know standard logic to
change the expression in different ways
move operators around to produce a more
efficient plan so this high level
technique is called query rewriting so
this is that rewriting step that I was
talking about before right after the
binder we can do a tree rewriter where
we can look at the relational algebra
representation of a logical plan and
then move things around to produce
something that's more efficient so let's
look a really simple example here let's
say I have two tables student and
enrolled and I want to do a join where I
between the two tables where I want to
get all the students that are enrolled
in the class where they got a great egg
so if I almost take a literal
translation of the seco statement I
would roughly come up with a relational
algebra statement like this do a join on
student enrolled then apply the the
filter on grade and then have the
projection where I just produce the
course ID and the name of the student
right so what's a really stable
optimization we can do for this
yes brain he said push the filter to be
inside and rolled right so he's exactly
right so this technique is called
predicate push down so the reason why
it's called he said push into I'll say
the typical term is pushed down because
you're pushing it down into the Cory
plan so let's say this is this is the
query plan tree and so when you take
this filter and have it be before the
join right cuz what are we doing here
well we want to reduce the amount of
work we have to do in our joint joint
operator so rather than having the
filter be above the join operator where
I'm just taking all the students and all
the enrolled records and in the doing
the joint on them then apply the filter
it's better for me to do the filter
early think again always think of in
extremes say my enroll table has a
billion tuples but only one student ever
got an A in any class then I would do a
joint on a billion tuples all only the
end up producing a single result as much
as my output but if I do my filter early
here and now I'm doing a joint on one
tuple because then this is this is more
expensive than this in general
I said this is the general idea what
we're trying to do here in query
optimization we're trying to identify
cases where we can end up doing less
work because that's what minute and of
the day that's what we want to do if you
do less work it's an have lower cost to
faster runtimes and require potential
less hardware yes this question is what
a query optimizer also be able to change
this or change change left in or yes
we'll get there but not yet so his
question is it might mice this is like a
super simple example like like I can do
this the heuristic I have a query plan I
always want to push down the predicate I
don't need to look at what the data
looks like to do what you're asking
should this be the inner versus the
outer I need to know how much data is
getting fed into this because again the
the smaller table should always be the
outer table that requires a cost model
we can do this we can do this push down
without ever looking at the data yes
right so question is what does a look at
in relation out it's just moving the the
grade-b inside of this right sitting and
join this so I mean there's a
parentheses so this is saying do the
filter only rule table back standpoint
yes yeah yes correct yes yes he died
great yeah good question okay first
question is can predicate pushdown ever
be bad yes so in this really simple
example here like doing that something
you know something that's easy to do
there are some predicates that can be
expensive to compute so now this is
where the end the data systems cost
model can try to say well so example so
sometimes there you could have will
cover this next class on Monday next
week but there's things called
user-defined functions so it's out of
having like a function you know it's an
expression either touch a constant or
another another naturally and a tuple I
can have it invoke a function that can
then be any arbitrary code like I can
have a user-defined function written in
C or Python and that Python code makes a
call out to a remote server does some
kind of computation maybe a pays in
Bitcoin for the micro transaction and it
comes back so if I know that for this
predicate here to do the join this is
super selective meaning there's not very
many tuples coming out of this it may I
may be oak better off applying this up
here because that this is you know
monetarily is more expensive than doing
this so you don't always want
to push this down but in general you oh
yes you do my microtransaction is a
far-fetched example you could do it but
like it's stupid you wouldn't want to do
that right but there's other things too
like if there's computing the hash or
something like that or some kind of
crypto stuff you may want to put that up
above here here but again the data ISM
can reason about that okay so let's go
through now a bunch of these different
operators to talk about what kind of
optimizations we can apply for the other
relational operators and our query plans
so we've already covered this one right
the predicate pushdown right the idea is
that we want to do filtering as early as
possible ignoring the cost of applying
the filter but that's gonna allow us to
throw away data more quickly in a disk
based system applying a filter sooner
sooner rather than later it's usually
better because then I'm not copying as
much data up you know up above and
polluting my memory you can also reorder
the predicates themselves so that the
more selective ones are applied first so
let's say my last example where I had
great you know someone has a grade
equals a but let's say I had another
predicate where age equals you know
great age greater than 99 so find me all
students at Carnegie Mellon that have
got an A in the class and are under
older than 99 years I don't think there
is anybody right so it's better off for
me to apply the the age predicate first
because that's gonna filter out way more
things before looking at the at the gray
predicate now you may say all right ways
in that just you know a slight
computational overhead yeah for dismay
system maybe doesn't matter that so much
but in in other systems like a memory
system then that can matter a lot yes
yes so so his statement is like for this
one I'm claiming that we're not looking
at selectively the data so you couldn't
actually do this one yeah that's true
yes for this one yes you're right but
pushing down you always want to do that
yes
breaking a predicate we better than
emerging it ladies like merging movie
night human scan of the data once and so
his question is why would be breaking it
up be better than just having to be all
at once again if the computational cost
of one of the predicates is more
expensive than another
maybe you want to break off that one and
have them be up above in the query plan
yes if it's a column store then maybe I
want to do a pass through the column
first toast everything out and then for
the things that match them to the next
one yes but that is the right example
and then for this one here again you can
simplify complex this is a simplify
complex predicate to be more easy to
compute this is a trivial example X x
equals y and y equals 3 well again
through through the transitivity calls
we know that x is just this is just x
equals 3 so we can rewrite it like this
so now what happens is that in when we
use going through a billion tuples we
can just look at each edge with x and y
check to see whether equivalent to a to
a constant which is way cheaper than
having to go get the reference of the y
attribute in the tuple and then copy it
you know to some register or some
variable and then doing the comparison
right this is like a micro optimization
that would mostly only matters for the
in memory guys all right for projections
we can also push them down as early as
possible and the idea here is that we
want to minimize the amount of data we
have to copy going you know from one
opera to the next and this mostly
matters in the rows store systems
because if the rows really wide and I'm
moving that entire tuple up from one
operative the next then if I can strip
out as much data that I don't need it
early as possible then I'm copying less
data from one step to the next right so
in say in this example here say the the
student table has a thousand columns but
my query only needs two attributes it
needs
and he's the student name so I can then
introduce now a projection in here
before I feed into my joint operator so
I strip out the nine hundred ninety
eight columns that I don't need and only
pass in the two that I do need right
this is very actually very common in
distributed databases because moving
data over the network is expensive and
slow so if I'm getting this is on one
node this is on another node and I'm
doing the join on the same node that I
rolled on then I want to strip out as
much as I can before I send that over
the network all right so everything I've
showed you here so far these are doing
applying optimizations on one in a
relational algebra operators relational
algebra expressions we can apply these
same optimizations for the underlying
predicate expressions themselves in our
queries so I'm going to show you a bunch
of examples of how different data
systems can rewrite query plans to
simplify them or avoid doing stupid work
and this comes from this great blog
article over a few years ago where
somebody lifted out all here's one of
different operations you can do that
doesn't require a cost model and we'll
we'll give a demo of some of some of his
comparisons but it's really nice because
he provides a there's a github
repository that has the sample database
he uses for his analysis and it works on
sequel Server db2 Oracle like working on
a bunch of different data systems you
can take the same database same queries
and see how the different optimizers can
can can rewrite things and fix things
okay so the first kind of thing we can
rewrite is to remove stupid predicates
or unnecessary predicates so in this
case here select star from table a where
one equals zero what is this value a
true false so what does that mean that
means for every single tuple I'm going
to scan on table a I'm gonna check oh is
the predicate false equal to true it
never will be equal to true so therefore
no tuple would match right so the data
easily recognize that I have an
impossible predicate where no tuple
could ever possibly match this it can
just actually skip the scan entirely
and just produce you back a an empty
result right away so you may say all
right well this is stupid Annie why
would anybody write one equals zero
nobody would actually do this number a
won't correct theory people you know
people shouldn't be that stupid but a
lot of times in applications the the
queries not gonna be constructed from a
single line of code you're not gonna
have a string variable in your in your
application code that you then just you
know immediately send off to to the
database server a lot of times these
sequel queries are constructed from like
dashboards and tools where people click
from different things adding different
options or composing the query so now a
buncha different libraries so that a
bunch of different functions are all to
be constructing a a sequel query so
there's not one single place you can
look in the code and see you know where
one equals zero it may come from some
other function from some other part of
your organization from code that you
didn't write so if the data can
recognize this that this is stupid and
not do this this is a huge win for us
because now we don't even have to look
at the data likewise you can do the
opposite you can have one where
everything's gonna match one equals one
right so in this case here every tuple
is gonna match but I don't want to
actually I don't want actually apply
this predicate and see whether they're
gonna match again if I have a billion
tuples I don't want to have to go
through every single tube oh and say hey
for this tuple does one equal one true
yes I'll put it next to but what does 1
equal 1 yeah it's true I'll put it right
instead I can say well I don't need to
do this 1 equals 1 at all and now I just
do a scruncho scan straight dump of the
table as the output and not worry about
applying any predicates
alright then that's cutting down on the
computational calls I think I says you
just rewrite it like select star from
egg alright so these are pretty simple
but we can do this for other things more
complex queries we do the same kind of
thing for joins so here now on my table
a this scheme is up there the primary
key is the ID column so here I'm doing a
self join where a as a 1 joined on a as
a 2 on a 1 to ID equals a to die ID so
what is this query actually saying it's
saying for every single tip on a check
to see whether it exists in a
and of course it's always gonna be true
because we know ID is the primary key so
do I exist in this other table the
answer is always gonna be yes so it can
identify that this predicate is entirely
wasteful with this join is entirely
wasteful and is rewrite it as select
star from egg and again relying on
relational algebra equivalencies we
would know that this is equivalent to
this yes because that his question is
wives conditioned on ID being the
primary key because you know it's unique
and you know it's not null so therefore
you can rewrite it if it is if it could
be null then null doesn't equal null so
therefore you wouldn't have a match
right no it's always no like no we can
over the turban I'll try this one
doesn't equal null actually the the
result of this one equal null is null
right
you unknown so your question is is no
equal to null unknown is no no I think
that one actually evaluate to true but
in this case here if it's no then it
won't work all right so what are more
complicated things we do so we can also
now ignore projections that are
unnecessary so in this one here this is
sort of a rewrite of the of the last
query the self join so this is a select
star from a and then in my where clause
I haven't exists where I just say this
basically says return true if there's
anything that matches any any result
inside the the inner query here so this
is saying if for every tuple in a
produce the output if there exists a
tuple where the a dot ID equals the a2
to ID and against the primary key so
it's always gonna match so inside of
this we're materializing or have a
projection on the vowel column but this
is completely unnecessary right this is
us having to do not only the waist will
join but also copy this projection which
is copy this attribute out it's part of
projection and that's unnecessary as
well right so in this case here we can
just rewrite this
entirely this part here it is entirely
like a select are from a the last one is
to emerging predicates so this one here
we have select star from a where val
between one and a hundred and bow
between or val is between 50 and 150 so
in this case here if you just think
think of the number line this is
completely redundant because if it's
between 1 and 100 then it can also can
be between 50 and 150 if it's between
50-100 so for this one here I could
rewrite this to be a single between
cause we're 1 between 1 and 150 okay
select so this is how you know this is
sort of obvious to see how how you want
to do this let's see whether who
actually does it everybody loves demos
right so as I said that blog article
that I mentioned has has source code you
can download and includes the the schema
and insert statements for for a bunch of
different 8 assistance so unfortunately
I broke my sequel server installation
yesterday so I can't get to work but
I'll do a demo on Postgres my sequel
oracle maria DB and in sequel light so
again the the schema looks like this i'm
not sorry
right so the the sample data is we're
gonna use its it's like a it's like a
online video store but it's sort of like
the IMDB stuff you looked at there's
actors and then people are renting
movies right but we're gonna focus on
the actor table so again the nice thing
about this is that the they provide for
the same you know the same database for
all these different for all all these
different database servers right so
again there's two hundred tuples in this
and then we'll just go into to my sequel
real quickly select star or sub count
star from actor alright there's 200 in
every single one okay
so the first thing we want to try out is
that impossible query where one equals
zero so again what I'm doing here is for
Postgres right this is Postgres you have
explained keyword will spit up the query
plan and then the impedance you put the
aniline analyze modifier after explained
that will actually run the query but
then still show you either the query
plan and what it actually did right so
in this one here it says up above one
time filter is false so it recognized
that one equals zero is always going to
evaluate to false so it applied the
filter once installed that for the
entire table no tuple is ever gonna
match so it didn't actually didn't
actually run and run read the data it
said oh it's false it's nothing gives
you back nothing right away so we can do
this in my sequel so then my sequel
explained is not as good like if you
just do this then you get something like
like this but if you do the for whatever
reason the - or that /g then you can
actually get a tree it is one of those
but here you see the in the extra
parameter they say have been possible
where so I recognize that nothing's ever
gonna match don't even bother applying
that where clause it also has this
little warning thing here which is
annoying this is my sequel 5.7 I I don't
know what it's been fixed in in my
sequel 8 but you have to run show
warnings and then it spits out like what
actually happens so you see here in the
where Clause they rewrote my 1 equals 0
that is wrote that as 0 so everything
evaluates to false right so now we'll
try in and let's do Oracle
so with Oracle the way it works is I say
explain plan for and the syntax is
always slightly different and it says
explain which now I got to go now to
another table it has the the plan that
it got explained so the oil explained is
actually is exactly betterment then sexy
better than post quest post best one is
very good this one is actually pretty
good too because it shows you like you
know computational time then I'm at Rose
and data there accessing is actually
really nice so what are they saying here
all right so this says that it knows I'm
doing select statement and it has a
filter and it says how I'm gonna access
the table right so the thing to point
out though down here they have
information with the predicate so they
say we're filter null is not null so
Oracle doesn't doesn't support boolean
z' right so it has no way to say true or
false so it rewrote my does 1 equals 0
to be null is not null which is always
false cuz null is null so this is their
this is the way they're representing
false so they rewrote now the query plan
recognize that this thing that's false
and therefore you don't actually have to
run it
let's just go back to post us real
quickly and - well he was asking before
right so I can say select right I can
treat the data since like a calculator
but I can say select norm right that's
nothing but there's no equal null
nothing it's no is no equal false no
nothing right this is falsely equal to
false true is true you know just so
anything that any any time you say
there's no equals something
the answer is null the empty space is
null the way to get around that is null
is null then it's true so what Oracle is
doing is no not no false ok
all right so then last one would you
seek a light again the syntax is always
different they have explained query plan
without before and then it produces this
so this is not actually that helpful
right this is just telling us that we're
doing some kind of scan on the actor
table so if we removed the query plan
part then you get something that looks a
lot different than when everybody else
should now you get something that looks
like assembly or some kind of machine
code so without going to the details of
wasting code light works is that they
actually convert the logical plan or the
physical plan that the optimizer spits
out into a bunch of these op codes think
of this is like the JVM bytecode and
then they have an interpreter that can
they'll get and now execute these
bytecode so this is like this is
literally the program to execute this
particular query and so from what I can
tell right they say where r1 is not you
are - I'm not exactly what that means
then you go to ten but in this case here
it looks like they're actually doing
doing the scan here so the best I can
tell I'm not sure whether they're
actually stripping this out actually no
not equals this yeah
it may be truncating it they're
recognizing that I don't have to do a
scan all right so everybody can handle
this this is good so let's try now the
useless predicate let's try the one
equals one let's go back to Postgres
well now it looks like it's telling us
it's actually doing it well I said he
should do it cuz it's one equals one
right so this is just saying that I
recognize that I can remove the filter
and I just execute the query right away
try the same thing in in my sequel
no Annalise sorry right and this one it
figured out that it can just throw away
the filter entirely and just scan
everything so that's good
let's try Oracle explained and then go
back to this right the filter is
completely gone it just now it's just
Swiss straights mental scan and then for
sequel Lite this is not helpful so we'll
remove that query plan part and then now
you see that it's inside of this the for
loop here where they're scanning over
the table they've removed the predicate
all right
so let's look at an example where you
have more compliment
could look at the catalog and try to
figure out what the right thing to do is
so the schema for the the actor table is
pretty straightforward right we just
have an actor first name last name and
last update okay so what we're gonna try
to do here is we're going to try to have
a query where we say the where the actor
ID is null so we want to run this query
and so what should happen here is that
we would look in the catalog and say
well the actor ID is the primary key and
it can't be null so therefore I know
that no tuple will match my predicate
and therefore I can remove that that
where clause or to just end of return
back immediately the you know an empty
set so this is an example where the
rewriting phase those rules could look
in the catalog and understand something
about the table or the attributes that
are being being you know it may be
accessing the predicate and start
throwing out crap that's useless so just
to prove that that our table cannot
support
no attributes for the idea for the in
the actor IDE if I try to insert a tuple
with a null for the first column then it
you know
Postgres picked it out and says there's
an error if I try to do the same thing
in in Oracle Oracle flips out says that
the actor IDE can't be null throws an
error let's try this in my sequel my
sigil does have default I think we gotta
go current timestamp actually new
default should work here let me insert
it let's see whether that's actually in
there
we're lastname equals Pablo let me do it
right cuz the way my secret works is the
the the actor ID is an auto increment
key so instead of in this version of my
sequel instead of throwing an error if I
try to insert null it says oh you're an
auto increment key so go go ahead and
let me just run that and replace the
null with the next value whereas every
other system will throw an error says
you trying to insert null my sequel will
let you do it alright but let's let's
try to run our query so we know that
that no attrex should actually null the
no-no tuple should have a null actor ID
so we try to run this query now where is
null right
Postgres that looks like it actually is
going to run it
now she did run it right applied the
filter and remove two hundred tuples
so Postgres was not you better recognize
that no tuple with a new tube was at
actor ID could ever be null and not
actually run it and actually and still
ran it let's try it in in my sequel my
pc go figure it out
impossible where and it can be like
Amelie ignore it try it in sequel server
or sorry in or Oracle explained and then
there's our lovely null is not null
there's our false so a recognize that
this is this is never good actually
gonna evaluate to true and get thrown
away so post goes actually got it wrong
my C gonna walk around it right all
right two more examples
let's do now that range query we have
before where we want to say we want to
get all the films that are where the
film ID is between one and two and film
ID between 199 and 200 so this is again
another impossible we're right so
nothing should come back we're on
explain so my post guys couldn't figure
it out right it's doing that lookup that
that should never happen that would
never produce any results in in my
sequel
this one I'm not sure about there's no
matching no matching rolling Khan stable
I think this means that they were able
to figure it out that they yeah this one
I'm not sure about this it has a warning
though see what see whether he wrote it
to this question isn't this a status
fearless I build a problem and which is
np-complete yes but like but for basic
things I can I could identify that it's
never going to you know produce anything
and throw it away
so this is this one or actual crisis no
no no hope for this one you could have a
rule you could write a heuristic that
says if I have if I do all my lookups on
on the on a given attribute right and I
have a range here between 1 and 2
inclusive and between 199 and 200 the
sets don't intersect and it's
conjunction where I had to have both of
them I know it'll never match I can
throw it away that's like that one
that's not sad that's pretty
straightforward all the parts are
satisfiable you have to do with that yes
all right so any questions about what
I'm showing here I'm showing that you
can just reason about what the query
looks like without actually looking at
the data without actually having to run
anything and determine whether you know
it's a ways to simplify the predicate
will lead into now the discussion of a
how are action committees estimates so
the for these symbolic demos here this
joins a pretty straightforward
so we can you know easily maybe a reason
about which one should be the inner
versus the outer things go bad though
when you start having a lot more joins
because the complexity of the problem of
making this decision is going to explode
so the number of different ways we can
do a join for
for a query when we have n tables to
join is gonna be four to the N so this
clearly there's no way we can enumerate
every single possible join ordering and
for our query and try to figure out the
best one alright you know it's a large
number when it has a name right so we're
gonna see how the data center is going
to be able to strip down the the number
of different combinations and plans that
have to enumerate for these joint
orderings and that's going to reduce the
search base of the problem but before we
get there we need to understand how
we're actually gonna estimate how much
work we're gonna do for these joins or
these different scans
so I've already said this a little bit
before but the the cost model is gonna
allow us to assess or an estimate how
much work we think we're gonna have to
do in our database system and again this
is an internal synthetic number that is
only allows us to compare the relative
performance of different query plans and
we within the same database system we
can't compare across all of them so this
could be a combination of a bunch of
different things we've already seen that
when we talk about joint algorithms that
you want to do you want to base it on
the number of disk I'm out of disk IO
that I'm gonna have to do it all so you
betta how much DRAM how much memory
space you're gonna have to take up on
your buffer pool as you're computing the
the query if you're gonna distribute a
database then the number of messages is
also an important thing because the
network IO is slow and inefficient so
the the main takeaway for this is that
the cost models that allow us to say is
one plan better than another without
actually having to run the query plan
because that's the only way to get the
actually the truth the true cost is
actually run the query plan but you
don't want to do that cuz if again I've
had if I have 4dn different joint
orderings
I can't run for dit for to the N
different query plans for one query
because that'll take forever so a cost
models that allow us to approximate this
you know will giving up sacrificing
accuracy of our estimates in exchange
for efficiency now there's some database
systems where they don't have a cost
model they don't have a query optimizer
they actually just fire off all queries
and see which one ever comes back first
and that's the one they pick
so the only system that I know that does
this is actually MongoDB right and it
seems kind of stupid why would you do
this why would you put a cost model well
they weren't supporting joins back in
the day and they needed a cost model
they need a query optimizer
so if I have to figure out what index to
pick and just fire fall of Aquarius
whichever one comes back first that's
the one that's the fastest and then I
just remember that every single time I
see that same query over and over again
and eventually you know they'll run the
trial again and first as sort of
simplistic as it is it actually works
quite well for them this is where their
rights doesn't matter right what is the
right right is doing a like a index
lookup to find something right and then
you make the modification the index
lookup is the more expensive part
finding the data is more expensive than
the actual right but yes if I'm updating
the table and my index is now changing
its distribution then what they would do
is they would have to have a trigger to
says well I've run the same query a
thousand times let me refresh and rerun
everything again or my table is my table
in their world collection has changed
I've updated by 10%
let me just rerun that trial again it's
just heuristics yes these questions are
they running sequentially are they
running one after another so like
MongoDB is a distribute database as far
as they know the way they do it is I
have I have a query that need to run on
a bunch of nodes and they have a
different segments or partitions of the
data and they all have the same indexes
just based on different parts of the you
know the the table so for this one I'll
use this index this one I'll use that
index and so forth and see which one
actually is the fastest and then you see
the same query again that you needed to
strip it across all of these different
nodes you just pick that same index so
that was the fastest one for everyone
again super simple but it works pretty
well
all right so the way we're going to be
able to approximate the cost of
executing a query is the this is by
maintaining internal statistics about
what our tables look like this has come
up multiple times throughout the
semester where I say oh the day says we
can know something about the tables this
is what I mean this is how they're
actually able to do this so
inside of the system catalog we're going
to maintain metadata about what our
indexes of what our tables look like
what the values are in the tuples and
then how we're actually gonna maintain
this information is gonna vary based on
the different systems so I said like
getting a simple heuristic like if my
table changes by 10% we collect my
statistics other systems can say well
while I run the query also look at look
at the tape look at the data as I'm
going along and then propagate you know
information about what I see back to my
back to my internal says sister catalog
you can also run this manually so in
again this they all vary in the
different systems about what the syntax
actually is but in general can analyze
so the commonality of across all of them
you call this analyze function and that
kicks off a sequential scan that does
looks at the date the data and again
updates this internal information about
what the distribution looks like and
then you think it's you you could
trigger this based on updates to the
table or like a cron job that runs every
day or so forth and we saw about multi
version control let's talk about
vacuuming think of that like a garbage
collection and the JVM you can run
analyze at the same time as well because
when you're doing twitch will scans
you're looking at everything and you can
update these things alright so in the
sake of time I'm going to cut it off
here because now we're actually gonna
get to the formulas of how you use the
statistics to estimate these values well
we'll pick up on this next week and then
we'll get into actually how do you do
the enumeration in the columns as well
okay alright so again on Wednesday in
class we're having the exam it's real is
not a joke one year somebody was like oh
I thought you were kidding no this is
real
bring your CMU ID bring your sheet of
paper but notes and then bring a
calculator and I'm having office hours
neatly afterwards but if you need to
talk to me and you know at a different
time send me an email
I'm happy to meet with anyone okay all
right guys good luck and see you on
Wednesday
Oh
cool to settle the case it means a nice
little bits of broken bar goes in
crushed up can let the cows in the demo
I'll try he's with see knives in my
system I'm blessed
let's go get the next one get over good
there will be Sun ricochet jelly hit the
deli for a boat one naturally bless ya
what rap is like a laser beam the boys
in the bush say nice fella can't even
wrap the bottle of us a nice sympathy
goes don't feel like drinking that
quality to you token can't drop cross he
was alive and if the sake don't know
your phone can tap a tank