[Music]
hi guys let's get started again round
applause would you drop tables down all
right how are you thank you okay yeah
okay awesome all right before we get
started I want to go through some
comments and feedback we've had on the
course on the nose or bane of all the
places we could get feedback about the
course and that's YouTube so here's some
of the comments we've gotten so far on
on YouTube and it's the sort of standard
stuff right and he's the worst professor
I don't learn anything about databases
that's okay
he wasn't hoping I get cancer soon this
guy says he all my friends go to see him
you they say this professor has the
worst hygiene anybody on school
he smells like old boiled eggs so that
is true I did I did you should have a
hygiene problem and now you use like a
special shampoo but if it's overpowering
it was still an issue of let me know and
we got feedback about you right yo DJ
drop tables beets are so fresh that I
had to take my shirt off and not sure
what that means and they want us to
feature you more look Norway this kind
of crap but there is actually one
mistake I made last class that people
correctly pointed out and he when we
were talking on hash functions I asked
he named sha-256 and I think he named
md5 and I incorrectly said that sha-256
is not a it's not a symmetrical meaning
you can't reverse it and this guy says
take down the whole video but whatever
um but my point still stands right so
sha tsui g6 has cryptographic properties
that we don't care about when we're
doing our in our hash table so we would
never actually use that the X has X hash
or the city has farm hash stuff that we
talked about before that's the kind of
hash function we don't use
so in theory you could still use sha-256
it's not reversible but nobody does that
because it'd be too slow okay all right
so the other things that can just
reminder for everyone what's on the
docket so next week on Friday project
one should be done that's due at
midnight
much we have already finished but again
post on Piazza if you have questions as
you go along and we've been updating
slightly there's your pin post that
provide clarifications on Piazza that
help guide you along too if you have
questions about different aspects of it
and then homework too we released on
Monday this week and that'll be due the
following Monday after after the first
project is due okay so any high-level
questions about project one who here is
not tried to get it running on the local
machine or their development environment
I was at least try that okay good
awesome okay all right so recall from
last class we started talking about
different kind of data structures we
could have inside our database system
and we spent the entire lecture talking
about hash tables and we talked about
how hash table are - in general but
especially hash tables can be used in a
variety places inside the database
system like using it for internal
metadata actually storing the underlying
tables in our database and also
temporary data structures like you know
building hash table to do a join so for
the first three uses of data structures
for a lot of these cases the the hash
tables gonna be good enough right for
think of like internal the system it's
not very often you need to be able to do
range queries most of the time you want
to say go give me a single key and give
me you know for giving key give me the
value you're doing point query lookups
so the thing we want to talk about now
though is table indexes and this is
where we we may want to actually run
queries that want to do range scans and
therefore hash tables are going to be
insufficient for us because you know
because you can only do single key
lookups so everyone here should be
roughly aware of what a table index is
but I just one provides some a more
formal definition so that we have a
basic understanding going throughout the
rest of the lecture what we're talking
about so a table index is a essentially
a replica of some subset of attributes
in our tables and that we're storing in
a more efficient manner that allows us
to do efficient lookups to find the
thing that we're looking for so you know
in the worst case scenario if we want to
find a particular key in our table you
just do a support
scan for that but the idea of putting
into a table index we would have sit
this auxiliary data structure that we
can traverse or do a lookup into and
find exactly what we want more quickly
than having to ask when shal scam so the
key thing to point out here is that the
index is going to be a replica of the
table so that means that has to be
synchronized with the table meaning if
we modify a tuple in our table we want
that change be reflected in our in our
index because we don't want any false
negatives or false positives we don't
want to add something to our table not
put in our index and then we do a lookup
to find that that that tuple and it's
not our index and come back with it with
a negative result right so the database
system is would be responsible for
maintaining these indexes and keeping
them completely synchronized with the
with the with the underlying table and
this is completely transparent to you as
as the application programmer I don't
know when I insert I don't the say o
insert in this table and all by the way
update these other indexes the database
system at least have a sequel database
system would see the insert query and
know that you not only don't need to
update the table also to update any
index as I have on that table so there's
this trade-off now in our system between
having a lots of indexes make queries go
faster and then the cost of maintaining
them and we'll see this as we go along
today and we saw this actually with hash
tables last time right
inserting something into an index
sometimes will be really fast and
sometimes could be really expensive
depending on whether you know whatever
we want to insert a given key there's
something already there or not so again
when we have a query show up the
database system is responsible for
figuring out what's the most efficient
access method for me to use for the
system to use to answer the result of
your query and again this is transparent
to use the application programmer I just
write my select statement I don't
specify normally in some cases you can I
don't specify normally exactly what
index I want to use the database system
can configure that out for me and again
going back to the very first lecture
this is one of the the benefits or the
advantages of the relational model and
it's clear language like sequel if I now
my table I are very much rely
application and then later
and decide to add to index I want to go
back and rewrite my secret and I'll use
that index the database system configure
that automatically for me in theory it
doesn't always get it right so this
particular step of actually taking a
query and picking out what indexes use
this will falls under the umbrella of
query optimization which is a super hard
problem we'll cover it us in after the
midterm but this is sort of it's like a
optimization problem to decide you know
what's the best wave XT given query
amongst all these different choices I
have so we'll cover that later on in the
semester but for now just assume that we
know what index we want to pick what we
do lookups so of course it's now as an
always in computer science and databases
there's just trade-off between doing one
thing a lot versus doing it not at all
so if you have a lot of indexes that'll
make your queries certainly go faster
did you look ups on them but now you
have this additional cost of having to
store those indexes and actually
maintain them I said again indexes are
going to take up pages we're to store
that in our buffer pool while the write
that out the disk so that takes up space
but then now as I said when I do updates
to my tables I have to go and also
update my all my indexes to reflect
those changes so if my table has a
thousand indexes which would you know in
practice people do that kind of stuff if
I now do an insert I have to do a
thousand updates to all those indexes
and my update operation or insert
operation isn't considered done until
I've modified all my indexes because
they have to be always synchronized so
again we're not really gonna discuss how
you decide what indexes to pick but this
is another hard problem in databases as
well they have tools to do
recommendations for you to decide what
mixes when it pick or you pay a lot of
money for human DBAs to do this for you
all right so the things we're talk about
today is just an overview of what a B+
tree is and then we'll do we'll spend
some time to discussing like you know
one of the implementation details we
have to be concerned of when we build
out our index and then we'll finish up
talking about some additional
optimizations that real systems actually
do to actually make this thing be useful
in practice ok so the first thing we
need we need to address
is this this what is it B plus tree and
how does that relate to a B tree so this
is sort of the downside of databases is
that a lot of times the same word is
used to reflect different things and be
quite confusing for someone we can try
to get started to understand what's the
actual difference with these things so
first of all there's sort of this class
of data structures called B trees and
then within that there is a specific
data structure that is a B tree so
oftentimes people use that B+ tree and B
tree interchangeably but if you go back
to the literature back in the 1970s
these were actually distinct data
structures and wikipedia has them as
distinct data structures today so the
first B tree came out in 1971 the then
the B tree B+ tree came out two years
later in 1973 there's no paper that
describes what the B+ tree is there's a
1979 survey paper that says here's all
that you know the B+ tree or B trees
that are out there and oh by the way IBM
invented the B+ tree in 1973 and
supposedly there's a tech report that
says describes this but you can't easily
find it on the internet and then during
the 70's and 80's was a bunch of these
other ones that are variants on this the
P star tree is variant on the B tree and
then actually the B link tree is came
out in 1981 and actually this was
invented here at CMU this is the paper
that describes it so this is written by
Phil Lehman that dude still works here
he's in the dean's office so you if you
loved this lecture you can go talk to
him he loves every time I see him I
always like oh we discuss the peeling
tree in my class and he's like all that
paper so right dope forty years later
it's it's still around so the reason why
I showed these these other these other
trees it's because we're gonna focus on
the B+ tree but we're not gonna in a
modern system we're not gonna use it
exactly the way it's described in like
the 1970s we're actually gonna borrow
bits and pieces from all these other
trees that existed before but now we're
just gonna call that the B plus tree and
a lot of times you'll see in in database
systems they'll say we're using a B tree
I can almost guarantee you or at least
I've yet to see one assistant where they
say they're using a B tree and it's not
really actually a B+ tree like the
look at the Postgres source code a
person has documentation they talk about
using a b-tree but from from as much as
I can tell looking at at what it's
actually doing it's really a B+ tree so
again these words are used
interchangeably I'll try to say always
B+ tree I'll pray for mention what a B
tree is later on but in practice this is
what we care about this is what we want
to use in our system okay so a B+ tree
is a self-balancing tree data structure
so the B in in in in B+ tree or B tree
means balanced and the idea is that it's
gonna keep data we insert into our urns
our data structures in sorted order and
that's gonna allow us to do efficient
searches rental scans along the leaf
nodes assertions and Dilys image and we
can do all this in in log n again
contrasting this with the hash table the
hash table in the best case scenario was
a 1 worst case scenario is o n in a B+
tree because it's balanced it's always
gonna be log N and that means
essentially no matter that the distance
from the root to any any key in a leaf
node is always log n no matter how many
times we delete and insert and change
things around so the B plus tree came
out in the 1970s because they were
trying to build a data structure that
would make it efficient to do you know
index lookups on Horn Hardware where the
disk was super slow and memory memory
was limit limited so the B+ tree has
this nice advantage of compared to like
a B tree is that you can just scan along
the leaf nodes after you traverse to the
bottom and you'll read everything in
special order or sweater doing so when
to scan along them you don't never have
to go back up in general the again even
though this was designed in the the
1970s it's still widely used today and
actually even for faster discs and for
in-memory databases where there is no
disk the B+ tree actually outperforms a
lot of things and it's still very very
useful so this is the original paper
this is one that everyone cites the
ubiquitous B tree from 1979 and it's
here in this paper they describe or they
mentioned that oh yeah there's this
thing called the P plus tree from IBM
and it came out in 1973
and this is what normal people cite when
you want to cite a paper for for the be
blustery so what are the properties are
going to be plus tree so it's considered
an M way search tree meeting we can
within every node in our in our in our
tree it can have M different paths to up
to other nodes or up to n paths not
always exactly M again it's perfectly
balanced we're going to mean this is the
data structure maintains the balance
over time as you as you modify the tree
and so by balance I mean that in the
distance from one leaf node or any leaf
node to the root is always going to be
log n it's always gonna do the same the
other thing is have to do is that we
have to maintain this this guarantee
that the each node is at least half full
so again if I for the number of keys I
can have in my node I have to have more
than half minus one half number passed
in my in my tree and then I have to have
less than n minus 1 so n minus 1 would
be a completely full node so I always
have to be at least half full and then
we'll see this when we started doing
deletes if I'm not then I have to start
moving data around so that my note is
half full and again that's how they're
gonna guarantee this first one that the
distance is always always the same and
then the simple one is that every every
inner node which I'll describe in the
next slide if you have K keys in stored
in your node and you can have up to n
minus 1 you have K keys you're gonna
have k plus 1 non no children job cabe
pass or pointers to k plus 1 pass are
pointers to children below actually quit
show hands who here has seen a B+ tree
before very few good ok good
again this is the best data structure
for databases so this is why you're here
alright so this is the basic B plus tree
all right and the layout is that again
along the bottom we have our leaf nodes
and then any node that's not a leaf node
is considered to internode now this tree
has a height of 2 I mean it has two
levels so the inner node is also the
root node alright there's always been
one node at the top because that's how
you enter into the tree and then down
here in the in the leaf nodes we're
actually gonna have sibling pointers so
this is something that came from the be
link tree so at any internode won't have
sibling pointers but any leaf node will
so now I can traverse at the bottom and
scan
and you know in any direction I want to
keep finding my neighbors get more
getting more datum so in the Internode's
it's gonna be this this combination of
keys and pointers and so for the
Internode's the pointer it's always
going to be to another node or null that
there's nothing there and then the key
is just the the whatever attributes
we're building our index on whatever
we're trying to store in this and then
these keys are then used to determine
which path you should go down as you
start doing a search for a given key so
in this case here for this first key
five so the path to the left of it going
this direction will be for any value any
keys that are less than five and then
for the the one that comes after it
would be implicitly anything less than
nine or greater than five so if I'm
looking for something a value a key
that's less than five I would look at
this and say well I'm looking for key
one one is less than five so I go down
this path and now I find my leaf node
not tonight and I try to you know find
the thing that I'm looking for the leaf
nodes the key value pairs are just in
just the key the same way they are up
above in the inter nodes but then the
value can differ we'll see this in a
second could either be a record ID to a
tuple it could be the actual tuple
itself it doesn't matter it's just that
the inner notes have pointers the leaf
nodes have had datum so again this is
just a repeat what I said but then the
the way to think about it in each node
it's a it's an array of key value pairs
and you're using the keys to determine
whether it's the if you're in the leaf
node whether it's a thing you want or if
you're interlude whether you go left or
right
so in general but not always the keys
are always in each node are always
sorted in whatever the the sorting order
you want the collation you want for that
node right so my example here we
disordered you know we in a numerical
order and so that's gonna allows when we
jump into a node potentially if
depending how its implemented we can do
binary search in each node and try to
find the thing that we're looking for
rather than just having you a linear
search but sometimes when your search is
good too so the contents of again of
what these values are in
leaf nodes can vary depending on the
database system again it could be a
record IDs it could be it could be the
actual tuples themselves and we'll see
some examples in a second all right so
let's actually look to see how this leaf
nodes were actually implemented so again
logically you just sort of think of it
like this that you have this this this
this array and you alternate with key
value pairs and this is typically how a
lot of textbook should show what a B+
tree node looks like so the first thing
to point is this since this is a leaf
node we have pointers at the end at the
end of the beginning of our array to our
siblings right and this would be a node
ID or page ready to allow us to go in
either direction or if we're at the
right side of the tree or the left side
of the tree it would just be null again
nobody actually stores no real data a
system would store their their their
inner internal internals key value
arrays for a B+ tree leaf node like this
and these years key value pairs and
these user pointers typically it's
stored separately so just like in our
slot of pages we would have a header
that tells us some metadata about what's
in our page so in this case here we
could say what level in the tree we are
essentially how many steps away from the
from the root we are how many free slots
that we have remaining in our in our
node and then the next person and then
now you see that we separated out the
the keys and the values everything I
guess why you'd want to do something
like this yes he said so that for a
given page on a B+ tree node that all
the keys can fit in one page and then
the values can fit another page know the
the keys and values are typically always
stored in the same page yes exactly says
they're not of the same size right
furthermore also too when if you're
doing binary search on this you want
everything to fit in your CPU caches so
if you have if you're back here with all
this intermixed in order to binary
search I actually don't need the values
at this point because I'm just trying to
find the key that I want so if you break
it up right depending whether it's fixed
length or or vary length you can jump
through the keys much more efficiently
the values typically are always fixed
length
they're either like you know 32bit or
64bit record IDs if they're tuple that's
a little complicated but in general you
you always want to separate them right
and again the way it works is just
whatever offset you are in in the key
array corresponds to some offer that in
the in the value ray so if I find a key
I'm looking for I'm gonna offset for
then I know just to jump to offset form
the value ray and that finds the thing
that I that I want so as I already said
the the values can vary depending on the
system some systems will destroy the
record ID this is PI the most common
implementation that people use this is
what Postgres does this is what all the
other commercial database systems do
what's more complicated and we can talk
about next class is what does it look
like when you actually stored the tuples
in the data so think about this instead
of having a table heap with my tuples
and then a B+ tree that stores my my
primary key and so in the front to keep
in sync what if just they were to merge
together and the the leaf nodes what's
actually the tables that the tuples you
know corresponding to a primary key so
now when I want to do traversal to find
out a particular key or particular tuple
instead of having to do in the first
case I traverse the index get a record
ID then do a lookup in the page table
and find that and they go scan inside
that that block to find that tuple that
I want what if as I do the traversal
when I land in the leaf node there's
already the data that I want so my C Co
and C code later probably most two
famous ones that do this in cases like
Oracle and sequel server I think by
default you get the one at the top but
you can tell it to do this at the bottom
now you get the specimen special flags
so now I want to distinguish since we
understand the basics about B+ treating
let's distinguish it from the original B
tree so the major difference is that in
the original B tree the values of the
stored in the index could be anywhere in
the tree I mean any internode could also
have a value - like a record ID or they
actually - for themselves in the B+ tree
the values are only in the leaf nodes so
what are the implications of this well
one in the B tree case I don't have any
duplicate keys because I can guarantee
that each key will only appear once in
my
in my in my tree in the B+ tree because
I have all this guideposts up above in
the inner nodes I'm basically
duplicating keys
furthermore if I delete a key in a B+
tree I would remove it from the leap
from the leaf node but I may not
actually remove from the inner nodes
depending whether our rebalance or not
right there I may not have a path going
down to it I started by dealing from the
leaf node I may keep it in the inner
node because that's how I figure out
what path to go down if I'm looking for
other keys so Abbey tree is gonna be
more economical and how much storage
space it occupies because it's not
duplicating keys but the downside is
gonna be and this is why that nobody and
end up actually using this in a real
system is that it makes doing updates
more expensive when you have multiple
threads because now you could be moving
things up and down right the tree you
know I have an inner node I modify
something and I made it propagate a
change below me and above me and
therefore I have to take a latches on
both directions and that causes as we'll
see you next class or next next week
that caused a lot of issues in a B+ tree
I only make changes to the leaf nodes I
may have the propagate changes up above
but I only go in one direction yes yeah
so the question is can I repeat what I
said about duplicates in a B+ tree so
going back to to this guy here so this
is the B+ tree so the keys that I have
that I'm trying to index are 1 3 6 7 9
13 but if you look in the in the the
root node I have a 5 5 does not appear
anywhere in the leaf node meaning hey
probably got in this case area but had
gotten inserted and then it got deleted
but I didn't reach up will reorganize my
my tree so I left it in in in the inner
node in a b-tree that'll never happen
each key only appears once and any if it
appears in the tree then it appears in
our key set and exits
a questioner semen is we leave in here
for searching purposes and it's still
stored physically in our in our nodes
but if I asked if I asked this tree
do you have key five I would say no
because I always have to go to the leaf
node then I try to find five and I'm not
gonna find it so it still be there but
it's it's not actually a real key yep
yes okay so question is how do we do
with inserts when we felt on the leaves
we'll get that in a second yes that's
the next topic this question is will
there not be any duplicates in the leaf
nodes yes and no so we'll see in a
second so this this would be considered
a unique index of unique tree where
they're unique keys you can't have keys
that have non unique values we have to
handle that we'll get to that in a
second as well okay so I think the next
topic is what he was yes is how do we
actually how to actually modify this
absolutely yes inserts okay so the way
we're gonna do an insert is that we want
to find that we want to traverse down
and figure out what leaf node we want to
insert our new key into so again we use
those guideposts on the Internet's aside
whether we go left or right depending on
whether a key is less than or greater
than what's stored in those key arrays
and then as we traverse down eventually
we'll get to a leaf node and then the
leaf node is where we want to start a
key and so if the leaf node has space
then we just inserted in for keeping the
keys in sorted order maybe we should we
sort them but there's enough space we
just insert it if there's not enough
space then we have to split the node
let's put the leaf node we would we just
inserted into and so the way we're gonna
do this we're just gonna take a halfway
point in our key space put all the keys
that are less than the halfway point and
one one node all the keys that were
above that in another node and then we
update our parent node to now include
that that middle key and then we have an
additional pointer to our the new node
we just added
and that may be happy to say all right
well this is actually a recursive thing
because if now my parent as I try to
insert the new key in to the parent if
it doesn't have no space then we have to
split it and then propagate the changes
up above so for one insert we may have
to reorganize the in the entire tree and
this is what I was saying before like
like just like in the hash table if I
insert into it index or through the hash
table and nothing's there it's really
fast but if I have to scan a long long
time to find the slot I can go into that
can be more expensive so sometimes we
would insert into our tree and it's
gonna be an expensive operation because
we're reorganizing the entire data
structure and other times it'll be super
fast and we don't have to worry about it
all right so let's do a let's view a
demo of this so this is using this is a
you know rather than me doing animations
in PowerPoint this is from a professor
at university San Francisco that has a
nice you know a little web-based
visualization we can use to carry yes
okay no out of type remotely alright so
we'll do a max degree of three so that
means that the the max number of nodes
we can have is two or started keys in
our each node is two and can have at
most three paths going down so we insert
can ever see that you start to know if
it's a physician mean yes so the degree
says the number of paths coming out of
it so degree of three means I have I
have most three paths coming out of me
if I'm an intern ode and therefore I had
to store it I can store at most two keys
because again so good I mean going back
to what we showed in the very beginning
Russian why do I said two three or why
is it that way so again so this is say
this is that a this has a degree of four
so it's always the number
passes is the number of keys plus one so
I be 2 1 2 3 keys and this guy has to
have a right pointer and a left pointer
right and he has have a right pointer
but that's shared and there's the one at
the end
so this there's four paths coming out
for three he's okay alright so is there
a way to make this looking better
well let's just keep going see how go so
it's down over there so I've only
inserted and it's the demo I've only
started two keys or one sorry one key so
right now it only has one entry in it so
now I'll insert we insert six right so
again it just it had space in that node
so I was able to insert it and now I
insert four and at this point it has to
split because it can only you can only
store it can only store two keys so it's
split in half put two over here
four and six six in its own node and
then they took the middle key for and
moved it up as the new root and again I
have pointers going down to both of them
so now do it in certain v right back in
fit over there accommodate just fine
it's not now insert five what should
happen right it'll say well five is
greater than 4 it's greater than equal
to 4 so I no need to go down this
direction but I can only sort
I can always I can only store two keys
in this node so I'm gonna have to split
this guy's and then rebalance everything
so hit enter right 4 goes down there
puts 5 there right it's split then split
the node put 4 in the middle over here 5
and 6 over here and then put 5 up
because that was the middle key and now
we have pointers going to this node the
middle node here with 4 and that one 5
right so again this is recursive as I
keep inserting more stuff and I keep
splitting I keep splitting the changes
up yes
so he says what if we have duplicate
keys so actually I don't don't know
whether this will matter so I just
earned a certain four yeah it did that
um so there's different way sorry how do
i the res the resolution is jacked mmm
11 no how did I do that
sorry there we go okay sorry
so this is just sort of a toy diagram in
in in a real system you could store for
together and just maintain multiple
entries for for all the unique values of
that you have the same key so okay your
statement is if all my keys are the same
it's four four four four four four then
if I'm looking for an exact key value
pair then it's law it's n because I do
its crunches can yes so yeah we can pop
up Postgres we can make a table has a
billion rows and for one column we set
the value to one and we can call crate
you know every so every where every 1
billion row has the same value for that
one column and post guess will let us
build an index on that on that it on
that column it's a split in next to
build because as you said they're all
the same so input it so and so how to
say this people will do stupid things in
general
don't be stupid and don't build indexes
on things that you shouldn't use right
there's all the types of indexes we'll
see so a hash table there's other things
like inverted indexes we could use that
could be better if you had a lot of
duplicate values but think of like email
addresses or think of like phone numbers
or things that work it's gonna be vastly
diverse then we won't really have that
problem or primary key right primary key
has to be unique that would be great for
this alright so again so this is this
clear
okay so let's go back so the new deletes
now we have the opposite problem can
insert so if we got to full we run up
space we have to do that split if we
delete then it may be the case we end up
being less than half full which would
violate the guarantees we have to have
in our B plus tree and then therefore we
have to do the opposite of a split which
is a merge so delete something again I
just do my traversal I go down the tree
try to find the the key that I want to
delete I'll and I'm always gonna lay in
a leaf node if my leaf node after
deleting that key is still at least half
full then I'm done I just remove it
maybe reorganize my my sort of key rays
but then that's it but if I'm less than
half full then now I have to figure out
how to get rebalanced so the sort of one
easy trick we could do is look at our
siblings in other leaf nodes and that's
why we have those sibling pointers we
can look at them and try to steal one of
their keys to make ourselves balanced
and long as long as that our sibling has
the same parent as us then it's okay for
us to steal this because that doesn't
require any rebalancing up above so if
we're not able to steal from our sibling
then we have to merge I think we ought
to go take our take take one of our
siblings combine all our keys together
that may actually end up being too full
as well but then we could we could split
think that split that as buff as well
that's the same thing as just copying
this but we would merge delete it delete
a key up above and then now where
everything's balanced again again just
like in splits we're like I may have to
go propagate the change everywhere when
we merge and with deleting keys that our
parent now may become less than half
full and it has to merge and that for we
have to maybe restructure the entire
tree all right so let's go back and to
our example here and do our demo because
now I got to figure out how to get to
the top right corner
so we just maintain the siblings in
correct he's question is to be
maintained the siblings only in the leaf
nodes yes all right so look to let's do
delete for I want September delete five
let me scroll down and then hit enter so
we can see this alright so just a
traversal are those insert sorry
delete five yeah that's insert as Polly
again sorry for the low resolution all
right so it's deep v in this case here
it should find both him there's only
found one of them so let's leave the
other one goes down that's fine again at
this point here both these nodes are
still more than half full so that's fine
so now let's delete four and I suspect
it will try to delete the one that's
farther on that side go down found that
deletes that again that node is now half
empty I mean it has to have at least one
and because it was empty a reamer it
merged everything and decrease the
height of the tree yes this question is
if only the leaf nodes have sibling
pointers then how do you actually do
this merge so the way it works basically
think of the think of a thread going
down it can maintain a stack of what
notes a visited as it goes down and
we're actually gonna need to do this
when we do what's called latch crabbing
or coupling as we go down and we take
latches to in case we need to reorganize
everything and so I have to know what I
have to hold latches up you know at when
I go down somewhere I have to hold and
latch my parent in case I need
reorganize whatever I'm doing down below
so I don't release it until I know I'm
safe so I know how I got there yes
yeah his question is if there's two
siblings to the left the right which one
you choose
it depends right typically you choose
the one that has the same parent as you
okay I think you have two actually but
if you're like if you were in the middle
yeah these guys have the same parent so
you say you want to reorganize this you
could choose to either left to right it
doesn't matter let's see what this one
does so we so if we delete for that
should take it out of the middle and
then now I delete two and it's gonna
pick people up too right okay actually
it's only has can only have one or two
or one or two so it might empty not
clear but crease it agree to the tree
but like it doesn't matter it still be
correct
and so this one also this this diagram
shows the the sibling pointer is going
in one way you can't have a go in both
directions you have to do extra work to
make that happen but like you can do
that a lot of times again for simplicity
but you could just have a go in one
direction but then you can't do you know
order by in descending order and go the
other direction if you wanna do scans
right pretty straightforward of course
getting the the details of the deletes
and inserts doing that split merge is
actually very difficult in practice and
we'll see in next week how to actually
make sure make sure that when we're
reorganizing the tree that we're threat
safely and we don't have any integrity
issues all right so the in practice the
the in in in the research shows that the
typical feel factor for a real tree on
real data is about 67 to 69 percent
meaning the the the amount of data are
storing in your nodes that's actually
real is up to you know sixty-seven
percent of his actually use useful datum
so typical capacities you can have you
know when for the 8 kilobyte pages with
a this number of pages are at four
levels you can basically store 300,000
key value pairs right so you can index
and get in log n time to any one of
three 300 300 million keys very very
quickly
and most of the data is going to be
stored on the leaf pages as you would
expect right because guys as you add
more keys you start to fan out and most
of the data is gonna be stored in the in
those leaf nodes all right so let's talk
about some other things you can do with
with with with these indexes so there is
this concept of this notion of more to
call clustered indexes and so I said in
the beginning that the table heap for a
database is unordered meaning we can
insert tuples into any page in any order
we don't the follow the you know the
temporal order will how things have
inserted but there may be some times
where we actually want to have the data
sorted in a certain way like for example
like the primary key so these would be
called clustered indexes so you can
define an index when you create a table
you can define a what's called a
clustered index and the data ISM will
guarantee that the the physical layout
of tuples on pages will match the order
that that that they're sorted in the in
the index so this is useful for certain
things like you know if I'm doing a lot
of lookups within is that range is the
primary key if I know my tuples are
stored on that print in the same order
that primary key now when I when I you
know traverses the leaf node within a
small number of pages I can find all the
data that I that I need if I'm not
sorted on my I'm on the key I'm doing my
lookup on then every single record idea
I could have could point to another page
and I could be doing a bunch of
different random iOS to go read the data
that I want so not all databases
imported census you get this by default
like my sequel by storing the tuples in
the leaf-nosed themselves it's it is a
clustered index so it's guaranteed to
have on the pages on disk the tuples are
sorted in the primary key order in case
to my sequel if you don't define a
primary key they'll make one for you
right they'll have a synthetic like row
ID a record ID that's transparent to you
but that's how they use to to figure out
you know what where your tuple is
actually located case of Postgres we can
do a demo next time but they have
clustered indexes you can define one you
say cluster my table on this index but
it won't actually maintain it in that
order
does the sorting once stores on disk but
then over time it can get out of order
because I won't do it for you
automatically and when we talk about
multi version to encourage hole it'll
become very clear why this is the case
for them so let's talk well how we can
do some lookups on the one our B plus
treatment so again because things are in
sorted order
you know we can do fast traversal to
find I think we're looking for but we
made one advantage you can do with a B+
tree that you can't do with a hash table
is that you don't need to have the exact
key in order to do a lookup you can have
actually some part of the key so the
save real simple simple table I have an
index on attribute ABC so I can do
lookups like this where a equals five
and B equals three where I have I don't
have the C but I have a and B and I
don't need to have the C and I can still
find the things that I'm looking for you
can't do that and a hash index because
think what happened I would take this
five and three try to hash them together
without the C and that's gonna jump to
some random location that's not just not
what I'm looking for you can also do
queries where you only have maybe the
middle guy right you don't have the
prefix you can hunt the subjects you
just have the middle the middle key
again you can't do that in a hash table
so not all data is have to support this
pretty much everyone supports the prefix
one where you have at least the keys in
in the order as they're defined for the
index not everyone can do this middle
one here actually I think maybe only
Oracle a sequel server can do this so
that's a little more concrete example so
let's say we have an index that is
defined on two to two columns or two
attributes so this would be called like
a composite key so instead of being on
for one column it's actually two columns
combined and the order of how we define
our index will determine what kind of
queries we can do on them
so again if I'm trying to loop do look
up on eight say it's a trying to find
key a B well in that case I have both
attributes that I've defined in my key
so now I can just do a straight
comparison of look at the first key and
then look at the second key and then
determine whether I want to go left and
right so in this case here a is less
than equal to a and B is less than
equals C so I know to find the key and
I'm looking for I go down this path do
whatever search I want to do in my node
and then I can find the entry that I
want let's say though now I want to do a
prefix search where I only have the
first element to my composite key but
not the second one so again I can just
look at the first key or first
activating the key a is less than equal
to a so I know that the starting point
for what I'm looking for it has to be
down in this direction so I go down here
but now I'm gonna do a sequential scan
across my node and going across the the
leaves to find all the entry I want up
until I reach a key that is less than or
equal to the you know my key a so in
this case as soon as I find one that
starts to be I know my search is done
and there's not gonna be anything else
remaining in the leaf nodes that would
satisfy my predicate so this one this
one's pretty easy or not easy but a lot
of data systems can support this one the
hard one is this where you only have you
only had the last element not the first
one so the way you actually end up
implementing this is you try to figure
out at least in the top and in the root
node which which portions of the tree do
I need to look at it could be something
that there's something could be there so
in this case here I know that no matter
what I have for the first value it's
always gonna have to be less than C for
the second attribute that's the second
value so I don't need to look at this
guy over here
I only need to look at these other ones
so essentially what you just do is you
end up doing multiple index probes or
muscle traversals and substituting
different values for the thing that you
don't have see we look at the top and
say well I know I have an A I have a B
and I have a C well there's nothing for
this C that would find over here so I
can skip that so let me now do a lookup
in these guys and I substitute the star
with an A and each one of those is a
separate lookup and then you combine
them all together and produce the final
result so Oracle calls this skip scans I
don't know what other systems column yes
yeah yes yes you're right that's wrong
but yes so you would include that but
it's each one of those use it separately
to Russell okay and you're just feeling
in the values whereas like in this one
here the main point I make is like this
one he like for this one and the first
one I had to do one traversal and then I
found the thing I was looking for this
one is you have to probe down multiple
times and you fill in the values
thank you I'll fix that okay so let's
get to the good stuff so we know what a
B+ tree is now let's talk about actually
how you want to build it it makes it
this thing actually useful so there's
this great book which i think is free
list if you google it it shows up free I
don't know whether that's true or not
there's great book written a few years
ago by Gertz graphy who's a famous
database researcher he's gonna talk
about a lot of this stuff he's done for
query optimization later on but he
basically he wrote this book is like all
the modern techniques and peaks and
optimizations you can do in a B+ tree in
a real system so we're gonna cover some
of some of these things and actually
it's a really light read and it was and
like it covers all the really important
topics and in a way that's easy to read
so which I had a hand notice Isis how to
do merging how to hand over blank keys
the non unique keys what they asked
about and then internode search how to
do better searches inside the node so in
general the the you can think of a node
in our B plus tree it's just a like a
page in our table right so the size of
the node could be the same as a page
size in practice though it doesn't have
to be and depending on what kind of
hardware we're storing our database on
we actually may want to have even larger
page sizes are smaller page note sizes
are smaller know sizes so it turns out
the research shows that the slower the
disk you have you're just drawing your
index on your tree on the larger the
node size you want and you know it
should be obvious right
the for every disk i/o I do I'm bringing
I can read the the nodes sequentially
all the pages for it
and that's gonna be much faster than you
went to random i/o two different
different notes if my node is is a
smaller size so if you're in a spinning
gets hard drive you have no sizes up to
one megabyte that's usually a good
number SSDs roughly 10 kilobytes which
roughly corresponds to the the node
sizes or page sizes that real database
systems use but then if you're an emery
database you actually want to go low as
512 bytes and so the this is another
good example what we talked about how in
our buffer pool we could have one but
for pulling our system for index pages
and one buffer pool set for four data
pages and we could set them to be
different sizes so I could set if I'm
going to slow spinning this hard drive
and I can have a buffer pool for my B+
tree pages and have them be one megabyte
whereas my data pages I'll keep them at
8 kilobytes or 16 kilobytes the optimal
size can also vary depending what kind
of operations or queries you're doing on
it so leaf node scans we're doing long
frontal reads those are typically better
to have larger node sizes because I can
do more sequential i/o where if I'm
doing a lot of lookups a lot of
traversal that's a lot of random i/o so
therefore I want to have smaller node
sizes so the next thing we can do is
actually violate the very thing that
said in the beginning about how the we
always have to merge anytime the anytime
we're less than half full and the demo I
did it was sort of simple it would do
exactly that but in practice you may
actually not want to do this immediately
when you're less than half full because
it's just like we saw in the hash table
we do did Leitz with linear hashing at
the end
I'm a Compaq something I'm a merge
something because I went less than half
full but then the next operation inserts
into that note and now I have to just
split all over again so the the merging
operation is expensive splits off the
top splits are also expensive but it
splits we have to do because we ran out
of space in our node the merge is weak
actually relax that that requirement and
not merge things right away so it gets
slightly unbalanced over time and then
in the background we can have like a
garbage collector or something go
through and do rebalancing or what's
often times the case people just rebuild
the entire tree from scratch and that
fixes all these issues
so these a lot of times you see this in
you know high-end commercial enterprise
systems you know though they'll shut the
database down over the weekend because
they're gonna rebuild all their indexes
and that's essentially what they're
doing there their rebalancing everything
because it wasn't always merging
correctly anytime you see like a bank
says they're down at 3 a.m. on on a
Sunday in the morning it's probably this
is one of the things they're probably
doing all right so now we want talk
about how we actually want to handle
forever length keys so again everything
I've shown so far we assume that the key
is a fixed length and the value is
always fixed length and in practice the
values will always be fixed like so
there's four different ways we can
handle this so the first approach is
that rather than storing the key itself
in the node we destroy a pointer to the
actual attribute or the tuple where we
can do a lookup to find what the key
actually actually is so again if I have
you know if I have an attribute that's a
very very like bar char instead of
storing that varchar' in the in the node
I have its record ID and then when I
want to figure out whether the key I'm
doing a look-up on matches that key
that's stored in that B tree I follow
the record ID go get the page and go
look at them with a real value actually
yes
so this is obviously super slow it's
nice because if we're storing less data
because now we just tore the pointer
instead of the actual key in the in the
in the in the node but it's expensive to
do that lookup you know as we're
traversing people tried this in the
1980s for in memory databases because
memory was really expensive but nobody
actually does this anymore
everybody stores the keys always hole
and then in the node the next you could
you have variable length nodes this is
basically allows the the size of a node
can vary based on what's stored in it
but we've said this is a bad idea
because we want our page sizes to be
always the same in our buffer pool and
on disk so we don't have to worry about
doing the thin backing problem to decide
how about you know put you know fine
free space to put in what we want to
store so nobody does this one as well
the next approach is do padding or
basically we say you look at what the
attribute is and you're trying to index
on and we say that whatever the max is
it could be no matter what key you give
us we will Pat it out with either null
bits or
or you know zeros to make it always fit
exactly our our note size so everything
is always nice and nicely aligned so
some systems actually actually do this
I think Postgres does this and we can
look at that next time but again you're
in the trade-off I'm wasting space in
order to store things so this Y is also
- it's super important to make sure that
you define your schema correctly
like if I'm storing email addresses
which are you know maybe 32 characters
or 50 characters but I set the varchar'
size to be 1024 if I'm padding it out up
to 1024 even though most of my emails
aren't that big
then I'm wasting a lot of space yes that
me correct yeah so when you call Crate
table you can define varchar' you define
the length in it you don't have to put
it in I and I I don't different systems
to deal with different things but in
practice you always want to say this is
the max size of what I actually package
min store right and then so varchar'
supposed to be very length so even
though I say the max size could be 32 if
you give it a 16 16 you know character
string it could in theory store that
more compactly some systems are
different things I some systems actually
say it's a char and where it's always
gonna be that size that's always padded
out they actually just still that store
that as a varchar' so logically you
don't know you don't care
underneath the covers they can do
different things and my sequel was
always the worst offenders so if you say
the max size of our string is like 16
and you give it a 32 character string
it'll store it just truncates it
silently for you all right so Postgres
and all the sisters will throw an error
but the database system should enforce
that correctly
same thing for index we like to build an
index we have to be told you know here's
the here's the attributes and our tables
your indexing so we know what their type
is we know what their max sizes and we
can pad out and as needed all right with
probably more commas is to use in an
indirection map where
store pointers for our keys inside of
our sort of key array but we're still
the pointers are just actually two
offsets in our in our node themselves
rather than to some arbitrary page so it
would look like this so we have a sort
of key map so again this is sorted these
are just pointers are all sets to down
here but these are sorted based on the
values of the keys so to be very clear
the keys themselves not the keys
corresponding value but the actual
string that we're trying to store right
and so just like in the slotted page
layout for tuples we're going to grow
from the end to the beginning and this
side grows from the you know from from
beginning to the end and at some point
we get to full actually I think this has
to be fixed size so we have to set a
degree at a time so but if I if I don't
run out of space for what I'm trying to
store here then I can have an overflow
page that's that's chained to this so
again this is just just a an offset to
whatever the key is so now if I'm doing
binary search as I'm jumping around this
array I jump down here to see what the
actual key value is so what's a really
simple optimization we can do to make
this go faster into that it statement is
is it a statement or a question do we
store this as an array or a linked list
it's always stores in a rack okay so his
statement is I'm storing this as an
array or vector u vectors as a wrapper
an array if I now do insertion or
deletion that's gonna take Oh N or yes
but again like this is this is just
within the node itself so the size is
not that big right so you know fan out
of like maybe 32 so I have 32 elements I
need I need to keep sorted I can do that
in cash that's very fast so
correct okay so say I'm doing binary
search so in this case your binary
search is just you just do the linear
search so I've just fought scan along
and I want to see is there's the key I'm
looking for a match what what I have so
I have to follow this pointer but again
it's just an offset it's in the same
page so it's gonna be your maybe 16 bits
I follow that offset to jump to where
this is and then I do might might
comparison and if it doesn't match then
I jump back and do the same in jump down
here and so just like in slotted pages
where the two books want to be sorted in
the order as they're laid out in the
page and the same way that are sorted at
the slaughter a this verbling theta at
the button down here can mean any order
that at once I just know how to you know
I know how to jump to it based on this
his question is for non leaf nodes do
you do the same thing yes it's and this
is for very well liked data and any note
so this is this is sort of micro
optimization and going to disk is always
the most expensive thing but a really
simple thing we could do is just
recognize that before since this is only
16 bits in general I have a lot of space
up here so maybe I just take the first
character of every string and just embed
it inside upper here so now when I'm
skating along and trying to find the
thing I'm looking for
if my key doesn't match exactly you know
the first character that I know I don't
need to traverse down and find it again
this is like this is this is all going
to be in memory this is like avoiding
cache misses in making the binary search
and making the search on this woman
faster okay this is a micro optimization
a voting disk is always the major thing
that we care about in this course but
this is a really simple trick that you
can do to speed this up yes again it
looks like what if there's two persons
that name is start the same letter again
you'd have to depending what you're
looking for you if you want to find
exactly one you find the first one
you're done if you need to find anybody
you have to go to both of them alright
means same way here right for this one
here I'd have to
I'd have to if I'm trying to find
everyone's different here but if there's
like Paul and Prashant
who's my PhD student I would scan down
here find Prashant then actually go to
the next one just make sure that that
one doesn't have the same you know
doesn't have the same thing as well okay
so his coalitions
so there's dip so I'm showing LexA
graphical ordering alphabetical ordering
for this they're in high-end database
systems you can actually define
arbitrary sort orders everything still
works the same you're talking like
dictionary codes for not anytime I bad
you I could have different you know
sorting based on whether it's you know
code or what language I'm using for that
one you have to begin the data system
would know this is how the sort order is
so what you know it would know what what
prefix if it wants to store up in here
again the high level high level ideas
that's still the same yes sir he said so
he said if you have K keys you have at
most k plus one pointers to other things
not necessarily for simplicity yes you
just scan along the keys do linear
search so his statement is that the
really the complexity should be K times
log n yes the that back that's a
constant we can throw out because the
log n is the maximum number of page iOS
I have to do to traverse that's always
orders of magnitude faster than doing
the cache line lookups here remember I
said in the very beginning here's less
storage hierarchy anything above memory
we don't care about we can throw away is
to disk IO is the real color we got to
avoid that
what we do by we'll get to that a second
okay all right so now I'll get to the
other thing as well is how we handle non
non unique indexes well this is the same
thing we talked about in hash tables
there's two basic approaches you just
duplicate the keys and be mindful like
in our example here the duplicate key
split over to another to another node we
have to be mindful that that could occur
and make sure we read everything we need
to read or we destroy a value list where
we store the key once and we duplicate
the value or have a separate space in
our node to store all the values for
that given key all right so it looks
like this so if i if i duplicate the key
right i just have the key multiple times
and again it's just like before the
offset points down to wherever the value
is and you know if i insert a new one
then i know i inserted here and certain
new k1 i inserted here and move
everything over and everything still
works
the value list since you just looks like
this i destroy the key once but then now
I also have a pointer an offset to
somewhere else in the node where I have
all the values that correspond to that
that giving key that's the first
approach is more common I don't know who
actually does this one here yes so her
question is can I assume for that
duplicate keys will always be in the
same node no so the example I showed
from that demo it actually moved it over
as a sibling key that's one way to do it
all those systems actually would have an
overflow chain that would say for that
given leaf node oh by the way here's
some other pages or other nodes down
below you that have that you have the
keys that correspond to what you know
what you're actually storing up above
the question is if I'm searching for a
given key how would I know what key to
follow so going back to that example I
would I found looking for a greater than
equal to four I had I have to go down on
the on this side and find the
first entry point four four then I keep
scanning along the leaf nodes until I
find something that's not equal four and
then I know I've seen everything again
the data system knows where the keys are
unique or not so it knows whether it has
to do that so it knows that oh this is a
primary key or this is a unique index so
the thing I'm looking for should only
pair once and therefore I just get to
the one leaf node that it has what I
want if it's non unique then you have to
account for that and either again you if
it's if it's just duplicated across leaf
nodes I scan along siblings if it's an
overflow I just find that the first leaf
node and then scan down its chain yes
the question is the size is besides the
key always the same or do besides the
key is not always the same or the values
or this always Sam again I'll show this
next next class if the if the value is
just a record ID for a tuple always the
same see the 32 bits or 64 bits
depending on the system if it's the
actual tuple itself like in my sequel
then you got a deal whatever flows that
way and that that's more complicated
we'll discuss that next class all right
again we've already discussed this
briefly but I'm gonna show that there's
different ways to do searches within the
node again I Traverse as I'm traversing
the nodes are touring the tree I have to
do a search on the key the key array to
find a thing I'm looking for to decide
whether you know there's a match that I
want or whether I need to go left or
right
so the most basic way to do this it's
just a linear search so I'm trying to
find key eight I just start at the
beginning of my sort of key array scan
along to I find one one and I'm done
right worst case scenario I have to look
at all K keys binary search if it's
sorted then I just find the middle point
jump to that figure out is that lesson
or less than or greater than the key I'm
looking for or the one I am looking for
and that tells me whether I go left or
right in this case here I'm looking for
eight
I'll Anil seven I know eight is greater
than seven so I jump over here then I
think the halfway point of that I get
nine then I go go go to this direction
and I get eight and I find what I want
one thing though that is kind of cool
you can do if you know what the values
actually look like for your keys
actually what the keys look like is that
you can use an interpolation technique
where you can approximate the local
the key by doing some simple math to
figure out what your starting point
should be for your linear search
so rather in case of linear search you
start for the beginning and good all the
way to the end if I know that my keys or
in this case integers and I know
something about their distribution then
I can do a really simple you know it's
cool math and say well I know I have
seven keys in my array and the max key
is 10 and I'm looking for 8 so if I take
10 minus 8 and get 2 and then seven keys
- minus 2 and get five I know I can just
jump to the fifth position and that's at
least a starting point for what I'm
looking for so this one this this
obviously works because they're always
increasing the monotonic order right if
there floats this is hard to do if
there's strings I don't think you can do
this but this is another technique you
could do to make that that search go
faster this one I don't know how is calm
how common it is the binary search I
think what everyone does but again
there's this trade-off now an ordinary
binary search I had to make sure my keys
are in sorted order if I'm doing the
linear search I don't have to do that so
therefore as I update the nodes I don't
pay that penalty of maintaining the sort
order all right so let's finish up real
quickly to let some optimizations we can
do it to make it go better so these are
the kind of things that like again a
real data system would actually do to
make B plus trees go faster so the first
type first who think we're told if
equates to compress the datum so the
first kind of question scheme we can do
is called prefix compression and this is
based on the observation that because
we're keeping the keys in sorted order
it's very likely and a lot of data sets
the keys that are stored in a in a
single node are actually going to be
very similar to each other all right
because that's because we end up sorting
them right so in this case here I
haven't know that has three keys robbed
robbing and robot well all three of them
share the same prefix are OB and so
rather than me duplicating or storing
that redundant ro B over and over again
for every single key what if I extract
that out to store the prefix once ro B
and then for the room for the the keys I
destroy the remaining parts of that's
actually different
so this is very very common this is
these are called sometimes previous
professional Peter trees this is why you
use in a lot of high-end or a lot of
large data sets they debate systems
because you know because there's so much
duplicate data so Facebook uses this for
all their internal my sequel stuff and
it makes a big difference for them as
they save a lot of space so this is sort
of one way to do this those other
optimizations you can do like if again
if I'm doing a clustered index where I
know all my tuples the tuples are on on
disk or on pages in the same way that
they're sorted in my index then it's
very likely that tuples in the same node
their record ID will have the same page
ID because they're all going to land on
the same page so rather than storing
that page ID over and over again for
every single for every single tuple in a
in a node I destroy the page ID once and
then store their offset or slot
separately right yes yes the question is
how do we actually decide what to do
right so you basically can say every
single time I insert I figure out what
the common prefix is and that's what
I'll store you could say anytime I do
like a compaction or do like a real
optimism then I decide what the best is
right that you know for the for my keys
right then and there in practice also
think of it like in a lot of database
systems the the newer keys might get
inserted in always on the one side of
the tree like this is always increasing
in value and so therefore the a lot a
large portion of the tree on the other
side is going to be static it's gonna be
you know mostly read-only so at that
point I can make it a hard decision like
here's how I want to do compression or
compaction different trade-offs you do
it online or offline yes
so this question is what happens to
someone insert the words sad right and
ends up in this node then yeah you have
that you have to account for that you
have to maintain it on the fly correct
yeah or you could say source mesh and
distro metadata to say this prefix is
only used for the first three keys not
the other ones right there's the bunch
of tricks you can do so the the opposite
of prefix compression is suffix
truncation and the basic idea here is
that we can recognize that we don't
maybe need to store the entire key in
our inner nodes to figure out whether we
want to go left and right so in this
case here we have ABCD up to K for one
key and lMNO up to V for another key but
if I'm just trying to see whether I want
to go left or right I can probably get
by just looking at the first you know in
this case here first character so
instead of storing the entire key in the
internode aisle to store a uniquely
distinguishing prefix of it and then
throw away the remaining suffix so in
this case here I could distort L and a
and L and that woulda been enough but
I'm showing ABC L M nm right and again
down below I still have to store the
entire key because I need to go be able
to have it be it'll say you know is the
key I'm looking for here but it might
and my inner guideposts I don't need to
have this have the full key and of
course again you have to maintain this
if something and somebody insert
something that would violate these this
we have to know we order it or we
organize it but in practice that you
know if the data is is not changing a
lot then this could be another big win
so as far as you know prefix compression
is more more common than the subjects
truncation all right the last few things
I want talk about is how to handle bulk
inserts and pointers whistling so in all
the examples I showed so far we assume
that we're incremental e building out
our index we're inserting keys one by
one but in a lot of cases you have all
the keys ahead of time so it's a very
common pattern that people do in
databases that say I want to bulk load a
new data set now I've collected data
from some other source and I want to put
it into my database a lot of times what
people do is they turn up all indexes
bulk load the data insert it into the
table and then they go back and add the
indexes right so that way you as you as
your insert
the new data you're not trying to
maintain the index which which is
expensive so in this case here if you
have all the keys ahead of time a really
simple optimization to do to build the
indexes rather than building it top-down
like we've done so far you actually
build it from the bottom up so let's say
these are the keys I want to insert the
very first thing I do is just sort them
and we'll see in a few weeks we there's
an efficient algorithm we can use tech
that can sort data in such a way that
max is my maximize the amount of
sequential i/o we have to do so we can
sort it and that lets me way more
efficient than actually building the
index one by one and then we just lay it
out along leaf nodes have everything
filled out correctly and then going from
the bottom to the top we just fill in
the inter nodes and generate our
pointers so again this is this is a
pretty standard technique that any major
data system we owe to support when you
call create index and a large dataset
that already exists and then once it's
already built once it's built then I can
you know maintain our do any changes I
want just like before there's no real
difference to it the day to day sim
doesn't know whether you did the
bulkinsert
versus the incremental build to build an
index everything's still the same in the
back yes so this question is what
happens if you want to merge a small
people street into a large people street
let's take that offline and we have a
paper that does something like this but
I would say in general building index is
very building indexes with bulk inserts
very fast is a very very hard problem
and it's at least in academia it's
underappreciated this is very very
common so how do you do this to me this
as fast as possible is super important
so let's talk about efforts all right
the last thing I'll talk about is called
pointers Quisling so again I talked
about how the way we figure out how to
traverse the index is by having these
pointers from one node to the next in
actuality what we're storing is not you
know raw memory pointers we're storing
page ids and whenever we want to do
traversal the same when I find key
greater than 3 we start here and we say
all I want to go to this this node down
here well how do we actually get there
well in the root node
I'm storing a page ID for this index and
now I've got to go down to the buffer
pool and say hey I have page - if it's
in memory if it's not a memory go get it
for me I'll and and then give me back a
pointer to it so then I go get now my
pointer to it and now I can do my
traversal same thing as I'm scanning
along here I want to get to my sibling I
this is my siblings page three because
that's what's stored in my semi my node
I got to go down to the buffer pool and
say give me the pointer for page three
so as I'm traversing I keep going back
to the buffer pool manager and saying do
this conversion from page ID to two
pointer and this is really expensive
because I got it you know I had to
protect my hash table in my and my
buffer pool with latches and therefore
I'm going to much the steps just to get
this pointer so with pointers Quisling
the idea is that if I know all my pages
are pinned in memory meaning I know it's
not going to be going to be Invicta well
instead of storing the the page ID I'll
just replace it with the page pointer
because I know if it's pin it's never
gonna move to a different memory address
so now when I do traversals
instead of doing that lookup to the
buffer pool I have exactly the page ID
or pate the page pointer that I want and
I can go get exactly the data that I
want and I don't have to go ask the the
buffer pool of course now I'm gonna make
sure that when I pick this thing I write
it out the disk
I don't store the page pointer because
when it comes back in that's gonna be
completely different so you don't blow
away the paging idea entirely it's just
you have a little extra metadata say
here's the pointer you really want not
the page number so you may say alright
when would we actually pay when would
actually would be pinning these pages in
memory well maybe not for the leaf nodes
but at least for the upper levels on the
root and maybe the second level those
things are gonna be super hot because
I'm always gonna have to go through them
to get down to the leaf nodes so maybe
it's not that big of a deal for me to
pin those pages and they're gonna be
relatively small compared to the size of
the entire tree and then I can use this
optimization site because I know my
pointers are always gonna be valid so
this one is actually very common
pointers whistling is used in in pretty
much every major system okay
all right so to finish up the beef
industry is awesome hopefully I've
convinced you that it's a good idea to
use this for your your for your you know
if you're building a database system
next class we'll see some some
additional optimizations for this and
maybe do some demos with Postgres on my
sequel but then we'll also you talked
about two other types of tree based
indexes we may want to use tribes or
radix trees which are gonna look like be
trees were slightly different because
that we're not store entire keys and
indexes don't know you can't