[Music]
[Applause]
so in today's class we're going to talk
about server-side logic execution again
I'm at my house here with the Terrier
who for some reason smells like onions
I'm not sure what that what that's about
um so for today's lecture this is a
topic that I find very interesting and
it's not something I would say that is
critical for building a sort of modern
high-performance inmate database that
we've been talking about the entire
semester this is now making it so that
people can you know extend your database
system and have it integrate with more
different types applications so again
this is not something we're going to do
try to support because we want you know
you absolutely need to get the best
performance although it's gonna help in
the way we're gonna exclude our UDS are
gonna help this is more about sort of
extensibility of the database system but
we want to do it in a really smart way
so for today's lecture we're going to
first start talk about the background of
this what I mean by server-side logic
execution and then we'll focus on how to
optimize the performance of user data
user defined functions the one way would
be the the inlining approach that was
used by Microsoft and the fraud paper
that you were assigned to read and then
the other approach would be a newer
method at a Germany on converting UDF's
into common table expressions again both
of these are about making UDS run faster
so as I said server-side logic execution
I think is an interesting topic I used
to teach it in the introduction class
the last night audit I think was maybe
2018 and unfortunately last mr. we had
to cut it out so this is not something
that maybe if you've been here at CMU
that you may be familiar with so it's
been a little time discussing you know
what it is you know we're actually
trying to do on our database system so
the key observation you have to make
about what server-side logic execution
is going to do for us is that up until
now we've assumed that there's
then this clean division or dichotomy in
our application stack between the logic
that's in the application server and the
logic that we execute in the database
system and the database system would
only see queries that were being sent
over from a like what I'll call a
conversational API like JDBC or ODBC
like what we talked about early in the
semester and the downside though with
this approach is that it's going to be
you know it's it's a chatty API like
hypocenter query get resolved and then
process it and send result back all
right so we saw this a diagram sort of
like this before when we talk about JDBC
or ODBC right on the application side
this is where our essentially our
program lives right whether it's written
in nodejs or a PHP or Django you know
Python application right here's all the
business logic or of our of our program
and so when we started transaction we
would call begin and then we would
execute a gift to a Segal save and
execute something that would then go
over the wire again throw through ABC or
JDBC and that'll run through the full
stack that we've talked about like the
sequel parser the plan of the optimizer
and eventually due to the query executor
now you can use prepared statements
maybe skip the first fresh two or three
steps but in the end you're still going
to execute the query so then now the
data system X uses the query and the
sends the result back and then now the
application server can proceed with the
program write this the sequel call is a
blocking call on the application side so
now while goes off and execute some or
program logic to process whatever the
results that it got from the sequel
query our database system is idle for
this particular connection now again
it's a multi-threaded system or multi
process system so therefore we could be
processing queries from other
transactions or other you know from
other connections at the same time but
for the the context handle we're going
to maintain for this particular
connection it's essentially idle so that
means that it for running is in a
transaction if we're using something
like two-phase locking as a concurrent
you to a protocol whether locks that we
acquired for this sequel statement are
now just being held on the servers
side because it's waiting for the next
command to be told what's gonna happen
for this particular transaction and this
network round-trip is not cheap but you
know best-case scenario we're running on
the same machine but that's not very
common it's usually you have a service
reapplication a separate server for the
database system as you can sort of scale
them independently and so maybe you're
on the on the on the rack unit right
above you know the application server is
one unit below the database server and
the same rack but again that's pretty
uncommon too high so this could be a
couple milliseconds to send this you
know these back and forth and who knows
how long this program log just gonna
take to execute so then now after we
complete the program logic here maybe we
do the same thing we exit another sequel
query send it over get a result send it
back we do some more processing and then
we wait and then eventually our
application says okay we're done we send
a commit message and then we can release
whatever locks or whatever memory we've
allocated for this transaction whatever
we did to maintain the state that we had
this connection open and they were
exiting transaction when we get the
commitment we can finally finally start
to clean things up so the things we're
going to talk about today are
essentially how to take that application
logic on this side and now move this
inside the database system to avoid
these round trips and have the you know
have transactions take longer or
whatever the query we were executing
take a longer try to combine everything
into a single vacation invocation that
we can send just one request to the
database server and not go back and
forth to the application we're also
going to bed logic that allow us to
extend the functionality of the database
system so in some cases we'll be able to
do certain types of manipulation or
filtering or other types of steps we do
when we process queries we're able to do
that in a way that the original
developers of the database system may
have not anticipated or may not you know
offered to support so again so the
benefit will get from this is that
because we're going over we could make
fewer round trips that'll improve the
efficiency and of our system
because now transactions can take we're
gonna execute in less time we're also
going to get some reuse because now if I
have some functionality inside a bed in
my bed it's on my database system with
now I have my my web application now is
to be ported over to a mobile phone
application instead of rewriting the PHP
code my web application to now be swift
or whatever I'm using on my cell phone
like whatever that application logic I
had to use to interactive a database
system and the website I got to ported
over to the web to the mobile phone
application but if I can embed it inside
the database system then now potentially
the same logic that would be executed on
the on the web site could be executed on
the mobile phone again depends on your
application stack a setup I did it
assume that there's a logic running it
and button both in both of them so what
does that look like so one example a
simple table that I just showed here
that we could take this entire
transaction logic and somehow send that
over to the database system it'll get
installed and then it will the ability
to call it will get exposed through some
kind of function handle like what's
called as proc and then it takes an
input argument of whatever you want so
now if I want to invoke this transaction
in my application I don't do that back
and forth that I had before now I just
use this invocation or this command
called call so I call the function and
pass in whatever argument I want to that
function I send that one request over
like an RPC
it executes commits and then I get back
the result so the benefit about this is
that it's one round trip over and to
execute all this complex logic where
before it was multiple round trips now
in this case here I'm invoking with call
other this might be the in the seagull
stander and other databases systems
might support exact or execute I but the
basic idea is the same so this is what
is called a strop a seizure with the
idea is that we can take a chunk of
logic and wrap that into to the
procedure call that we can then just
invoke independently
of a query the other types of embedded
logic can you do the ones we focus on
today are user-defined functions where
it's UDF is attached to a query so you
can't invoke a UDF independent of a
query it has to be part of a select
insert update or delete where storage
procedures can be separate triggers are
a way to have functions get invoked when
when a certain event occurs like if I
update a tuple in a table I can have
that fire fire off a trigger actually
before an update or after update update
and then invoke some function to do to
do something so let's say that I wanted
to every time somebody up to the table I
want to insert an audit record in
another table so I could put a trigger
on that table to say anytime it's
updated keep track of what that change
was in another table a user-defined
types are a way to extend the the
internal type system of the database
system and allow you to support again
some more complex object types that go
beyond maybe within what the base scalar
values of the primitive values that the
data supports user defined aggregates
are a way to have some more complex
aggregation functions other than you
know minimax count and some things like
that so I can't prove this but it is my
is it my intuition based when I play and
what I've seen out there in programs and
talking to people the prevalence of
these different applications that are
using these these types of embedded
logic is that the top would be the most
common going down to the least common so
user-defined functions are very very
very common you see these all over the
time all over the place and then
user-defined aggregates are a little
less common triggers and stored
procedures they're probably
interchangeable but again like the way
you implement a trigger is through a
user-defined function the other thing to
about I think in the in the Microsoft
paper they talked about how well
user-defined functions cannot update
update tuples or update tables they can
there they're the read-only where store
procedures you can update things that I
think is a
is specific to sequel server I don't
think the sequel standard specifies one
way or the other
so you could have user-defined functions
that actually do update update tables
okay so the what we're going to focus on
today though is user-defined functions
because again this is this is the the
most common one and you know it's it
could be used in combination of at least
for the store procedures and triggers
you tud keys and you da's are sort of a
severed Beast okay so use defined
function UDF is gonna be a function that
is written by the application developer
that allows them to extend the system
functionality beyond what its built-in
operations provide I said the sequel
standard defines some basic sequel
functions string length string upper you
know casting functions things like that
but there's also now to go beyond what
what the sequel standard says or even
with the proprietary functions that the
database system supports you can write
user blind functions that that you would
invoke just as if they were a built-in
function and so the setup is that you're
always gonna be given as a scalar input
arguments so like single primitive
values or even arrays of scalars but but
but not like you know table sets or row
sets then you perform some kind of
computation in them and this computation
is going to be the the standard
imperative language constructs that
you're familiar with for loops while
loops if clauses things like that and
can also be invocations of other sequel
statements or other UDF's within the
this UDF and then you get to return a
result that's either going to be more
scalar values or a relation or a set of
rows right so that's the basic idea what
we're trying to here so let's look an
example so this is going to be written
in for all the examples in this first
part for Freud we're gonna show examples
in a programming language called T
sequel or transact sequel so this is the
UDF language that microsoft sequel
server supports and fraud was was
improving UDF's in sequel server so
that's why we
using this so TC who comes from Sybase
because Seco server originally started
off as a licensed licensed Fork of
Sybase in the 1990s they ported it to
Windows NT since then the forks have
diverged significantly Sybase got bought
by sa p and it's kind of more or less in
maintenance mode at this point we're a
sequel server is still very
state-of-the-art and still being active
actively developed another way think
about this is like there's a lot of
major major corporations and major
applications running them on Sybase but
you know no startup with a you know
bunch of like 20 20 year old kids are
gonna say you know I'm gonna build my
startup on sideways the PI doesn't
happen anymore
we're siegel server actually still was a
is a still is a good choice for from
many applications okay so i'll say also
to the the sequel standard Divine's
defines a language called a sequel PGM
as far as I know nobody actually
supports that to the exact specification
in the sequel standard they all the
things that look close enough to sequel
PGM still deviate from it so Oracle has
PL sequel Postgres has PL PG sequel
which is a slight variant or is a
variant of the local one usually PL
sequel again PL sequel looks close
enough to sequel PGM but it's not
exactly the same but at a high level it
all looks like Pascal it all looks like
sort of like ADA so other than the more
complex things that the the going from
you know record up press is it a major
change transact sequel it's a little bit
different but it still at a high level
looks the same
alright so here we have a function that
we really fine that's going to get all
the custom IDs from the customer table
and offset from the orders table and
it's gonna compute what customer service
level that they're supposed to have
based on the amount of money they have
spent and the total number orders that
they've they've submitted so our
function is gonna take in a integer
that's the customer key and it's gonna
return a 10 character or string so in
the beginning we will have to declare
all our variables again this is a this
is a remnant of peski
or $1 worth sinking PGM is based on so
in Pasco you define all your your your
variables at the beginning and then we
have now a select statement that again
looks like just like a regular stick
select am except we've added this little
at sign total equals where we're taking
the output of this summation and storing
it and this variable here that we
defined up above then now we have some
if clauses to say if the total order is
greater than a million then there at the
Platinum level otherwise there at the
the regular level and then we just
return the level value which is a 10
character string so the way we would
invoke this for in a query would be a
scam like this on the customer table
where we begin for each customer key
will invoke this function to get the
computer service level okay so the as I
said before the there's some important
advantages of UDF's that sort of explain
why they're actually very very common
again the first one be that they
supporting modularity and reuse because
again if I have a complex function or
complex logic that I need to reuse
across multiple applications in the same
database
I don't want have to re-implement that
logic over and over again
I can instead and bed it inside the
database system and have all instances
of the application no matter how many
times I refactor or change it all rely
on that using that same centralized
location of that logic the we talked
about before having fewer network round
trips again that makes the the queries
run faster because the database has
doesn't have to go back for that never
to say what should you know to find out
what to do next all the logic can run
inside the data system and this one is a
bit subjective but there's been some
arguments that say that the for certain
application domains the sort of the
logic you need to write in your
application is easier to express in
UDF's in the sequel i prefer so then for
some things yes it still makes sense for
other things you know with CT ease
things have gotten a little bit better
but yeah it's certainly some things I'd
like you just don't want to do in sequel
and UDF's are better way to do this by
simply ml gait analysis things sometimes
are better and something that looks like
UDF all right so this sounds amazing
right this sounds like UDS or a big win
we totally want to use this what's the
problem why are we actually spending
time today to talk about how to make
these run faster well the first issue is
going to be that when our query
optimizer encounters in UDF it doesn't
know anything about them and essentially
has to treat them as a black box
because it doesn't know what the
functionality it's going to be right
this is because a UDF's are written in
an imperative language like you know PL
sequel or single PL and we're a sequel
is a declarative language that means the
uploads can reason about what it is if
there's queries actually wants to do and
it also knows something about the data
although as we saw the estimations are
easily wildly inaccurate but Headley
says some some sense of what's what's
happening and so when you encountered
UTF you basically say I don't know what
this is gonna do for me and so if now
you have like a UDF being using the
where clause we're like you know some
value you know just some column equal
another column after it's been churned
through or run through a UDF you have no
idea what their transformation that UDF
is gonna do so therefore you don't know
what the cardinality of the selectivity
of that predicate is going to be so you
basically throw your hands up and you
know you use some I know I don't know
what you do and sometimes the ultimen
time you just say it's the worst case
scenario you say it's the worst
selectively you could ever have like
everything 300 sent selectively or did
the other end could be 0% selectivity or
just take the average you could do a
little bit like the adaptive query
optimization stuff we talked about where
you can run it for a little bit see what
happens and make a decision but as I
said till very recently most systems
didn't actually support those least
commercial systems and none of the open
source systems to support this and when
they do support UDF's all right so the
next one is a bit more nuanced but it's
basically says that the next problem is
that the because the the
is an imperative code we essentially
have to exit them sequentially line by
line and so that means that we're not
going to be able to paralyze any of the
operations on the inside because the
output of one line could be used as the
input for the next line so we can't
execute it to eat so we X Q what came
before it so that sort of lends itself
to Sara execution now it doesn't mean
that if we're doing a scan in parallel
and parallel across multiple threads
that each of those things could invoke
the UDF sequentially but we're not
getting any of the benefits of
recognizing that you know maybe there's
a bunch of sequel queries in the in the
in the UDF that we could run combined
together maybe playing them at the same
time or optimizing at the same time and
instead of invoking all the individual
queries one by one we can combine them
to one one giant query with joins and
make that run fast we don't know
anything about what's going inside so we
can't do those kind of optimizations
that we normally could do and if we had
regular queries the other really tricky
thing is gonna be also is that some
UDF's
actually can contort UDS can create
dynamic sequel statements so essentially
you can declare a string variable and it
incrementally construct the string like
you concatenate strings together say
select star from table things like that
and therefore like you have no idea what
the queries gonna be and to actually
execute that code and then once you have
the string then you invoke that string
as a sequel statement and then that runs
as it you know as a query so you have no
idea how to even prepare for this
because you don't know what the queries
gonna be ahead of time all right some
more problems you have is that the for
complex UDF's the when you have being
there selects tables or where clauses
the database system is gonna have to
execute these things execute the UDF on
each each each each row or each tuple
one by one because again I don't know
what the UDF's gonna do therefore I
don't know whether the logic inside of
it could change from one tuple to the
next because you know I don't know
whether you're just gonna access you
know attribute foo or actual
you know bar in my in my in my to pole
so therefore I don't know how to then
maybe combine multiple in vacations or
vectorize multiple indicators
invocations of the UDF within a batch
you throw your hands up and basically
have to do one by one so Microsoft's
world they have they coined this sort of
the the the term Rho by agonizing bro
are more to represent like how bad you
have to execute why things are bad we
execute UDS so then the last one is that
you know so related all this because
you're executing the the commands or
instructions in the UDF moment one it's
hard to do the cross statement
optimizations for the the for
invocations within the same the same UDF
okay so how do we solve this well one
approach would be to have that people
tried is Microsoft actually tried to
convert the UDF's
into machine code the same way we talked
about we did Co gen for for queries we
could do the same thing for our for
annuity yes but and this may speed up
the invocation of the instructions or
the in the UDF but it still doesn't
solve our paralyzation or a cost
estimation problems or the cross
optimization problems again it just
makes it makes the clapping you di run
faster the the opposite end of the
spectrum tied the worst type of
invocation of the UDF it's not the worse
but it's like the probably the slowest
in the type of invocation would be what
Postgres does which actually converts
each line into a separate query itself
then it invokes that means clever from
the engineering standpoint but from a
performance team point I think it's
pretty abysmal alright so let's see how
bit the bad things can actually get so
this is a curry 12 from TPC H using the
scale factor 1 and so they've modified
the the query to introduce this this
artificial predicate here that have that
invokes a invokes that UDF we saw before
but we're gonna compute the customer
rank all right so we're just gonna get
the customer name
for for each each customer we're looking
at and we just check to see whether it's
it's not null
and so this UDF would just looks like
this all it does is taken the customer
key and it does a single select
statement to do a lookup to get the
customer name and so this this predicate
is essentially useless because in TPCC
for this column the the sorry for the
customer name column it's never going to
be null right but the the optimizer
doesn't know what this is doing here
because this is just a black box now you
could say all right why couldn't try to
interpret what this is you know this
query here and try to inline it but it
doesn't do that because it's not gonna
know not all queries they're gonna not
all you guys are gonna be this simple
so the optimizer doesn't know that this
that no customer name will ever evaluate
to not null or to ever value eight to no
therefore this predicate is always true
so this is just wasted work right we're
invoking this function for something to
check something that will never be false
so if you execute this just the original
query in sequel server you can without
the UDF you can invoke it in in eight
hundred milliseconds but if you just add
this this this simple UDF the same query
now takes 13 hours alright because again
it's for every single for every single
for every single tuple its invoking the
this function over never again now to me
this seems super surprising because it's
like alright well if I if my scale
factors one and how many customers or
line numbers are actually gonna have how
bad that could actually be but for
whatever reason again secret over chokes
on this and getting that goes thirteen
hours so what we'll see today is a
technique called Freud is how to in line
this inside the function to avoid this
you know all the bad things we talked
about and the spoiler D if you write the
same function have the same code and ran
this and Freud you can get it down to
900 milliseconds so it's a hundred
milliseconds slower than then what the
original query was but it's certainly
not the you know
it's not going up to 13 hours like in
orders of magnitude for all right so
let's look at this in shooting history
from how we got to to Freud in single
server and so the in 2001 Microsoft
added support for the scalar UDF's again
computing or taking in scalar values and
producing scaling scalar results in
around 2008 people start to realize that
oh these UDF's are actually kind of bad
they're making things really really slow
like they're great for programmability
and extents extending the the
capabilities of the database system but
it's just crushing performance and so
there's this blog article from an on
Microsoft employee where he basically
says that oh these these UDF's are evil
they write they're making everything
really slow then in 2010 Microsoft
actually publicly acknowledges that
UDF's are evil and they come up with
this blog article that says oh yeah you
do DSR evil here's why
and they actually actively encourage
their developers using sequel server to
not use UTS again and they explain why
and this is when they also introduced
the the native compilation to machine
code of the UTS but even then it doesn't
solve that problem of invoking the UDF
one by one for each tube or each row so
now at this round 2014 there is research
being done at IIT Bombay which is
probably you know it is the best
database school in all of India and they
were doing research on UDF correlations
so it was like early work before Freud
that showed that you can actually do in
lining of UTS and this work was being
done by Karthik Rama Krotz Rama Rama
Rama Chandra who was a PhD student at
IIT Bombay so then he graduates kartha
graduates and then he joins the the Jim
Gray lab in
in Madison Wisconsin she started
exploring how to go further with this as
part of Freud um and so the but by 2018
Microsoft announced that Freud was going
becoming generally available in sequel
server 2019 and last year Microsoft
released the version of secret server
that actually includes Freud and if you
can look in the documentation and Sherin
office says here's here's how to do the
the the in lining of the UDS using the
Freud ticket now they don't call it
Freud because that's like the research
name from a product name no one would
understand that it's just called scale
you know you definitely name but it's
sorta like hackaton Microsoft doesn't
call the the in-memory engine for a
sequel server
Hecate on the researchers know what that
is the researchers know what Freud is
but maybe if you search for a fried in
their documentation it's not going to
show up it's called in mining so this is
say this every year the second year of
talk dick taught us this is very
impressive to go from like starting a
project in 2015 and then getting it
actually in production in in in you know
a major major piece of software that
makes markets all billions of dollars
that will have a lot of impact cause I
mean a lot of people were to get exposed
to this can UDS or use all over the
place but this is a short amount of time
to do some of this this is very
impressive so one it shows you how you
know how significant the gains that
Freud are gonna is going to achieve
because Microsoft put a big engineering
effort to get this in production get
this in the you know the real version of
sequel server and this is rare because
most the time database companies least
the the major ones in Oracle IBM and
Microsoft they are quite conservative
about pushing out new features very
quickly because people rely on these
things and if you know if your product
is seemed especially a database system
it's seen unreliable or kind of flaky or
you're not taking the engineering
process seriously that can seriously
hurt you know sales and your reputation
so to go into this short amount of time
to get this in production is it
is is a big deal all right so what is
Freud so as I said Freud is a is a
technique for converting imperative UDF
code into relational out for expressions
that we can then embed inside of a query
plan inside of a query plan that we're
invoking that UDF right and the reason
why we want to do this is because this
is gonna enable the query optimizer and
the rest of the system to reason about
what the UDF is doing and optimize it
just as it would a regular query but
it's good basically you're converting
imperative code into declared or sequel
declarative relational algebra
expressions all right and the advantage
you're gonna get from this is that from
the application developers perspective
you don't have to do anything you're
just taking your UDS you already have
and you flip a switch to say I want to
use Freud and it'll do that inlining for
you it's it's not like you need to even
touch your application again this this
is super rare think about this anytime
you know there's a new secret say
there's a new magic sequel function
that's gonna be that can make your
application faster they oftentimes
they'll keep the old one in place and
then you have to go change your
application to use the new one or change
how you're instead of the queries there
something like that you don't have to do
any of that Freud it just it just works
right that that's very cool
so what's gonna happen is that the
queries gonna show up that's gonna
invoke an EDF and then Freud would do
the conversion in the sort of binder
rewriter phase before you get to the
cost base clear your query optimizer so
all the rules that we're gonna do to do
this inlining are just don't require a
cost model like they're sort of static
heuristic to say the static
transformation rules to say here's the
minute here's the how to manipulate the
UDF to make the to convert it to
something that i can inline the only
sort of thing you need to consider is
sort of parameter or flag that would
specify how deep you want to go and
instead of doing the in linings for like
nested UDF calls like you can have UDS
called UDS call you do yes
and if you try to inline all of that
then that becomes it becomes you know
more difficult now for the optimizer to
try to to plan and optimize because now
you have this giant giant query whereas
before it was just all bunch of UDF
calls so there's only there's it's far
as you know there's only one parameter
that says how how deep you want to go
and so essentially what's going to do is
it's going to try to do this inlining by
creating sub queries and the reason why
we want to do this is because all the
major database systems especially sequel
server have very sophisticated
constructs or transformations for
unnecessaries and converting them into
either joins or or temp table
invocations right so we're going to burn
all our UDS into sub queries and then
let the optimizer rewrite them those sub
queries into a more optimized form so we
didn't we didn't get the talk about sub
queries too much but I didn't want to
talk about them and lateral joins or the
apply operator because these are these
sort of the set up to understand what
we're gonna do so with the sub query
it's basically when you have us a select
query inside of another query and the
idea is that the the daily system
conditioner to treat these the sub query
the nested query as almost like a
function that will can return a single
by or set of values so so conceptually
the sub query is almost the same thing
as the UF or it's like something inside
of us and you can get back values so as
I said the way the optimizer is going to
handle this is two approaches you either
rewrite them to be correlative flatten
the queries so that they're doing joins
or in some cases you can rewrite them
into a single table query or are you
gonna break out the nested query store
its result in a temporary table or sort
of run that separately first why they're
not attached to the same query plan or
it's broken out the separate query plan
that depends on the implementation
ideas that we run the the inner queries
first materialize it to a temporary
table and then we run the outer query
and then they can do is read that joins
against that temp table and the temp
table is thrown away when the query
finishes so let's look at a simple
example of doing a rewrite so say you
have a query here where I want to get
the name of the sailors that reserved a
boat from the made a reservation for a
boat on this particular day so I just
have give me all the you know I have a
where clauses that exists a tuple where
there's a reference to the the sailor ID
from the outer table and a reserve ID on
the inner table so when a database
system sees this and if it can do
rewriting it could rewrite this as a
simple join like this right because the
alternative would be I run this query
for every single tuple I have in the
sailors table but that's going to be
super slow so I can just rewrite it to
this and then I then I do whatever the
hash join of additional join that I want
to do all right so again we're not gonna
talk about this so much the there's a
group in the in the course is doing this
for the final project and as they talked
about when they do the proposal and
status update the different types of sub
queries that they're going to try to
support in our system the thing another
thing we haven't talked about is lateral
join and the way I think about a lateral
join is when I have nested queries I can
have the inner query reference the the
outer query right so inside my inner
query here I can reference the sailor ID
from the outer table here but if I had
the two queries not nested but sort of
executed one after another like my from
clause I can have a bunch of select
statements inside of that a lateral
joint is gonna allow me to reference the
the attributes or from tuples from
queries being executed sort of
sequentially or executed at the same
nesting level all right so the
without this lateral keyword you and you
would execute each sub-query
independently and you wouldn't be able
to refer to the items of each other
attributes of each other in the from
clause but when this we allow ourselves
to reference the other attributes right
so the this will make more sense when we
see examples in a second but just know
that like in the Freud paper they're
using what is called the apply operator
to do these lateral joins I think that's
within the sequel standard but other
systems like postgis and Oracle you
explicitly call this as a lateral joint
okay so let's go through a Freudian
so it's gonna have five steps so in the
first step we want to transform the
sortie seco statements in our UDF into
sequel queries and then now we're going
to convert the UDF into regions that are
going to allow us to then reason about
the sequel queries within that region
and then we'll combine all the
expressions from each region now weather
gets the individual sequel statements
within a region into a single sequel
statement and then now we can inline the
the UDF expressions that from the
combined the combined giant query into
the query that invoked our UDF and then
we just run this through our query
optimizer to do the optimization that
and the unnecessaries as needed all
right
so what I'll say is that for this
example with Freud I'm gonna show an
illustration that I'm going to show you
these steps using sequel queries but the
real implementation of Freud in sequel
server doesn't operate on sequel queries
and instead operates on relational
algebra operators but I'm using sequel
because it it's easier to read this way
the second technique will to do inlining
I'll show you actually does operate on
sequel queries ok connects going to
convert them into comment expressions
viii immediate forms aren't to be
exactly sequel queries but the end
result is is what it in lines are sequel
queries whereas what this is inlining
is relational algebra expressions all
right so our first step is assuming we
had that example from before where we're
getting given a customer key we'll tell
you what service level your app in the
first step we have going to break up our
all of our imperative statements that
are in our query but we have the you
know setting a level the Select
statement here or doing the if Clause
here we can convert all of these into
into sequel statements we have to do
this because this is t sequel commands
this is not sequel this is not relate
your algebra things right so we have to
convert them to sequel statements so
that we can then combine them together
so it's almost always gonna be a 1:1
mapping so from one sort of statement
within the UDF will produce one query
it's not always the case but for our
example will be right so for this
setting the variable level to Platinum
that's the same thing as doing a select
when you take the constant string
platinum and project it into the
attribute level in the output the Apple
result for the query by this table is
query which is valid sequel then for
this one here computing the sum well
that's the same thing is just using the
same query as before computing the sum
but then again projecting it out to the
total the total attribute and the last
one here if total is greater than 1
million that's just a case demon I bunch
of in an estimate if clauses but to then
produce prettiest applets and then since
we don't have an else statement here we
don't know what else to do we end up
putting a null all right so now the next
step is again we says we know how to do
this conversion now what will break up
our UDF into regions and then construct
a relational algebra expression or a
sequel query for for each of those so
for this first part here we're going to
quote me where we declare some variables
and we then take the compute the sum
total price for the customer starting
and the total key we're gonna create for
each region a synthetic table where we
can assign again the values that
needed to store in variables to be
projected output attributes alright so
in this case here we initialize the
level attribute sorry the level
attribute - - - nothing here so we'll
just you know send that out to be Nome
and then in here we compute that sum we
had before and we'll sign it to the
total variable and then we'll store this
in a synthetic table for our temporary
table for for this portion of the query
as you are one now for this next one
here our second region is going to cover
this portion of the if clause and again
it's that same case statement that I saw
in the previous slide right and then
we'll destroy this in let's gonna store
the result of this into the level
attribute and then we'll store this in
the ER PR - er - table so then the third
one here will be just the other port
part of the if statement and this would
just be the the opposite of what exists
or if the total is less than equal to 1
million then we'll set it to regular but
notice actually for both of these here
the on this case here the the if I don't
have a if if my if if the total that's
presented from from this this guy up
here if this is greater than a million
set at the Platinum otherwise use
whatever the level value that was a sign
up in here right so I'm referencing this
table I'm referencing you are one down
inside here because I'm sort of again
going from top to bottom if I didn't set
level here that I wanna make sure that I
did propagating what the level was up
before I don't know whether was set up
above me in our example here it's at the
null but it could have been set by some
some other computation and so I'm just
saying that I don't know what it is so
just and I'm not I'm not modifying it so
just pass down whatever it was in the in
the region up above me the other thing
I'll point out too is for this example
although it's cut off this is one two
three I could have a single region for
my if statement that included the F else
because then the the else portion of of
this case statement up here could could
have just been the regular thing and
then I don't need to do
you know total lesson Eagle million for
for this example you could do this in
other examples you cannot because the
you could have like return statements
inside of us again like this is easy
because this is like this is like for
inside be of calls I set one variable
but I think again I can do anything I
want inside of this this if calls like
if I fall into it I can call another
function I can return statement actually
a query and if that's the case it'd be
hard it may be dirt to declare that
inside of this I and have an else
statement so for this reason for sort of
simplicity we're breaking it up into two
separate regions alright the last one is
the return statement this one will be
easy to handle
we'll just see this on the next on the
next slide
it's just producing whatever the output
of level is when I combine these these
the queries for the different regions
together again for this one it's super
easy because inside my function there's
only one return statement the paper
talks about how for statements you could
have returned for some UDS you could
have return statements in all different
parts of the program at the end of the
day you always kind of need one return
statement at the bottom and so the way
they handled that is they look they'll
create a synthetic variable called
called return value and instead of
calling return and try to return the
result there you'll set return value
inside of where it wherever it was
invoked and then just returned that as
the output at the bottom alright alright
so now we have our regions that we
defined the queries we define for the
regions that we broke up our UDF into
the next step is now to start merging
these into two to one one select
statement so that's what this is here
and this is where the the lateral
joining or the cross apply comes into
play alright so the first thing to point
out through is like here's our return
function here's the return value that we
had before right
er ER 3 dot level right cuz that's the
last thing we're gonna look at the
bottom of the UDF and then we want
whatever the level was set to and
because that's the output but now you
can see why we need to use these cross
joins because I have my from calls from
the top and then I have three sub
queries that aren't nested inside of
each other right there they're executed
has
your service siblings for a lack of a
better term so in order for this sub
query to reference a attributes in this
sub query up here I gotta use the cross
apply or I gotta use the lateral join so
that I can reference er one here because
without this I can't I can't do that
it'll say undefined attribute alright so
this also shows you that the output or
they the computation of each each of
these sort of sort of regions depends on
the previous one and then I'm gonna as
I'm setting up a modifying level as I go
down and then I the last one whatever
gets set up down here is what I produce
as my output alright so this is it so
this is this is the seagull clear we
would generate for that original UDF
that we saw in the beginning written in
T sequel like this will produce a
computation that is a produced result
that is equivalent for an e for any
given key so now we need to inline this
we need to put this inside of our
original query so if we go back the
original query was that we're invoking
the customer level function for each
customer key in the the select output
clause so all we need to do now is just
replace customer level here with our
with our combined together applied
operator query from the from the last
slide and then here's again all the same
regions that we have before okay so now
with this giant sequel statement we will
now want we want to inline this into our
we've inline this into our query and now
we can run it through the optimizer and
let it let it do its thing to produce a
more efficient query plan by rewriting
and and breaking up our run nesting or
sub queries here
so what sequel server optimizer will
generate is is an equipment plan like
this where it no longer does all these
these sort of these sort of sub selects
I'm just doing a left outer join
inside this where I compute the you know
I get the total total amount I
compute the total amount of orders
placed for each single customer you're
doing the group I on the customer key
then I do is join against that and now I
pushed Mike Mike a statement up here in
the Select output just to look whatever
the output is from this aggregation and
then produced the right output level
right so what what went from a blackbox
invocation of this this computation but
to get some customer level thing I just
completely rewrote it into a a simple
aggregation followed by a left outer
join this is amazing right this is think
about it it's like you're doing this for
any UDF almost any UDF they can do this
on so it's not like I had a like you
know I had to pay someone a lot of money
to sit down and look at my UDS and
figure out oh how can I actually rewrite
this into a query because not every you
know well it's gonna be invoked it's
gonna be different from you know
sometimes it'll be in the phone calls
even though we're close like it could be
invoked differently every single time
but and then rather than having to
rewrite every single see coke where to
use it by doing this conversion into
this this giant seagulls inline sequel
statement I produced a more efficient
query plan him know change the
application code didn't have to hire a
man do that no changes to the query
optimizer the query optimizer can
already handle this there's nothing
specific about Freud in this in this
query it's all you know vanilla sequel
servers sequel syntax so this is amazing
so now also to the benefit is that UDF
is no longer our black box and the
optimizer in terms of from a cost model
perspective so we know how to do you
know search for the most efficient
physical plan for for this sequel
statement you know the logical plan if
we can now invoke this in parallel as
well is I can have a parallel threaded
compute the the group I I can now have a
parallel and then parallel thread do the
do the you know produce the output every
single query in the you do after you
couldn't do that so again I'm super you
know excited about this because I think
that this is a huge win okay so now
let's talk about what are some
additional optimizations the query
optimizer can do that we can get because
we've in mind
single statement so let's look at really
simple UDF like this so-called get vowel
where you input some value to this
function and some may be some integer
and then it's gonna tell you that if it
turns back a string that says if the
value is greater than a thousand and for
turn hi if the gret the value is greater
than or less than a less than you go to
a thousand return low and then just
concatenate whatever that value is to
the to the string die so you get high
value low value based on the input
alright so say that we had this
invocation so we know what the value of
this this number is I said we can
substitute 5000 of X to be 5000 wherever
you need to so what we would get it with
Freud is a is a select statement it
looks like this right where I have a
lateral join where I'm taking the output
of this case statement depending what my
input is and I'll get high value and low
value so now let's go across and see
what kind of optimizations the well you
know the the rewriting the operators are
gonna do to cut down the complexity of
this program and it's gonna look a lot
like what a traditional compiler
optimizer will do but you know for a
pair of languages like C or C++ like
this is something the optimizer can do
its query optimizer video so the first
thing is that we can you dynamic slicing
right we can recognize that we know the
exact value that that's been given to us
so we can throw out the the low
conditional low path in our in our in a
program because we know what the content
is for the X so we know that we're never
even gonna execute this so we just we
just remove it entirely then we could do
propagation constant propagation and
folding again recognizing here that we
have a select query that all it does is
produced the output hi and then there's
a select query that takes whatever this
thing produced and produces that as the
output so and then you know do the same
thing over here or take take append
these two things together
so rather than invoking all these these
these sub queries with the with the
lateral join eigen is evoke that as
they sort of combine that together into
a single constant that I produce right
and then the equivalent in the UDF will
be up here and the last step would be
dead code elimination again recognizing
that I don't need to even set the value
to high or set it and clear available
produces the output I can just return
the value directly I say the same thing
in the PDF the same thing as a has as in
the relational address so Freud is
essentially achieving the same thing by
using the the query optimizer to do this
to do these rewriting steps we're
getting all the same benefits you would
get from a traditional like GCC client
query optimizer so again but they didn't
have to write that because they got the
UDF into relational algebra form they
got all that for free from Microsoft's
you know very expensive and very good
query optimizer so what can fluid
support so as of twine the 2019 in
sequel server and the paper you guys
read Freud can support most of the
constructs in T sequel so declare and
set select statements if-then-else
returns exists and other set operators
they can handle recursive calls or
nested calls to other UTS they can
handle all the possible sequel types as
of this this you know this paper here
and in in in production sequence over
2019 they don't support loops they don't
sort for loops while loops they don't
support dynamic queries because again
you don't know what the query is gonna
be before it runs and you doesn't
support exceptions which are
surprisingly common in UDF's
so alright so you say well there are
some limitations but how how prevalent
are these things in in in in sort of
real world applications so in the paper
what they did is they looked at the top
100 sequel as your databases running and
running the cloud for them and they just
sort of look at all the scalar UDS the
people are using and there's like it's
over 85,000 of them and
of those 85,000 UDF's they they found
out about about 60% of them could be
inline with the technique using Freud
and then in the paper they evaluate
three different customer workloads and
they're showing here again what
percentage of the yes that they're using
our Freud compatible right so again
there are you know they're argue that's
out there using for loops and dynamic
reconstruction that fraud can't support
but for our large percentage of them
this is this is quite significant and so
the benefit the speed-up you're going to
get for some of these customers are very
impressive so there are some cases where
Floyd actually makes things worse I
forget why the paper said this was the
case I I don't remember just because it
I don't remember whether because he may
be optimized and run longer or maybe
because it picked up a wave on that I
don't remember but there's still a you
know large there's a so this is long the
the x-axis is just a unique invocation
of one particular UDF and then it's
sorted based on the speed-up they're
getting so again for these cases here
they're getting you know up to 800 X
improvement in performance for for UDF's
without having to change any application
code this and this is unheard of because
all of them in like you know the money
if you buy new Hager unless your hugger
like you're running on like you know
computers from like nineteen nineteen
then you buy brand new computers maybe
you know you would see the speed-up
but you know where does it ever the case
that there's something that you can get
a huge speed up like this for these
queries without having to modify your
application code at all and again I
think this is telling about why
Microsoft got this in production very
quickly because the performance benefit
you can get from this is so massive the
coach and stuff we talked about today
like in certainly in that case if you're
going from an interpreted engine to a
compiled engine you're gonna get a huge
speed up but when you know so that one
would be it's an example of something
similar to this where you can just you
could run the same sequel queries and
get the same kind of speed up um but
like the vectorized stuff that we talked
about sure like in the columbia paper
for individual algorithms they were
getting
big speed-up but that only happened when
everything sat in in CPU cache but when
you actually put things in and things
exceed the cache and you actually got a
you know spilled and DRAM you know maybe
the best you're seeing like a twenty
five twenty percent fifteen percent
improvement like this this is 800 X
that's massive so this is again this is
why I teach this paper because I think
it's actually it's a huge huge deal okay
so as you can imagine
Microsoft has patents on this so it sort
of limits you know at this point I'm not
a patent lawyer but I imagine the you
know using the Freud technique and other
database systems would be well good you
know could cause some legal problems but
the good news is there's other ways to
do this inlining without going through
the same kind of transformation steps
that Freud does and so this came from a
paper published actually this year in
January at cider on how to convert UDF's
into common table expressions so rather
than rewriting the UDS into relational
object sessions that you then inline
into the query plan where instead of
gonna rewrite them into siegel queries
using recursive CTE recursive comment
expressions and what this is also going
to get us is that other than you're not
doing exactly weighted fluid does it it
also gets you supporting iterations and
loops and other control flow concepts
our constructs that were not possible in
that version of freud now i will say
there is a newer version of freud freud
tupelo know if you want to call it that
being published this year in sigmod i
was given an early preview of the paper
a few days ago so and hans time to
discuss here and in that version they do
support loops but up until now this
particular purchase i'm showing you here
is the only one that can do this so the
other interesting thing about this
approach from another set of Germans is
that the the rewriting technique that
they're proposing can actually
and as a middleware layer that does not
need to be intrinsically tied or tightly
coupled with the after database system
implication so in there in this paper
they show that they're doing this on
Postgres but you could do it for Oracle
you could do it for for any any gaming
system that supporting you yes and also
supported recursive comic expressions
all right so let's see how they're gonna
do it and how it has to be different
than fluid so it also is gonna have five
steps where the last step is again
running it through the query optimizer
but they're gonna take a more I can't
comment on like whether this is more ple
or overall principle I this is not my
area it it just seems it's a different
approach to end up with sort of a
similar end result that you can in line
these UDS so we're gonna go through each
of these one by one but basically we're
start off with our PL sequel or PL PG
sequel UDS that's gonna have some kind
of arbitrary iterative control flow in
them more so you know going beyond what
before I can do and then in the first
step we're going to do is convert them
into SSA which is going to convert it
into a program that uses go-to based
control flow then we're gonna hand this
off and now convert the SSA form into an
administrative normal form that will
give us a mutually tail recursive
function then we'll convert that will
convert the type recursion we're doing
here into with the tail recursion and
actually we can then rewrite that into
the CTE using with the with recursive
command and again now we have a giant
sequel statement as we did with Freud
and then we shove that off to our
optimizer alright so for this one we're
going to show an example in NP OPG
sequel so again it's it's different than
T Seagle but as you can see it roughly
looks the same like the difference is I
declare my variables separately outside
the begin where T sequel you give us all
you declare them after the begin right
so it's like minor differences like that
but at a high level is still the same
thing so this is going to be the power
function where we given
a base value and then we gave an
exponent and then we're going to take it
to the nth power so forgive an axe
ticking to the nth power so and the way
we do that is just do a while loop for
the number of iterations that are less
than the nth power and we're going to
multiply the the value by itself and
then we return it so let me record it
convert it into SSA form again this is
now the control flow of the function
expressed with go-to statements and the
other aspect of SSA is that each
variable within a within the block other
than the program can only be assigned
once so I'm not a compilers person but
my understanding yet this is what this
is what compilers are doing on the
inside when they when they convert their
programming languages so in this case
here write the same thing as a power
function I assign my variables and then
I use a go to is to jump other to the
exit to return values or loop through
and with the body of the loop there
alright so now that we have our UDF in
it SSA form we want to convert it to the
a normal form and for this one here this
is being mutually recursive calls where
we were just doing the the recursive
call to another function is always at
the tail at the bottom of the of the
whatever the function block so we call
power we set up some variables then call
our while loop and then this spins
through and in this case here this is
our exit exit clause right if we if
you've added enough that were greater
and greater than equal to n which is the
the number times when it you want to
multiply the value by itself if we
satisfy this constraint then we break
out so this is essentially the return
statement here otherwise we jump in here
and actually do the computation but then
loop back all right so now with the in
the a normal form we can then convert it
into using direct recursion so I'm sort
of simplifying the step here but now I'm
combining now the while the wild block
and the body block in tow stable run
block where I do all that same
computation yeah but before
so now this is a single recursive
function that is only using the tail
recursive calls right there's no
recursive calls somewhere arbitrarily in
the query so then now with this I can
take this imperative code and convert
that into a giant secret single
statement would see with CT ease so this
is a bit gnarly to look at but briefly
the way to think about this here's the
first part of the function that does
some initialization so I'm setting up my
my I vow to keep track of enum times
I've looped setting up the P bio to keep
track of you know the running total as I
do my my my reason I think to the power
and that's just the Select statement
here which is just setting up some
variables as the initialization Clause
of the CTE but then the Union all it
allow me to invoke the same same query
over and over again and get that gift of
recursive the recursive calls that we
need so all of this here is combined
into this sequel statement here which
does the logic that that we need right
so the if I've gone past my number
iterations then I this thing evaluates
this thing would evaluate to false would
and then I can break out and then all of
this down here like so this is sort of
confusing but this call thing here this
is the name of a of an attribute that
we're defining as but the name is call
question mark when you put the quote
double quotation marks around it to make
sure that it's sheena treated this
ballots equals syntax so we're using
that variable to decide that the false
or true whether to keep calling myself
and then when this thing evaluates to
false then I my program breaks wrap
breaks out I unwind from all my
recursive calls and produce the output
to the Select statement here so again
this is widely different than what Freud
is doing but a conception you end up
with the same result where you have the
ability to now inline in arbitrary UDF
with actually four loops and you get the
four loops with using recursive
recursion and be one of oak them in a
query so at this point it is unclear
whether
produces more optimal plans than Freud
that spearmint of that evaluation has
not been done this also does not support
the dynamically structure sequel queries
and that doesn't support exceptions but
this is something back to you we are
talking with now with Karthik and
Torsten the the other friendly German
that made this paper that I wrote this
work we're looking at sort of sort of
comparing all these together along with
the the compilation stuff of the UTS
effect for the for the UDS you can't
actually inline if you compile them with
the LLVM what happens so this is sort of
ongoing research what we're exploring
here at carnagie mom alright so one
graph to show the benefit you can
actually get so this is running this is
running that same pal function on on
Postgres 11 and the x-axis is scaling
the the number times you want to iterate
the call and keep producing you know
raising the the base value so the black
line is with the original UDF and then
the red line is with the CTE and so you
you're getting about a roughly forty
forty to fifty percent performance
benefit over the UDF call and again from
this case here the for this particular
example there is no you know there's no
issues of the optimizer choosing bad
plans cuz because you know not knowing
the cardinality UDF's this is just
showing you the from a pure performance
benefit which you can get from using
recursive calls versus the using the UDF
and so where you're getting the benefit
is because in the case of post rest as i
said all the the individual lines are
the the commands within a UDF get
convert into select statements there
that are then sent to the parser or the
binder and the optimizer the core planet
and executed you know for every single
line so there's essentially for every
single line the UDF there are voting a
query and so this is showing that
avoiding all that overhead by being able
to do as a recursive CTE is a big win
okay
so as I said the these results are huge
in case the Freud the the Florence gains
are quite significant the CTE approach
is still very new so it's unclear how
much how much benefit you want to go
from that's polluted the early results
are very promising and as I said like
show me another example where unless
somebody was doing something stupid and
like Bitcoin mining in the middle of
your XP of your query engine while you
run queries like showing you is
something you can do well you'll have to
change anything your application and you
get a 500x improvement like this this is
quite significant and as I said the
another approach that we're exploring is
to how to compile the the UDF into
machine code the same way you would for
a query this doesn't solve the optimizer
cost model problem like you still need
to use the CTE or the Freud push to get
that benefit but for some computations
that you can't inline that actually may
be a better way to go but I think the
real end up the solution is gonna be a
sort of hybrid approach where sometimes
some Porsche me some portion of you do
you have to be in line another portion
could be cogent and how you balance all
that and where you make sort of the cut
points is is the interesting direction
that I want to explore okay all right
guys so the next week will be the last
lecture we have for the semester and
this will be sort of a reoccurring theme
of in databases of like what happens
when new harbor comes out and how can
you have your database system take
advantage of it often times when new
harbor comes out the now it's it's
machine learnings probably the hot thing
so there's a lot of are tailored for
machine learning but traditionally you
know as Intel or disk manufacturers or
whoever puts out new hardware one of the
the obvious targets it's gonna be
database systems because no one ever
complains that you make your data so
faster so for next class we want to see
you some of the newer this or the newer
data base hardware
sorry that's coming out in the past the
way we design architecture okay guys
[Music]