[Music]
[Applause]
so today's focus is on like how to
actually then build the second major
component of a Curie optimizer of how to
actually do estimations on what we think
this system is going to actually do when
the excuse to query like how much this
is gonna cost us to execute the query so
yeah so this is not working so the the
the reason why we have to do this
I should be sort of obvious when we talk
about the cost based search models from
the last two classes I said that there's
a sort of black magic box thing that
that's gonna tell us that here's what
the expected cost of executing this
particular query is and again it's an
internal cost it's not something that's
meaningful outside of the database
system I mean you can't take my sequels
cost model have it spit out a number and
then take Postgres this cost model take
that number and then make a comparison
right this is completely dependent on
the implementation of the system and
it's really just meant for us to be able
to say this query plan is better than
this other query plan for some reason
which will describe going forward in
this lecture and therefore that's what I
want to use right so the other thing
important to understand - this is also
independent this cost model is
independent of the search strategies we
talked about last time meaning whether
we're doing top-down or bottom-up I it
doesn't matter right we at the end of
day we still need a cost model that and
still needs me to make predictions about
you know whether one plan is is better
than another so if you're gonna build a
cost model how would you actually do it
well there's a couple different things
you can include in it so the first is
are the physical cost so these would be
what is the hardware actually going to
do when it X use the query right how
many CPU cycles how many cache misses
all right how many how much date you're
gonna read from disk right this is
obviously dependent on the the machine
that you're running on and it's hardware
configuration because as we saw
couple of different examples right the
whether you're using a Xeon CPU for a
Xeon Phi those CPUs have very different
characteristics and therefore the
performance of your algorithms or your
query can vary depending what hardware
it is so this is usually pretty tricky
to do because because of that reason
because it's hard to actually have build
models based on all of them possible
hardware configurations that could exist
the next approach is to do what I'll
call logical costs and these are where
we're basing their cost estimates on the
what the operators in a query plan are
going to actually do at a logical level
so no it's a physical level would be
again I read this when to block some
disk a logical level would be I'm gonna
read this many tuples from a table or my
joint operator is gonna spit out this
many tuples after the join or my scans
gonna filter so many to so many tuples
so for these this is gonna be
independent of what algorithm we're
actually using in our query plan so this
is only looking at the logical operator
something physical operators right and
this is this should be sort of obvious
right if I'm doing a nested loop joined
versus a hash join the end of the day
both algorithms should should generate
this the exact same result writing the
same number of tuples because otherwise
I have problems in my implementation and
so therefore we don't care whether in
the for logical aspects we don't care
about whether it's you know it's one
algorithm versus the other so the tricky
thing is gonna be and what was in the
paper you guys read about and we'll talk
about going forward is you're obviously
gonna need to be able to estimate
accurately what the output of an
operator is gonna be because that's
gonna be fed and as the input for the
next operator so in order to say are you
the number two because I'm gonna read
into this operator and therefore um
generate this much output and you need
to know what came below me in the query
planner and that again that that's gonna
be the hardest thing we have to do and
the last one is going to be sort of
average the cost or asymptotic
complexity of the of the operators right
and this is where it actually matters
whether we're doing a hash join or a
nested loop join or index scan versus
Quantrill scan right and again for these
ones we you know we can just
we can sort of have weights that's
people say oh the the hash joint is is
you know x times better than a messy
loop joint and therefore prefer that but
there are obviously some scenarios
within a solution would be better so as
well see is going going along and
actually I'll show the next couple
slides what we're primarily gonna do for
an in-memory database is gonna be a
combination of these two for this one up
here if you can do it but it's hard and
this is another good example over like
the difference between the commercial
database systems of the open source
database system so at the talk the
redshift talk on on Monday if you went
to that epic Rattus mentioned they're
like oh like the the query optimizer in
their system is is maturity difficult
and you know the they've spent a lot of
money fixing it up at Amazon and it's
way better than any of the open source
ones that are out there
it's sort of commercial grade or
enterprise grade because the enterprise
guys are gonna include all these things
the source guys probably just include
two these two guys so for a disc based
database system the most obvious thing
that we care about is the disc right
it's the end of the day that that's the
most expensive things like feeding
getting things off of a you know
spinning this hard drive or SSD so in
this world the CPU costs are they're not
negligible in the sense of like we can
ignore them but if your cost model only
includes how many blocks are data that
you know how many blocks of data that I
read and write from disk that's probably
gonna get you you know 90% of the way
there right who cares what you actually
do when you bring the data into your
into memory I guess it's getting from
dishes most expensive thing now
obviously on a it's it's less of an
issue on modern SSDs but definitely if
you have a spinning this hard drive you
know taking the account the difference
between sequential i/o versus random i/o
is a big difference and a lot of times
you can you see in a disk or in a
database system especially older ones
they use algorithms that are that are
designed to optimize the amount of
sequential i/o you're doing alright so
the important thing that
you know understand but and the disk
based system is that the database system
is gonna have complete control over
what's in memory over its buffer pool
management assuming you're not using em
map which well we can discuss later the
you know we know exactly in our
databases we know how we're actually
bringing blocks in we know how our
writing blocks out we know what you know
what algorithm are using to decide what
data is colle what data we want to evict
right so we have complete control over
this and we can include this in our
calculations in our cost model we know
how you know if we're gonna give this
amount of mem this this amount of memory
and a buffer pool to run this query and
therefore it has to read this amount of
data whether that's sequential over says
random i/o we can then you know take
that and account into our cost models to
make estimations what we think the query
is actually gonna do all right so I
would say you know this is this is what
I'm describing here is how you would do
this on a single node displace database
system if your distributed database just
replace the word disk with network right
that's it's basically the same thing and
you have the same issues so I want a
quick example what Postgres does the
reason why I always like to use
post-course as an example for describing
how you know how real Sussman actually
implements so this is that in my opinion
it's like almost like a textbook
definition or implementation of a
database database systems like if you
take any introduction class you take the
textbook when using that and the way
they describe the algorithms and in the
textbook assumes exactly how it's
actually implemented in in Postgres so
for Postgres they're gonna use a
combination of CPU and i/o costs they're
gonna be weighted by these what are call
magic constant factors right magic magic
weights and the reason why you do this
is the basically just say like because
it's dependent on what the hardware
actually can do so they'll say you know
sequential i/o will be you know x times
fast direct times better than then
random i/o and memory i/o will be x
times faster than so catch why oh all
right so in this environment they are
obviously targeting
in these sort of default configuration a
database that's on disk and therefore
you don't have a lot of memory so they
again they want to use that in their
cost want to account for you know what's
actually going on but the tricky thing
is they expose this to you as as an
administrator that you can actually tune
these waits for you right so the default
is the memory is 400x faster than
reading from disk and then scratch iOS
for it's faster than random i/o so you
can go in the look in the documentation
to see how you change these these costs
but then they had this nice little
warning here that basically says like if
you start mucking around with these you
could have problems right because again
these these are highly dependent on what
the actual workload is and what the data
looks like and what your hardware
actually looks like it's really hard to
get this right right so most people
don't you know don't don't tune these
things because they don't know you don't
know what you're doing
and you don't want to cause regressions
on you know some portion of your
workload United what a commercial system
does we can look at what db2 does in
their system of all the three major
systems db2 sequel server and Oracle db2
is actually the most open about
discussing what their query optimizer
does and what their cost model actually
does right I
there's no as far as I know there's no
major publications from Oracle or sequel
server that talks about what what they
do right we just sort of know some
things based on talking talking to
people there but iBM is actually pretty
good about discussing this and this call
comes from a presentation from guy Loman
who was the guy that invented the
starburst stuff that we talked about two
classes ago so the db2 cost model is a
combination of all of these things so
the first of all they're gonna look at
what the database actually looks like so
the schema and he says they collect on
the tables the columns are in the
indexes but then they're also when you
when you turn the system on they're
gonna run these little micro benchmark
micro benchmarks that are going to
stress tests like the CPU the disk
memory and the network if you're if it's
a distributed system I and then we used
that to essentially generate the weights
that I was showing you in the last last
slide for Postgres so first question get
the set these weights manually db2 tries
to figure this out
you and tries to be real fine grain
based on what your hardware can actually
do but then also when you actually start
doing cost estimation for the query that
shows up they just don't look at your
query in isolation by itself
they also account for what what other
things are running at the same time and
then use that to determine you know what
the effect of those concurrent
operations are on for your particular
query like if you're running by yourself
then you know you take all the memory in
the world and you run really fast but if
you bunch of other queries aren't at the
same time you're not gonna get all the
memory so that far they may take they
take that into consideration when they
estimate the cost of your query plan
right so again this is just it's way
more sophisticated than what any of the
open source guys do and the Postgres one
as far as I know at least Alessa med
locus is is much better than my sequel
one probably the best open source it pi
is the best open source query optimizer
cost model that's out there today
he's leased a year ago when I looked at
I don't I don't know I don't can't think
of anybody else that got better all
right but we care about in the my
databases so what do they do so from
looking at the documentation and manuals
of the major in memory database systems
as far as they can tell everyone does
does what i'm scribing here so basically
the disk is gone so you don't care about
disk i/o yes you have to write to the
log but that's incidental right that
doesn't affect whether you choose one
particular query plan versus another
like if I update a table like who cares
like the disk is not considered in the
cost of that of writing up the log
records right so at the end of the day
that they're all the intermediary bases
are going to do a combination of
primarily how many tuples are being
processed by an operator or how many
people star general and some basic
weights to do to say hash join so better
than the initial loop joins but the the
number of tuples in and out is the major
factor the reason why you can't actually
do anything more fine-grain or like in
like count for how much memory I'm going
to be able to use for my query in the
same way you could with in a disk based
system is because we have
control over actually the the cash
management of our systems that's all
done by the CPU and the CPU we can
provide hints to it we could prefetch
things we can try to pin things in our
caches but the end of the day that the
CPU decides on its own what gets what
gets moved in and out of the cache so we
don't even bother with any of that so we
just try to estimate how much data might
as my operator going to read and write
it turns out that ends up being a well
I'll say a reasonable estimation of what
the CPU resources I'm gonna I'm gonna
use to run my query and this also say us
also this is not also accounting weather
like whether I want to run one thread
versus 100 threads right that's sort of
a separate policy that's different than
what we're trying to do here but that's
almost like a mission control or
resource management for the system so
typically as far as I know you don't you
don't see that in an accountant for than
the cost model like that sort of cabins
after the path and again if you have it
like even if you if you're an in-memory
system like a look at mem sequel since
they're distributed again go back to the
last slide they care about the network
so they have to account for that and not
so much in this don't matters but like
the network is the major factor alright
so I want to give an example of a of
what was a sophisticated cost model from
the 1990s done in small basis it
actually does some of the things that we
talk about with db2 so what they would
have is they have this sort of two-phase
approach where the as the vidalias
developers were building the systems
like at at the company that were
building small base they would try to
identify what are all these low-level
primitives of of during that occurred
during query execution whether or not
they're primitives like in the same way
not really like in vector wise
primitives where you had like those for
those but it's thing of like low-level
things like I read an index or I write
to a tuple so they generate these
low-level operations and then they
create these micro benchmarks that allow
them to sort of simulate
each of these different operations so
then now at runtime in your system when
you deployed to deploy a small base they
would take all these micro benchmarks
run them when you turn the system on and
collect some profile information about
how fast your machine is and then in the
cost model when you look at a query plan
you count up the number of these
low-level operations or primitives that
they're doing multiply that by them by
the micro benchmark results that you
collected and then that's how they're
determining what you know what the cost
of executed query plan is all right so
for again small base was this early in
memory databases some prototype at HP
Labs HP labs then spun it off as a
separate company called times 10 and
then times 10 got bought by Oracle in
like 2006 and it still exists today you
can download it the old system used to
beat it we haven't tried it against a
new system yet the Oracle primarily
sells it as like a CPU cache or sorry an
in-memory cache for the the main Oracle
like flagship database but you can't
still run this as a standalone system
but as far as I know again by looking at
the documentation what they did the 19
it like this paper in the 1990s they
don't do in the real system today they
still do they do what I've described
before they just estimate what's the
number to balls in and out for an
operator is this is similar this
approach is similar to boga mips if you
know what that is in linux right when
you boot up linux they run this thing
this little micro venture called booger
bits that tries to approximate how fast
your CPU is and they use that for
timings decisions for like interrupts
and scheduling if you ever looked like
/proc slash cpu info you'll see like you
know here's the here's a here's my Intel
CPU here's the the the model number
here's an of course I have there'll be a
little entry karpova mips and you use
that as an approximation of how fast
your cpu is ok so I said that the most
important thing we're gonna care about
is the number of tuples in and number
two was out or process by by by an
operator so now we got to figure out how
we're gonna actually gonna be able to
estimate that
so the way we're going to do this is
that we're going to try to estimate the
selectivity of an operator which is
going to determine the percentage of the
tuples that are fed into it it's the
percentage of the tuples that would then
be admitted as output all right so if I
if I'm given a hundred tuples and my
selectivity is 10% then I'm gonna admit
ten tubal's all right so the way you
traditionally do this in a database
system is you can just model this as a
the probability of whether a predicate
will be satisfied for a particular tuple
all right and so the way we can generate
now these these probability estimations
is through a combination of these
different techniques so we can have
domain constraints right this would be
something like if we know the you know
the value range ahead of time of a
particular attribute like if it's an
enum field we know that there's only the
cardinality is fixed we can rely on pre
computed statistics that we can generate
and put into our data blocks and our
tables I mean we talked to us before
when we talked about compression these
are like zoom maps so I can pre-compute
aggregations for different columns in my
in a block and then when I want to
figure out whether a what's the
likelihood that my operators gonna match
where my predicate is gonna match a
tuple within a you know within a block I
can look at the zone maps and maybe
derive some early information like a
mini max value we can also use
histograms or approximations which I'll
talk about in a second and then we also
do sampling so there's no one of these
is better than another like you kinda
wanna use a combination of all these
things that you can to try to estimate
selectivity like the more information
you can get the better so the now the
number of tuples that we're going to end
up processing is going to combination
the is the number two boats we're in a
process it would be 10 and on dependent
on three different things so first is
obviously the access method that we're
using to access to read to Plus from the
table right if it's a sequential scan
then we're gonna potentially look at
everything unless we push down the limit
clause if it's an index scan that we can
even more fine grain and on
look at you know the subset of the total
key space then we have would actually
the distribution of the values of the
database attributes right this is where
the estimation stuff is gonna come and
come into play see I don't know if for a
given predicate what's the likelihood of
probability that I have values in and
you know that would satisfy that I'm
gonna course then also what are the
actual predicate s-- themselves right if
I'm doing a quality predicate on a
unique column then I know my selectivity
is gonna be one over the number of
tuples that I have because the only one
actually can match but now if I start
doing a range scan then this becomes one
problematic to try to estimate this
right so the main takeaway is that for
simple queries like something equals
something we can do a reasonably good
job for for matching that if you start
throwing in inequalities throw in range
scans thrown disjunctions then it
becomes really hard and again because
more data you can get the better so one
approach again we in intro class we
teach you how to generate histograms
right that's basically you run the
analyze function for analyze operation
in your database system and that does a
sequential scan of your table and it
computes some kind of histogram based on
what the what values it actually sees so
that's the thing that's the standard
technique what's been sort of more
prevalent in recent years is to generate
set of exact histograms to generate what
are called sketches which are these
approximate data data structures that
can give you a hint about what the you
know is contained in the data so think
of this as like a hit like a like a the
bloom filter is an approximate data
structure right because it can give you
false positives but I'm never gonna be
false negatives and you can't actually
tell it won't tell you what values or
keys are actually in the bloom filter it
is if you just ask it whether something
exists it will give you a true or false
so these sketches are a lot more
complicated rather than giving you you
know simple true and false is they can
actually tell you values that could that
could exist right but again you could
have false positives I don't know what
some of these I don't actually sometimes
I don't know whether you get false
negatives as well
so there's a bunch of different kind of
sketches that people can use right the
reason why I bring this up was a few
years ago we had the the CEO of splice
machine come and give a talk in the
intro class and he see me alum he's on
the board of advisors for the Dean and
he was here in February and he made this
comment about when he was talking about
their query optimizer and their cost
model was they did the textbook way
initially where they distilled
histograms first and they used the
standard algorithms equations to try to
do estimations on the selectivity of
predicates and their operators but then
they ended up using this sketching
library from Yahoo that did these
approximations right so you you can
bound the you get bare error bound and
estimates to be able say like oh this is
what I think it's gonna be and here's
here's my confidence about but what what
I'm telling you and they said that when
they switch to using these sketches
instead of histograms the accuracy of
their predictions and the robustness of
the query optimizer I primarily because
it because of the better cost model the
the difference of quite significant so I
think they said they like in the old
system when they were using histograms
they could do the cost model would be
okay up to like 10 tables per per query
look at 10 table join but when they
added this then they I think we could go
up to like 75 tables which is again it's
not then I'm saying that the right
metric to use to determine the quality
of your cost model but that was sort of
anecdotal evidence that suggested that
using cash is better than histograms and
in our old optimizer in the old system
we ended up using histograms as well but
I'm sorry yes then I'm using some of
these sketches as well but we never we
never invented it we never no we never
actually measured how much better it
actually was and again I this approach I
think is also used in the commercial
systems the other main technique to
generate estimations about the
selectivity are to do sampling the basic
idea here is that rather than look at
these sketches or the histograms and try
to approximate what the selectivity is
let me actually just take a subset of
the tables I'm accessing
run my query on that or run my skin with
predicate on that and then determine
what my selectivity is and then assume
that my sample is a good approximation
what the total table actually looks like
and then now I have better knowledge
about making my might make my choices in
my cost model right so there's basically
two approach to do this it's like online
versus offline so the offline approach
is you you in the background every so
often you you generate this this
read-only copy of the table that you
sort of put aside and then you do that
your sample and you use that in your
cross model to predict the selectivity
of your predicates right and then you
have this sort of this this background
job that looks and say says well what
how much of my data has changed and then
if it's you know it's above some
threshold then I go back and refresh my
my sample the other person to do this an
online fashion is when the query shows
up and you go in your cost model you
actually go on the real table and run
your a little bit of your query now and
and then determine what the selectivity
of your predicate predicates are and
obviously this becomes tricky because
you have to you trying to do a cost
estimation for for running your query
but now you actually run and run
something up the query it's some subset
of the query on the table and that could
end up being slow and then you also
don't want to slow down other
transactions or queries that run at the
same time so you want to run make sure
you run this on read read uncommitted
without you know without editing any
latches or locks to avoid interfering
with anybody else so the way to think
about doing the sampling thing is like I
had my where clause rather than do it
make any joins that is pick out the
predicate sfrom from my where clauses
and we're joined clauses and I just run
that on the on the you know on the
tables themselves to compute this the
course now this becomes hard if you have
joins because now the selectivity of the
join is tough to compute unless you
start joining things so to the extent in
which people use different systems use
sampling aggressively will vary and this
is where again the
where we get into like commercial
systems are doing something that they
don't really talk about publicly so it's
hard to know what they're actually doing
all right but I know in the case for the
paper you guys read I think they
mentioned some paper sequel server
performs the best sequels our servers
doing a combination of histograms or
approximations plus sampling okay so any
questions about this so we're using this
to figure out we have to use either
histograms sketches or sampling to
figure out the selectivity of all these
predicates and then we can use that
compute the cardinality of our operators
which is then the the amount of data
that's that's being generated right as
the output right and the reason why we
want to know what this is because that
is then being fed it's the input to try
to our next our next operator and the
problem is gonna be the the more
inaccurate our estimates are for the
cardinality the selectivity of our
predicate in these operators at the
lower parts in the tree then that's
gonna amp get amplified as you go up
because I'm off of the bottom leaf node
as I go up that error gets carried over
and now become a more off I can in again
this is what you saw in the paper you
guys read all right so the textbook way
you would actually compute the
cardinality is by modeling the the
selectivity as I said as a probability
and then you make the following three
assumptions about that those
probabilities to be able to compute what
what you know what the the cardinality
is gonna be the selectivity is gonna be
right and again so I would say this is
what I'm describing here is what we
teach you in the interruption class to
go read every single text book about
databases this what they would tell you
and hopefully they would say the caveat
like oh this goes this goes real wrong
real quick but people still do this
right because there's no there's nothing
else right look the only other way to do
the only way to get the exact cost of a
query is actually to run the query but
that's actually super slow so you can't
do that so you make use of some soon as
you make these these should reduce in
the accuracy just be able to get
something that works reasonably well so
the first assumption we're gonna make in
many cases is that
we have a uniform distribution of values
for in our attributes meaning the
probability that a given attribute
appears in my in my in my column is the
same for all values of course we know
that this is not true like more people
live in New York City than men in
Montana so I can't assume that that you
know that the ZIP codes in Montana have
a the same probability of occurring for
people a people database than people in
New York City right the way you
typically get around this is to maintain
a separate data structure for what are
called heavy hitters this thing of this
is just like a little hash table on the
side that says here's the top 10 or top
20 values that occur in my column
because because more times than you know
I'm more likely to query those values
and therefore I can go do a lookup in
this heavy-hitter table and get more
accurate estimates but then everything
else is just assumed to be uniform the
next is that we're gonna assume that all
our our our predicates are independent
again we're modeling these as
probabilities that means we can actually
multiply them together and that's gonna
produce the true selectivity of our
predicate of course that's not going to
work we'll see that in the next slide
and the last one is that the we're gonna
assume that the join keys for inter
relations that we're trying to join on
will always exist in the adulation right
this obvious doesn't work and if you
start doing left outer joins or right
outer joins this becomes problematic
again this is this is another major
assumption that people people have in
their cross model so let me show an
example how this all goes bad and this
great little bin yet or this this sort
of simple problem that again that was
that was a blog honor from guy Logan but
I like this because the illustrates
exactly all the problems would have that
you have when you make all those
assumptions so say you have a simple
database keeping track of cars and you
have you have in your database you have
ten different models like Tesla Honda
Ford and so forth and then start using
ten mix test well-fought Tesla Ford
Honda Toyota and then you have a hundred
ifferent models so like a
that Ford Escort is is a model or a
Toyota Corolla is a model so you have a
hundred of those so if you have a query
now that says where make eCos Honda and
model equals a chord right so we have a
conjunction and to equality predicates
if you make the independence and
uniformity assumptions from the last
slide when trying to estimate the
selectivity of this predicate right then
you're gonna end up with one over ten
because we have ten makes right so we I
mean it's an equality predicate so it's
Honda can occur once so it's one out of
ten and we multiply that by one over 100
because again we have a hundred
different models and Accord is one model
so it's 1 or 1 over 100 so in this case
here the the selectivity is estimated to
be 0.001 but in reality we know that
Honda is the only one that makes them
the recored so it's not you know it's
not this it's not 1 over 10 times 1 over
100 these columns are actually
correlated like if you have if you have
an accord then you have a Honda Accord
right so the true selectivity is 1 over
100 so again that that independence
assumption that from the last slide is
going to make us be an order of
magnitude off in our estimations and
then now if I start saying if I'm
automatically off at the selectivity of
some lower low operator and I feed that
now into another operator who's also
gonna be another order magnitude off
then then I'm really screwed all right
so the way to solve this problem and as
far as you know this only this this this
feature only exists in the commercial
systems is if you would have called
column group statistics or basically
telling the database system that these
columns are correlated and therefore it
should maintain statistics about them
and when it computes the the prek the
the selectivity during its cost model
estimates to treat them as being
correlated right and don't assume that
they're independent right so again
basically the way it works is like the
DB has to come in and tell it to do some
hey these two columns are correlated and
then if the system supports that then
they can they can update their cross
model appropriately
and again only db2 and Oracle do this I
don't think as far as I know my sequel
and Postgres don't do this and none of
the other major of the source system
systems do this now main thing why does
this why is this manual right why does
the DBA have to tell the dinner system
and I think that's why why can't we do
this automatically
cuz it's hard right like think about how
to figure this out in this example here
it's super easy right because it's I
only have you know 10 10 makes and 100
models but I have a billion tuples and I
have you know and they have a really
wide table with a thousand columns now I
got to go look for every single unit
combination of you know of different
columns look at all different possible
values that can occur right this thing
is gonna blow the search base is just
massive so this is why you can't do this
automatically now there may be ways to
approximate this automatically but again
as far as I know no no major system it
can do this automatically for you happen
tell it ahead of time we we can talk
offline about whether deep nets help
with this there people are looking into
this now but nothing is nothing is
nothing nothing exists yet all right so
let's look now about how these simple
examples can really foul us up right mo
we start thrown in joins into our query
plan so here we're doing it a simple 3
Way join on ABC where a ID equals B ID
ID go see ID and then b ID has a filter
where the ID is greater than 100 all
right so assume here we have a for
there's a there's a you know filter
predicate in v or operator in between
the B and then join right am for
simplicity reasons I'm just showing the
filter being done down here right so the
first thing we need to do is compute the
cardinality of the the access methods
that are that are retrieving tuples from
from the tables right for a and C
there's no filter so therefore the
cardinality of the operator that's
scanning a and C is just the number of
tuples that are in the table and that's
that's easy for me to compute I can get
that from the catalog for B it's going
to be the number
be multiplied by the selectivity of our
predicate here all right so now we're
gonna feed up the output of these scan
operators into our joint so now we need
to be able to compute the cardinality of
our joint operators so what's gonna
happen here is that if I if these guys
if this is if this thing is bad right
ANC is simple right because there's no
filter but if this thing's wrong then
now I'm feeding in the incorrect number
tuples into this joint operator and then
now I've got to figure out what the
selectivity of these two attributes are
assume I don't have a foreign key assume
that these guys aren't correlated like I
know nothing about them so I am now I
got to figure out for every single value
that exists in a for a day eight ID how
many values are going to match that in
be ID and I can try to figure this out
and in my hit my histograms but you know
back that's gonna be hard so then now I
take the output of this estimate and now
that's gonna be fed into this estimate
here took from this join this thing is
just reading the table so that's super
simple so now I had the same problem
that I had before now I gotta figure out
well what's the likelihood that a tuple
that matched a ID equals B ID here will
exist and get fed up into this thing and
then also be able to net match on see
that ID right so again I get that wrong
this gets wrong and then see this gets
me more wrong alright so this this is
what we're dealing this is like the the
math it just is not in your favor here
regardless of whether we're treating
these things of probabilities it's not
like these experts are always gonna get
wrong and and just it gets worse as we
go up so again this is you were to see
this in the joint on our benchmark in
the paper you guys read the more tables
you add the more bad guests right for
this reason here what is throwing errors
and pop of errors a puffing up another
query plan all right so the the paper I
had you guys read came from from the
hyper team in Germany
and it was an evaluation of how how
accurate are the the sort of the
cardinality estimates and operators for
a variety of different database systems
and then they wanted to use that to
figure out the just how bad things
actually can get how all four you are
from from that to the real time so the
paper doesn't not telling you how to
build a cost model I sort of roughly
sketched it out how to do this here but
it's just showing you what happens when
the caught and the s was in your cost
model go wrong and and then they sort of
proposed some some sort of design so
design principles of building David
system sort of what you should focus on
on trying to make the system more robust
to you know deviations or errors in your
cost models so in the paper they
proposed a new benchmark code the Jo B
that joint ordered a benchmark so in
this one they're actually it's actually
based on I think the IMDB data set so
the the movie website so and this is a
real data set so the the the tables are
actually gonna have skewed based on a
real-world distribution right and like
tpc agent TPCC
these are having uniform distribution
where everything you know the likelihood
of one attribute occurring is is the
same for all started like kind of one
value occurring for a given column it's
the same for all values in the joint
under benchmark is actually real you
know has real skew in it
so they're going to generate a bunch of
different queries that are going to join
more and more tables and then they want
to be able to measure what the cost
model thinks the selectivity is going to
be of over the cardinality of the good
operators and compare that with what
actually the real what the real data
actually looks like right so for this
the way they're gonna use this is that
they're they're gonna load the data in
you know in once and then they're gonna
run analyze which and that fires off the
background job to actually go scan all
the table and let the system compute
whatever statistics that I want to
compute that's the best-case scenario
there's no update so just I load the
data in and run analyze anything they
want to see in this best-case scenario
however
things get so once you have this one
graph here because this really this is
the most important one here and so the
way to understand this is that the
y-axis is the how far away you are from
the from from being exactly accurate in
the in the cardinality estimations so
this middle line here is when you're
perfectly accurate and then if you're if
you're above this then you're
overestimating estimating if you're
below this then you're under estimating
right and then the the what the x-axis
is the number of tables that they're
joining in the query here all right so
the first thing to point out is that
everyone the overall trend seems to be
that everyone is under estimating right
as you add more tables everyone sort of
starts to it starts to go down all right
Hey so again what is that from well that
that as we showed in that when we talked
about there's assumption so I can be
assumed that things are independent then
I assume my selectivity is gonna be way
way less than it actually is so that's
why they're again they're all under
estimating from what the actual value
should be so the first one to point out
is this this this one this one guy here
actually does reasonably well up to
about three or four tables right and
cross all of these they're actually the
they're the most they had the most
tightest balance from from the you know
being one person accurate versus all the
other ones the three systems here are
essentially how all had the same trends
okay but the the the the bounds are all
very right again as you add more tables
the the estimation gets worse and then
you you know it's six tables it just
it's really bad and then you have this
middle guy here who's just like way off
right away it's just okay with two
tables and then after that it's just
it's way it's under estimating way more
than everyone else
so I think in the paper they tell you
that that the the first one in the last
one or Postgres on hyper right and I
think I slowed it last time who is
the best one here right let me take a
guess what this one is Microsoft sequel
server okay then we think you guess what
these other two ones are which ones
Oracle this one here you Teddy titovs
this one I originate a fake Oracle's
this one radiative you think Oracle's
this one okay and then there's we need a
last lesson what took a db2 okay so you
think you think this is db2 this is
Oracle okay there you go so yes so there
are let's focus on sequel server so
sequel server does is Cascades
but again the cost model is independent
of whether or not you're doing Cascades
or or bottom-up right but they're doing
sampling they're doing histograms I and
it's just sequence it was just really
good in my opinion I considered to be
all of these three systems here I think
it's the at least what they talked about
publicly in my opinion is the most like
state-of-the-art leading-edge system
right workin db2 are good they're not
bad systems it's just I feel like sequel
server is they've based on what they've
talked about publicly it seems like this
thing is his way you know farther head
net and then everyone else getting
across so I would say for all database
systems open source and commercial
secrets of reply has the best query
optimizer so and it shows here but let's
now look into see a little more detail
about what actually happens when when
you when you get correct estimates so
for this one they're gonna instrument
Postgres 9.4 and the way to understand
this graph here is that the the the
x-axis is what percentage of the queries
that they're going to execute are within
the
how much slower are they from the the
actual execution of the query itself
right so if you is that how much I mean
sort of they instrumented Postgres and
they they made it so that rather than
doing using histogram to estimate the
cardinality of an operator they modified
the system so that it this you know
whatever function says go estimate what
the cardinality is they replace that
with a magic Oracle that always gives
them back exactly the correct answer
every time right so the way to read this
is it's how how far they are from the
what the real estimate is gonna do
versus what the if what the query
performance will be if you have the
exact eczema's versus what if you use
the built in cost model but that's
making approximations so if you're in
this band here 0.9 at one point one
means that you're the the performance of
the query using the approximations is
roughly the same of what you get when
you have approximate you know what if
you have the exact result and then over
here is like you're getting way you know
way way slower as you go in this
direction and then this is what
percentage of the queries in the total
number of queries that they gave into
the system fit into these different
buckets here right so this shows you
that when you're using estimations that
60% of the queries are 1.2 to 1.1 or 8
more times slower than the you know the
queries you have the true cardinality
exact estimations here right and so
what's going on is because Postgres is
under estimating this the cardinality of
its operators it thinks that the the you
know the number of tuples that it's
going to is going to pass one opportu
the next is is less as lower than it
actually is and they use these
cardinality estimates to size the hash
table for when you do a hash joint right
or decide whether you even want to do a
hash joint and all right if if you're
only going to access a small number
tuples and enjoying the if you're then a
nested loop joins is super fast
because you don't have to set up a hash
table you don't have to build it you
don't probe it you just do these two
little four loops on like four tuples
and the outer table an inner table
that's you know as fast as you're going
to ever get so Postgres ends up because
it's under estimating the cardinality of
his operators to sing o your app you're
operating one of ten tuples Nestle's up
joint right and then it starts running
and it says oh list is not this is
not ten do pools but by that point the
query plan is baked right you can't
switch back to do the hash join right
why not
because you see that one you'd have to
do adaptive query processing right so
you have to be able to say I my query
optimizer made a mistake go back and
rerun you know run the optimizer and get
a new plan based on something I you know
based on what data I've seen so far
Stadium next loop join hash join and get
the same as all right but like so you
could do it the way actually one way to
do this is that if I see now the as if I
see that I have like I thought it was
kinda like ten two people so now I have
1 billion tube was coming in before I
even start the nested loop joint I could
say don't do that slip joints which ever
do a hash join you could do that in some
ways it depends on how they're
pipelining tuples but they don't it's an
engineering thing right sort of like
it's like once the optimizers makes the
decision they go with it
now adaptive query processing or
optimization is when you say I think the
optimizer made a mistake go back and
regenerate a query plant and then now
yet you know now you have to you get
into this world of like do I throw away
all the data I process so far and start
up from scratch or can I come up with a
new query plan that can use some of the
data already process and just you know
continue with with that that would
essentially do what you're proposing but
as far as you know I mean I know
Postgres doesn't do that I don't know
actually what sequel server and oracle
do I think they throw everything away
and start over right you primarily you
primarily do that for it for for John
ordering
switching routine Nestle pet and hash
join there's no reason you could in
poker doesn't do it
I think we're engineer reasons okay so
the right so in this case here again
things are running slower because a lot
of quotes are end up being nestled up
joins when they really should be hash
hash joints
so the next thing they did was in
Postgres you can pass a flag to say
sorry yes yes but I don't know why we we
can a specter I don't know just noise oh
god okay so he said like the air for the
first drone operator fed into the the
first join overestimated the second join
that have fed into underestimated and
then that came out to be exactly exactly
correct now why this is running you know
zero point to be faster or I don't know
all right but it's I mean it's it's it's
a pretty low amount like it's you know
one or two percent all right
so all right what I'm saying I was
saying here is that again the the the
first sort of assessment of why things
are running floors because it's picking
measure Luke John when you can hash join
so in Postgres you can pass a flag in
your session and the Gilberts terminal
and you can say set no merged or
something like that or no nest luke join
you can tell the optimizer to not even
consider a nested loop join for your
query so in this case here to only
consider as a hash join but now you
still see that you're still getting
worst performance right then then you
know where you should be if you have two
cardinalities right it did help right
fewer queries are getting picked as a
nested loop joining but still your some
queries to start running slower in this
case it turns out that the in this
version of Postgres they were using the
Cardinal cardinality estimates from the
operators to decide how to allocate the
hash table when you do the hash join
right so you say you know I'm gonna do
100 I have my card in alleys 100 so make
sure I have a hash table that has you
know 200 slots for you know to put
things in and so if you undersized the
hash table what happens is that as we
talked about you end up with these
really long you know I think they were
doing a bucket hash hash table so you
have these really long bucket chains
that essentially becomes a sequential
scan every single time you do a probe
right so and if you had correct
estimates about what the cardinality was
then you could say all right well my
hash table need to be this big because
my data sets coming in is gonna be this
big and then you don't worry about you
know these these long special scans so
to prove that this was actually the case
again this is a post missed nine point
four then in Postgres 9.5 they had the
ability to do dynamically resize the
hash table if your estimates go wrong so
they back ported that feature for post
post 9 by 5 into 9 point 4 and they
reran this the same experiment and that
now you see that there's more queries
that are actually mattered or getting
closer where you should be if you have
the true cardinality right so the this
is a good example of showing it's not
just picking whether one operator is
should be a hash joint versus a net
that's looped on it's actually what
you're actually doing in that operator
can be greatly affected by the the
estimations that your cost models making
all right all right so Victor then say
you know were talking about this and he
sent me sort of a synopsis of what he
thought were the most important things
that came out of this experiment or this
study that he did and the the first is
that they felt that having an accurate
you know cost model from your query
optimizer and of actually being in some
cases more important than is having like
the fastest engine in the world
right like if you you know it who cares
that we knew Cindy processing or query
compilation and all the other tricks
that we talked about the entire semester
if our optimizer is total and we're
like picking the worst doing orders and
we're always doing this a loop join then
who cares how fast the engine is in like
you know simple examples when we
actually throw real real-world data at
it then we're just gonna get you know
we're gonna get crushed so the the in
being able to pick up the joinery is ply
the most important thing from all of us
the other thing they found was basically
that the cardinality estimates are
always gonna be wrong
so when you actually implement the
operators in your system you want to
have them be adaptive enough to not
adapt it so they don't they rely on
estimations coming from from the query
optimizer because you just assume that's
gonna be wrong and as the data comes in
you want to be able to adapt to whatever
it is your system is doing to account
for the actual data that it's actually
seen right so being but a resize the
hash table automatically rather than
just you know taking where the cost
model gives you and just fixing the size
to be exactly that and we're doing this
now in our own system we haven't pushed
it to the master branch ad this is in
the separate LLVM branch but we can
reorder like predicates so some
predicates and more selective than
others the cost model might think that
you want to execute your predicate in
this order we can then shuffle things on
the fly as we see real data the other
things that he said that and you sort of
see this in the design about in hyper is
that having an engine that is can do
faster quencher scans and fast hash
joins may actually end up being better
than having all these sort of fancy
indexes to do joins and and and and
lookups right because the more indexes
you have and the more complex the
estimations have to be for your in your
cost model so rather than try to account
for any of this you just say screw it
honest I'm gonna sequential scan
everything and just rip through the data
really fast and and and who cares what
you know whether an index would help me
here
for analytical queries I maybe agree
with this for some things maybe not not
enough for others right I had mixed
feelings about this one last one he says
that trying to have a more accurate cost
model like using the micro benchmarks
the stuff that I talked at the very
beginning like trying to you know
profile the hardware and include that in
your estimations they felt that was a
waste of time just having better
cardinality estimations is the most
important thing that means having better
statistics better sketches whether
you're throwing deep nets in there or
not we could talk about that separately
but getting this right is more important
than having some more fine-grained
accuracy and what the harbor's actually
can do okay so I thought these are
pretty useful right again like some of
these we've adopted in the design of our
system other ones not so much alright so
the last thing I want to talk about and
this will lead us into what we'll talk
about a Monday is this project from from
IBM from I guess this point 2000 2001 so
18 years ago for this thing called Leo
so you may be thinking and sort of what
he was sort of suggesting earlier is
that if my cost model is gonna make
these estimates and they're gonna be
wrong
then as I run my query and I see oh the
data is actually completely different
can't I just fix myself or can't I just
possibly also go fix the estimates right
and this is what IBM was trying to do
with this thing called the learning
optimizer so the idea would be that my
query shows up I run it through my core
my query optimizer I generate the cost
amount of generates estimates about what
I think's the data looks like I then run
that query and then now I observe are
the estimations about the cardinality in
the selectivity of my predicate is that
matching what I'm actually seeing in the
real data and then when the query
finishes they they check to see whether
the estimations differ from the from the
real data and if they differ then they
try to feed back the real data back into
the optimizer so that when the next
query shows up they can rely on the data
they've already collected from the
previous query all right so this seems
this would solved this problem right
it's like like oh we're some it's wrong
we run real data see what actually
happens the I would say that every db2
administrator that I've ever talked to
and I asked him about this that they
always say the first thing they do when
they install db2 is they turn all the
ball cuz it never worked and we had
Oracle has something similar to do
memory management like automatic memory
management for the buffer pool manager
and we talked to some DBAs a few few
weeks ago and it like yeah we turn that
off immediately like all this automated
stuff not right I so I mean I never ever
found out why why I've heard there was
some engineering difficulties at IBM to
get this thing to actually to work the
way they wanted to work and fit into the
rest of the system correctly I think
this didn't work because of engineering
reasons and it's a shame because it
seems like this would would solve our
problems but because of this I think a
lot of people a lot of these a lot of
commercial systems have been hesitant to
adopt similar techniques just because
this thing's sort of you know fell apart
but but this event lead us into what
we're going to talk about on Monday of
like the sort of revival or not a
revival but a continuation of a long
history of trying to do automated tuning
in in in database systems to sort of
leave e8 some of these difficulties
right so now you know what's in vogue is
machine learning and the people trying
to apply machine learning to these
problems but actually goes back into
like the 1970s like people people have
been working on this problem for a long
time so so this is just sort of one
example it does that didn't work okay so
the main takeaway today is that for a
memory database being able to estimate
the number of tools we're gonna process
per operator is gonna be the for us a
reasonable approximation of what the
cost of a core is going to be of course
now that means that in order to to
estimate the number to was gonna process
per operator you got to know what the
card in the cardinality is of your
children operators and then as we show
things can go bad
quickly and so I think the way Microsoft
does the cost estimation is using
combination of sampling of sketches is
the right way to do this and we tried
doing this in our own database system
but we never vetted it to determine
whether it was actually accurate and
what will happen is in the summer when
we bring over the the old optimizer from
peloton into the new system we're
probably not gonna bring over the cost
model we will start with a simple cost
model that basically says if I haven't
indexed my cost is zero if I have a
sequential scan that cost us one that's
the simplest cost model you could ever
have that won't handle drawing ordering
for us but at least that'll get us
started on being with a pic indexes okay
what is this I won't be to say you take
a seat pray