[Music]
[Applause]
so today there is actually one of my
favorite lectures we're talk about Davis
compression again the high-level idea
here is we're just gonna be able to
squeeze down the size of our data in our
database and you know save memory save
storage but in some cases actually we're
also gonna be able to execute queries
faster because of the way we're going to
compress things we can we can be aware
of how things are laid out and do things
more efficiently quickly Before we jump
into that just reminder that there's a
tech talk today at 4:30 over in here in
Neil Simon from Oracle the one of the
guys that works on the in-memory
database team so he answered in that
come check it out the other thing I want
talk about too is last class we were
looking at mem sequel and we had this
bit type and we were like oh how can a
bit type be a bytes and I I read the
documentation for in the sequel standard
and and in other systems it's actually a
bit string not a single bit so you can
specify like how many bits you want but
I emailed the mem sequel guy last night
said this documentation is kind of
confusing because like you can set an
arbitrary size for this but it's unclear
like why is it 8 bytes right like if I
set it to be bit one it's just drove one
bit and I really gonna store that to be
8 bytes he said they're trying to it's
some kind of compatibility of my sequel
they're trying to follow and then
actually in their new column store
system that they call single store they
can actually compress compress this
bitmap I don't know exactly how they do
that but we'll see how to do bitmap
compression in this clip in this lecture
earlier just again just to show you what
this looks like so this is actually
Postgres so I can declare a table that
has a bit type right and you can specify
the number of bits you want and then
this one here you can specify that it's
it's a verbal number of bits so - I
don't like this little varying thing
this is from the post documentation so
you guys replace this
with with barb it like that right and
then now if I certain to the table I can
specify that I want a bit string like
this right and go ahead and store that
and then when I do a select I get back
Fitch drinks and in the case of Postgres
that there's two bar bit and regular bit
is if I try to now insert something that
in the first one because I'm saying
there has to be three bits if I try and
search something that's just two bits
[Music]
like that right it'll throw an error
good because it says the bit string has
to be three is that it - why do we need
what why would you ever do want to need
a bitmap to store natively in your
database with a bitmap as so statements
do you know as a bar chart that would be
wasteful so what they really do is these
case of Postgres I don't know exactly
what them seagulls doing like Postgres
will say all right you're saying this
thing has can be two bits I can store
that as a single byte because I just
wrote eight bits
yeah yes it seemed to Mac size that I
can store is five so I try to do this
right it won't store it
well actually didn't like the first one
but like if I go make this one one right
it's too big for for the bar bit one but
the point I'm trying to make is like for
the bar bit one I can store this be one
bit and it'll let me do that because
this story that the regular pit and the
bar bit one
it'll store in the case of this they'll
store the size plus the bit the
screen itself yeah okay you don't here
look a bit strings in the post grassman
that's not the point of this lecture I
just wanted to clarify because we I
didn't know the answer last time okay
alright so we're gonna talk about today
is compression schemes so we'll force
provide some background a sort of
obvious but why ever you want to do
compression actually it's more obvious
maybe in a disk based system but we'll
see why we still want to do it in memory
system then we'll talk about how to do a
basic naive compression scheme where the
database system doesn't know anything
about how they did is actually being
compressed then we'll look at the more
sophisticated techniques of doing
columnar columnar storage compression
where the database system itself it was
responsible for running the compression
album and then it knows that had a
natively stored this compress data and
they can operate queries on top of them
and then we have time at the end we'll
finish up talking about some research
we've done here on compressing
old items okay okay so we didn't talk
about compression in the disk that the
in the intro class when we talk about
disk or any databases but it's sort of
obvious that if you're assume your
databases on disk and you're fetching a
lot of pages from disk to a process
queries then compression is gonna be a
no brainer in that environment because
the disk i/o so expensive so paying some
additional CPU overhead to compress the
data when it comes into memory is is
going to be a good trade-off for us
right because the disk isn't getting
that much faster and something that you
but we have more cores we can Xu there's
more computational power available to us
than there possibly is for us to get the
data in off a disk but now for a memory
database this trade-off isn't so obvious
right because now everything is in
memory that I'm not paying that big big
IO penalty and I'll also allow to do
byte level access to to jump to you know
different offsets and my comms or my
data and access single actually is very
efficiently whereas in a disk based
system I'm bringing in four kilobyte
pages at a time so the scope of what I
can compress is is slightly different so
for it
database we're gonna have make this
trade-off between speed and compression
ratio and to the best my knowledge in
most cases from mme databases that are
going to support compress data they're
gonna choose speed over compression
ratio that means that there's gonna be
some compression algorithms that are
gonna get an amazing compression ratio
you can take the original data and
compress it down to a much much smaller
size but it's very computationally
expensive so they're not going to do
that they're gonna instead choose a
compression scheme oppression protocol
that maybe isn't as as doesn't produce
as good of a compression ratio but it
can run fast yeah
quickly and then there's also be the
straight awful by the way you want to
compress very quickly or decompress very
quickly and in most cases we're gonna
care about decompressing quickly so I'll
because that's one new most of the time
so why we want to do this right well
DRAM is not cheap I have to pay for to
buy that hardware and actually pay to
keep refreshing it to keep the charge in
that cost energy so if I can store my
database on a smaller machine with less
memory then that's gonna be a good win
for us and in some cases when we when we
compress the data we're actually gonna
get better performance as well because
now things be able to fit me CPU caches
or for that for a for a looking at a
smaller portion of data we can still
compute the same result for query so
this is gonna be a win-win almost all
around so to understand why we can
compress the data we're gonna start to
understand a little bit what what real
databases actually looked like and so
the first thing is that the real data
sets are going to be very skewed right
that means that like the the
distribution of values for a given
column are not going to be uniform right
to using zip codes as an example there's
more people that live in New York City
then live in Montana so when I look at
if I have a list of all you know people
and I'm storing their zip codes there's
many more people living in New York than
in Montana and I could take advantage of
that in my compression compression
protocol another good example is there's
also the brown corpus and this exhibits
this property called the zipping
distribution so the brown corpus was
this project in the 1960s at Brown
University where they basically took the
what they considered to be the
the the most emblematic books in the
English language and they just counted
the number of words that were in these
books and we suggest let's take a guess
what the most common word was duh yes
right th e but then what happen is the
next Muskaan word was the word a and the
the word a or so word the appears twice
as many times as the word a and a
appears twice as many times as the third
word and so forth so you have this sort
of power law curve so a lot of real
workloads are gonna look like that and
these are the kind of things we can take
advantage of oh you think you like
reddit or hacker news there's a small
number of articles that actually get a
lot of comments most people submit crap
and no one ever sees it right and so if
we know this then there's a bunch of
things you know the long tail stuff we
can then maybe compress in a different
way or get a good compression ratio the
other thing also too in our data sets is
that they're gonna be highly correlated
so that means that the values of
different attributes in the same tuple
or often times gonna be correlated or
related to each other alright so like my
zip code for my address that can be
correlated to my to my city so I know my
city name and state I know its zip code
I'm in or if I buy something on Amazon
oftentimes the the date that something
was shipped or started the date that
somebody placed the order is only gonna
be a few days it's only a few days later
would actually be shipped so I buy
something today
the Amazons ship and out the same
day like I buy something today it's
gonna be shipped tomorrow so maybe
instead of storing a full 64-bit date
and time stamp for the order date and
ship date if I just store this and I can
now maybe store the Delta which is like
you know a couple hours off of this then
I can say space there so these are a lot
of these techniques about these aspects
of real datasets is why we're gonna be
able to get a good compression ratio and
employ these techniques without slowing
down the system entirely so what do we
want in our compression scheme well for
most is that we need these compression
schemes to produce fixed length values
because again remember we had this fixed
length data pool and that's the sort of
the the the you know the the the the
main primary location of a tuple
so in order for me to jump down to
different offsets within that fixed
thing a fixed-length datapool all my
values need to be fixed length so if I
start compressing strings that you know
from two random sizes that's not going
to work for us so everything has to be
fixed length datable the other exception
would be when we shove things out the
bar length datapool since that were
recording the size of the data in the
very lengthy de poule it's okay for that
to be variable sized but the most of the
data need to be fixed length the other
thing we want to be able do is postpone
the the had the gauge of some weight as
long as possible before it actually has
to decompress the data in the lifetime
of the lifecycle of a query so what I
mean by that is if I have a bunch of
compressed datum I want to try to do my
query X you might as much as my query I
can all in that compressed data and only
until I have to then produce a result to
a human or to the outside world of the
database ISM then I go ahead and
decompress it all right that's gonna be
a big deal this is called late
materialization and this is why we're
gonna want to do native compression
inside of our database system instead of
using a look at general-purpose Alvin
what we do doesn't know anything about
what's actually being stored and the
last one is sort of obvious as well but
we should just sort of bring it up
because there's different types of
compression algorithms and we make sure
that we only pick ones that we actually
want to use so any compression scheme
you want to use has to be lossless what
does that mean what's that
yeah you don't well yes you don't lose
data but like if I take some original
data and I compress it and then I
decompress it I should be able to get
back that original data
what's saving is a ball of a lossy
compression compression algorithm and b3
exactly yes
so in our database and we have to be
almost always be lossless because people
don't like it when you lose data but
again if it's your bank account you put
$100 in and they come back to say no you
have you have 80 dollars you're gonna be
pissed so any compression scheme can't
that we want to use can't do this if we
do want to do a lossy compression scheme
then that must be done at the
application level meaning some human has
to make a value judgment that it's okay
to lose data in our database the
database system we're not gonna figure
that on Onis own
because the best compression scheme is
to write everything that dev know and
lose everything right it's gonna have an
amazing compression ratio it's gonna be
really fast but of course you don't have
any data so in that sort of an extreme
example but that's the basic idea the
data stem doesn't know what you actually
care about so it's not gonna do anything
that's lossing the we're not going to
talk about this but there's there are
techniques call it approximate queries
that sort of look like lossy compression
so if I have like a column of people
visiting my website and I want to count
the number of people that visited the
website in the last month I can you know
look at every single tuple and can add
that all that up and count it or maybe I
could sample it or maybe just you know
skip some portion of it and then try to
approximate that count and the idea
there is like you know who cares if I
had a you know I had a million users to
my website but then my approximate count
comes back with you know 980 thousand or
some like that like it's close enough
and so again we're not gonna like this
but these are called approximate queries
this is actually now being showing up in
in the commercial systems they'll
support this today like the habit
explicit like approximate count
operation or aggregate aggregation
function in Oracle and sequel server and
I think TB 2 might have this so we're
not gonna talk about that but like ok
this is the next slide
sorry this is I mean so this technique
actually does exist and then a sequel
server I think just added this within
the last year again the idea is you're
just sampling on the data and produce
counts pretty segregations a another
type of technique is to do zone maps and
so I would categorize both these guys as
in data skipping meaning like we're
trying to avoid having a look at a bunch
of data the compression scheme we're
gonna talk about today we stopped to
look at everything but the things we're
looking at is compressed these are
techniques to say like well I can miss
ignore large chunks of things so zone
maps I think we covered in the
introduction class it's not really a
compression scheme it's just a technique
for in for skipping data the idea is
that you pre compute some some
aggregations on columns and then when
you start executing queries you can look
at those those pre computed aggregations
and decide whether there's anything you
even want to look at and give
Wacka datum so they're called zone maps
by Oracle I'm sure that they have
patents on this sometimes they call
pre-computer aggregations but in general
in databases if you say zone maps even
if you're not talking on the Oracle
system people know what you're talking
on did you talk about this thing so
let's say I have a column here it has
five values and so I can compute of zone
map where I'm going to have all the
aggregation functions I may want to run
compute it for this column so the main
max average sum and count and then now
if a query shows up like select star
from table where values greater than 600
instead of scanning through the column
assuming this is a block of data said of
having to scan through this and find all
the records that where values greater
than 600 I can use instead look at my
max value for my for the zone map and
see it the VAX value for this block is
400 so therefore I know there could not
be any tuple in here that is going to be
600 or greater so I don't even bother
looking at this I just look at the zone
map see that thing doesn't satisfy my
predicate and I can ignore this so yes
so this question is if you're running a
BTC when would you update zone map so
you so for this and the compression
stuff what about today you typically
only do this on cold data that's not
being modified all the time so you would
leave it uncompressed don't compute a
zone map and only when you recognize it
know when we've come and updated this
block in a while let me go ahead and
compute these things all right like I
said this only appears in the more
high-end commercial systems going back
here Oracle has this Vertica mem sequel
mateesah was a fpga accelerate database
that IBM paulette they killed at they
killed that off last year but I think
zoom Maps originally originated from
these guys and then everyone else
adopted the same idea but only Oracle
calls them zone maps cuz because that
that's the Oracle term and everyone else
causing pre-computer aggregations or
something or okay all right
it'll is that okay let's focus on the
compression stuff that that's that's the
main thing we won't talk about today so
if you want to add compression to our
database system
the first question we have to think
about and in sense weird ones actually
building the system is what are we
trying to compress and based on that
decision that'll tell us what kind of
compression scheme we could possibly do
so the first approach is just do it on a
block right it could be a block of
columns or it could be a row store it
doesn't matter but it's a block of two
floats within the same table you could
even do even more fine-grain than that
you could do another tuple level so
within a single tuple you compress all
the values even more fine-grain is you
have a single attribute within one tuple
and you want to compress that all right
that sounds crazy but if you have a
large text field that that might make
sense like Wikipedia has those all those
articles are all every revision of a
Wikipedia article is its own accurate
value in a tuple and you want to
compress that or we can compress it on
on the entire column so we take all the
values for a single attribute across
multiple tuples and then the table and
we'll go ahead and compress this and
this primarily we only want to do this
if it's a column story so most systems
most of the OLAP systems are going to do
this and any other system that does do
compression may be like a naive
compression look at my Segal we'll see
in a few more slides they'll do this
there are some systems that can support
this like sequel server can do this
there's a variant of rocks DVD called
Terra at a China and they can do this
this appears for only variable length
fields if I have a large blob large text
field then I can compress this but again
the compression scheme you're gonna want
to use for all of these are gonna be
much different but for this I could do
naive compression like gzip or snappy
but for this one we'll use the
dictionary coding or the other
techniques okay all right so let's let's
first focus on naive compression because
this is like if you're coming from you
know if you if you know something
roughly about compression and I'm when
I'm saying oh we're gonna compress data
this might be the first thing you think
of so the idea here with naive
compression is that we're gonna take an
off-the-shelf general-purpose
compression algorithm that our people
using already and other things in our
databases and we're just going to take
our sequence of bytes from whatever data
we're trying to compress whether it's a
tuple whether this thing will add should
be
with its column or block and we're gonna
run run it through these algorithms and
they're gonna produce a but hopefully a
block of data that's smaller than what I
gave it so the sort of the the kana
algorithm is people gonna want to use
I said gzip but that's usually not what
you want to use because gzip is an
example of a heavyweight compression
algorithm where it's gonna get a better
compression compression ratio than these
other ones but it's gonna do much more
slowly with like L 0 or LZ 4 these are
some of the first protocols people have
developed where they are you don't get
it's good a compression ratio but
they're much faster
snappy is from Google that's another one
that's very common in database systems
broadly is from Facebook this is not
typically using databases because this
is designed for like compressing
webpages or there's some there's some
magic in here that you know if you have
a much HTML tags and you see over and
over again they can make it in
compression them better Oracle has this
thing called a zip that's their own
patented proprietary compression
algorithm it's you know it's it's a
variant of these like LZ for dictionary
based compression schemes but what's
fascinating about it Oracle bought Sun
some was making the spark chips so for a
while I don't think I think they
discontinued spark I forget but for a
while they were actually storing the the
a zip decompression and compression
algorithm on hardware right so you can
actually do this as accelerated on if
you but if you bought spark chips and
ran Oracle on it Z standard is
considered to be the sort of the
state-of-the-art one today that gives
you the the same speed as snappy but a
better better compression ratio so a lot
of times you'll see snappy but newer
systems are starting to adopt Z standard
so again we've already talked about this
there's computational overhead of
compressing the data and decompressing
it and so we need be mindful of this and
what we're always going to try to pick
something back is faster than D kress
even though if it's syllabus Florida to
compress because most of the time I'm
just gonna do decompression so let's see
how my secret does this so this is my
sequel in a DB so in what you can do and
my sequel when you cook when you call
create table you can pass in a flag and
say I want to store this as I want to
store this as a compress compress blocks
and so what's gonna happen on
again my sequels not not an in-memory
system so this is a disk system but I
just show you that the implications of
this and it's the clears explanation I
found how did you naive compression so
what they're gonna have on disk is
they're gonna have these compressed
blocks that are gonna be of four
different sizes all powers are two one
two four eight kilobytes and the idea
here is when you have the uncompressed
block and then you compress it whatever
is the ceiling of the size up to the
next boundary that's you Pat it out to
so if I have a block that's one point
five kilobytes I'll Pat it out so it's
two kilobytes and they do this or that
they can pack things in and align them
nicely out on disk so you're gonna have
the compressed page but then you're also
going to have this uncompressed mod log
that sits in front of it think of this
is like a delta store that represents
the changes that I made to tuples that
are represented in this in this block so
now if I have a query comes along and
wants to access some data then I bring
it to my buffer pool and I keep it
uncompressed and if the query is an
update then all that need to do is just
modify what's in the mod log so I can
sort of Penda entry say I made a change
to something down here to here the data
that I know you have like so you have to
have an index up above and say oh I'm
here's the page that has the tuple
you're looking for so let's say like I
do a set value you know update to both
set value equal ABC then they don't need
to look to see what the original value
was I just need to put my mod log and
say the new value for this attribute is
now ABC so if anybody comes along tries
to read that you check the mod log just
like you did in the in the BW tree when
you pick me went to the virgin chain and
you say oh this is the latest value for
this particular tuple that's that's what
I'm looking for but if the thing you
want is not in the mod log then you got
a decompressive and so what they
actually do is when they decompress it
they both keep the the compressed
version and the decompressed version in
memory and then decompressed version is
always gonna be 16 kilobytes all right
because they do this to align things
again and in the buffer pool so they'll
have us you know I've region 4 16
kilobyte pages and then for all the
different compressed page sizes they
have a certain separate region for that
so then now if I make any changes and I
want to write them back
if I modify this page then I'd have to
replace this thing before I read it out
otherwise if I don't modify it then I
could blow this thing away and then if
this thing's I modified I can blow that
away as to it were free from the payment
from the buffer pool so make yes these
questions can be add things to the mob
log beyond this like so this is a fixed
size I'm about to fix size so you run
out of space in here then you have to
decompress it and and come you know
compactor code I apply all the changes
yeah it's like it's like the Delta store
part for the bead every tree we have is
a fix number of yeah okay so the main
thing I want to point out about this is
that as I said if I need to access
something that's in the compressed data
I have to decompress it because again
assume I ran this through snappy or gzip
or whatever you want to whatever album
you want to use the database doesn't
know anything of what's inside those
bytes of the page right underneath the
covers these algorithms are actually off
oftentimes using dictionary compression
but you don't you can't see that in the
database system unless you know how to
interpret the the compressed format of
those different algorithms but I don't
think any system actually does that so
this now means that this is gonna limit
the scope of what we can actually
compress because if I try to compress an
entire column and I need to get one
tuple at the in that column now I got to
decompress the entire thing right so the
main takeaway from this is that because
we're using an IE compression scheme
with it is it doesn't know what's going
on we're losing all high-level
understanding of what's in the what's in
the thing we're compressing and what are
the semantics of that data so we can't
do any any we can't really do anything
other than just decompress it every
single time so this is now where we're
gonna talk about these these better
compression schemes where again the data
system is natively gonna do this because
it's gonna know how things got
compressed what it compressed and then
in some cases when it sees queries it
can maybe just compress the things that
the queries are looking like look
they're trying to look up on
actually the predicate of the queries
and do your matching on that and you
never have to decompress the original to
pour the original data so so they say
this is my table of users and I have
their salary and I have just two tuples
Andy and Matt and we have our fake
salaries so if I compress it I'm not
saying how I'm compressing this assume I
could and for every single value in my
table I may have a compress it with
something that's smaller than what the
original size was and so now if I want
to say find all the users were named
equals Andy you know don't assume I have
it an index assume I'm gonna do a
central scan well in order for me to do
that match I'd have to decompress this
but instead what if I actually just
encoded the thing I was looking up one
the same compression algorithm and now I
do my match directly on compress data
all right that's that's why we do we
want the data system to do all the
compression stuff ourselves we don't
want to rely on external algorithm now
for range predicates this is gonna be
more tricky right find all users where
names greater than Andy this is you know
depending how we compress this it may
not work but we'll see how to handle
that in dictionary encoder okay all
right so we're to talk about seven
different question schemes today and
again this is all gonna be for columnar
compression in ole ETP systems you
typically do not compress the data when
it's in memory because as I said it's
gonna be too expensive to to decompress
and recompress over never again as I
start making changes so this is only for
cold data that's not to be modified and
we can we already know we can store it
as a column store so we're sort of a
null suppression run decoding and bitmap
coding does encoding and all these other
ones are again there leading up this
with the paper you guys read but these
are much of other things I think are
interesting to know about but dictionary
encoding is going to be the most common
one but it's not always gonna be the
best one there are there's be some
special cases where these other ones can
do much better okay all right so the
first one the easiest one is called null
suppression and this is a variant of run
run like for coding the basic idea is
that if we have a table that is has
attributes or columns that are sparsely
populated meaning most
the values are null then instead of
storing the null repeatedly over and
over again for every single instance of
a tuple we can then instead maybe just
record somewhere that says hey I have
this many Noel's at this location and
then I only record the exact non null
values in in the table or in the column
now how we actually can do that can vary
one example would be this oral-b BBC
self we'll see in a few more slides but
like I said this is just like this is
pretty common when you know things are
gonna be if you know you have a lot of
sparse data a lot of times the JSON
databases can do this kind of things
because if they organize it as a column
store because most of the time you don't
want maybe have all the attributes that
that other documents have but those are
get run that occurred run link decoding
again is the is sort of be the higher
higher level idea that nil suppression
is and the null suppression is a sort of
optimized version for nulls so the idea
here is that with run like decoding as I
said our values and our columns are
gonna be oftentimes skewed so we have
this a bunch of repeated values over and
over again so if we know that we have
runs of values in our columns that are
all the same then it's again instead of
storing that unique value over and over
again for every single tuple I can
instead store a triplet that says hey
here's this value I met this all set in
the column and here's number of times
that has been repeated and then once you
how I'll have a different value that's
different than what's in that run then
you have another triplet that records
that information right so we'll see this
in the next slide but we talked about
store sorting columns column stores last
last time with Vertica the rumble
encoding the benefit or the compression
ratio you can get with running encoding
is gonna be amazing if you're able to
pre sort your columns in such a way that
you have these long runs of repeated
values so let's see it a really simple
example so we have a table here of
people with their IDs and their sex and
so we want to do run length encoding for
the sex column because assuming that
there's only two two sexes male female
there's only two values we could ever
have so we're gonna we know we're having
much of these repeats over and over
again
so if you wanted to run length encoding
now we can store this as a bunch of
triplets where for each triplet would
have what the original value was what
are all set is in the column and then
how many values got repeated right so in
this case here the you know for the
first one I have three M's one two three
and so in this triplet I have M starting
at position zero three times so now if I
want to do a lookup and say alright well
what is the sex of the the tuple at
offset three then I would scan through
this and say all right with a boundary
of what I'm looking for it can be found
in this this triplet and therefore I
know what the value is you know other
obvious optimizations too and now if
you're doing like a group by count
instead of again having to look at every
single value in the entire column I
Ignace rip through and just look at the
count and the and and and the value and
populate my my hash table between my
aggregate very efficiently that way so
what's one problem though with this
example well one problem this example
here is that it's actually not we're
actually not getting a good compression
ratio right for this small example but
you'd imagine it if the table is you
know billions of millions of people then
this could be problematic because we
have like alternating patterns of
male-female over and over again right
and so to store one tuple in one
instance of this of this value here
female I have to store a full triplet
right because the run is only the run
length is one so what I've quoted stored
as maybe just eight bits over here now
I'm storing as assuming this is like you
know 64 bits for each one that's a bit
small but you know and it takes me more
space to store the triplet than I did
the original value so but if I sort it
now and now I have all the males first
followed by all the females now when I
do run length encoding and I'm getting
I'm getting an amazing depression ratio
because I just have one triplet and say
here's all the males with the length of
six here's all the females of the length
of two and again now you imagine in a
large column with a million people this
thing if I do it this way it's gonna be
amazing
yes
normally when it's uncompressed like you
got like a one-to-one mapping like oh
yeah
this question is when it's uncompressed
if I'm if I met like this offset here at
6 and I want to know what what is what
is the sex of this person I know how to
jump to this offset and just see it but
in this world I if I'm here I gotta then
go scam from the beginning to figure out
where I belong I were at what offset my
boundary can be founded correct so one
is think of this like I'm doing I'm
doing I'm encoding per block so it's not
like I'm scanning the entire tuple right
and the other thing is like for OLAP
queries know you really don't care what
is the value for this single tuple I
don't care what a nice X is I care to
know what is the distribution of sexes
across the entire university or the
class or something like that yeah so
you're doing full scans and that in that
world it's fast
I said overall makes up for it mean for
the workload we're trying to target like
the analytical operations this this
would be a big win for OLTP when I'm
saying go get this one record this is
gonna be this this could be back yes
this question is are our compression
schemes using HTF systems yeah so this
is like if you do the fraction mirror
push we told it last time like Olga does
this they had the the column stores
compressed because you're almost never
updating that and then you have the the
roast or the uncompressed right so in a
chat systems you can do this in our
system what we do is we have a slightly
different layout of the blocks when it's
the data is cold so we actually do
dictionary compression for the blocks
when it's not being modified
change button values the world if you
think you have to change the ATM one
fraction mirrors yeah so member from not
everyone was in intro class but they
they talked about this last clip today
money talk about it today they talk
about how like me a little put a little
marker in on the fraction mirror side
and the column sort of says this thing
got modified don't go look here for this
exact value go look in a row store yes
if they handle that in peloton
everything was all sort of an in in in
the current system everything was always
a a single storage base and it's just
that the the layout of the data may
change this was felt on the layout video
may change if it was a roast or column
store if it was hot or cold and we were
doing a pen only MPC C so if you modify
something in the column store then that
version chain would then get updated to
now point to the row store in our in our
current system that secession we do the
same thing to right we have a block of
data that's compressed it can't be
modified it's a beautiful so if you
modify a tuple we instead of appending
the virgin chain exactly where that is
and now gets moved over some results we
treated like a delete followed by an
insert okay so the cool thing about our
run length encoding or le I think I also
did Vertigo's probably the most of all
the columns for systems that out there
they're the most one of the biggest
heavy users or proponents on this
approach most other systems we're going
to do a dictionary encoding but the cool
thing about RLE is that we actually can
apply this in conjunction with other
compression schemes and we get this like
nice multiplicative effect we're like we
can then compress the compress data
which is kind of cool
so with bitmap and coding the idea is
that it's a bit so we're not we're gonna
show how to do orally on bitmaps in a
second but like this is another pressure
scheme you could do where then you can
also apply r-la but you can also apply
orally for delta encoding so with bitmap
decoding the idea is that it's a
different way of organizing the datum
where instead of storing for every
single for a column you're storing the
individual in attributes you're instead
gonna have a separate bitmap for every
single unique value that a column could
have and then that
way if I want to see this there's this
attribute this offset had this value I
look in the corresponding bitmap and I
check to see whether it's it's 0 or 1 at
that position right so this is only
gonna work if the value cardinality is
low for the thing I'm trying to compress
so if I have a small number of possible
attribute I could be because I need to
have a bitmap for every single one then
this could be a big win but if I have a
lot of different possible batteries or
every single value is unique then this
is gonna be a terrible idea because I'm
gonna negative compression because my my
compressed data is gonna be larger than
the uncompressed data which is which is
obviously bad so as I say before it
we're gonna break things of the Davis up
to blocks or chunks so that we don't
that allocate these super large bit
bitmaps right we're have a bitmaps per
block so going back to our example here
we want a bitmap compress the the
sex-filled so again we only have two
values male or female
so in our compressed version we would
have a bitmap for the male a value and a
pit map for the female value and again
if I want to know what the value is at
this offset I just look in the in the
bitmap the bitmaps at this offset and I
check to see whether 0 1 right so this
starts to be a big win so in my little
toy example here I have 9 values
assuming I can store the the male female
as as a single byte or 8 bits so this is
gonna be 72 bits but for this one here
in the compressed version I have two
bitmaps
so that's each one bit piece one bit per
value that I have has 9 times 2 so
that's me 18 bits then I need to store
the original values but I only store
them once all right so that's gonna be 2
times 8 bits so 16 bytes plus 18 bytes
is what is 34 bytes so I can store my
original date with 72 bits I can get it
down to 34 bits again now extrapolate
across millions of users
this has to be a big deal yes your
question is why not store oh I think
what you're saying is this is the binary
male female so instead of storing
separate pitmaster 1 like yes oh his
David is if you have with with vectorize
instructions instead of storing this as
a separate bitmap for each of them
couldn't I just or a essentially doing
dictionary encoding storing a taking a
potentially larger size value and
compressing it down to a smaller
encoding store those contiguously and
then run sim D on that that's ridiculous
all right this is an alternative yeah
the other cool thing you actually can do
I don't think you could do this in the
dictionary codings that what you said
but one thing you can do is like we
already know that in the query optimizer
we're going to we're going to evaluate
the predicate s' than in our where
clause so that we try the more selective
ones first and we start throwing out
data as quickly as possible but this is
actually little bit different now to we
can actually order the the the the way
in which we check the bitmap so we know
one bitmap is super selective within a
single attribute we can actually check
that one at first that brings a hug a
whole nother level of optimization which
is totally different than we talked
about for I don't think we'll talk about
other bitmap encoding schemes but this
is there's other techniques you can do
that are really kind of cool if you
start encoding your values as bitmaps
not exactly in this way we're scribing
here but like you know if I'm looking
for values that are greater than some
you know looking for values that are
greater than some given value if these
things are sorted in such a way that I
know that you know I can look at the
first bitmap first and I could throw
away more data by looking at that
because that's more selective I'll try
to maybe cover that when talk about
vectorization later on alright so this
is this was a good good
this is an obvious win we all know if
it's male/female they we're gonna be
able to press it down by a lot let's do
example we're bitmap encoding could be a
bad idea so let's say now I have a table
of customers and I had the zip code
field here I want to try to bitmap
encoding on this so assume in my table I
have 10 million people and in the United
States there's roughly around 43,000 ZIP
codes it's really like 41,000 I think
but assuming that's the case so if my
uncompressed data but I have 10 million
people and assume I can store stored the
zip code is just 32 bits then the total
mount of space I'm storing for this
column is just 40 megabytes but now if I
do bitmap encoding I need to have a
bitmap for every scene single unique ZIP
code in the United States and that
bitmap needs to be 10 million bits long
because I need to represent for every
single to blow to my table so now the
total size would be 53 gigabytes right
so again this obviously be super stupid
to do so bitmap and Cody can get great
compression ratio but this is something
that like a human has to decide am I is
this the right way to actually do my
encoding so for this reason I don't
think bitmap coding is commonly used
it's only really you only really see the
Sinister the high-end commercial OLAP
systems this is not really an issue we
organize things plots we could imagine
if now I start serving tuples in two
different offsets in my bitmap I got
everything else and moving them down the
same problem we saw last time and that
can get really expensive if I have
43,000 bitmaps just from one attribute
so one thing we can do though in
addition to just doing that I'm coding
these bitmaps are just fight sequences
right there's ones and zeros like like
finish or like like all datum we
actually can do compression on the
bitmaps themselves to get even better
compression so the most simplest way to
do this is just run that same snappy or
lz4 or gzip algorithms we talked about
before take our bitmap that we're
storing and didn't run that through our
compression scheme and then we could end
up actually with pretty good results
because again most of the times it's
gonna be a bunch of zeros and these
algorithms are you know that's that's
the ideal case for for compressing bit
sequences
again we're not going to do this for an
enemy database because this is gonna be
expensive because now I have single time
I gotta do a low couple when these
bitmaps I got to decompress it and
that's gonna be slow you could say well
let me combine together a bunch of
bitmaps in my zip code example from zip
codes where nobody lives in like Montana
and Wyoming and I combine those together
and most the times they don't need to go
look at those but when I do then I have
to decompress them yes you could do that
but as far as I know this is a lot of
engineering overhead and no system
actually does this what you do see
instead though is to do again sort of
native database compression on the
bitmap codes where you know you're gonna
have a bunch of zeros and you can try to
take advantage of that and we use a
variant of a run length encoding so I'm
gonna describe now one technique that
Oracle used to do called vitelline
bitmap codes or BBC's the spoiler would
be there they don't actually use this
anymore and explain why at the end but
this is I think a good example of the
sort of low-level bit it's kind of bit
you know bit level compression you can
do on bitmaps if you know you're gonna
have a lot of zeros so I like this
because they're from my opinion this
this is easy to understand and then you
can then build upon this and do more
sophisticated things or things that are
better for today's hardware so again
assume we're doing bitmap coding so we
have these these long bitmaps for our
column and we want to compress it down
to B so that takes less space and again
most of the bits are going to be zeros
so we're going to organize it into these
chunks where we have a bunch of a bunch
of bytes whether all zeros followed by
some bytes whether there are some ones
so they're gonna designate any byte that
has all zeros as a gap byte and then any
byte that has a 1 in it in any position
they'll call that a tail byte and so
that we're doing we're gonna encode a
chunk where we have a bunch of gap bytes
followed by some number of tail bytes
and we're gonna break it up and compress
it that way
so the gap bytes will compress with run
length encoding and then for the tail
bytes where there are there is a 1 in it
will keep track of either where that one
is located if it's a special case we
just have one bite or weirdest or them
uncompressed or in in verbatim as they
call it
so let's look at visual example so say
this is my bitmap here and we can see
that we it's all zeros except for this
byte up here we have one one and then
this byte here these two bytes here
there's a one here and there's two ones
in this one so again what they're going
to do they're going to break up the the
bitmap into segments or chunks where we
have a bunch of gap bytes where they're
all zeros followed by some byte where
there's at least one one so for the
first one here again here's our gap
bytes that are all zeros and then here's
our tail byte where there's one one in
it so the way we're gonna encode this
all right here's the other one right
because we have to have down here so way
we're gonna coat this first one is that
we always have to have a header byte and
the header blights gonna tell us what is
in our our chunk so the first 3 bits are
gonna be organized to tell us how many
gap bytes that we have up into seven so
we can begin the code and this port this
portion of this header but you say we
have at most seven gap bytes in our
chunk and we have more than we have to
do something else so in this case here
we have two one two gap bytes so we say
record that we just have the number two
here then in the next bit this is a
special flag that says that if this
thing is set to true then we know
whatever tail byte we're looking at we
only have one in our chunk and that it
only has one one in it so this is saying
if this is set to one so we know that
it's a special case so then the next
four bytes tells us at what position in
our byte that one is located in so in
this one we're encoding for so in our
tail byte we have one two three four and
that's where the one is located all
right so we're able to take three bytes
in our bitmap and encode it down to a
single byte so that's pretty good let's
look at the next chunk so now here again
we have thirteen gap bytes followed by
two tail bytes so when we write out our
header we can't record that we have
thirteen gap bytes in it because we can
only store up to eight or seven in this
in this three bits so we set it all to
ones right and that's going to tell us
that this is a special case that we need
to look at the first byte after our
header and that's gonna tell us the
length of our cap so we're in court
thirteen here and that
represents our 13 cap lights right that
that's the that's the runtime from
coding part part then we look at this
special flag here and again that tells
us whether we only have one byte has one
one in it
this is set to zero so that means that
in the next four bits we're gonna record
how many verbatim bytes we have right
and this is where we encode exactly
whatever how the bits are found up here
down in here or just make a straight
copy of them yes yes yes I know sex yes
but high level I just saw the same okay
so in this example here I was able to
take a bitmap that was 18 bytes and
compress it down to 5 bytes that's
pretty impressive right so again I'm I'm
instead of now storing the the if I'm
doing bitmap encoding instead of storing
the the bitmap for every single value in
its uncompressed form I can take that
bitmap and compress each one separately
yes
[Music]
and one comprehension having you know
sighs all right so you're it so you're
saying rather than throwing these four
bits here for this sorry do what I
connect say here's the position that bit
by logic lying to have a larger gap size
yeah I think that would that would
potentially work yes um
they didn't do that way all right yeah
I again like I Isis I suspect media for
a reason rather they looked at they look
at their bitmaps for their databases
this is Oracle right so they have real
customers they have real data and they
made that decision that this for the
most cases this is the right way to do
this I would assume that right alright
so as I said Oracle doesn't do this
anymore this is considered an obsolete
format so the reason is because although
we're gonna get a great compression
ratio the it's actually gonna be
terrible for modern CPUs because there's
all this branching right as I'm going
through like in order for me to go
figure out like you know I'm operating
on these compressed bytes I had to go
jump around like oh is this thing all
ones if so jump over here or this thing
is is a smaller than that then I no need
look at this but this is one jump here
if this is zero do something else right
that's terrible for modern CPUs because
it's all those conditionals are going to
be hard for the the branch predictor on
the CPU to predict because it's gonna be
different for every single you know
chunk sequence and we're gonna have a
lot of miss prediction and that's going
to have to cause us to flush our
extraction pipeline and that would have
CPU stalls so for this reason they then
came up with another version of an
improved version called right-aligned
hybrid bitmap encoding that's designed
for modern CPUs the BBC stuff was
patented but it was like the 90s - it
might be gone it might be patent expired
right now this thing is still I think
patented I've never read it
database patents and and II don't mix so
we
we don't read anything like that but it
they do have something out there that
does this again the other thing to point
out too is that in all these cases the
this bitmap encoding scheme it doesn't
support random access that's okay if
we're doing OLAP queries because we're
gonna scan from beginning to end but if
we had we want to say find at this
position whether the bitmap is set to 1
or 0 we have to start from the beginning
and decompress everything and so this is
not gonna work well for OLTP for OLAP
this is fine alright so let's go to some
other crushing schemes so Delta encoding
the idea here is that if we know that
values within the same column are going
to be have a small difference in between
them then instead of storing again a
complete copy of that value for every
for every single tuple we'll restore a
Delta between the between consecutive
values right so the idea here say this
is my table and I'm recording the
temperature of this room it's 99 degrees
it's super hot but I'm taking a
measurement in my sensor every minute
and then the the difference between
these temperatures is not gonna be that
much because you know if it's think of
the physical world
this room's not gonna go from 99 degrees
to a zero degrees in a single in a
single minute so the most of time these
deltas are gonna be overly small
increments so what I'll do is I'll take
the first value in my two columns and I
will record them in their entirety but
then everything that comes after that is
just a delta between the previous one
alright so here I'm storing plus one
plus one to represent that I'm you know
I'm going one minute ahead and so forth
what's another technique way to get
further compression on this RLE right
exactly what it says that guy so in here
again I'm I'm quoting it's measuring
every minute I'm gonna have a bunch of
plus ones over and over again so I could
take this now and run orally on that and
now store that as a single you know
single double here plus one followed by
the size of the rock alright so in this
looking with my toy example here the
original data assuming that we're
storing the timestamp and the
temperature as 32 bits that's wrong it's
read 5 times 2 or did you just take the
so we have five values each one's thirty
bits that's 160 bits in this case here
assuming that we can then store maybe
this as 16 bits deltas so now I'll get
down to 96 bits but if I can do RLE on
this say I store the original 32 bits
followed by just two 16-bit fields like
the the Delta and then the the lengths
are wrong I can get it down to 64 bits
so that's that's pretty good
but again same thing like the all the
other seams I said before if I want to
know the exact value is for for this
unless I'm storing run-length encoding I
basically at the recompute this thing to
get down to what get the correct time so
this is where our le could actually get
us better computational and performance
improvements because I don't have to
reapply this I can just look at this and
say oh I know that's plus 4 and there's
do simple math to get there okay so
variant of Delta encoding is called
incremental encoding and the idea here
is that for Strings if we recognize that
we have repeated prefixes and suffixes
we just stored the difference between
between the consecutive values so say it
is my original data I have four strings
Rob Rob robbing and robot so the first
thing I need to do is figure out what is
the common prefix between consecutive
values so in the case of the first one
Rob well this is there's nothing before
it so we have to store that in its
entirety there is no common prefix but
when we look at the next one here robbed
well this shares the first three three
characters as this one appear so we know
that this is the common prefix from this
attribute to the next attribute all
right this bag to the next time we do
the same thing for all these other ones
here so now once we have this common
prefix the compressed version could just
store the the length of the prefix that
we're sharing and then the remaining
suffix that's actually different all
right so this absent only works if
things are sorted order it actually
would also work in inside of B plus
trees we'll see you later on but just
doing some quick math saying now I'm
storing all these characters is a bits
the total size of this data set here is
168 bits and then for this one it's 88
bits to store the suffixes and then say
four times eight bits to store the the
length of the the prefix
so in total that's what this 100 and 120
okay I'm also not storing the the length
of the the string I have to do that for
this as well and then same thing for the
suffix like I need of the length of
suffix yes this question is this yes if
it's sorted electric graphically I mean
this is saying let's abacus defining
what the collation of the sort order is
going to be so yes in my example its
ASCII sorting so yes alphabetical
sorting through this worked out great
for that okay so then the next scheme
that Myrtle that is not really a
compression scheme but it's a way to
encode data in in such a way you'd less
space so as far as they know the only
system that she does this is Amazon's
redshift and so they call this mostly in
coding so the idea is that if you have
an attribute where most of the time it's
not going to be the full size that you
define for the attribute then instead of
storing all the bits for that attribute
you just store it as a smaller data type
so this is oftentimes very common you
see this in people you know application
developers when they define their schema
they just say oh I want everything to be
in 64 but most the time you're only
storing you know something it could be
stored in 8 bits so if you know that you
can tell it isn't I want to do courts
called you know the mostly encoding to
say what used to be a 64 bit column now
I can is most of the times it's gonna be
8 bits all right but anytime that I have
a value that doesn't fit within 8 bits
then I just have a special flag to say
the original vector the full value
looking for it this offset is in this
lookup table here so now if I'm scanning
along and trying to find all values
greater than you know greater than 10 or
something like that if I come across
this I would have to know to jump over
here right so in this example here the
original size would be 5 times 64 bits
would be 33 and 20 bits assuming I again
I can store the this lookup thing as
just 16 bits plus a 64-bit value then I
get this down to be hundred 20 bits
right okay so I always we ran out of
time with compression but the thing I
want to spend time to finish up with is
the dictionary compression and the idea
here is that this is we're gonna find
frequently repeated values in the in the
values of the attributes and instead of
storing them in their entirety over and
over again we're just gonna replace them
with some kind of smaller code and that
anytime we want to do a look up to see
what was the original value we'd look in
this dictionary it can be a hash table
the B plus tree could be an array
different ways to organize it we can
then convert that encoded value back to
the original value so we obviously want
to support fast encoding and decoding if
it's really really expensive to encode
our block of data then this is gonna be
a bad trade off decoding can be gonna
gonna you know it's gonna be actually
matter more
but when I'll tell my bad V fast as well
and they were also one of us support
range queries so that we can do you know
find all attributes that are greater
than sum or sums follow tuples that were
the values great and some some given
value i don't want to be compressed that
to do that evaluation so if my
dictionary encoding follows the same
order of the original values then i can
operate directly on compress data so the
decisions we're gonna make for
dictionary compression is when to
construct the dictionary will should be
the scope of the dictionary like what
you know what portion of the data are we
looking at what data structure we want
to use and then what should be the
encoding scheme for the dictionary so
for the paper i have you guys read they
talk about you could use Huffman
encoding or who tucker codes who tougher
codes are actually gonna want to use
because their or their order preserving
we're not going to talk about what those
albums actually are because we don't
really care we just use whatever you
know we're database people will use
whatever just works but in general most
people mostly dictionaries are going to
use use the who tucker codes so we're
gonna focus on on the other ones up here
so the first one is we when do we
actually construct the dictionary so we
can do this all at once meaning we have
some some some some data that and we
know that there's nothing else going to
be added to it or delete it from it so
when you take that data and computer it
right then to them and this time you
know we're actually gonna possibly get
the best compression ratio because we
can assume that everything you know we
know exactly how to pack in the
dictionary codes in the smallest number
bikes that were ever gonna need
whereas now feminie comes along and and
wants to modify this we may have to
change depending or adding things or
deleting things we may have to recompute
the dictionary but if the data is cold
and this is not gonna happen that often
incremental encoding is where we would
we would have a dictionary where we add
some additional placeholders where we
know values could occur we don't know
what they are but we know in our and our
order preserving or the order of their
dictionary goes something could go there
so weasel is leave some extra space and
when these things show up we can
accommodate them and at some point we'll
still get to full and then that case we
have to recompute the the dictionary all
over again for the dictionary scope
again we talk to this a little bit
before but we'd have on a block level we
just take all the tuples on the same
value and compress them this is going to
be potentially lower compression ratio
and then these other ones because the
more unique the more repeated values we
see then the better compression ratio
we're going to get and the the fewer
copies of the same dictionary over and
over again we get the storm table level
would be we talked a dictionary for the
entire table this is gonna be amazing
compression ratio but of course this is
gonna be expensive to update because I
need to I'm inserting a lot of things
and I may have to recompute the
compression ratio or compression
dictionary all over again and then
multiple table would be we can record or
maintain a dictionary that can be span
multiple multiple tables and you would
do this if you have like foreign keys
where you know that you're gonna join
the the parent relation and the chav
elation through the spark and over again
so if you can compress them with the
same dictionary then they'll have the
same codes and you don't have to
decompress them in order to do the
comparison so let me skip multi I tree
coding in the sake of time but let's
focus on the order preservation stuff so
we already talked through this we want
to we need a dictionary that can support
encode and decode right encode basically
says for a given for given key its
uncompressed convert it to its
compressed form and then this is just
the reverse of this alright so the main
thing to point out is that there's not
gonna be any magic hash function we can
use to do this for us we're not that
have an additional data structure that
we're gonna have to compute in our datum
to do this for us right if you had a
hash function that could use this and
still be order preserving underneath the
covers the way it's actually can be
implemented right is probably gonna be a
hash table
just a dictionary so and we avoid all
that and to build the dictionary
ourselves so the reason why we won't be
order preserving as I already said if
now I have a query shows up like find
all the users where the name is like a
nd so for the app to execute this query
instead of having to scan through and
decompress the data and apply this
predicate I can just scan the dictionary
right if I can Rhian code this to say
now between 10 and 20 I can just scan
the compressed data and then I can
figure out what I actually want to look
at so the way you actually keep you at
this you do a and D you you like on the
dictionary first you figure out what the
the the between range is and then you
run that scan on this so this dictionary
is exposed or is maintained by the data
system itself so it can run like
preliminary queries on this to figure
out what is actually available in the
compressed data you do other things too
like if you want to say give me all the
unique count the number distinct names
in this column I don't even touch the
name field I just go to the dictionary
rip through this portion count all of
those or actually to know how many
dictionary entries that have that would
actually good enough to because these
are guaranteed to be unique right all
right so let's see now if we have a
query like this right we can already
talk about this the question is do we
have the performance control scan in
this case yes because I'll match on the
dictionary but I need to find what the
actual the tuples are but in this other
example here I just want to get the the
distinct name I don't want the
decompressor I only have to access the
dictionary yes good you keep bringing
this up some people's might get deleted
yes so if my dictionary is on a block of
data and I say that block is immutable
then that can't happen right sometimes
actually also too is in addition to the
code you also can store the count with
this right and that's cheap to maintain
every time I insert right yeah so then
you can just do more things on like that
it's sort of like again the pre-computer
aggregation stuff we talked about bazoom
at something beginning so I
for this for this value here's another
occurrences that I have for some queries
I just operate on the dictionary all
right so the different data structures
you can use for this the most simplest
one is just being an array so you have
all these very building strings and you
sort them in an array and the dictionary
code is just the offset into that array
again this works if the data is not
being modified over and over again right
as he's gonna ask about because if I
modify things and I add a new string
then now all the all sets change and I
gotta go recode everything so this is
actually what we do in our system today
because we followed the Apache arrow
format and the Apache arrow
specification Apache arrow is like a
open source universal file format for
in-memory columnstore x' and our data is
essentially follows this and so we they
do dictionary encoding this way even
though other encoding schemes might be
better Aero only does dictionary
encoding another approach did you use a
hash table so this would be fast and
compact to be with lookups the problems
going to be though you're not going to
support range queries or prefix queries
because you're not going to easily be
able to easily scan through the values
all right because everything everything
to be hashed and then the another
approach is use a B+ tree so this will
be slower than hash table in the arrays
and potentially take more memory but
this is going to support the the range
of prefix queries you may want to do as
far as I know most a lot of systems do
do this first one here I only know of
there's a patent on this particular idea
so I don't know who else actually does
this approach right yeah most of the
times you're compressing cold data so
this one is good enough let's see
actually how you want to do this so the
idea is basically you have to be plus
trees you have 1/2 encoding and that's
right side up and then you have 1 to do
decode and that's upside-down so you can
sort of go in both directions and then
in the middle they're gonna share leaves
that are gonna map values to codes or
they can use that to do reverse map code
to values all right so this is me the
shortest share leaf if I have a version
of value like Aboriginal string I want
to I want to encode it then I go through
this this index I land in my leaf node
find the entry that I want and then I
would produce
value but then if I have an encoded
value I use the bottom one do the same
thing but in Reverse
and then I can spit out what the
original value was and internally what
they're gonna do is they're gonna use
incremental encoding as we talked about
before because again within the node
there are gonna be sorted values and
they're oftentimes going to be repeating
the same prefix over and over again so I
can compress these down even further the
other thing they're gonna do also to in
my example here the codes are 10 20 30
40 so they're gonna leave gaps in here
between the code range so that if a new
tuple or new entry shows up that's in
between a a a a a B and a e I can insert
a new guy here give it code 11 without
having to recode everything as soon as I
run out of space in between these then I
the game's over and I've every start
okay so any questions about dictionary
encoding that was a bit fast yes yes
yeah so this example is and this one
here I have a be an AE so I know the
number of keys could exist in between
these can therefore I can Pat it out
that way you could do that I don't think
they do that though yeah like if you
know it can only be three characters
then that's okay right if you have if
it's longer than three then I like that
works it can be infinite okay so a quick
I'm gonna talk about how to do index
compression so as I said everything we
talked about here today has been about
OLAP common expressions you ever see
that mostly in the wild that that's the
most common thing but for OHP workloads
the the indexes themselves can actually
take up a lot of space as well right so
this is a study we did for a paper we
wrote it four years ago we took some
open source benchmarks TPCC articles
think of this is like hacker news or
reddit it's like people pushing articles
and then people write in comments and
then voter it came from both DB this is
a say the Japanese version of American
Idol it's like when people call them a
phone to vote when someone's like
performing this benchmark mimics that
you snicker but they sold
both to be a lot of to a lot of like it
ran runs the Japanese version American
Idol it runs the Canadian version of
American Idol I think there's no one on
Malaysia it runs like it's like it was
used a lot um I got hired based on this
right so uh so the original tuba size
for these benchmarks I for all of these
the indexes themselves are purp rising a
large portion of the data so again we
can't use the database compression stuff
we talked about so far we can't compress
the tuples because it's OTP we can
modify anything at any time so we can't
compress this part but here's all the
other data that we can potentially also
compress as well so the two most common
techniques to do in X compression are to
do prefix compression and suffix
truncation and this looks a lot like the
stuff that we already talked about
before we have bunch of sort of data and
in our nodes and then we repeat values
over and over again so instead of
storing the entire value repeatedly we
destroy the prefix once and then just
the suffix part that is actually
different right this one is actually the
most comments any and you'll see this
all the time in B plus trees that
support PBX compression they're gonna do
something like this now whether or not
the leaf nodes are compressed or just
the inter nodes or depends on what kind
of workload Turney think and a half like
most of the times you know most of the
updates are doing to it to a B+ tree
you're always gonna be the leaf nodes so
maybe you don't compress that part
because this thing's gonna change all
the time but for the inner nodes and up
above you could you could you could
oppress those yes this question is is
this a B+ tree approximation of a radix
tree yes that's one way to think about
it but again except the difference is
that the these key this is in this if
this is an inner node in the people s
tree these keys may not actually exist
right suffix truncation and the idea
here is that for the internodes we don't
maybe to store the entire key right we
just store that the we just throw away
the suffix word that doesn't help us and
only store the prefix in these case here
the the these two keys need for these
two keys they're unique immediately
after the first character a and B so I'm
looking for something that's that
greater than a then I know I want to go
one side I'm looking for something
that's less than a or I go to the other
side alright so I could destroy a b c
and l MN and that's enough for me to
distinguish which path i want to go down
and that can cut down the space alright
going back to this one real quickly I'm
shorting compressing keys you'd also
compress values the pointers to tuples
if they're look if you know that two
bows are being the same block then
instead of sorting the block ID maybe
destroy the offset like that that one's
more common in the displaced isms I
don't know about any in memory system
does this and I don't know of any a MIDI
Mr Justice a well prefix compression is
the more common one all right the last
thing we'll talk about is a paper we
wrote for hybrid indexes and again the
idea here is just to expose you to other
techniques of what other things we could
compress other than just data so we can
compress the keys in the index we can
press the values in the index but what
if we actually could also compress the
data structure itself but the internal
metadata we're maintaining to say this
actually a B+ stream so what we're gonna
do now is it's gonna call it hybrid
index we're gonna have a uncompressed
index and a compress index again this
looks a lot like the fraction mirror
stuff that we talked about for the
column store last class so the dynamic
index we fast update it's uncompressed
and then as data gets old we'll convert
it over to this compressed index that'll
be read-only and then every so often
we're gonna refresh the static stage by
merging in that the changes from the
front end the front end index to the
back end so it looks like this so we all
our inserts update leak go to a dynamic
dynamic index and then over time will
then merges with a static index that's
compressed but then we'll also maintain
this bloom filters so that when we do a
lookup we check the bloom filter to see
whether it the thing we're looking for
it could be in our dynamic index if yes
then we go check it out if not the blue
filter return tells us false then we
always go check the static index and
there's a voice that having any excuse
me any false negatives so everyone would
have bloom put there is who here doesn't
know what a bloom filter is
yes surely did this like yeah you don't
know what others okay I'll give you a
crash course in 30 sec okay so a bloom
filter is an approximate data structure
that answers set membership queries
it'll tell you whether does a key exist
in my set but it may give you false
positives it'll never tell you something
doesn't exist when it does exist but it
may tell you something does exist when
it doesn't actually exist okay and think
it's just a bitmap and we're gonna have
to get a hash function on our key or
take a key hash it multiple times and
update different bits and that's how we
record whether something exists right so
the only thing we can do is insert and
lookup we can't actually delete things
we can't do any range queries so this is
my super simple bloom filter so say I
want to insert RZA from the Mouton clan
I have two hash functions I take the key
I hash it I'm modded by the number of
bits that I have and I go flip these
bits to be one now I do this for the GZA
same thing i modded by number bits i
update that played this so now if i do a
lookup does this bloom filter contain
the key RZA then i den do the same thing
take the key pass it then I do my lookup
if all the ones of these positions all
the positions are these bits are set to
1 then I know the thing could exist
right and true in case of Raekwon a hash
him now one of the bits are set to 0 so
I know this thing could not definitely
does not exist but again you can get
false negatives if I do a lookup with
ODB then the hash will take me to bits
that are worth set but I never actually
inserted this so it's telling me this
key exists when it doesn't actually so
in my going back to my example that you
got it now ok so going back to my
example from before if I with this bloom
filter it could tell me something exists
in this dynamic index but it doesn't
actually exist because I've already
merged it back to the static stage but
that's ok because you know I maybe I do
a look up here and it's wasted but I'll
never say this thing doesn't exist I go
look in here and I don't see it when it
actually existed there so how can you
compact a B+ tree other than is doing
the compressing the keys well the first
thing is that because we have this rule
for B plus trees they say they have to
be at least half full we
no we're gonna have a bunch of empty
slots so if our index is never gonna be
updated
we don't actually never need these empty
slots so we now we can compress every
node down to be just storing exactly the
keys that exist but then the next thing
is that we have these pointers now
because these are just random nodes in
the heap so these are may 64-bit
pointers to some location in memory
where the next note is so instead of
storing these pointers in their entirety
if we just had a offset to some starting
location in an array then that could
then we could jump down to exactly where
where we should have been if these were
separate nodes
even though it's one can check you know
containers piece of memory so that's how
you can compress a B+ tree you can do
the same thing right for a skip list Mew
the same thing for an art index right
again recognizing that we're never going
to update the index all these extra
stuff we have in our system or in the
index so that we can accommodate updates
are unnecessary and we can throw them
all out and compress it down so in terms
of its size you can get this throughput
member formants with the hybrid index it
actually turns out being faster because
there's a product it's smaller and
therefore you have fewer cache misses
and then the overall size is reduced
quite a bit as well so again this is a
paper that we wrote a publishing sigmod
a few years ago no system actually does
this but I think these techniques again
could be applied for in a column store
system when you know tuples are not
gonna be modified yes question do you
have a separate bloom filter for each
stage if you have multiple stages like
you could say like here's a here's a hot
index here's a great cooler index and
here's the cold index you'd have a bloom
cluster of each one there you don't need
for the static one right because because
this is saying this is a query shows up
do I need to read this yes or no and the
blue meter tells me whether I need to do
that and the idea is that because I say
I do much inserts into my dynamic index
over time I want to then merge it all
those keys now exist in the static side
they're no longer exist here this thing
becomes empty
questions why don't we you just interior
cuz we have other problems yeah I say
also too like we don't have a we don't
have a multi-threaded thread-safe
merge algorithm we did this in HD or HD
or single-threaded engines so like we
we'd stop all transactions while we
merged it cuz otherwise you have to like
merge this and worry about people
reading the same time or make me make
two copies and that gets expensive
because they ex can get kind of large
okay so that was rush to the end I
apologize but beginning the hope of the
main takeaway you got from this is that
hey the database system knows what the
data looks like it knows what the types
are it knows how the query is gonna be
accessing them it can now make better
decisions on how to compress the data
beyond what I can ieave compression
scheme can do right and we showed how we
can do we can apply we can apply
compression on already compressed data
like doing RLE on delta encoding and get
even better compression ratios alright
and then we talked to how about we can
wait as long as possible during query
execution before we have to decompress
the data only when we tell the outside
world here's the answer the query then
ideally we have to decompress it for
joins we'll see later in the semester if
you're joining two things that are
compressed and their own a different
dictionary you have to be compressed one
and potentially re-encode the other one
and that gets expensive but that's
unavoidable okay alright so next week
we'll talk about our started one
Wednesday today's Wednesday thank you
yeah all right it's been rough alright
okay baby all right
so Monday thank you Monday we'll talk
about logging checkpoints so now even
though we're in memory database we still
need to be able to recover after a crash
so I had to write out things to disks
and take checkpoints up quickly as
possible okay
alright have a good weekend see ya Bank
it in the side park what is this
some fools hey yo
spica's ain't with that here called the
okay cuz I'm all Chi I stood down with
the testy hi you look and it was go grab
me a 40 just to get my buzz song cuz I
needed just a little more kick like a
fish after just one slip put it to my
lips and rip the top off the truck the
same as hot and my hood wants me to say
I'm nice to take a seat to pray