[Music]
[Applause]
today we're going to talk about hash
joins again I'm just here my home office
it's me up here with the terrier in
attendance so it'll be asking questions
as we go along today so why are hash
coins important well it's joined in
general are important because that's one
of those common things operated with an
execute in analytical workloads so for
today we're gonna start talked about in
the background of what it means for to
do a joint algorithm
I had a high-level and in some of the
history of the back and forth between
the performance trade-offs of a hash
joint versus the sort merge join that
we'll talk about have you a parallel
house join and in the different ways to
do the three phases and then we talked
about how did you build a hash table the
hashing scheme the hashing function and
then we'll finish off with a discussion
of the evaluation of the based on some
of the results and in the paper you guys
were assigned to me so the in the
introduction class last semester when we
talked about joint albums we didn't
really talk about how to set execute
them in terms of multiple threads at in
parallel we mostly focused on trying to
assess you know how much disk IO we were
going to incur for the different
algorithms but now in an in-memory
system we don't have disk and now we
want to maximize the amount of
parallelization we can get across on our
course on our CPUs and now we need to
focus on how we're actually gonna use
our hardware efficiently to do the joint
so parallel joint is just taking two
tables two relations that we want to
join together but we're gonna do this
joint across multiple threads I'm going
to try to minimize the amount of
contention and synchronization as
possible so that we get the best
performance so the two main approaches
we're going to do the view joins in an
OLAP system are going to be either
hashing or server or sorting these are
there's no other sort of way to
magically be able to identify when you
have matching tuples right it's either
one or the other and so for this class
also the means we're not going to
discuss national loop joins because
that's like the worst case scenario in
in an OLAP system because it's just
doing a brute-force search of scruncho
scans over the tables to try to find
matching tuples
so in OLAP systems you're not gonna see
nested loop joins except for some rare
cases when the tables are super small
and so for that reason they're also you
know running those in parallel is the
same way you would just sort of run a
scan in parallel so there's not that
much we talked about here the other
thing I'll say also - though in OTP
systems you will see initially joins
because awesome talk oftentimes these
database systems that are designed for
transaction processing workloads don't
need to do hash joins or don't even need
to do sort merge joins because they're
not doing large joints between different
tables it's always doing foreign key
lookups or small number key lookups to
go get data that you would then give out
to the application or like render a web
page let's think of like Amazon when you
log in there could be a nested loop join
for taking Amy's account and getting all
andis orders so there'll be a foreign
key reference from the the order
customer ID to the customer table right
and then that case is just an index
nested loop joint which will be super
fashion way more efficient than you
would do a hash drawing because you
don't need to build the hash table to do
the join you just use that that existing
index so for this reason an index in
this loop join at a high level is going
to look a lot like a hash join it's just
that the the data structure you use to
find matching tuples already exists
because the OGB application already
defined the index that you're gonna do a
join on I said again the high-level
differences here is that a hash join
builds a data structure like an index
that allow you to find the matching
tuples but when that query finishes it
throws away the hash table and an x
squared comes along and just really
about the hash table again in a index
mmm as a loop join the index already
exists so you don't need to build it on
the fly you just use that in order to
find the matches for your tuples but a
big difference is that in ocean settings
this index is most likely going to be a
tree based data structure so either be
plus tree or a radix tree that we talked
about before and and so that means
you'll get login
Gups when you do the join but for a hash
join you using a hatchet we'll give you
on average oh one lookups which is way
more faster so that's why nobody builds
a B+ Trading when you do a join with
some rare exceptions when you're doing
like you know range range predicates and
things like that on the joint but we're
focusing on equi-join
so perhaps on we're gonna use a hash
table because that's gonna be more
efficient so the debate of whether sort
merge-join is faster than hash join is
one of these classic problems in in
databases that over the last 50 years
it's gone back and forth of which which
approach is actually better so in the
1970s the conventional wisdom was that
sort vers join with superior because the
amount of memory that was available to
these early date early computers early
systems back then was was quite limited
and they had algorithms to do external
merge sort so you could spilled a disk
and still sort the data and so I it's
unclear whether they knew they could do
a hash joint that could spilt a desk or
not but the conventional wisdom was the
sort MERS joined was better because they
already had that external more short
algorithm then the 1980s came along and
then there was this movement called sort
of database machines where they've
identified that hash twins could be
superior if you had a specialized
hardware support to do the hashing and
do the hash join and so in the 1980s the
potential wisdom was that hashing
patterns were superior because they had
because they had hardware that could do
it more efficiently than you could do
sorting so we we don't really talk about
davison machines anymore the idea I
think of this is like it's a custom
appliance that has special instructions
or special hardware specifically for a
particular database system they sort of
went out of vogue in the 1980s because
Intel and all the other chip
manufacturers were putting out new
things new CPUs all the time and even
voted with Moore's law things got faster
and faster because you had more
transistors so by the time if you were a
database company the time it took you to
fabricate or design and fabricate your
database machine with specialized
hardware and then actually put it in
production and start selling it
Intel or whoever put out already new
CPUs that were that negated any
performance gains you had in your custom
hardware you don't really see this
anymore aw that's kind of coming back in
vogue not so much with specialized
Harvard like they didn't data's machines
but more like FPGAs GPUs and and other
types of hardware accelerators that it's
there's still commodity base but you can
design custom kernels for the database
on them then in the 1990s there was this
paper from gertz graphi the same guy
that did volcano the same guy that did
the BP plus tree stuff we talked about
before with latching he came out with a
paper that said that the algorithms are
basically equivalent that for all
different real world scenarios on the
marver that existed at the time you
wouldn't really see a noticeable
performance difference between being
short version hashing so they were Dean
equivalent but then in the 2000s as
there was more and more analytical
databases being created like Vertica
greenplum aster data things like that it
was shown that hash joins were
considered to be superior on the horror
that was available at the time and
really since then that's that's been the
case right in the 2010s it wasn't so
much a debate about whether certain
bursts join was better than hash join if
the debate was whether you want to do a
partition hash join or non partition
hash join which is what we'll talk about
today and in the in the current decade
again unless there's some unless there's
some major breakthrough in the hardware
I don't think that certain version will
ever come up on top again I think
hashing is it's been proven to be
superior in many cases now obviously if
your data is already sorted on the join
key then you don't need to do the sort
at all and just doing the merge phase
then you know that's the best-case
scenario and that that certainly will be
the beta hash joint algorithm but
databases normally don't keep things
sorted all the time all right so let's
talk about now what the last decade
looked like sort of how we got to where
we are today and why
I signed the paper you guys were reading
so again the 2000 and the early 2000s at
the turn of the century it was deemed
that the research showed that hash join
was superior so the one of the key
papers in this came out from Intel when
Oracle in 2009 where they showed that
hashing was indeed superior than the
sword merge but they speculated that if
we now had larger Cindy registers in
particular 512-bit Cindy registers like
avx-512 for Intel then sort MERS join
would actually be faster now as far as
they know I there hasn't been a paper
since 2017 when a tx5 spell came out
that has actually tested this theory but
the ancient you can see whether that
that's actually you know what this is
actually true or not but again still now
everyone's still just doing a hashed
joins then in 2011 researchers at
Wisconsin put out a paper that started
the debate of whether you went to a
partition has joined versus a non
partition has shown and will discuss
these results later later in this
lecture but then the the Germans with
hyper came out and said Oh Intel is
actually wrong and Wisconsin was wrong
certain was joined is already fast or
even without the larger Cindy registers
and they showed how how you could do
this in hyper but then they came out a
year later with another paper that said
ignore what we just said in the previous
year we were wrong hashing is actually
superior and here's and here's a better
implementation for it then in 2013 there
was another paper from researchers in
Switzerland from ETH where they have a
bunch of ways to make a radix hash
drawing perform more efficiently so a
radix hash drawing radix partitioning
join we'll discuss this and few more
lectures they just showed how you can
you can do this more efficiently than an
on partition join but then another group
of Germans in 2016 came out and said
everyone needs to hold out but and stop
publishing these papers that say you
know here's my hash going back look how
much better it is they actually then did
a an exhaustive evaluation of
the different design decisions you could
have in your in your joint algorithm to
better understand what the trade-offs
are and which one is actually going to
be better than another so again that's
why I signed you guys this paper because
I get rather than just saying here's
this one-off implementation that we did
as Wisconsin did or hyper dated or ETH
did they just sorta did a complete sweep
over all their possible parameters in
these implications and showed you know
in what scenarios would one be better
than another so the so now if you want
to design our joint algorithm but that's
sort vers joint or hash join what are
some things you should think about to
make this thing run efficiently and it
could give performance so at a high
level of the two goals that we're gonna
have is that we want to minimize stick
Rinna's ation and minimize the cost of
accessing memory while we do the joint
so the first ones are obvious right we
talked about this before it basically
means that we want to avoid having to
take latches to protect critical
sections of the data structure of our
join so that you don't have any
contention or complex between threads so
that every thread is basically running
at full speed and they're not waiting
for another thread to give up some some
resource okay so I'll step to this this
doesn't necessarily we need to make our
algorithm latch free and there are latch
free techniques to do sorting and and
and merge or sorting and hash joins it
just means we need to get smarter about
how we're we're taking our latches for
the second one here the idea is that we
want to make sure that any time we have
a worker thread that's computing a join
any time they have to touch data access
it to do a check or write something we
want to make sure that that data is is
local to that core and this could be
either in the same numeration or ideally
in the same CPU cache right we want to
minimize the memory cache misses and
never minimize a number of cross
interconnect traffic between between
sockets so the way we can do this does
this last one improve our cache behavior
is twofold
so the things are going to matter for
most for us when we when we when we have
our algorithm that's gonna cause us to
have cache
is is we need to account for the size of
our cash and our TLD translation
lookaside buffer so that we're not
trying to access a large number of pages
at the same time so think about this if
I now need to touch ten to 'pls
if those ten to poles are in 10
different pages I only have five entries
in my TLD that's mapping the virtual
memory address to the physical memory
address then in order for me to actually
do my operations on those ten things I'm
gonna have to start addicting things for
my TLB and therefore of a cache miss on
the data that I want plus a cache miss
in the TLB II said I big my access go
twice as slow so ideally I want a brave
it'll bring a small amount of data or
the middle amount of data I need to do
whatever operations I think it need to
do and complete all those operations
before I move on to the to the next name
and that's sort of called locality the
temple and spatial locality so I'm just
making sure that I'm accessing that fie
access this thing multiple times I want
to do this within the same short time
window so that it's always in the cache
and I'm accessing multiple things I'll
make sure that they're close together
either in the same cache line all right
ideally in the same cache line so that
I'm not paying the penalty of multiple
cache misses and polluting my TLB so the
way we can achieve this is is is we need
be the way to achieve this we need to be
aware of the what kind of accesses we're
going to do and the two type of excesses
are either essential scans or random
lookups so with with non-random access
where I'm just reading a sequence of
bytes in order then again I want to make
sure that that data it will fit into a
single cache line so that's one you know
cache miss and one memory stole to go
fetch it and bring it bring it into to
the CPU and then for everything I bring
in to my CPU caches I want to execute as
many operations because I can't on them
if I do have to do random lookups though
I want to make sure that those random
lookups are getting clustered together
within the same cache line so that I
again I ever do Stan umber of lookups
that I have to do
to memory so this is this classic
trade-off between the number
instructions we're gonna have or the
cycle Grantham incur versus the amount
of memory and so the will see this you
know in a second but like the way we can
achieve all these things is through sort
of careful partitioning and being aware
of what data exists and in what location
so that our threads are always accessing
data that's that's it's close to it okay
so for the parallel hash drawing again
hash join is super important for us
because it it's gonna be the most common
joint algorithm that's implemented in
systems and a lot of OLAP queries are
going to contain joins we want this form
efficiently as possible in the paper you
guys read though you saw that the the
join portion of one particular TP CH
query actually was not the the bulk of
the execution time I've actually seen
numbers that go in both ways I've seen
numbers from Impala that shows the the
joins are like 45% of the time of the
system in the case of the sort of the
testbed system you guys read about from
from Germany or Saarland it was maybe
like less than ten to fifteen percent of
the total time so just how much of the
time the system is going to spend doing
hash coins you can vary from system to
system but certainly there's gonna be a
lot of joins and these joins are almost
always gonna be executed as as hash
joins so we're gonna run that as fast as
possible so at a high level the goal is
where the parallel hash one album is
that we want all our cores to be busy at
all times that nobody should be stalled
winning get data no should be nobody
should be stalled waiting for another
thread to complete some operation before
they can proceed ideally you want
everyone just running full blast all the
time and of course this is easier said
than done so a hash join is comprised of
three phases
partitioning build the partition build
and probe so we're gonna go through each
of these one by one
but it's one show this as it as an
outline for well where we're going to go
in this lecture so in the first phase is
it's entirely optional the partition
phase and the idea here is that we want
to divide our table tables that were
joining together
into smaller chunks based on the hash
key so that in the subsequent phases we
can have threads operate on on just data
in their partition they don't need to go
look at data and other partitions so if
your member for an intro class we talked
about this doing partitioning and
spilling buckets at disk this is also
called sometimes the grace hash join
right the grace hash join just means
you're at a high level you're doing this
this partitioning phase but how you do
the partition can vary from from one
implementation of the next and then once
whether or not we do the partitioning
the next phase well do the we'll build a
hash table so this is where we're
scanning through the outer table our and
then we're just gonna build a hash table
on the fly for the for the join key that
that our query is asking for then in the
second fit or that sort of the final
phase for the probe we're gonna do a
scruncher scan on the inner table s and
we're gonna look up as join key hash it
do a probe into the hash table see
whether we have a match and if so then
we'll produce will combine the tuples
and produces as the output of the
operator that's then fed up into the
query plan so the important thing to
point out though is in this probe phase
and the paper you guys are assigned to
read in a real system after you if
you've a match on the probe you actually
need to materialize this combined tuple
and then and then copy it into an output
buffer for the operator and a lot of the
hash drawn papers that I showed of
beginning or the join papers Dutch in
the beginning they actually don't do
this last step just because you know
then one of the numbers to look really
really good or they sort of they didn't
really sort of think about it but in a
real system and in the Saarland paper
they actually do this last step which is
important because that can affect the
performance of the rest of the system
we'll talk about the implications of
this with a limited early
materialization and late materialization
in a few more slides all right so let's
go to each of these phases separately
and we'll talk about the different ways
to implement them so again the the
partition phase is we're gonna take the
both relations the inner one and the
outer one we're going to scan through
them look at the join key hash them and
then assign them to some output buffer
the partition buffer and so the whole
idea of this is that although we're
paying an extra an extra cost of having
to scan through the data and copy it
once the idea is that if we're
intelligent about how we do this we can
write the data out in such a way that
when we do the buildin probe will
minimize the number of a reduced number
of cycles we have to execute those
instructions because we'll minimize the
number of cache misses I will make sure
that the the threads are operating on
one data that's that that's a local to
them I so again the idea is we pay this
upfront cost to make other stuff go
faster later on so sometimes in this
literature as I said sometimes can be
called a queries hash Dorn sometimes
called the hybrid hash drawing or the
radix hash join right whenever you see
those sort of these qualifiers in front
of the hash join just means that they're
doing some kind of partitioning step in
front of it so as I said in the last
slide we need be aware of what we're
actually putting into our buffers
because that's gonna greatly affect the
performance well it turns out the what
you etching you put in your buffers is
gonna depend on what the storage model
is that we talked about before so if
it's a row store usually they put the
entire tuple in the upload buffer
because even though I only need maybe
need a subset of the attributes to do
the join or X be the rest of the query
it's just either to copy some contiguous
chunk of memory and write in to my
output buffer Hertz my partition buffer
in a column store oftentimes what you do
is you only store the keys that you need
to do the join and then the offset to
where to find the rest the to posts if
you needed it stitch it together and the
reason why you can do this is because
you want to do this is because you're
minimizing the amount of data that
you're actually copying copying from you
know and making these partitions and you
don't have to worry about chopping it up
as you would in a row store because it's
already divided or partitioned for you
as a column store so the more efficient
approach to do again is just the bare
minimum number a bare minimum
information you need in order to compute
the join and then if another part of the
query up above and the plan needs
additional columns are additional
attributes you use the offset to go find
find that information
so for partitioning there's two
approaches there's the non-blocking and
the blocking partitioning or the radix
partitioning and so with the non
blocking approach the idea is that you
have a set of threads that are going to
go through and partition the data so
scan the adder at our inner table start
producing these partitions and then as
it's generating is output you can have
another set of threads we'll read that
data and start start the next phase to
start populating the hash table right
and you can do this because you're not
worried about any false positive false
negatives
I'm sorry false negatives like as the
data is partitioned you can then
immediately populate the hash table it
depends on whether you're doing one pass
to pass but in general for the non
blocking one people do people do one
pass right in the second approach when
you're doing the the radix partitioning
the way it works is that you can have
all the threads will scan through the
the table once and the tables once and
produce the partitions and because you
don't know exactly how far each thread
it's gone and you know whether since
everything's already broken into buckets
you can't be guaranteed that you have
all the data you need to fill the hash
table so all the threads were doing this
but this partitioning at the same time
and then when that completes then you
switch over and do the the build phase
so let's go through each of these one by
one so in case a non-blocking
partitioning there's actually a two sort
of subsets or the two additional ways
you can actually implement this again
this is this we're gonna scan the
relation and then once and then build
the output on the fly so with shared
partitions you're gonna have all the
threads try to write into the same
memory locations at the same time or the
same buckets for your partitions and
that means that you have to use a latch
to synchronize the buckets to make sure
that one thread doesn't doesn't
overwrite something that another thread
wrote it wrote into incorrectly in the
second post you used to have private
partitions where each thread now has its
own set of buckets that they can
populate there's no other thread writing
to this bucket so you don't need a latch
to protect anything and then once the
once this
first phase is done with first pass it
down with the private partitions
then you can go through a with another
set of threads and then populate the
global partitioning buckets that you're
doing the first one so again a classic
classic commuter science here there's no
free lunch right on one hand in this
case here we're using latches to protect
the data structure but we only have to
go through the partition every pass once
in this one it's latch free but that now
means that we have to then take a second
pass through the data to consolidate
consolidate all the information that's
spread out or divided amongst the
different threads so we'll go through
let's go through each of these so here's
the the share partition approach alright
so we have our data table we have three
columns and the first thing we're gonna
do is just divide up the data into
different chunks or morsels like we did
before and these are just ranges of data
we don't know actually what's in them
yet we just say you know the first
hundred two blows goes this thread the
next hundred - blows goes this other
thread so now say we wanted you to do a
join on column B so we'll take the value
of B and every single tuple and we're
gonna hash it with the same hash
function we're gonna use for the the
buildin probe phase so the we have to do
this because you have to make sure that
if we hash a key in one in one phase
that if we hashed that same key later on
we end up in the same location or in our
hash table or in our bucket to make sure
we can find the information that we're
looking for so we're gonna hash that and
we know that our patient's we're gonna
we're specified ahead of time so we're
just gonna mod that by the hash value by
the number of partitions and that'll
tell us what partition chain we're gonna
go into so now every thread is going to
write into for every single value of the
hash it and mod and that tell you which
one they go right into them
and so again this is a global - set of
buckets so every thread can be writing
into any any bucket at any time so we
just have to use a latch to protect the
the last place where you want to do an
insert I want you quite a lot then you
can insert a new value in there the
other approach again is with private
partitions same set up we revive the
data up amongst different threads and
they're just
threw a hatchet and then modify the
number petitions that we want to have
but what's gonna happen is each thread
has its own sort of group of buckets
that we saw in a previous slide so now
when I do my write into these different
buckets at each thread I'm the only
thread writing in there I don't need to
protect me two latches so this is gonna
go really really fast now once all the
threads are done then I have to do
combine everything together to create
that global partition of the space that
I had in the last slide so to do this I
can just have a bunch of the threads
each pick a separate you know partition
group of calls to different threads and
be responsible for populating this thing
so I in this case here I don't need
acquire latches when I do this
consolidation but I still have to take a
second path so thread two we'll go do
partition two and thread three do
Parchin three and so forth alright so
again this is also a good example of
where materialization issues can be are
important because I'm copying the data
twice at the copy the data once out of
the data table into my partition and
then out of the the private partition
into the combined partition so if I'm a
row store and I'm copying the entire
tuple of my two bolts very large then
this copy is expensive if it's a column
store and I'm all in copying the middle
amount of data they need to do to join
plus the offset well that can be much
smaller than the full size of the tuple
and therefore this copy can be you know
less pressure on the CPU caches and
memory and certainly potentially you
know less instructions okay so so that
was an example of the sort of the
non-blocking partition scheme let's talk
about now with the radix partitioning
approach and the idea here is that we're
doing the same kind of partitioning that
we saw before but we are being more
careful or more careful we are doing the
partition in such a way that we can we
can have the threads write two separate
locations in memory without how to take
latches but we have to wait
everyone finishes before we can move on
to the next phase because we don't know
what what else is missing and that'll
make more sense when we talk about I'm
gonna show the diagram so with the rate
of partitioning we're gonna take
multiple steps to go the multi step pass
over the each of the relation and so in
the first step we're going to scan
through and compute a histogram that's
going to tell us the number of tuples
we're gonna have her hand then we can
use that histogram to compute what is
called a Pixum that'll tell us at what
offset in our partition space should we
write a particular tuple then now we're
gonna go through and scan our again and
now do the hashing and based on where
we've defined where we turn to our
writes with a previous column then we
write into that the partition space so
again we'll go through each is one by
one so the first thing to point out to
also is that the term greatest
partitioning is is just means the digit
or a byte of the total key it's the same
rate X term that we saw when we talk
about radix treaties before right
instead of having the entire key I just
gonna hash or partition basement on a
chunk of it the prefix column is just a
way to do a again that determine what's
the starting location that we want to
write into our global global partition
buffer for each thread so let's let's
let's first understand what a prefix um
is so again the raid X is just the is
just a value of some digit within the
key all right so my keys are 89 12 2300
841 and 64 so the raid X at this first
position here for each of these keys
would be nine two three eight one four
and then the raid X for the next key is
just eight one two and so forth like
that so that's all that means with the
raid X partitioning we're going to look
at one digit within the key at a time
hash that figure that where that goes to
and then if you want to do additional
passes we could look at we could look at
Malton people get subsequent digits so
the in modern CPUs you can compute this
radix
pretty efficiently with this
multiplication instruction so this is
not it's not an expensive operation to
do this
so now with this radix the radix is of
these the keys we can compute what's
called the P Pixum and that's just a
running summation a running count of the
numbers and the position of the of the
prefix um in the output determined is
based on what keys came before it so I
have the keys 1 2 3 4 5 6 so for my
prefix um in the first position the
previous time was just 1 because it's
just there's no nothing that came before
it so it's just a value 1 but now for
the next position I'm gonna take the
value of the previous prefix some
computation and then the value of this
key and add them together and that's now
my prefix um for this position so 1 plus
2 is 3 same thing now I take this
position here 3 3 6 10 15 20 and 21 and
so forth like that and the reason why we
learn to do this is because now we can
use these these pick some to tell us
again what offset we want to write into
because we say like if I have one tuple
before me then I should start writing my
like my tuples that after position 1 but
then now this guy says I want to write
tuples in and he knows he just started
offset 3 these are essentially gonna be
used offsets within the partition array
so let's look at a dues rate of
partition so again the first step we
need to do is inspect the input keys and
crater histograms so say the output the
input keys that we're dealing with here
are already the that we've already
hashed it we've already modded by the
number of partitions that we have I just
a goodbye we haven't mired by number of
partitions we've we've hashed it and now
we want to look at the digits of the
hashes so what we're gonna do is look at
look at the the first digit here and for
each each thread you're just you're
going to stand through your assigned
range and compute what the histogram is
right so it's the number of values that
will appear at a particular partition so
in this case here for CPU 0 at partition
0 it had 2 entries 1 2 at partition 1 it
had 2 entries 1 2 like down here it has
at partition 0 it has one because
there's 1 0 there and then for partition
1 it has 3 1 2 3
I think we just compute this histogram
by scanning through the data efficiently
then now we're gonna do is compute the
offsets in our partition array that the
threads can all right into so we have to
block and wait until all the threads
complete their partition and then we now
compute the prefix um based on the
histograms that tell us where we're
gonna start writing in to where every
thread can write into this partition
array all right so be like this so
partition 0 for CPU 0 is right here and
the partition 0 for CPU 1 can write here
right so position 0 starts at position 0
because with the previous um petition 0
at CPU 1 but right here because it's
this value was 2 because the previous
column will be 3 so 1 2 3 and so forth
for the other one so now what does this
do for us this is now gonna give us a
giant array or giant buffer that the
threads can start writing into and they
don't need a coordinator acquire latches
to protect any any location in memory
when it does this right because it's
already computed the prefix own we
already know that nobody else will be
writing into our location so we can just
write into it just fine and we have to
maintain an internal counter in our CPU
to say oh 4 partitions 0 I've already
inserted you know one thing or two
things or 3 thing so using my starting
point I can then decide quickly at what
all set should I write my my new my next
piece of data into alright so now with
this this we've computed this this
partition output and the starting
location is where we do our rights now
we go back and do our scan again and now
we do our partitioning and now we're
copying in the values of the the keys
that we've hashed into our partition of
writing and again we can do this without
applying latches so now at a high level
the way to think about this is that
we've have we have partition 0 and
partition 1 and so at this point we can
then hand that off to the build phase or
and and start the computing the hash
table or if we wanted to we could start
dividing this up even further sub
partitioning again so that our chunk of
data in these partition can now fit into
a cache line or a small number of cache
lines all right and so to do that we
just go back now and do jump to the next
next radix right within this the next
radix value and this do this you know
partitioning all over again all right
but I would say in the in practice well
in practice most people don't do rate
partitioning although it is shown to be
superior and then the other few systems
that I knew that do this they're mostly
academic prototypes they almost never do
two passes is usually one pass and
you're done all right so now we have our
whether or not we done partitioning now
we enter the build phase and again the
idea here is that we're going to scan
the outer table either just in the
original table itself or if we partition
and then the partitions and then for
every single tuple we're gonna have
we're gonna hash it on the same key we
use in the partitioning phase and then
we're gonna store it into a hash table
right and ideally we wanted to design
our hash table such that the the size
every bucket that we're writing into is
going to be you know just a few cache
lines in size right because that's gonna
last a good go through things more
efficiently so we now need to discuss
what this actually hash tables gonna
look like right sort of said like oh
great the buckets we write into a hash
table will be a few cache lines well
what does that actually mean right what
what is what does our hash table
actually look like so
to understand what a hash table is we
need there's two main design decisions
typically when people say they have a
hash table it's sort of used colloquy
just to mean like the data structure
itself but in in in practices actually
commits a combination of these two
things the the hash function the hashing
scheme so the hash function is a way
we're going to take it take our key
that's in a larger domain alergic space
and we want to map it to a specific
location or slot in our in our hash
table data structure but it says like
you take all possible strings and you
want to have a hash function that can
then convert it into some integer that
we can then say you know within one to
ten or something some smaller range you
know what slot we're going to write into
so let's see in a second B we have this
contention between
having a hash algorithm that is fast and
also having a hash algorithm that has a
low collision rate because we want to
make sure that if we take two keys that
are distinct we don't want them to hash
to the same location but we want to be
able to compute that hash very quickly
the the second design decision is the
hashing scheme and this basically says
that after you've done the hashing if
now you have two keys that hash to the
same location meaning you have a
collision on that key how do you
actually deal with that and so again
there's trade-off between allocating a
ton of memory for a hash table so that
every possible cache P I ever see it's
guaranteed not to collide with any other
key but that would take a lot of memory
and so if I want to support collisions I
want to have my collision reconciliation
you know method or procedure being
efficient as possible so I don't you
know I'm not spending a lot of
computation time to find or insert a new
key again we'll cover each of these one
might want I will say though although
I'll present a bunch of different
approaches to doing hash tables or hash
functions every single database system
that I've ever talked to every company
that ever talked to they usually just
pick one they'll have a reason why they
picked it like oh we ran some benchmarks
and it seemed you know seemed to work
well and although in some cases some
hashing scheme might be better another
for different workloads of different
query types nobody as far as I know is
actually tries to be adaptive everyone
sort of picks one hash table or one hash
function and tries to make that be as
efficient as possible they don't try to
automatically adapt the hashing scheme
they're using based on what the query
the dataset looks like everyone just
sort of picks one and runs with it all
right so for hash functions again the
idea is that we want to take an
arbitrary key of any possible length an
impossible domain and then map it to a
smaller domain that we can then you know
use that to find a location in our hash
table so this means that although those
those hash functions out there that
provides security guarantees a
cryptographic hash functions or two-way
hash functions like I can encrypt
something and decrypt it we don't care
about any of that right we all the care
about is having an efficient one-way
hash with a locally generate and we'll
see what some examples are in the next
slide
so the the best way to understand this
trade-off between collision and
performance is think of the two extremes
so the fastest hash function you could
ever have is one where no matter what
key you give it you always return the
value one right that's like there's
there's no computation it's just you
know writing one to the staff or the the
output of the function and then you're
done but of course this means that the
collision rates can be terrible because
no matter what key I give it it always
comes back with value one so it's super
efficient but my collision rate will be
is bad on the other end of the spectrum
I can have what is called perfect
hashing where it's a magic hash function
that no matter what key you give it it's
guaranteed to always produce a unique
hash key so again these exist in the
literature or in theory in practice and
nobody actually implements them because
typically the way you actually implement
them is do you need to know all the keys
ahead of time and you you would then
build it with it the mapping function
with a with a hash table itself so you
would need a hash table to in order to
have a hash table which sort of defeats
the purpose of having you know an
efficient hash table so again these are
the two extremes we want something in
between so the you know this is sort of
active development area for both
research and for companies and startups
and sort of hackers in general so
there's this benchmark created by the
murmur to hash guy call it SM hasher and
this is sort of a benchmark suite that
has measurements to determine the
performance and collision rate of a
bunch of hash functions so if you're
interesting this kind of stuff you can
go check out his blog or the game page
for this but I want to focus quickly on
just sort of five high level hash
functions that you see often in the wild
CRC was originally developed in the
1970s to do error code detection for in
networking there's now on on modern CPUs
there's there's built-in instructions to
do CRC very efficiently I think in the
slides I'll show the next slide
I don't think I'm using those
instructions actually I'm pretty sure
I'm not so if you just use the algorithm
you get a software-based here I see it's
gonna be really slow you use the
instructions it'll go faster murmur hash
was this random dude on the internet who
said hey here's this hash function
I developed that's general-purpose that
well as fast a bunch of people seem to
like it they picked up picked it up and
sort of expanded upon it or modified it
and in particular which Google City hash
was based on member hash but they
designed it for their for their
environment where they wanted to do how
efficient hashing for short keys
there's the Facebook xx hash which is
considered to be the state of the art
now I this is from the same guy at
Facebook that inveteracy standard of the
compression again this is sort of doing
it's just you know the mathematical
variation of the of the methods being
used in member hash and then farm hash
is a newer version of City hash that's
designed to have better collision rates
for larger keys so there's also in 2016
there was a highway hash from Google but
that that has like guarantees for sort
of the encrypted you know cryptographic
analysis and you can't leak any data
from from the hash functions again we
don't care about that in our hash table
because is it this we're using this hash
function internally it's not exposed to
the outside world so this is just a
benchmark that I run every year where
it's it's not SM hasher it's it's a
different type of workload we're just
trying to measure the throughput rate
you can have for these different hash
functions
so again CRC 64 I think this is just all
software based actually I should rewrite
that to be use the harbor instructions
but that the main takeaway here is a
common common thing you'll see is that
you have key sizes of either 32 or 64 64
bits that it's 30 32 and 64 bytes you
don't see like super large keys and this
just sure just showing that there's if
you have if you have key sizes that are
aligned to cache lines then these
algorithms can form more efficiently so
the sort of the salt to the patterns is
when you have
is when you start going through the next
cache line you pay that penalty so the
main takeaway here is that again X X
hash 3 is considered to be the fastest
and then followed by by city has some
farm hash I think this is an older
version of murmur hash 3 I think there
might be a newer version that would be
it would could perform better but again
in our own system we use excess hash 3
because that pin this determines that
things are
this shows that thing it's it's much
better ok so let's talk about now
hashing schemes again the hashing scheme
is is what we handled collision so where
our hash function says this key should
hash to this bucket or this slot in our
in our data structure and something's
are being there how do we deal with it
right so what's up well and so I was
I'll say - these are also for the most
part except for chain hashing these are
static hashing schemes meaning I'm gonna
size the hash table before I actually do
anything with it so I sort of have a
rough approximation of how many keys I'm
gonna have to store in my hash pump or
hash table and if now I have a collision
that I can't reconcile because there's
no free space based on on the protocol
I'm using I then have to resize it and
the way you typically resize it is just
you double the size and rehash
everything and put it back in chain
hashing you can just extend the hash
chain which I'll show in the next slide
indefinitely but but this can then
generate to a to ask when to scan when
you do lookups if everything hashes to
the same chain so chain hash tables
people think about when they think about
a hash table I think this is what you
get in in Java when you say you want a
hash map class and the idea is that
there's a there's an array of pointers
to chains and I take my key I hash it
that tells me what offset I want to look
at in my my chain and then I can I can
jump to that location right and so the
way we're going to resolve collisions is
that if two keys map to the same chain
we're just gonna sort them into the same
bucket and if my bucket gets full then I
just extend it allocate a new bucket and
I added to my linked list so again the
chain can grow
infinitely and if everything hashes at
the same location then doing any look of
a sasquatch will scan all right so let's
look at a quick example so ignore this
for now but like here's our buckets
again so within each bucket we have two
slots so I take my first key I'm gonna
hash it and the it's gonna match this
bucket here this bucket is empty so I
can insert my key into the first slot so
the thing to point out here though is
that we want to store both the hash of
the key as well as the original key and
the reason why we want to store the hash
is because now if we're gonna do a
comparison to see does a exist if we
already have the hash we can do that
comparison very quickly with just
integers but if this key is like a bar
chart or something larger then we
obviously need to make sure that this
thing we have this original key so we
can determine what wave of people false
positive but we keep this one as well so
that we can do that lookup more
efficiently so a goes here we can write
to that first location B B goes here I
can write to that location C goes here
right match to the same bucket this slot
is empty so can write into there but now
D wants to write into this bucket but
the two slots are full so all we need to
do is now allocate a new bucket add a
pointer from the first bucket to the
second bucket in our linked list and now
we can add in D same thing for E this
bucket is full we follow the chain and
go here and now we can write E and then
F gets written down here so again now if
I want to do a lookup say find me key D
D would would hash to this bucket I
would do a sequential scan within the
bucket looking in every single key
typically you do with the hash first cuz
that'll be more efficient if I don't
find a match then I know I need to and
there's there's if I don't find a match
in the bucket I'm at and there's a
pointer to it the next bucket they
didn't need to jump over here and
continue my special scan
so one interesting optimization you can
do with the slot array is instead of
throwing these as 64-bit pointers or you
store the store pointers at 64 bits
because that's what Intel hardware tells
you you have to do but Intel action
doesn't use all 64 bits for every
address you know actually
uses 48 bits so in the case of hyper
what they do is they actually store for
all these pointers they store a bitmap
I'm sorry a bloom filter that says
here's all the keys that exist in my
chain so now what I can do is when I do
a hash and I say I should go to this
bucket and I look at this point in to
tell me where I need to go there's
actually gonna be a bloom filter inside
of it that we then check to see whether
the key I'm looking for is actually
gonna exist in my blue footer because
the bloom filter will give you it won't
give you false negatives but it could
give me false positives so could tell
you this key exists and when it actually
doesn't you have to go scan and find it
just to see that it doesn't exist but if
it doesn't exist in your key then this
thing would be guaranteed to say it
doesn't exist so you don't actually need
to follow the chain you just need to
look at this bloom filter so I think for
this reason the the hyper guys say that
the hash chain hash table is to peer to
all other hash tables if you do this one
trick the problem though is although I
can agree with that the problem is that
the Intel's not guaranteed to only use
60 48 bits for all pointers in the
future right it's some late appointment
may say all right well now use all 64
bits and then this thing doesn't work so
then maybe they could just store the 16
bit bloom filter and Pat it out sort of
like the the Judi fat pointers we saw
with the Judea Ray's you could store
that on the slot array well alright the
so chain hashing is pretty common in
data structure used in database systems
for joins though most of the time you
see a linear probe hash table because
it's so simple and just ends up being
more efficient so with leaner probe hash
table I think it's a giant table of
slots and I'm gonna hash my key and I'm
gonna mod it by the number of slots that
I have and that's when tell me where to
jump to find the memory address of the
slot that I want so when I want to do an
insert if nothing exists in that slot
then I can just go ahead and write into
it if something does exist then I need
to scan down in going from the top to
the bottom from that slot location and
look at all the slauson's wife
one that is empty and then I can go
ahead and insert my value in it now this
means that when I wanted to do a lookup
to find my key I'm gonna slaughter jump
to that same location and I have to
start looking to see whether the key I'm
looking for is actually there that's
because I don't know if it's got if it's
not actually in a slot that it should
hash to it maybe below that I need to
scan through until I find it
or I find the empty slot which tells me
that the key doesn't exist so this is
look an example does say again I want to
put these keys in here first one we hash
a we modded by the number of slots and
that tells us we want to write into here
that's fine nothing was already in there
we can go ahead and do that now I want
to do hash on B I can write this slot
nothing's there so we're done now I want
to do an insert on C C hashes to this
slot location but a already exists so I
can't store it here I'm gonna store it
at the next empty slot I can find which
is just the one below it so again now if
I want to do a lookup on C I would hatch
here C a and that I would see the key a
that's not the one I'm looking for
so then I scan down till I find either
an empty slot or the key that I want in
this case here I would find see in the
next location now with DD hashes in this
location again we can't write it because
into there because C's are two here so
we write it the next one he wants to
write to a we can't do that
we can't write to the next one Karen do
the next one and keep going till we find
our empty slot like that F like likewise
Wright State what's right here but it
can't so goes go to the next one so the
thing you got to keep track of with this
is if I do a lookup or an insert I need
to keep track of what was my starting
location into the slot array of for this
table because if I loop back around
trying to find the thing I'm looking for
or empty slot and I and I come back to
my starting point then I know my hash
table is full and there's no more free
spaces for me to insert something all
right the key I'm looking for is not
there then I have to again rehash
everything and by doubling the size or
buildin hash table doubling the size and
rehashing everything so again trying to
pick out the right hash table size can
be tricky and we'll see and a few more
lectures how this can be problematic if
you don't get the if you don't estimate
things correctly in the first
so the other interesting thing about
this data structure and we'll see some
variations in in the next slides is that
it's gonna penalize the the collision
scheme who's going to penalize both
inserts and lookups in the same way so
in the case of this one here I want to
insert E and I had to jump down to four
slots into stored here if now I want to
do a look-up on e I'm gonna pay that
same penalty because I'm gonna hash here
and I have to scan down until I find an
empty slot of the key that I'm looking
for so there's nothing in this collision
scheme or this hashing scheme that
prefers making inserts be faster or
making different buffers making lookups
be faster in a hash join depending on
whether the the the the size of the of
the inner table versus the average of
depending on that ratio you may want to
choose a different collision scheme that
makes inserts go faster if the the outer
table is bigger or loves lookups go
faster if the inner table is larger but
again as I said as far as I know most
energy systems don't don't switch up
it's always pick one scheme and
oftentimes this one is the simplest one
and important in that feature shows that
this performs the best okay so the we've
already talked about this you know in
order to reduce the number of wasteful
comparisons we have to do we want to
avoid collisions on hash keys of course
that entirely depends on how good our
collision rate is per hash function and
one way to avoid it entirely is that we
can just have a huge hash table with two
EPs a number of slots we expect to have
so that every single time you hash your
key and put it into the data structure
it's there's nothing going to be in the
slot that is trying to write too but
again you pay that penalty of allocating
more memory for your hash table so how
do I get balanced this correctly is not
trivial so let's look at some variations
of linear probe hashing that do try to
switch the dynamic or switch the penalty
between insert
and lookups by changing how the
collision the collision protocol we're
going to use so one approach is called
Robin Hood hashing and the idea here is
that when we do an insert if we find
that the slot we want to insert into is
already occupied then we look to see
whether the key that exists in the slot
we want to write to is farther away from
its home slaughter it's not where it
should be then where our key is and if
it isn't then we're gonna steal it slot
and force it that other key we just we
just evicted to go to a new location
so it's called Robin Hood hashing
because the idea is that we're gonna
have Porky's steal from that we're gonna
steal from the rich keys and give the
slots to the poor keys and again this
the the wealth of a key is based on how
many hops you are you are away from your
your big the position the optin position
for you where you should be in the table
all right so this is an old technique it
was virtually published in a tech report
in or in a public paper in 1985 it sort
of was lost or not lost or like really
didn't get any attention until recent
years and particularly this showed up on
Hacker News a couple years ago and now
sort of this is there are a few systems
that actually using this although I will
say the research shows that this is
actually a bad idea
because you pay a penalty of just
copying and moving is expensive all
right so let's say it's the same skin
keys we want to have before again Robin
hashing is an a variation on lunar probe
hashing so it's just a giant slot array
we start off by hashing a that goes here
just like before but now in addition
just drawing the hash in the original
key we're also going to store the number
of jumps that this key is from its
optimal position and the optimal
position is determined by where it
should have been or what was the first
location that we jumped to when we did
our initial hash right like if you were
looking for this key and used this hash
you
hash function where could you find it
immediately assuming there wasn't any
other collisions saying they would be
now bu hashes up here it sits in this
optima position so it's the number hops
it is from away from its where it should
be zero but now we're gonna hash C C's
gonna land in the same position where a
is so now we need to look at to see
whether we should evict whatever is in
the slot we want to go into or should we
leave it alone and and jump down to the
next slot just like a linear program so
this first jump here the a is a is zero
hops away from its its optimal position
and C is zero hops from its original
position so C will leave a alone all
right because they're considered
equivalent so then now it'll jump down
here this flop is empty so now we'll
store C in here so now this is saying
that C is one hop away from where it
should have been originally D comes
along here D wants to go where C is
located C as a has a hop cost of or a
hop distance of one therefore 1 is
greater than 0 for D because D of D is 0
steps if we could go here so in this
case here C is considered more poor than
D so D will leave C alone and then we
jump down here and we write D now we
write e egh wants to go where a is you
can't do that a a 0 is equal to e 0 so
we leave it alone then we come down here
and at this point E is now one hop away
from where it should be but oh so is C
so they're also equivalent so we leave
those alone but then we get here and now
he is two hops away from where it should
be and D is only one hop away so so D
considered more rich or more wealthy
than e so easily slot insert its key in
and then now the thread continues on and
figures out the next location to put D
which is the next empty slot and then
now D is two hops away foam from where
it should be and then now we get to F F
go where where D is but it can't do that
so then it goes down here so again the
idea here is that we're amortize ingush
stealing the slots and reinserting key
that are already in the table the ideas
that were amortized
of any given key by having each key be
closer to the where they should have
been originally so going going back here
with with e under um regularly no
problem
II what it ends up here and do you
everyone left alone here so II would
have been three three hops away from
from its original location and D would
have been left left knowing with with at
one hop away but on a Robin Hood they
both end up being two hops away so who
on average you're saying the lookups are
roughly equivalent across all keys so
that you don't have one key you know
take take much longer than other ones so
this seems like a decent idea alright
see if this seems kind of interesting
but the research literature shows that
it is bad because this was stealing the
keys is terrible for you know cache
performance and so it makes the inserts
so much more expensive that any benefit
you get from doing the the lookup for
making the fines go faster is completely
negated now for a hash join you know
we're building these ephemeral hash
tables where we insert them do our
probes and in the bill phase or so the
pro phase and then throw it away if your
data structure might be longer living
like you build the hash table and then
you keep doing the lookups over to again
then this approach actually might might
be preferable for perhaps joins it won't
be another technique is called hopscotch
hashing which came out in 2008 from
Maurice Hurley who used to be factor
here at CMU and now he's a professor at
Brown and so the idea here is that
rather than letting a rather than
letting a key change position like in
Robin Hood nashing to any possible
location in the in the in the slot array
we're going to bound how far they can go
into what's called a neighborhood so
neighborhood we defined as a a
contiguous range of slots that a key is
allowed to it
and it can exist anywhere in in that in
this neighborhood so if you're looking
for a key and you look at this where it
should be in this neighborhood and it's
not there then you know the key doesn't
exist so you bound how far you actually
have to scan through so the size the
neighborhood is being configurable I
forget what the ritual paper says but in
for this example here we'll use a key
size our neighborhood size of three so
again it's just linear probing so we
haven't we have our slot array and so
the first neighborhood for this first
position here will be size of three so
one two three
but the neighbourhoods are overlapping
so for the next one and the next one so
forth right there they have a portion of
the previous neighborhood in their
neighborhood and you would do this all
the way down so now let's say I want to
start and start inserting these keys so
just like before I want to start a it's
it would go in here and its neighborhood
is it's three three slots so I can sort
it anywhere that I want and practice
though you've just inserted it into the
first location if it's empty right and
we're done then we do an insert for B
same thing we go to the first location
in this neighborhood and we're done but
now we want to start at C C should go
where a is but it can because a is
occupying so we say we need to find the
next empty slot in our neighborhood to
insert into into all right so we just do
it now sequential scan down till we find
up for empty slot let me go ahead and
serve ourselves like that's so far this
is the same thing as linear program now
I want to start D D you should go where
C is against crunch we'll scan down to I
find that and then I got certain there
but now I want to start e ninis going in
this neighborhood but as I do my
sequential scan I would find that all
these these slots in my neighborhood are
occupied so now I need to go outside my
neighborhood and find the first free
slot which happens to be here and so now
what I want to do is I wanted to
determine whether I can swap in reverse
order any key or any key my previous
neighborhood that I'm trying to get into
with the this empty slot and that way I
could then insert my key into my
neighborhood and the idea here is it to
make sure that we bound whatever key
we're moving
to make sure that it is in our slot here
so in case of D ID should belong here
so it's neighborhood are these two
things one two three so it's okay for D
to them get moved down here and then we
can hash e and put it into our
neighborhood and then we're done it now
I insert F F should go where D is its
neighborhood or these two and this one
could be wraparound and in this case
here I can just scan down I find a the
free slot and I get started alright so
how this works is that you have to
maintain some metadata about in every
neighborhood about what keys are in them
or what what neighborhood I belong to so
you can make make a determination of if
all my keys in my neighborhood that I'm
trying to get into Perl occupied are all
belong in my neighborhood then I have to
I have to double the size the hashing on
the Builder and rebuild it so the idea
here is we're bounding how much we have
to look to find a free slot to just be
local in my neighborhood and if I can't
in turn anything in my neighborhood or
not finding a I'm looking for in my
neighborhood then I don't need
potentially scan the entire thing so
just so it's a variation I think a robin
hood hashing where you're bounding how
much you know how you bounded the
insertion search space and they look up
space alright
the last hash to mean what about our
cuckoo hashing and this is me different
than all the other ones where we are if
we hash something we you know you're not
guarantee that the slot you jump first
lot you jump into it's gonna be exactly
the thing you know it will be exactly
where your key can be found in the case
of hopscotch hashing it would be in the
neighborhood in the case of linear
probing or Robin Hood hashing you have
to keep scanning down till you find the
key looking for odie find empty space
but with cuckoo hashing when you hash
you deal with lookup and you're
guaranteed either the key doesn't exist
or the first place that you jump into
will be the key that you want this is
the way they can achieve this is that
they're gonna maintain multiple hash
tables simultaneously each of their own
hash function so now when I want to do
an insert I hash it multiple times and I
see whether I can insert it into any
free slot and any my tables if now that
slot is being on
then I'm gonna steal that slot take that
key out and then have that that key I
Vic tada rehash that and put that into
another table the idea is that you could
have this thing changing changing one
hash table a key you could have a key
that already been inserted change its
hash table multiple times
you
what is this
[Music]