[Music]
[Applause]
today we'll be talking about query
optimization this is a really important
topic in database systems so again I'm
here in my house I have the terior over
there whose be asking questions as we go
along so when we say a query
optimization the idea at a high level is
that we want to take a query that's
written in a declarative language like
sequel and we want to then translate
that into a execution plan that the
database system can execute and so with
query optimization the idea is that we
want to find a correct execution plan
that will have potentially the lowest
cost so the two words that I'm
emphasizing here are correct and cost
correct is kind of obvious it doesn't
help us if we find a really fast plan
that ends up computing the wrong answer
returning the wrong result for our query
like that doesn't help us at all
and the term cost is in quotes because
the cost is going to be this relative
metric that's not necessarily tied to a
real-world metric it's just something
that's that the data system would say
this is the best query for me to execute
so the cost could be in terms of
execution time in terms of monetary cost
after running this on a page you go
cloud system it could be in memory usage
that could be could be any possible
thing but at a high level it's you know
some objective function that the the
database system knows that it wants to
optimize for so the query optimizer is
going to be the hardest part we're gonna
have to touch or a component we're gonna
have to implement in the database system
because finding a you know optimal near
optimal query is going to be super
challenging it's gonna day it's proven
to be a np-complete problem so this
means that although the name of the
component we're going to build is is you
called the query optimizer were almost
never gonna be able to find the optimum
plan because it would just take too long
to look at all possible solutions for
all possible query plans and pick the
best one so what these upcoming lectures
are really about are the techniques that
we'll use to simplify the and reduce the
search space so that it's not an
exhaustive search and techniques we can
use to estimate what the plan cost will
be without actually having to really
execute it so let's make more sense as
we go further along and we talk about
cost models but the way to think about
this is if we need to ask me what is the
cost of one of executing one query plan
to get that true cost we could just
execute the query but now if you want to
look at thousands and thousands of
possible different query plans that's
not feasible for us to do so we need a
way to estimate it and this cost thing
is also going to be a internal metric
that the data system uses to determine
whether one plan is better or not better
better than another and it may not
necessarily be tied to you know the wall
clock time our real cost so this is just
sort of just set us up but what we mean
when we when we start to mount query
optimization the for the next three
weeks would have discussing a lot of
different things in this in this four
query optimization so that I said as I
said the end of last class I will fully
admit that query optimization is the the
one aspect of database systems that I
know the least about and I'm always
trying to learn more and so this year
we've expanded the discussion to include
an extra lecture on sort of extra query
optimization methods beyond the
traditional two method two approaches
that we'll talk about in this lecture in
the next lecture so where we're going
for the next three weeks over the next
four lectures is that we'll spend time
the beginning talking about how to
implement a query optimizer essentially
what does the search strategy could look
like this so that sort of the search
engine inside of it look like then we'll
talk about how to do plan rewriting
query rewriting plan enumeration and
then we'll talk about sort of
more sort of sophisticated techniques to
do at adaptive query optimization and
we'll finish up with talking about cost
models so I'll briefly touch on what all
cost model is I think a little bit in
this lecture but that'll be sort of the
end thing to say well after we design
all this the search stuff that we're
talking about here the cost model is
already used to guide that search so the
for today we're mostly talking about
optimization search strategies because
that's sort of them one of the two main
parts you need to have and then that'll
then segue into these these other these
other topics so for today again as I
said well start talking about search
strategies because that's the most
important thing and that's sort of the
basis of what you need to actually
implement a query optimizer and then
we'll go through the different
approaches people have tried to building
a query optimizer over the last 50 40 50
years and then that'll motivate why we
want to use a more sophisticated dynamic
programming technique or the Cascades
technique that you guys are read about
for next class so today is sort of like
a bunch of background information that
then leads up up into the the modern
implementations so at a high level the
the the the the stack of the system that
we're talking about and what I've sort
of referred to the front of the system
is gonna look like this and this is the
part that we're talking about now in our
system so we start with a sequel query
that the application sends us we can
first pass that into a sequel rewriter
which means that will transform the
sequel string itself to annotate it or
modify it in a certain way and this is
this is optional not all systems have
this you see this sometimes in
middleware systems that are doing
sharding and sometimes can rewrite the
sequel query to to add in you know go to
this table or I'm sorry go to this this
node versus that node but this is sort
of this is like sequel query in sequel
query out there just modifying the
sequel query then we take the sequel
query run it through our sequel parser
and then that will spit
out a abstract syntax tree that just has
the tokens the string tokens of the
query I wouldn't have the token of the
table name of the column names and so
forth and then now we pass us into the
binder which does lookups in the system
catalog of the database system to map
the table names in in the the reference
in the query of the column names that
represent the query into eternal
internal identifier so this is allows
you to get like the the the the type of
the columns whatever constraint you have
in those columns and so forth so then
the binder would then spit out what is
now called a logical plan so this is a
high-level description of what the query
wants to do right sorry I have a select
query that wants to access table foo my
logical plan will be to say scan table
foo doesn't say how I want to scan it it
just says I want to access it then we
can take that logical plan and pass it
into a another optional step called the
tree rewriter and this is again logical
plan in logical plan out these are think
of these as like heuristics we can apply
to manipulate the structure of the tree
for some optimizations that we know we
always want to do if we don't need to
estimate the cost of the change we want
to make so like we can like a predicate
push down here or sometimes you see
rewriting view queries or CT ease into
nested queries this way again this is
entirely optional then we now feed this
into our optimizer
and at a high level we'll be calling you
know we'll be focusing on a cost based
query optimizer right where we have some
cost estimates that are based on
statistics that we've collected from the
database itself that allow us to predict
or estimate you know what's the
execution time of a particular query
plan and then again this is where we can
enumerate a bunch of options and choose
the one plan that that we think is gonna
have the lowest cost and so once the
optimizer is done with this step then it
fits out a fit spits out a physical plan
that would go off and execute it now in
the case of our system and then we talk
about query compilation we take that
physical plan
and then we use we have cogeneration to
convert it into a domain-specific
language that we then compiled into
machine code but other systems you can
take this physical plan and start
interpreting it annex to name right away
I said this is this is at a high level
whoever going for today and the upcoming
lectures so we're mostly gonna be
focusing on these two parts here the
tree tree writer and the optimizer for
sequel rewriting as I said that's mostly
done not really doing that for
optimization as you're doing it for like
redirecting queries or yeah it's most of
them is like control playing stuff not
necessarily for execution stuff the
binder there's not really any magic you
do there it's looking up rickie form you
know looking up cable names and things
like that all right so let's now discuss
this distinction between the logical and
physical plan because this is going to
come up multiple times when we talk
about query optimizer so the essentially
what the optimizer is trying to do is
trying to map a logical algebra
expression of the query itself into a
equivalent physical algebra expression
so as I said like the logical plan would
say I want to access table food the
physical plan would say access table
through using index you know XYZ for
access table food using a square scan or
binary search on the actual table itself
I said is it that high little bit the
distinction is that the physical plan
tells you how you actually want to
execute a you know the query itself but
the logical plan says that this is what
I want the query result of beam so the
the physical plant operators themselves
it's gonna have low level information
that is specific to the physical
properties and the physical format of
the data that they're accessing so in
some cases the physical operators will
know that it's producing a data that's
sorted on a given column or no that's
gonna be operating on data that's
compressed in a certain way it maybe
needs to decompress it into another way
the logical plan has no notion of this
it just knows about relations
so one important thing we'll see and
this will come up when we talk about
Cascades the next class is that the
there's not always going to be a
one-to-one mapping from logical
operators to physical operators so I
mean that is like in the case of like
access table foo I can imagine
easily how that would be mapping the
logical operator to access table food to
a you know a sequential scan to access
table foo that would be one-to-one but
sometimes we'll have logical operators
that can then expand into multiple
physical operators and likewise you can
take a multi logical operators and and
coalesce them into a single physical
operator it depends on the
implementation of the database system
usually you see the logical operators
being exploded into more operators
that's more common than the other way in
my opinion like I actually take that
back right so a logical join with a
logical order by could be merged into a
physical sort merge-join
because you're doing this you know doing
the join and the order by together all
right so a another portent aspect about
what we're doing here relies on this
notion of relational algebra
equivalencies again this is something
that we've covered it in the
introduction class last semester but the
basic idea is that since we know the
commutativity and associativity a chance
transitivity properties of relational
algebra expressions we know we can
define rules that allows to do
transformations of the query plan in
such a way that we know that the end
result is equivalent to the original
plan so in this case here if I'm doing
natural joins between tables a B and C
and if I join B and C first then take
the result of that joint and now join it
with a well that's equivalent to me
joining a and C first and then taking
the output of that and joining B and I
can do this because this is an inner
join or a natural join where I have the
commutativity property I can reorder
them any way I want left out or joined
you can't quit you can't do that because
they're asymmetric whereas these things
they're symmetrical so I can flip these
around in any order I want so now you
can kind of see what the optimizer is
actually going to try to
is if it knows it needs to join table a
B and C together it's gonna try to
figure out what is the correct correct
ordering I should do for you know
joining B and C first or joining a and C
first and so forth
hey can use a cost model to estimate
which of these join orderings is going
to be most efficient then now you can
think about the physical operators as
well I can now decide what what
algorithm do i when you use to actually
do this joint go I'm gonna do the sort
merge stuff we talked about before do I
want to do my parallel hash join so
forth so for these lectures are most of
you focusing on analytical queries
because in this world the the the
difficulty or challenge in finding an
apple query plan is much much much
greater than doing in this for all to be
workloads or transaction processing
workloads and this is because most the
time the the queries and ultimate
workloads are considered to be what is
called sorrel and Sarge will just shorts
is a acronym for the search argument
able some term they made up in the 80s I
don't know why whatever and for these
Sargent queries the reason why it
they're going to be easy for us to be
query planning on is because in old
people workloads you're almost always
doing lookups on on you know a small
number of tables at a time and you
usually have index defined on the
attributes you're trying to do lookup
lookups on in these tables so the many
times the the challenge is just trying
to pick what is the best index for me to
use for this particular query alright so
say I have a simple table foo has two
columns and a name an entry ID and name
ID is the primary key so if I have a
query that comes along that doesn't you
know there's an equality predicate where
ID equals one two three there's not
really any complex search I need to do
to figure out what the best access
method is to access table foo here I
just look at my catalog and say well I
know I'm doing an equality predicate on
an ID field I have a primary key on the
ID so therefore it has to have an index
so I know in this case here
I just use that index to do the to do
the lookup and I don't need it you know
even consider what we all possible
indexes I want to choose
likewise for for for joins they're
almost always going to be an OTP setting
on a foreign key some applications are
not well designed so you they they may
have not defined a foreign key sometimes
you see sort of the applications written
by people may not know what they're
doing databases so clearly it should be
a foreign key but they just didn't
confine it that way in the scheme um but
even then you still figure it out put it
fairly easily but in this case here like
if you have a foreign key relationship
and you know I have a small cardinality
yeah it's gonna be an index to enforce
that that that referential integrity in
the parent table so again when you
wanted your join it's it's pretty easy
to pick out like the the parent table
should be out at our table and then the
inner table is the foreign key child and
I'm doing the nested loop index probe
alright and this loop index join to join
these two tables together so again in
this environment for ot queries it's
usually pretty simple to do query
planning and you can get by doing simple
the simple heuristics based optimizer
which we'll talk about in a second
MongoDB is probably the most famous
database system out around today that
still uses the sort of basic heuristic
to do things like this because in the
type of workload that they originally
were targeting they weren't doing
complex joins because they didn't really
had joins until only a few years ago so
in this world they could get by with
simple heuristics all right so I also
talked briefly about cost estimation the
beginning again the idea here is that we
have we have a query comes in we have a
logical plan and we want to figure out
what's the best physical plan to execute
to represent for that that logical plan
and so we have to use a Cost Estimator
to predict what that you know what won't
be the execution cost of executing that
that physical plan or one of the
physical plans and then we can use that
to determine which physical plan is
preferable
to the other one so there's a bunch of
things we could use to figure out what
should be our or cost we can look at to
see how the queries gonna interact with
other queries running at the same time
that's actually pretty tricky and few
systems actually do this real common
thing is to say well what's the enemy
its size what's the output size of all
my operators and certainly use that as a
proxy for what resources I'll use it
could be just like the asymptotic
analysis of the algorithms we're using
for our physical operators but we know a
hash join is gonna be more efficient or
it you have incur less you know less iOS
or less overhead then a nested loop join
right so we can bake that into our
contest modes how much CPU or memory I'm
gonna use and then some information
about what does the data actually look
like like where is it physically located
how is it compressed like all these
things we can incorporate into our cost
models to make estimates on what will be
the the cost of executing a physical
plan now this is super hard to do
because you're estimating based on a
summarization of what the data looks
like because again I can't scan the
table and say how many tuples you have
it what's the distribution of these
values because you might as well just
execute the query and for really large
databases that's not feasible so you're
trying to estimate this as quickly as
possible because you want to you want to
evaluate as many physical plans as you
can quickly as possible so that you
maybe find the optimal one so there
should be not next week but in two weeks
well we'll discuss more about cost
models and we'll see how wrong they
actually actually get and this can make
lead an optimizer make bad decisions all
right so let's talk about now how to
actually build an optimizer so the
there's some first design situations we
need to consider before we can actually
say what is the search strategy that
we're going to use to enumerate plans
and look for a
an optimal plan so we're gonna go to
each of these topics one by one but an
optimization granularity will be the you
what are we what's the scope of what
we're looking at when we do query
planning when we five days off had a
handle player prepare schemas plan
stability and then when to finish the
search so again we'll go to each of
these so the optimization granularity is
what is the scope of the search problem
that the optimizer is gonna have to deal
with and the choices are to either do it
on a single query or do it with multiple
queries so single query is the most
common approach because oftentimes this
is all that you really have like a
client of misconnection sends a sequel
query you're not gonna wait around to
see what other queries show up from
other connections you take that one
query and you run it through the
optimizer at that point in time right
and the advantage of doing this is that
you're gonna have obviously a much much
potentially much smaller search space
because you're only dealing that one
query at a time you typically also don't
reuse the search results across queries
so you're essentially starting the
search from scratch every single time
now we can talk about some techniques in
adaptive query optimization had a had a
bridge information you've learned from
one search to the next but typically
most database systems don't do this the
other aspect of it is like if you want
to start figuring out like how much
resources I'm gonna use when actually my
query you may have to consider what
other queries running at the same time
so again like if you can do those
multiple queries but if you're doing the
single you do the single pretty much
easily that you do with multiple queries
because you don't have to worry about
what those multiple queries how they're
interfering with each other at the same
time multiple queries as I said is more
rare this would be like if I know I'm
gonna execute a thousand queries in my
application right now rather than me
issuing them one at one after another
like issue one executed get the result
issued the next one I could in theory
give the database system a batch of
queries and have it figure out a single
plan for the into all those queries that
it just executes and
knows how to route the requests route
data between operators that are shared
or not shared and produce the output for
those individual queries that I said
this mostly appears may be the sort of
stream processing systems or continues
continues query systems where I haven't
queries that it was gonna run forever
because there's some you know pipe of
data coming in all the time and I'm and
I'm processing them it did appear in
academic system mr. precision cost-share
DB that does something similar
materialized views are another way to
sort of this but as I said this is for
most applications this is not the
interface there this is not how they're
gonna interact with the data system
they're gonna do it this way open a
connection and send my query the
optimizer takes it plans and runs it the
next question got to deal with is when
are we actually going to fire off the
query optimizer so so this first one
again this is the most common one this
is static optimization would be the
query shows up in the system I've run it
through my optimizer I generate a plan
for that query and then once I leave the
optimizer I never go back to the
optimizer and I just go and execute the
query so it doesn't matter it's like I
so at the time at the optimizer it's
picking what it thinks is the best plan
but it may turn out to be one actually
run the query it it's not as good as I
thought it was I thought it was but I
can't go back like it's sort of it's a
static plan once the optimizer says this
is what you're gonna use you're stuck
with it all right so now the as we
talked about many times the the quality
of these plans will generate will be
highly dependent on the cost model
accuracy that's truly true for
everything but it has to be in this case
here is that you can't go back and tell
the optimizer you're wrong then you told
me something to eat what you told me was
wrong you know pick something better you
you you know you're more dependent maybe
then these other ones here now the other
thing you can deal with too is instead
of having to run this optimizer for
every single query over and over again
especially if it's in the same query you
can amortize this cost using prepared
statements and potentially you know have
a longer time the new query planning
than you would wouldn't normally
otherwise we'll talk about
the cutoff threshold for for the search
of the other parts in a second but think
about this is like you know when I open
up Postgres every time I see coal
whatever terminal I'm using for my data
system I tape a single query in I hit
enter and then I get back a result like
in that time it's gonna run through the
optimizer and generate you know a
physical plan then actually execute the
query and in some cases the queries can
run in in milliseconds so if I have a
bull or comets query that I don't want
to have it you know
you know I'm gonna actually this all the
time and therefore I want to spend some
extra time to do a better job looking
for an optimum plan I can potentially do
that with prepared statements we'll come
to that in a few more slides another
approach that is as far as I know this
doesn't really exist in sort of
relational sequel based database systems
today it mostly shows up potentially in
in stream processing systems but it
might be wrong and the idea here is that
my query shows up I generate logical
plan for it don't want to restart our
generate a logical plan for it and then
I break that plan up into sort of sub
groups of sub plans and before I execute
a sell plan then I run it through the
optimizer to generate the physical plan
and then I execute it and then now I'm
going to learn some information of what
the output of that sub plan will be that
I can then use to guide the optimizer to
find then the next cell plan our next
pipeline I want X dude I could have it
then generate physical plan using the
information I've collected and running
the first one you're sort of iteratively
building up the physical plan by going
back and forth between the execution
engine and the optimizer right so this
is this is rare Ike again I don't think
any commercial system actually does this
approach we'll see in the SEC angrist
actually does this and there it wasn't
so much they were doing this approach
before because they were sophisticated
it's because they were limited to the
sophistication of what the of what they
actually do in the software and the
query planner at the time but I think it
is
exist in academic systems but again I
don't think it exists in any commercial
systems the the last one that does this
one actually does exist in commercial
systems today is this idea called
adaptive query optimization or sometimes
called hybrid optimization and the idea
is that you still do this first step
when you go through the the query shows
up you go through the optimizer the
first time it generates you a plan but
then you your planets also gonna clued
include these built in sort of water
marks or thresholds you can use to
determine whether the estimates that the
cost model used in the first step when I
generated that plan the first time
whether those estimates are actually
matching up with what you're seeing when
you and you access the data so like if I
thought my query was very selective or
so my particle is very selective but
then i run the query and i see the
predicate is not selective at all then
if you identify that the there's a the
error rate for your estimations its
exceeding some threshold then you could
either pivot and change the plan on the
fly right there or you just give up and
go back to the query optimizer and say
hey your plan was wrong make me a new
one and make make me a better one
so the okay we'll talk about this in two
weeks this this one here is you bacon
the query plan itself additional
alternatives and so you can sort of
pivot or change based on what the
thresholds are this one is literally
like saying just stop executing the
query and go back to the optimizer so in
the easiest way to do this is just just
throw everything away and start over
from scratch and the idea is that you
you're you're you're making the gamble
that the physical plan you generate the
first time is so bad that you're better
off throwing away any work you've
already done going back to the optimizer
getting a new plan because that new plan
will be even more efficient than just
letting the first one run to attend
another approach is to then to recognize
how much work you've already done and
then you go back to the optimizer and
say I've already done you know I've
already scan or join these two tables so
generate me a new plan that has that
doesn't change that part I think that
part's fixed we've already computed it
I think everyone pretty much does the
throw everything away and start over at
least in the commercial systems today
alright so this is what prepared
statements so let's say I have a query
here that wants to do a three-way join
on tables ABC and I have some kind of
parameters here that I can use to filter
out the the to pose some of these two
tables so then this is a simple query
right this three by joint it doesn't
it's gonna take no time to execute but
let's say it takes a long time right and
let's say maybe it takes it takes 10
seconds to to run through the query
optimizer but the query only takes one
second to run so in that case every
single time I exceed this quitting say
I'm executing over and over again I
don't want to pay that 10 second search
cost for a query that's going to take
one second so what I can do instead is I
can declare it as a prepared statement
and it's essentially I'm giving this
this this query here this name my query
and now I use the execute command to and
to invoke it all right so now in this
case here the the debut system could
it's told ahead of time what the queries
gonna be as a prepared statement it can
run it through the optimizer take that
10 seconds cache the plan and now I
receive every single time I invoke it
I'm just getting that plan again I said
I so now it runs super fast without
paying the cost to go to the optimizer
so in this case here this is this is a
super simple example this would work
right there's no issues here but let's
say that I want actually this query over
never again but maybe not use these
values that I have here on the to do
this the predicate in the where clause
maybe I want to change these for every
single query so to do this I can replace
the constant values with question marks
which sometimes dollar signs to indicate
that these are input parameters and now
I declare when I declare my prepared
statement I say these are the three
parameters you can pass in and their
types and now when I invoke the query
it's like a function call where I pass
in these actual values all right so now
the tricky thing is gonna be though is
what should the physical plan actually
look like in terms of joint ordering for
this query if I don't know what these
values are at the time
I'm told hey prepare the statement for
me right so if you know it maybe the
first time actually when I have these
values here
I would want to join a a and B first
then join C but maybe for another set of
values I want to join B and C first
followed by a but I don't know that
because all I have are these please
placeholder these variable markers here
I don't know actually what batteries are
gonna be used so there's a couple
different ways we can handle this with
prepared statements and a query
optimizer so easiest thing to do is
every so often we just use whatever the
last plan it is that we had so let's say
that the we call prepared statement we
don't actually prepare it right right
there we don't want to completely see
the query optimizer but when someone
actually invokes it and executed and use
uses the prepared statement now we get
some values we can then say well let's
just assume that those values are gonna
we're gonna represented what we're
always gonna see and I just cache that
plan all right and always use what I
read use before so I think that's what
Postgres does right it's it's pretty
simple the next alternative is that you
actually lose all the benefit of getting
a prepared statement where you set you
run it through the optimizer every
single time you invoke it you can be a
little bit clever and try to use
whatever the last plan you had as the
starting point in the search at least
had that say that you know here's here's
a good starting place for my physical
plan and based your search for the
better plan off of that rather than from
starting from scratch every single time
that it's actually using the previous
plan as an upper bound that is tricky
because that requires you to engineer
optimizer to be able to restart it from
an existing physical plan and most
optimizers written are not written to
handle that another approach is to
generate multiple plans for your
prepared statement so you could say well
I know I'm doing a prepare thing that
has one that has one input parameter on
this one column I can look at my
histograms or statistics that I've
collected through the analyze keyword or
the analyze command about what the
distribution of values look like for
that column and maybe I break them up
into two
buckets in my histogram and I each
bucket I'll generate a generative plan
so now when I invoke the prepared
statement I look at the value mean
passed in and I figure out what bucket
it belongs to and that's the plan I use
so for one variable that's easy to do if
now I have multiple variables and now
becomes exponential or the number of
plans now I'm gonna have possibly have
to would it explode and that would be
expensive to do so I don't think Oracle
might do something like this but it
might be wrong but there's sort of more
primitive versions of trying to look at
have an exhaust of the rate of all
possible plans the last one is just to
say well I know what my parameters are I
can infer what columns doing doing look
doing a lookup someone or what actors
that are accessing and I'll just look at
my statistics take the average value
that each of those columns could
represent and use that as the input
parameters when I prepare that perfectly
when I invoke the prepared statement
through the quarry optimizer so again
there's not one approach that that all
systems actually use this is obvious the
easiest one but I think this is actually
a good research question and I want to
investigate at some point as well all
right the next thing we got to deal with
is is stability so plan stability means
that the that the performance of the
query of a particular query will be
consistent from one day to the next like
if I run the query today and it takes an
X amount of time if I run that same
query tomorrow on the same sort of
database you know modulo some minor
changes I should should take this
roughly about the same amount of time I
would I don't want to happen is I run my
query today and it's it's you know it it
takes this time it run tomorrow and if
you take its half the cost is the
exchange time is cut in half but then
the day after that now it's back to the
original time like I don't want those
oscillations because that makes it super
tricky for it for us to identify
performance bottlenecks and performance
issues DBAs are very conservative about
upgrading database systems David says
some software because they'd rather have
stability and then just better
performance all the time
so how can we achieve stability and have
queries so again this is all about the
query optimizer so we want to make sure
that our query optimizer is generating
plans for queries that from one day to
the next will have state stable
performance so one approach is to
provide hints to the query plan so this
is where essentially you can annotate
the query either through like special
comments in the header or if it's a
graphical tool sometimes you can do this
where you can specify what you want the
query optimizer actually to do all right
for certain choices it has to make so
all the times you'll see this like I
even you can provide a hint to the
optimizer and say this query scene you
should use this index on this table I
don't care about other indexes or scan
so you make sure using its index right
or the join ordering will be another
common one another one is to you can
tell that some database systems which
optimizer
version they want to use for a
particular query so a lot of times when
people upgrade the database system
software expect this is in particularly
for Oracle you can specify which version
of the optimizer you want the queries to
use because if you've already vetted say
a previous version and the optimizer
generated plans that you can understand
you have stable performance numbers when
you do the upgrade maybe you don't want
to update the optimizer and have it
generate different plans for queries and
now the numbers may vary right so again
DBAs are very conservative it's not it's
not helpful if we upgrade the data to
system software and 99% of our queries
now run faster but then 1% of the
queries run slower because the optimizer
picked up a different plan than it used
to
that's me bad because the people whose
queries run slower now are gonna get in
the phone and call you and complain and
say why is my query run slower please
fix it the the the other 99% the queries
those people aren't gonna call and say
you know thank you for making a query
run faster people don't do that
it's when things go bad that's when
people complain right so in this case
here again so if I upgrade my upgrade
Oracle I can say I want to run with the
previous optimizer because that'll
generate plans that I
that I know about the last choice is to
support backwards-compatible plans so
the idea here is that if I say I upgrade
my database system software but before I
do that on the old system I dump out or
export all the plans for my prepared
Sabres or queries that I'm executing all
the time and too much of files then I
upgraded the Devi system software and
then I load back in those plans from the
previous version of the software and
override any decision that the optimizer
make you're saying no for this query
absolutely use this plan that guarantees
you've had the same plan but you had
before so sequel server allows you to do
this sequel server you can dump out the
query plans as as XML and then load them
back into new versions that's the last
thing we talked about is search term
termination so again when you're on the
command line you write you type of query
in you hit enter and to run the query
optimizer and so you need a way for the
query optimizer to determine I've run
long enough and I need to stop because
again some of these problems you know
from very complex queries you know it's
the the search spaces and be complete so
you can just be running this for days
and days and days and people aren't
gonna like that
so the most obvious thing to do is just
set a wall clock time barrier that says
that if my optimizer runs first it
amount of time I just kill and I stop
all right another approach is to have a
cost threshold where you say that if I
find a plan
if I find a plan that has a lower cost
than some threshold that I want or
another one might be if I if I've run
for a certain amount of time and I don't
find a plan that's you know twenty
percent or ten percent better than the
best plan I've seen so far then I just
go ahead and stop myself
the last one is basically you say if you
can identify that there's no more
possible permutation or enumeration you
can do for the target plan then you know
you you're done for the search and
typically this is done on a per blue
basis right because if it's a lot a lot
of a lot of tables a lot of joins and
you don't ever actually exhaust this all
right so give it one example of how this
is used and
of my sequel you can specify the
optimizer search death in the search
tree so this prevents you from going
maybe too far down and the branching and
you started to artificially cut off the
search you know so many level deep so
that that you exhaust the number of
possible choices more quickly it's some
systems try to be dynamic and often hard
to get this right so it is this is one
semi Tina's blog article from percona
who is one of the major my sequel
consulting companies do a lot of
development my sequel so back in 2012
they talked about how they had this they
had this one customer that was doing a
select query on 20 tables and the
optimizer took took 5 seconds to find
the query plan and the query only ran
for 50 milliseconds because it was
reading a thousand tuples and so by
saying that like search death and
artificially cutting it all from just
doing his also search they were able to
get it down in the optimizer to
finishing in milliseconds so all the
various data systems have different
tools to figure these things out all
right so now we want to talk about the
serve again these are all the we just
talk about all the design decisions we
have to consider when we want to build
our optimizer how to handle prepared
statements how to decide when to finish
finish searching what to actually do our
search on one query multiple queries
things like that now we want to talk
about what the search is we know what
the this serve what the optimizer
actually looks like how is it actually
going to generate a physical plan from a
logical plan so the way to think about
what we're going to talk about today is
we're going forward into time and
complexity so it was like a from a time
being like historical points so like
heuristics based optimizers of what they
they first built in the 1970s and going
forward in this the you know we're
coming to newer newer implementations
the other I think also think about too
is these are these are the the heuristic
based one is in the simplest way to
build an optimizer
although the engineering side of it can
get very very messy but going down the
the implementations become more complex
and therefore the
query optimizations and rules they can
transformations they can apply become
more sophisticated so we'll talk about
these these are worth talking about
because this is what you'll see often
when people first build into a system
because they're not gonna have a call
space search model they're gonna use
heuristics and sometimes heuristics can
still be are still widely used today and
then the unified search and stratified
searches will we'll end up well talked
about today will get up to the volcano
optimizer and then that'll segue into
the next lecture when we talked about
Cascades in more detail okay so the very
first query optimizer is for the
relational database systems in the 1970s
for two of the three first relational
database systems we're using heuristic
based transformations and the idea here
is that in the code itself you're you
define these these rules that will
transform the logical operators and to
physical operators so the the most
common thing would be like if I'm doing
a scan and I know I have like an index
that had that matches all the predicates
in my where clause then that's the index
I would want to use all right so that's
sort of like that stargell stuff that we
talked about a few slides before so
that's that's sort of the standard
transformations you can do from logical
to physical but some of the
optimizations you can do to improve
query performance will be applying all
the the and the basic rules you want to
have for a query execution like
predicate pushdown let me push down some
things like that
my predicate push down would be instead
of having you know the may be the
predicate at the top of the query plan I
push it all the way down to my access
method so that I'm filtering out tuples
as quickly as possible I'm not not you
know passing in form one hopper to the
next good that would be expensive
another common thing will also be to do
to handle join ordering through just
cardinality estimates they could say
that you know we have joining two tables
you know which one potentially you can
approximate which one is gonna have more
triples feeding into the joint operator
so you make that one versus one the
outer versus one the inner it's simple
rules like that so the important thing
I've seen about this is that there's no
cost model involved in this it's all
static it's like I see a query a query
planner has this
pattern in it I always apply this rule
right I always push down the the the
predicate things like that so as I said
the the two or the three first
relational database systems from the
major relational database systems from
the 1970s ingress out of Berkeley from
like Stonebreaker and Oracle from from
Larry Ellison this is what what they
used and the in from back then like the
the resources that they had for you know
for you know competing researchers to
run actually run the Devi system
software itself was was quite limited so
the size of the databases they were
trying to store back in the 1970s were
super small right so like in was talk
about this in a second I mean case of
the ingress paper here like they're
talking about you know scanning tables
with like three hundred tuples and
that's that's like that's nothing so the
complexity of the problem they were
trying to deal with this is the kind of
queries they were trying to deal with
this is was much much less than what we
deal with today
in the case of Oracle like Oracle you
know they got huge and got you know a
lot of money riding on a you know the
the simplest type of sort of optimizer
an you can have again one that I didn't
have a cost model that all the things
were talked about and going forward like
they got huge just based on this so I
don't want to say I wanna make a sound
or sound like I'm saying you can't you
can't have a sophisticated data system
without having a cost-based optimizer
clearly Oracle got quite far with it but
again back in the 1990's the type of
queries they were dealing with like the
sequel 92 standard no CT es no one to
function and no use define aggregates
right all these things didn't exist so
it is actually viable but again also
got really big without having
having a cost-based optimizer as well so
I've talked to some people that worked
on the the Oracle query optimizer like
back in the day in the 1980s 1990s and
they would say that it was the largest
piece of code in the system and it was
quite sophisticated and what it could do
but it was like an engineering nightmare
cuz everything was written in C there
wasn't no debt you know high-level DSL
order declaration of the rules right he
was a bunch of if if then else
statements and so again they had a lot
of money and they had some really smart
people and they could have done you know
amazing things by expanding this but it
just got to come n tenable and I said
that's why they switched over to the the
the cost based models cost based
searches that we'll talk about in a
second right so again this is what
ingress did beginning this would all
post a in the beginning I'm not saying
that this is the right way to do it in
some cases it is some cases it's not and
so let's talk about what ingress does
again this is mostly just for her stroke
or curiosity
so going forward we're gonna use the
following three table schema and with an
example query of Spotify or Apple iTunes
database so we have artists and we have
albums and then out artists appear on
albums so we're just keeping track of
like what you know what would what
records what albums are being put out
and what artists are on that so let's
talk about ingress does so this is what
ingress used back in the 1970s so for
this we're to use this query here where
it's a three-way join between artists
appear as an album and we want to get
all the artists that appear on my my
next tape right so angrist didn't the
way it did joins is that Hedda says
ingress didn't support joins so they had
to rewrite all the queries into single
table queries so because again because
they couldn't join tables together so
the first step what they would do is
they would take a joint play like this
and then they would then decompose it
into single value queries so what am i
bad so say you take this query here and
we're gonna rewrite it into two queries
so the first query now is gonna just
just be on the album table where we're
doing the lookup on the album name
because that's what we're passing over
here right and so this is just a select
on the single table here but then we're
gonna write it out into a temp table and
then now for this query here we replace
album
with our temp table reference here and
here so now we're going to recursively
now rewrite this query to remove in the
the joins that we have and so now we're
gonna have the this new query here that
just does a lookup on a peers with a
joint on temp 1 and it's gonna write the
output into 10 - then this query on the
artists table will do a lookup or do the
join against Tim - so now once you do
this once you do the rewriting you're
gonna then substitute the values from
these temp tables with the actual values
that are produced by the query so say we
execute this first one here
well then generate get the output of the
album ID 999 so then now we go to the
next query and we replace the reference
to temp 1 now with 9999 that's being
generated by the previous query so now
this is no longer a joint this is a
single statement or single table query
and I'm just substituting that value in
that produced from the previous query
same thing here this query runs now
produces two output and then now I can
rewrite this query into two queries one
that takes artist ID one two three and
the Netherlands it takes artist ID 4 5 6
and I can actually both of them produce
results of those queries combine them
together and then that's the output of
of my join all right so this is pretty
impressive right this is like a way to
do rewriting of queries
I mean I'm showing this on the sequel
level they would be doing this on the
physical plan level you know this allows
them to actually joins without actually
having a joint implementation like
you're just doing the single statement
selects so it's been argued that this is
actually an early example of adaptive
query optimization because rather than
doing the static optimization approach
where I would generate the plan all at
once for my entire query I could take
the sequel query here I see as a miss
book they were not operating physical
plans they probably operating on logical
plans but I could take this query here
and only when I get the values one two
three that I want to substitute
substitute into it
then I fired off I send it off to the
query optimizer and then generate the
physical plan for it so it's sort of
like a late binding optimization
approach right so like like I can learn
from information about what's coming out
of these queries to decide what the best
way to actually this particular query is
it's sort of again it's not exactly what
an adapter query optimization is but
they're essentially running the
optimizer on a per pupil basis which
nobody does today okay so all right what
are some advantage the disadvantages of
the Harriston based optimization so one
it's it's easy to implement it's easy to
debug because you just walk through with
gdb or whatever your favorite debugger
is and step through and see what what
rules actually get fired and in order to
determine why I mean a why I chose one
particular plan versus another right and
as I said when you when you build a new
database system today just to get it up
and running and excuse some first
queries you can get pretty far with a
arista bake-off heuristic based
optimizer the downside though is that
oftentimes if you will have to have
these these constant thresholds or
values baked in the source code itself
or defined in a configuration file to
help me make determination about certain
decisions you have to make like if I
wanted to determine whether a if I want
to a join a herd a logical doing plan or
operator into a physical join operator
and then need to determine whether it's
sort merge-join as faster than a hash
join I have to have some notion of sort
of akin cost I make that decision and
oftentimes it may have no bearing to
actually what the data looks like that
can be tricky the other tricky thing
about this is that it's going to be
basically impossible now the generate
plans when the transformations are
optimizations you want to apply can have
dependencies in between them so that
means I'd like say you you want to I
wanted to turn I want to apply
optimization a and based on whether or
not I choose that optimization I may
want to may or may not want to choose
optimization B
and so now if I if I'm writing this and
just based rules I have to write that
explicit rule to know that if I do a
then don't do B or I do don't do a then
I can do B I have to write all that
manually and the source code
we're in a cost-based search we'll talk
about it next slide if you write your
cost model in a crack way you could have
this search sort of the the search
engine sort of find that for you
right and you don't have to code it
directly so again as I said the
heuristic based approach is what the
first two out of the three original
relational database systems major
relational database systems that came
out in the 1970s actually used the other
sort of famous approach used in 1970s
was a combination of the heuristics from
we just talked about plus a call space
search and this is going to be the
technique that all the modern optimizers
that we'll talk about what we will be
based on they they may not need using
exactly the approach that IBM system are
is using but the notion of using the
cost model to estimate the efficacy or
the cost of estimate of a plan is is the
standard push that everyone's use so
with system or the way it's gonna work
is they'll have static rules first
perform some initial optimizations and
then they'll use a dynamic programming
method to determine the best joint
ordering for the tables so I think we
talked about IBM system are a little bit
but again Ted Khan was a mathematician
in New York he wrote these for IBM wrote
this this this this the far-reaching and
and very progressive paper on the
relational model it was all mathematical
ingress and Burton a nursing at Berkeley
was was one people group appeal that
took the paper and try to build system
IBM trying to build a their own version
of the system at call system are in his
San Jose in California and they got a
bunch of people had PhDs in your brand
new PCs and computer science mathematics
put them in a room at IBM Gabe and Ted
cause paper and says all right go make
this and so a bunch of people carved off
different pieces of the problem you know
one person with a PC went and then its
sequel another person invented
storage models or two phase locking Pat
Salinger was somebody who got assigned
to work on the query optimizer and it's
been very very seminal work so this is
the first example of a call space query
optimizer it's also an example of using
bottom-up planning or forward chaining
explain a few more slides whether it
actually means but basically it's like
we're gonna do a divide and conquer
approach where we're going to start with
nothing in our query plan and then it
early build it up to say to produce our
final result by figuring out what the
join orders gonna be so as I said system
R was the first system that used this
particular invitation the first version
of db2 that came in the 1980s
I think borrowed the the query optimizer
from system R and then most open source
database systems are gonna be using some
flavor of the of the the system are
approached like this is what my sequel
press press and sequel like use the
commercial guys usually are having
something more sophisticated or are
using Cascades alright so let's go
through an example what it's actually
doing so again when a system our
approach would work is that you'd break
up the query into blocks and then you
would have logical operators
representing each block and then for
each of these a lot of operators you're
gonna figure out what are all the
possible physical operators I could use
to implement that operator and then
you're gonna it early construct a query
plan that has the minimal cost
essentially you're stitching together
all the tables you want to access and
and joins to figure out how to join all
them and produce the final is all so one
important observation that IBM made at
the time was that they were only going
to pursue left deep join trees so that
means that like all the joins are sort
of only on the unless left side of the
tree going up and contrast this was like
a bushy tree where you know I can join a
and B join C and D and take the output
of those two separate joins and join
them together this would join a leftie
tree but join a B first then take the
output of that and joined C they take
the output of that and join with T and
they made this decision to only look
left D trees purely to minimize reduce
the search space of the problem all
right so if you have to go consider
bushy trees and that um
there's again that increases the number
of choices you have to look at and again
for the hardware they were dealing at
the time that was deemed too expensive
sometimes you see this optimization or
this assumption made in optimizers today
even though sometimes a bushy plan will
be preferable will be better it depends
on the system all right but there's
there's nothing about the approach I'm
talking about here today that requires
you to have the only support leftie
trees that's just you know show up and
they took back in the 70s all right so
let's go back to my my query they had
before the one difference I'm gonna make
is that now I'm gonna sort the output of
this result based on the artist ID right
so again the first step in this is our
is that we want to choose the best
access path for each table so here's all
the tables that I'm gonna access here's
all my predicates and I'm gonna pick
some and with the best access method for
that so in the case of artisan peers I
don't have a I don't have a I don't have
a index I can use so they're doing
special scans Alamance a has an index on
the name and we will use that now
forgive we're gonna numerate all
possible join our readings for these
tables again this is just like you know
a permutation of every possible
different ordering that my my tables
could have and I can do joins I can do
Cartesian products although we can put
those out later all right
it's then now for all these possible
orderings I want to figure out what is
the one that it's going to have the the
lowest cost and I need to base that cost
on what physical operator I'm gonna use
all right so this is just a logical plan
I want to join artisan and appear as an
album
I'm not saying how to actually do that
join and this last step here this is
actually where we want to figure it out
so system R is a bottom-up approach
where we're going to start at the bottom
of the query plan where we don't have
any information we haven't done any of
the joins yet we just say we have these
three tables artist album appears and
this is this is where we want to get to
it
so we want to figure out how do
communities together to get to this
final result here right where we joined
artists appears and how them together so
we're going to look at a look at all
possible join our drinks for the first
stage so I want to take two tables and
join them together so I can join artisan
appears Alban appears appears in album
and then all the other ones that I
showed in the the last slide I'm
truncating here because we're out of
space and then what I have is going out
I'm emanating from the starting point I
have a path to get there that's going to
use a particular physical algorithm all
right so I could either do a hash join
to join artisan appears or I can do a
sort of or join to join artisan peers
and likewise to join album appears I can
do a hash join the servers join and so
forth right but then now for each of
these different physical physical
operators I can estimate what is the
cost of executing it and then I for each
from going from one node to this I one
of them select which path to get to that
node has the lowest cost so let's say
it's in this case here to go from this
node to this node the hash join has a
lower cost same with this one to here
but this one the sort merge has a lower
cost then now I want to do the same
thing starting from the next level of my
query plan I want to say what physical
operator could I use to do the last join
right so again I'm showing a subset here
I could do a sort most join or hash
Mahesh has join for these different
approaches and then now the same thing I
want to pick which plan on which was
physical operator from going from one
node to the next has the lowest cost and
then now once I have this I backtrack
and say well what was the path that got
me from my starting point to my end
point going through these physical
operators that that had the lowest cost
and that's and say that it's doing a
hash join followed by a hash join and
that's the one that produces the lowest
cost amongst all the joins and that's
the one I want to use right again the
divide-and-conquer because rather than
looking at you know complete pass you
know you know from here to here
but in order to estimate the cost I'm
only going from one stage of the next
and then once I figure that out then I
go to the next stage and then combine it
together that produces the result so but
this particular query though remember
that I've added the order by so so now I
care about the what's the sort order of
the output after I join them but there's
nothing in this in this plan that I've
generated here that tells me what what
that sort order could be right and this
is because at least how system are was
sort of set up there's no notion of the
the physical properties or the sort
order of the the data that I wanted so
in this case here I'm doing hash joins
and that means that the data is going to
be random in a random sort order and
then I need to now execute an order by a
sort of sort operator to put the data
into the physical order that I want but
going back here if I had known that I
needed this day to be sort of a certain
way then maybe I would have chose a sort
servers join because that would have
given you two for one I would have give
me either do the join plus put the data
sort it in a way that I wanted it right
but because the way this is set up
there's nothing about the physical
property the data that it can make
helping make this decision so that's
actually want to be the limitations
we'll see what system are and we'll see
how what we can fix this up in in the
stratified or unified searches later on
the yeah so the way system are a few got
around this was that they would actually
have to bake in the cost model itself
some notion of the sort order that they
wanted dated to be in so that they can
then identify that the SIRT merge was
preferable to the to the hash join them
and for this particular example but that
was you know that's sort of a half right
because now you're there's logical what
the data should look like is in the in
the cost model and then it's sort of
separate from the actual the the search
strategy itself so that's an issue
so I briefly want to touch on this
distinction between the the bottom up
and the top down so again what butters
showed you was considered a bottom up
query options
strategy it's where you start with
nothing then you build a plan up to get
to the output that you want so system R
and IBM starbursts became later on these
are examples of bottom-up approaches the
dynamic approaching will see an hyper
this is also considered a bottom-up
approach the fee current feeling from
the the research community is that this
approach is better for figuring out the
joint ordering the alternative is the
top-down approach is what we use in our
system based on Cascades and this is
where you start with the outcome that
you want and then you work down the into
the QWERTY plan and you start adding in
physical operators to essentially
reverse the steps to get back get you
back from where the goal you need it
so again volcano was what canaan Exodus
came from the same data to Cascades
Cascades is considered the modern
implication of this so we'll cover this
I will cover this furthermore I think in
next class I don't say too much but like
this is what sequel server and cockroach
DB used is what our system uses a bunch
of other systems use this so this is
sort of like again the the hash join
versus certain rejoin debate in for
joint algorithms for databases this is
sort of the same thing if you care about
query optimizer this is sort of the same
debate people can have okay so let's
talk about what Postgres does a little
bit so Postgres actually does what this
is system our approach is for like it
usually this is the case right we'll
talk about their other query optimizer
in a second but if you come along if you
have a query and Postgres that only
joins 12 tables then this is what you
get if you have 13 or more tables and
you get this genetic algorithm which
we'll talk about a few more slides but
the way it works is that they had this
rewriting phase that has all the static
rules that we talked about that can do
some initial rewriting or optimizations
on on the on the query planner then they
throw it into a cost-based search model
using the bottom-up approach the same
one as a system are to figure out the
joint owner ring then after that they go
back and add on the idea
the remaining things that are missing in
the query plan so these would be things
like the sort order or any kind of
aggregations you would have to have
right so the the and then you do the
same thing but you just recursively do
the same steps for any sub queries so
the Postgres is phenomenal I think the
postal code is actually one of those
beautiful database system source code
I've ever seen even least anyone written
in C the query optimizer is sort of like
the in my opinion at least one lesson it
looks at it a few years ago is one of
the dark corners of the system and so
the it's it's I've been told this is
very brittle because you implicitly have
in the source code for like is rewriting
phase steps that like you basically
bacon the source code assumptions about
what the output of that data needs to
look like if according to look like in
order for it to be then fed into the the
next set of you know heuristic
transformations that you're actually
doing so if you change sort of some
assumption you you have about what the
the next stage expects that the query
plan will look like if you somehow there
the query plan you're generating or
produce is now different then that can
break everything everything else and
this is sort of why I like the Cascades
or unified approach we'll talk about a
second because you declare all your
rules you declare your transformations
and the physical properties you expect
the query plan to to maintain and then
you just throw them the engine and let
it let it figure it out for you and for
in the force is all these things for you
whereas this one it's it's you happen to
understand what that you know in order
to modify anything you'd understand you
know everything step what's actually
happening alright so so again advantage
the disadvantages of the system are
approach so the advantage is that it
usually finds a reasonable plan at least
for joining for a moderate-sized nor
joins our number tables in a reasonable
out of time without having to do it it's
also search the downside is that you're
gonna have all the same problems you had
in the heuristic only approach because
that's the first step you're applying
before you go into it and do the search
this is only really limitation for
system are that they they're limited
- left deep trees modern systems I don't
think have that issue and then in the
example I showed before where you need
to have the cost model be aware of what
your data needs to look like if you have
sort orders or compression and other
properties on the data you got to bake
that into the cost model cuz the search
I'll go myself is can't can't force that
so this last one is the worst part this
is this is this is the major limitation
you're gonna have using this tomorrow
system our approach of using the cost
model to enforce physical properties
right that I think again I think this
makes it the from engineering standpoint
this is problematic so before we get
into the sort of the modern query
optimizer implementations I want to talk
about a another class optimizers that
are using randomized algorithms this is
another way to think about the the
problem we're trying to solve in the
quarry optimizer so the idea of the
randomized amalgam is that rather than
doing this this sort of branch of
balanced search looking for a better
better query plan we're just gonna take
our query plan and do random
permutations on it and just do a random
walk of all possible valid query plans
and then if we just haven't a
StumbleUpon one that's actually better
then that's the one we'll end up using
right and so for this one this is where
you actually need that threshold it's
like a time threshold today it'll say
I've searched long enough I know I know
when to stop because otherwise this
thing will just run forever so an
example of this will be Postgres to the
genetic algorithm which is actually in
the real system today we'll talk about
the next live but let's before that
there was an implementation using
simulated annealing so this is back in
like 1987 as far as in it far as I know
this F never actually made it into a
real system the basic idea is that you
show in your query plan that you
generate using the - the heuristic based
approach we talked about in the
beginning and then now you just do
random permutations of operators in the
query plan like swapping the joint or
two tables and then you estimate the
cost of that of
change of that new query plan and if
it's better than you just accept the
change if it's worse then you flip a
weighted coin to decide whether you want
to keep it or not and then the idea here
is that every so often you'll get up
you'll get a by accepting a change
accepting a new plan that actually made
things worse
this allows you to potentially break out
of local minimums and then find that the
the true you know the true optimum so
the tricky thing about this though is
that you have to write rules that make
sure you enforce any the the correctness
of the query plan so that you don't end
up producing you know incorrect results
so like if my if my data needs to be
sorted and I randomly permute the query
plan by putting the sort the order by
operator before the hash join and then
now my outputs not gonna be sorted I'm
gonna end up with incorrect results so
you have to either write all these rules
to make sure that this happens correctly
which can be tricky is there's a lot of
corner cases an example of a randomized
algorithm that is actually used in
production is the Postgres genetic
optimizer so again the way this works is
that if you use the system our approach
we talked about before if your query has
12 tables if you try to join 13 or more
then you get this one you can turn this
on and off there's a thresher let's say
when this actually kicks in but by
default I think it's I think it's 13
tables so they're gonna use a genetic
algorithm where at the beginning of
every round they're gonna generate a
bunch of different permutations or
random variations of the query plan then
they're gonna cook generate castmate the
cost of all those permutations and then
they'll pick some number of ones that
have the lowest cost as the ones to
propagate from one you know foot to the
next generation and then you have some
mutator function to flip around or
randomly permute the the best plans like
the idea is like you're getting genes
from the best plans and hopefully
producing offspring that produce even
better plans so visually it looks like
this so let's say that we in our first
raishin for a symbol say three table
join we can estimate the cost of EQ DS
and say this one ends up being the
lowest cost so we update our lowest cost
flag over here and then we're gonna
randomly permute aspects of this we feed
that over to this one and we kill off
this one and then now same thing we
estimate the cost find the one that has
a lowest cost this in this case here
this one is lower than this one so
that's our new best one we've ever seen
pick these keep these two guys around
flip some stuff and generate a new
clause like that and we just keep going
on over and over again until we find
until we run out and running out of time
so what are the advantages of this well
jumping around and random locations
allows us to get our local minimums and
potentially we can find a better plan to
the best my knowledge I've not seen any
detailed analysis or experiments about
how good the Postgres genetic optimizer
actually is compared to you know letting
the the regular optimizer run for longer
we also have low memory overhead for
doing the search because if we don't
need to maintain the history of one
generation to the next source of our
random walk then the you know the the
the memory footprint is just whatever we
use that you know whatever we're using
for that back current round the dance
advantages of though is that unless we
do extra work to make sure that the
randomness is deterministic we could end
up with you know a system that's
difficult to debug to determine why one
you know why the Davidson is why the
data some squares up matters decided to
use one plan versus another in the case
of Postgres they always make sure that
the the random seed is consistent for a
given query so if i've run the query
today through the genetic optimizer and
I run it tomorrow the same query
I'll always produce the same plan and we
still also have to still maintain any
correctness rules to make sure that we
don't do any mutations that end up with
an invalid query ok so we're going a bit
long here but this is good stuff I enjoy
it so the one observation we can make is
that everything we talked about so far
is you know mostly you can imagine
writing all these transformation rules
and these algorithms in a procedural
language like C or C++ and this is
tricky to do because there's no way to
verify precisely or through formal
methods that the the transformations
that were applying are correct that
we're guarantee sure that when we do a
transformation from one query plan to
the next that you know those two
algebraic expressions are actually
equivalent right so we could try to
verify this by running lots of fuzz
tests with random queries and just
checking that the output is the correct
but of course this is like trying you're
trying to prove a negative which is not
easy to do so actually let me let it lit
up the tear one sec
so a better push to doing this would be
if we could have a way to declare what
our transformation rules are through
like a high-level language or DSL and
then we can have we could feed this into
an optimizer engine who could then
generate the code or apply these rules
for us so that way now through these
declared is declarative rule rule rule
set we can then do our verification or
analysis on those rules to determine
that they are correct and the long as we
you know we're reasonably sure that our
rule engine is correct to execute them
we would know that we're always doing
transformations that are that are that
are that are valid so this was the this
was the movement in the late 1980s early
1990s to develop what are called
optimizer generators and think of these
are like as a framework that allows a
data system developer to declare the
rules throw transforming queries to
generate optimal plans and then this
this would all be separate from the
search strategy that we talked about
before right these are like you know do
predicate push down you declare a rule
to do that so no matter whether we were
doing heuristics or a like the system
our search we could be guaranteed that
we we would we produce that that
transformation correctly all right so
the first example of of this type of
optimizer was in the starburst system
Exodus was another first for a famous
one this is what IBM this was an
academic system and then there's been
some variations improvements from the
guy that Exodus of volcanoes cascades up
plus plaus was at Wisconsin Columbia was
another one at query optimizer in the
late 1990s at a Portland since then
there really hasn't been that much
research in this kind of optimizer
generators and they're primarily what
people use today is based on this work
done in the 1990s so we'll go a little
more detail about strawberry AIDS
in necklace but I'll briefly talk about
it just for them right now so the these
optimizer generators again they had this
wool engine that allows you to apply
these transformations and then you can
declare in the rule what physical
properties you wanted the operator to
enforce on the data that a better was
processing like the sort order example
that I showed before but now the
question is how we're actually going to
do you know apply these transformations
and do the search for the optimal plan
so the two approaches that are the do
stratified search of unified search so
stratified search is essentially what I
said the IBM where the system our
approach was where I can apply my
transformation and using heuristics
without a cost model first then I take
that out take that query plan and run it
through a search model that could then
find me the best drawing ordering a
unified searches where we're doing all
aspects of the query plan planning at
once so the transformations for doing
predicate push downs and all the sort of
those static rules if you will they're
done at the same time in the same search
space as you do figure out the best
joint odor so let start with the first
one so again the stratified search is we
first rewrite the logical plan using all
the transformation rules so you go from
a logical plan into a logical plan again
this is the same thing they were doing
in the here's to base approach and so
this rule engines gonna check to see
whether the transformation you want to
do is even allowed before it actually
applies this this make sure that you
don't end up with a invalid query plan
at stake so there's no cost model for
this these are again the same thing we
talked about for getting I always wanted
to predicate push down or a limit push
down I can write a rule to do that
transformation and then once the one
this step is done now you do the cost
based search to find a mapping from the
logical plan to a physical plan if that
could be the joint ordering or it could
be the you know figuring out whether you
want is a nested loop join or a certain
rejoin or a hashed one figure out those
algorithms the most famous one of these
optimized generators was with starbursts
that IBM led by guy lumen let's come and
again this is just repeats what I said
before you had a query rewrite phase
that does that can compute the
transformations based on these blocks
and that doesn't have a cost model and
then you do the system auto style search
to to find you know joint order things
like that so as far as you know know the
latest version of IBM db2 like their
their enterprise relational database
system is using this approach I don't
know of any other ones I mean starburst
was a you know star bus was system
developed at IBM so I mean it's
obviously make sense and to go in db2 I
don't know of any other davis system
that follows this similar approach so
what are the advantages well so in
practice it works well would think it's
faster performance the downside though
is that you have no way to clearly
define the the priorities you have for
your transformations again this will
make more sense when we talk about
cascades but basically like if I know I
can't exhaustively search and everything
so maybe there's some transformations I
want to look at first because I yeah I
think I'll get better benefit from them
and then oh and then that helps me maybe
then lower my upper bound for for my
query and then I know I can prune things
out that maybe don't aren't that I mean
less helpful so I don't apply those
transformations first so that so in the
original version at starburst you
couldn't do that the other aspect that
they talked about in the paper that was
a big pain was that because these
transformation rules are based on
relational calculus it became difficult
to maintain and find programmers to
write because writing relational
calculus code is sort of not um doesn't
come natural to to the writer assistants
programmers again I don't know whether
in the suburbs papers from 1990 88 I
don't know if since then it's been
rectified
alright so quickly the unified search is
where you have this notion of the
logical logical and logical physical
transformations done all together and so
you don't have these separate stages
because everything is just a
transformation you throw it into your
rules engine it does the search and
applies these things
for you so the major downside the major
tricky thing you have to deal with a
unified search is that there's me so
many transformations that you have to
use a memorization table to make sure
that you cache some of these
transformations so that you're not
replying you know applying the same
change over and over again so now this
makes the the memory footprint a little
bit larger here because I have to
maintain some some history of
transformations applied in the past to
know whether I want to apply a new one
in the future so Gertz graph II was the
same guy that did the volcano the the
you know volcano iterator model we
talked about for for query processing
models there's a volcano optimizer
that's part of the same project he's the
same guy that did some of the work that
we talked about for you know latching
and locking and B plus trees so when he
was an academic he built a series of
these these new systems that each had a
optimizer optimizer generator so the
second one here was was a volcano and
again this was a general-purpose base
cost-based optimizer that had these
equivalence rules baked into it for
relational algebra it made it really
easy to add new rules it treated first
physical properties of the data and
better as first-class entities or
components in the system itself so you
could you could understand whether
you're making a transformation that was
valid or not as you were going along and
rather than trying to clean up things
after the fact so this is an example of
a top-down approach will be the same
thing that Cascades will use double talk
about next class but this is sort of
like this was like an early prototype
this was a predecessor to two Cascades
right so as far as they know volcano I
mean the volcano itself was using the
optimizer other academic prototypes at
the time we're using this but as far as
I know this approach is not used in in
any any in any major system so let's
look at an example here
godamn don't restart okay
so the first thing we want to do is
start with a logical plan of what we
want the query to be so this is what we
want our output to be we want to do a
three-way join putting these tables and
we want have it order by on the artist
ID so again this is the opposite what we
saw in system our system are we started
up here and said here's all the tables
we have figure out how to get us up here
so we this is where we start with we
want to and then want to go down and
apply transformation rules to get us
there right so we can invoke rules that
as we go down to either do logical
logical transformations so like checking
you join on a and B reverse that and you
would join them BN a or we give you a
logical physical take you know join on a
and B and have it now be executed as a
hash join on a and B right so we then
add these nodes here to apply it apply
these transformations and then we use to
connect them and say how do we actually
get there and we can just keep going
this down you keep going down to do this
until we reach the bottom and in this
case here we could compute the cost of
what our query plan as is here and we
keep the check bad as as the lowest cost
so now we just keep doing look at all
possible other permutations and so forth
until we find in this case here we if we
tried to do a hash join we know that
doing this hash join would violate our
physical ordering that we have so we
know we can't do this so we can
introduce like a quicksort you know to
do the order by and then now we can do
the hash join and so forth right in this
case here say doing the quicksort plus
the hash join is more expensive than new
the sort merge join followed by either
the hash alone insert merge join so we
cut it off there so you're doing branch
and bound to identify that as I'm
traversing the branch on the tree if I'm
at a point where my query plan is
already more expensive than the best
plan I've seen before I don't need to
look at anything below it in the tree
because I'll know I'll never get better
than that all right so the advantage of
the of the volcano optimizer that we
have declared a rule to do our
transformations but strawberries have
the same thing but it's gonna have
better extensibility with an efficient
search algorithm because we can reduce
the number of redundant estimations we
have to do by caching our
transformations
the problem though is that the at least
the wave volcano was implemented is that
for every single possible trim like for
every single operate I'm looking at I
would expand out all possible
combinations like Earl your
transformations like I'd have and then
now start doing the the search and all
those rather than maybe traversing all
the way the bottom first and then it was
not easy to modify predicates I don't
exactly know this what this was about it
I think essentially it meant that you
couldn't do rewriting of like where
clauses because the the optimizer itself
only know how to do transformations on
physical arbiters and not be expression
trees inside of them so I rush this at
the end was just meant to show you what
a what a top-down optimizer looks like
but then next class will pick up on on
Cascades
so hopefully the main takeaway from all
this is that query optimization super
hard and this is part of reason why the
newest ecosystems when they first came
out maybe a decade ago they they
basically didn't implement a query
optimizer
because it ah we don't need to do joins
you don't need a declarative language
like sequel and part of the the
advantage of not supporting those things
is that you didn't have to build a query
optimizer but now for the systems that
did add something that looks like sequel
orderly's declarative language they're
having to go implement Cori optimizers
and then the the quality of them can can
vary greatly and they're usually gonna
be heuristic based systems alright so
next class will pick up discussing more
optimizers and then the real debate will
be again is dynamic programming versus
the Cascades broach the the bottom-up
approach we saw all system are first the
top-down approach which volcano is an
example of but a Cascades Cascades will
be more sophisticated implementation and
the this is what we use in our system
today ok alright so again I'm meeting
with everyone for the projects this week
and then will on the on Wednesday next
week we'll do the in-class presentations
or over zoom
ok wash your hands sink it in the side
park what is this
would say you're here I took the sipping
had to spit today with dead deer called
the hole it cuz I mochi ice cube down
with the test team I look and it was go
grab me a 40 just to get my boss song
cuz I need it just a little more kick
[Music]
that's a nice and my hood wants me to
say I've nice cute take a say I
celebrate