[Music]
let's get started
so DJ drop tables is not here today he
should be here next week he's a bit of
cracking up here so his it's his
girlfriend's birthday this week and he
blew off money last week in Vegas so he
lied and told her that he's going to
visit his family for Thanksgiving so
that's why he's gone this week but
that's just really get out of ruse of
buying him a present so he'll be back
next week alright so again just a
reminder for what's on the docket for
you guys homework 5 is due next week
project 4 we do after that the extra
credit for the feedback submission was
last night
some people emailed about about an error
cuz some funky Unicode issue but
everybody else should have submitted the
final exam will be on December 9th
actually they announced the room but I
have looked to see where it is that has
anybody looked it doesn't matter
we'll figure it out and then for for
next week again the Oracle talk will be
on Monday the assistants popery and the
final review will be on on the Wednesday
so we'll do the final review in the
beginning and then we'll do will cover
three or four different database systems
that you guys voted on and I'll just
sort of give you you know a ten minute
over your what's interesting about it
why it's good why it's bad and so forth
so if you haven't voted yet please
please go in here and vote the numbers
look similar to previous years ah so
again you can go look at the videos and
last year to see what we're gonna
discuss but go vote first then then go
look it up and as I said on Monday
Tuesday next week our friends our Oracle
are coming and there's a gonna be three
different talks so on mondays class in
here they'll be will have Shashank come
and talk about you know there's
something his group is building again
this is not a recruiting talk this is
like a you know a scientific or or
assistant discussion of what they're
building and basically he'll use all the
same key words and buzzwords that I've
used throughout the entire semester so
you realize and I'm not not
is making sure up so he'll come and talk
about their system there's a more
recruiting oriented systems talk will be
Monday at 4:30 in in gates and that one
will be pizza and then a pure research
talk would be on Tuesday December 3rd
the following day at 12 p.m. and the
CICU floor and so the Hideaki Kimura is
as I mentioned on Piazza I went to grad
school with him I he's probably one of
the most hardcore systems programmers
ever met my life he is also the most
stubborn man that I've ever met in my
life when we were building the first the
first summer we were building H store he
wanted we had to build our expression
trees like for the where clauses I had
my way of doing it he had his way we
literally had a four-hour debate in my
office just yelling at each other about
what to do and he just broke me down
said to do it he was wrong and we
removed what he did later on my coats
still there so I was right but in
general he's awesome so he's gonna come
talk about some he's just come talk to
the non-volatile memory stuff that
they've been working on for the system
because he's part of shashank group so
again if you're interested in doing
internships or full-time positions with
them
he will come and tell you the kind of
things you could be working on okay and
I'll some reminders about all these
things on Piazza and the questions about
any of these okay and then I also make
arrangers if you want to eat these guys
one-on-one to talk about internships and
full-time positions as well well I'll
send that email okay so last class was
the second lecture we had on distributed
databases the first class are just
defining what a distributed database
system looks like from architecture
standpoint what are the you know where's
data relative to where the computers
confused actually gonna run on it and
then last class was all about talking
about taking these trip to Stata bases
when you want to do transactions and
making sure that we provide all the
asset guarantees that we'd want on a
single node system but now doing this in
a distribute environment and we spend
most of our time talking about the
atomic commit protocol on replication
because again that's the hard part of
apps you have an issue of your database
when things are split up and now you
have transactions doing rights on a
bunch of different nodes at the same
time how do you keep it all in sync how
do you avoid losing data how do you have
reads not see stale data if you care
about those things so for today
class now we're going to sort up just
leave alone or you know leave all the
transaction stuff we talked about before
and now so I was talking about how to do
analytics where we're not doing a lot of
Rights we're not doing transactions
we're mostly going to be doing reads but
the amount of data we're going to be
reading is much larger than what the old
to be transactions were doing from last
class so I want to show what a sort of a
typical set up would be in a analytical
database and this doesn't does not
necessarily have to be a distributed
database but this is a common
arrangement so on the front end you have
your old to be databases okay this is
where you're ingesting new information
from the outside world and this could be
distributed could be single note it
doesn't matter and then you want to get
all the data from these front-end data
silos into your back-end analytical
database sometimes called a data
warehouse so there's this process called
ETL extract transform the load so
there's tools you can you can buy that
do this we just write Python scripts or
do whatever you do manually but the idea
is that to take all the data from these
different front-end OTP databases and
put it into a universal schema inside
your data warehouse so for example let's
say you have your front-end database one
application has that you know they all
have different customers names but this
one has FM for the first name this one
has first underscore name so you can't
just chuck that all into a single
database because the database doesn't
know that F name equals first name so
this is where you do that cleanup
process here in the ETL world so this is
a very common setup right if you're if
you're gonna build a start up you you
typically start with this because you
need to get data first and then once you
have a lot of data then you want to put
it into your back-end data warehouse and
the idea is that we don't wanna do
analytics on the front end because
that's gonna slow us down or slow down
our transactions so you can put this
into our back-end data warehouse so this
is what we're focusing on today how do
we actually do this so I use the term
OLAP online and local processing
sometimes you'll see see these types of
systems referred to as a data warehouse
or more traditionally sometimes they
call it decision support systems DSS and
again the idea is that these are
applications we're going to right now in
our back-end dip data warehouse
it's gonna analyze the data we have that
we've kept from the OTP side extrapolate
new information and then guide our
decision-making processes for for the
business for the organization or for the
old to be allocations right so very
common set up the one is they've always
like to use is like zinga zinga has all
their stupid farmville games up here
right these are all old to be databases
for every clique in the game that's
another transaction or another update to
the database but then there's a shove
all those clicks into the backend data
warehouse do some analysis on this at
whether your decision support systems or
machine learning to try to figure out
some of how to make you buy
more stuff on the front end right like
the the one example I always heard was
it's the candy crush game if you played
the candy crush game and so you get all
these updates on the OTP side and then
it's a you get a hard puzzle and you
can't beat it right and so you put the
game down so they're gonna collect all
this click stream to see how you played
the game and then they'll learn that oh
if you come back after not having played
the game for like a day because you got
frustrated they make sure you they give
you an easy puzzle that you can solve
right away so you get hooked again right
and then keep playing it because they
know if they give you a hard puzzle
you'll get frustrated and never come
back ever again
right so that extrapolating that
information that oh this is how I give
you know the person you know a game that
they'll be able to beat you figure that
out on this side and then you push the
update to the OTP side so the in general
at high level there's two different ways
you can model a database application on
a back-end data warehouse or analytical
database so you could take the standard
schema that you know your application
would have like typically it's usually a
tree schema because you have this
hierarchy I have customers customers
have orders orders have items but those
schemas can be quite messy and they're
not going to be very efficient for
analytical queries so instead you would
model your database using either what's
called a star schema or a snowflake
schema and sometimes you see analytical
databases that they'll say hey we only
support star schemas you can't do a
snowflake schema you'll see this is
basically a subset of this but you see
why let's discuss why this matching
might be better for it
some analytics so a very common
arrangement would be something like this
so this this is a star schema and you
have two types of tables in a star
schema you have facts tables and
dimension tables so the middle of the
star is the fact table think of this is
like every city event you're trying to
model this is where you store all the
occurrences of them so if you're like
Walmart and your data warehouse keeps
track of every single item that emam I
don't anyone has ever bought at any
Walmart stored at any given time all of
those items getting scanned at the cash
check or the checkout counter that's
another event that we've put in our fact
table so this thing is gonna be massive
like hundreds of billions of records
same thing Amazon every single item that
anyone's ever bought on Amazon goes and
you're in your fact table but we're not
actually going to store any information
about what these items are that someone
bought won't stick and have foreign key
references to our outer dimension tables
where they're going to maintain that
additional information all right cuz can
this is things we massive we want this
to be through as trim as possible
because we have billions of rows so we
put all the actual metadata in the in
the dimension tables but in a scarce in
a star schema you can only have one one
level dimension tables out from the
center of the of the of the star right
so there's no additional tables over
here that these guys can join with right
in this case here I have a category
named a category description so I could
extract that out and normalize that
store that has another dimension table
with another foreign key going from this
to this but under a star schema your
your you know you're not allowed to do
that and we take a guess why yes exactly
so you said the time it takes you to
diverse or join those different tables
is going to be expensive because again
we're not doing like fine ll and ease
items
we're saying find all the items that the
you know that the state of Pennsylvania
has bought within this date range can be
hundreds of millions of rows solely so
we want to avoid as much as doing as
many joins as possible so a snowflake
schema is where you're allowed to do
have multiple dimension
outside of it right so again going back
up here right I have now can break out
my category information I have a foreign
key in the product dimension table and
then I have what is called now a lookup
table which is the things beyond the
mention table where I have that
normalized information as the output and
as I said a some database system some
OLAP systems will say explicitly you
can't have look-up tables you can't have
multiple levels beyond the first
dimension table so the the main sort of
two issues in this world as she sort of
said one of them is performance the
other one is actually going to be the
the integrity of the data that were
storing again so going back here if I if
I collapse down my lookup table into a
single dimension table well I'm gonna be
repeating the category name over and
over again so now if the category name
changes I need to make sure in my
application code that I go update all
the records that have that same category
name so that everything is in sync if
I'm normalized out like this in the
snowflake schema I don't have that
problem because I don't have one entry
for the category right so if you do a
star schema then this extra work that
you have to do in your application to
make sure that your your denormalized
tables are are consistent you now
actually potentially storing more
redundant information that's unnecessary
and so your size your database could be
larger it's not that big of a deal
because again the fact table is the main
is the main juggernaut in this in this
model and we will have ways to compress
that down so the the storage overhead of
denormalized tables is not that big of a
deal it's more the integrity stuff
that's more important and then as she
said the complexity of the queries with
a star schema are gonna be significantly
less than the complexity of the queries
in a snowflake schema because there's
only so many joins I could possibly do I
only have to go sort of one level deep
as we talked about we talked about a
quart apptimize ation the having more
tables or join against just makes
everything super harder when we have to
figure out the joint ordering and so by
restricting ourselves to a star schema
but may end up finding a the optimal
plan whereas the snowflake schema
we may not be able to so again when you
go out in a real world if you come
across data warehouses you're likely to
see either these two approaches because
they're better for analytics and this
this distinction between the dimension
table and the fact table will come up
when we start talking about doing joins
because we need to decide how we're
going to move data between nodes if we
can't do any local joins a town are
machines okay all right so let's talk
about the problem we trying to solve
today and I've already sort of briefly
just mentioned just now so our query
shows up in a master node that wants to
join on our NS and let's say that the
two tables R and s are just split across
the different partitions on the
different nodes uniformly so what's the
stupidest way for me to execute this
query in this set up yes exactly right
the dumbest thing I could do and it
would work it would still be correct is
that I I know I need touch data set
partitions two three and four and so I
just copy them in their entirety up into
the the node where partition one is now
all my data is local I do my joint and
spit back the result why is that stupid
yes he says me you may not need all the
data potentially yes but team Team
stupider yes absolutely yeah you're not
doing any computation on the other nodes
like this defeats the whole purpose of
having your stupid database all right
think about what I did I bought a bunch
of machines I partition my date at my
table across these machines but then my
query shows up and I just copy things
back over to the singing machine anyway
so I bet it would have been better off
just buying this one machine and doing
the join there right so this is the
problem we're trying to solve today
we're trying to say all right if a query
shows up and it wants to do a join we
need access data that's put now across
multiple resources how do we actually
how do we actually do this efficiently
what do we what do we need to be mindful
of when we decide whether we move data
or copy data or push the query or pull
the you know pull the results all right
these are all bit
we have to deal with the threat this
also assumes in this example that my
database can it can fit in on a single
node right again think of like the
Walmart database it's whatever hundreds
of petabytes it's not gonna fit on a
single machine so we're gonna happen run
attribute environment order to get any
any work done
OTP it's not an issue for kids again Oh
an OTP I'm only touching andis data and
E's data is maybe couple hundreds of
kilobytes or megabytes right it's not I
can easily fit that on a single box and
do all my transactions on that one box
in analytics I'm trying to touch the
entire table or large portions of the
table I'm not going to be able to do
everything on a single node so today our
focus is going to be on first discussing
the excuse your models we have in a
distributed database system for
analytics
we've already briefly touched on this a
little bit in the first lecture but now
we'll talk about it more more concretely
and see why it matters then let's
briefly talk about the issues doing
query planning then we'll talk about how
we do distributed joins the spoiler
would be that all the algorithms we
talked about early in the semester are
still still remain we still do them
there's no magic distributed join that
doesn't exist on a single node it's just
the question is again where do we move
data or where did we where do we move
the computation and then I'll finish up
with sort of a quick smattering of what
this sort of state of the art of cloud
databases look like in the world today
and just you know just it again you'll
see how just because it's in the cloud
doesn't mean we still don't care about
all the things we talked about the
entire semester okay all right so as I
said I briefly touch about this first
issue for the execution model or when we
talked about just to the introduction to
distributed databases but the two two
approaches we have to execute a query
are either a push versus a pool so with
a push the idea is that we want to send
the the query or the portion of the
query like the plan fragment to the
location of where the data is located
then run that portion of the query at
that local data and then now just send
back the result to whoever asked for it
like the home node or the base note
that's coordinating the query the idea
here is that we want to just as we
we do projection pushdown or predicate
push down on a single node system we
want to filter out and remove as much
useless data as early as possible before
we send anything over the network so if
we can send a portion of the query to
where the data is located crunch on it
there do some early filtering and then
when we transmit the data back to
another node we're not just blindly
copying all the data that the node has
we're just limiting it to the subset of
that we actually need for this
particular query now we'll see in a
second the lines get blurred and I
shared this system whether you're doing
one of versus another because in a
shared distance to system in general you
can't do any filtering because it's just
a just you know read and write a single
page you can't do anything special but
for shared disk systems again the lines
are blurred the other approach is to
pull the data at the query which is what
I shared this system normally would do
where we grab whatever the data we need
for actually this query we recognize
based on the query plan you know these
are the pages I want to access we pull
the data out make a copy of it
transmitted over the network bring it to
the node where our query is located then
we can then process it and crunch on it
and of course again the dish issue here
is that in an analytical system the the
amount of data the size of the data are
relative to the size of the query is
gonna be quite quite starve equate
different like a query say it's just a
sequel query couple kilobytes the most
I've ever heard from like Google or
Facebook is that sometimes they have
queries that are like like the sequel
text itself is like 10 megabytes right
that's that's a large as query but still
that compared to like reading a terabyte
of data it's nothing so the thing we
have to be mindful whether you want to
one versus the other is you know where's
the data located how can I access it and
is my query going to be larger or
smaller in size to transmit over the
network then the data I'm trying to
access and in analytics it's it's always
the case that the the data you're trying
to crunch on is larger so let's see this
in the context of a shared nothing
system so shared nothing systems are
typically push data to push the query to
the node so my query shows up to this
node here it's in charge of coordinating
with the other node to process
process the join so we're gonna do our
query planner I want to say on this node
if we had recognized oh we need to
access the the ID field for our NS
tables and I know that this node down
here has a partition that I want to
access so I'll just send information
I'll send the query plan fragment down
to this guy and say hey I know you have
this data between 101 and 201 chievous
join and then send me back the result
and the node up above is responsible for
taking the result of that this guy sent
plus it's local result combining them
together to then produce a sing result
back to the application so again we had
this transparency issue or transparency
guarantee where the application doesn't
know doesn't care where the query
actually executed
long as it gets back a single result so
in a shared nothing system it's quite
obvious that you'd want to do push the
courage of the data right because this
makes no sense for us to actually have
to copy this data up and processes it
there it's just better just to send the
query do the crunching locally for this
example we'll see some scenarios where
maybe you do want to do do some copy yes
your question is what if if s is
distributed as well then what well in
this case here it is distribute I'm just
saying like it's partitioned just but
it's partition
well common to your question later on
like correct what we'll come to that
later the in this simple example assume
that R and s are both partition on IDE
the ranges of the values at this
partition are exactly the same so
therefore I know when I'm doing a joint
at this node I don't need to look at any
other other partition in my cluster
everything I need to have computer node
for a single tuple in R is located here
but yeah exactly right I'm joining the
partition key well see those scenarios
in a second yes question
the question is in my example here my
tables are partitioned on my joint key
which is the best case scenario how
often does that happen usually for the
fact table pretty often right like I
would say it's pretty common let me
think about it like in a real system
like so I want to partition I
partitioned on user IDs and you know the
fact table could say here's this this
person bought this item and so it's a
bad example so say I want to do a join
between like here's here's the user IDs
and here's all their items that they
bought and then here's the session of
how they visited the webpage just to
figure out what items I looked at before
I bought something anyone trying to
figure out to learn like oh if they go
look at these much items then they're
more likely to buy something and so in
that case the user ID would be the
partitioning key and that would work out
nicely so it's not always the case but I
would say it's common enough but we'll
see in a second how we handle case where
it's not this like this the main thing I
emphasized here is we can push the query
to the data and that's be better for us
because this this data is gonna be
larger than then this guy here plus we
can also get the the additional benefit
that we paralyzed the computation
because now the top node doesn't have to
do all join this guy can do the join you
know portion the join and this guy can
do the other portion the join and we
just combine it together and the
combined part is cheaper it's cheap
relative to the joint cost so the other
approach is the pool the data to the
query again this is where I'm saying in
a shared disk system the lines are
blurred so we send our query to this
node here this node would recognize that
we've logically partitioned the data
such that this node down here is
responsible for this range that node on
top of that range so then they then go
to the the share disk go access those
pages pull back the results or so pull
back the pages they need
and they compute their local join and
then this guy shows up the result to the
other one so again this step here would
be pulled of data to the query because
I'm just blindly asking for pages where
it's located here and I have to copy it
over here but then certainly this part
here was push the query to the data
because this guy was able to you know
compute the join locally and send the
result up
so would you say that this is a pool
versus a push again it's both well see
it it will I don't think I've a slide
about this but the cloud vendors are
recognizing about having a dumb disks if
you want to call it that
Indy share just databases is a bad idea
because again I'm just always copying
this page without checking to see
whether actually need end the date on
the page I just know that I think I need
to look at it so I just say go give me
this page on like Amazon s3 they now
have a filter command where you actually
can do predicate push down and even when
you say go get this page you can also
say like oh but it also check this
filter for me to see whether everything
actually matches inside the page and if
yes then send it to me if no then don't
write so again that's pushing the query
to the data so again the lines are
blurred okay so one thing we talk about
though is that I said that last class we
made a big deal about if we have a
transaction commit and it touches
multiple nodes I want to make sure that
everyone agrees that all the nodes would
have to agree that this transaction is
allowed to commit before retail the
outside world then it committed all
right because because we're modifying
the database we don't want to lose any
changes but in an OLAP database weird is
doing read-only queries so we're not
really worried about updating the state
of the data to some multiple locations
and keeping those in sync but now we
have to deal with the case where a node
could crash while we're processing the
query and we had to figure out how to
handle that so the important thing to
understand is that when we go request
data from another machine or the shared
disk and it we get we get the copy of
that data when we were
that that's gonna get stored in the
buffer pool just like any other data we
have that we read from disk but it's
stored in like a temporary temporary
buffer space meaning it could get paged
the disk because we run out of space but
if we crash or restart the system to
come back all that temporary displaced
disk is blown away
because the the query or the transaction
that was protected the query that was
that was running that needed that data
is now gone because I crashed and so I
don't need to persist anything
so these OLAP queries for really large
databases can take a long time it's not
unheard of to have queries that could
take hours I've also heard of queries
that take days for column stores that's
gotten much better but back in the old
days it was certainly very common for
like a quarter to take days like you
want you run your reports once a month
and takes like a week to run it so if we
had this long running query and our node
crashes what should we do it's not a
correctness issue because we weren't
updating anything but ideally be nice
may be that we may not have to restart
the whole thing from scratch if it's
gonna take days so the the design
decision that most shared-nothing
distributed databases make is that
they're not gonna actually support query
fault tolerance meaning if your
long-running query crashes if a node
crashes during why your query is running
unless there's a replica that has the
data you need that could you know fill
in some missing piece depending where
you are in the query plan they're just
gonna abort the query and throw back an
error and and tell you to restart it and
we take a guess why they make this
decision
it's expensive right I'm running a long
run in query it starts generating a
bunch of enemy results and now I got to
make sure I flush them all the right to
mount the disk and make sure there's
durable across replicas in case that
there's a crash that's gonna make your
query to run a lot slower because the
disk is super slow so in the
in this sort of traditional data
warehouse world they would say oh you
just pay me ten million dollars to for
this very expensive database system
software I assume you're not running on
machines you found at Goodwill I'm
assuming you're buying on high-end
hardware so the likely that heart that
high-end harbor is gonna have a
catastrophic failure where you know it's
gonna crash in the middle of query is
gonna be low so therefore I'd rather not
pay the penalty of of taking snapshots
or writing me results about the disk as
I run so in general most oh that systems
are going to if a query Fano crashes
during during Cori execution and let's
say it's not just reading from from a
disk where you have copies of like it's
it's some the middle part of the query
we have enemy results that you say the
query fails is when Hadoop came out in
the mid-2000s they were actually taking
snapshots they were actually taking you
know writing at every step of a query
plan writing that out the disk but that
made it super slow right cuz it gives
back in the old days when when even
still now but like when Google was
building that produce they talked about
running on you know cheap hardware where
if you're running a thousand node
cluster and your query is run across
1,000 nodes the likelihood that any
notes gonna crash during that time is
pretty high so and they're well they
would rather take the snapshots to avoid
this yes we're not so much transactions
here which read-only queries analytical
queries right so if it's a if say in
from last class which I went
transactional distributed distributed
datastore transactions if a node fails
that while we're exiting transaction we
just abort that transaction because who
cares so that transaction what ran for
50 milliseconds who cares if now I have
analytical where that's gonna take days
to run if it's take if takes five days
to run I cry
the fourth day the night's wasted four
days of work some people would get
actually pissed about that because now
you gotta you know start it up and run
run all over again and so you could take
a snapshot some systems allow you to
take snapshots as you run the query at
the oleg as the output of one query plan
as gets fed into the next operator I'll
just write all that out to disk as well
so that if I crash at that point I can
bring it back there's ways to turn that
on but by default most systems do not
because they don't want to pay that
performance penalty overhead so again on
a shared your system it's easy to it's
easy to visualize and we're doing that
same join we send the plan timing down
here and then as it computes the join
result it's gonna write that out to the
shared disk there's some notification to
a coordinator to say hey if you're
looking for this join result here's
where to go get it on the shared disk
and that way this guy crashes and goes
away this guy knows he can just pull it
from from there and not worry about you
know how to read good anything so so
again this is an important design
decision that the distributed Avis is
are gonna make their there they're not
gonna provide you what sometimes called
query resiliency or fault tolerance
where the query executes
they maybe restart the query for you but
they're not gonna try to pick up where a
node was running at the Miller at the
crash okay all right so the other thing
you got to worry about now is also have
new query planning so we have all the
same issues that we had before join
orderings how to do predicates pushdowns
or the projections all those same
decisions we had to do on a single node
system we have to do in the distributed
system but now we have a certain extra
level of planning where we need to
reason about where our data is located
how its partitioned or replicated and
now account for the network
communication cost for our algorithms
right and this makes more sense in a
second when we talk about the different
scenarios but like the joint ordering
still matters but now it's also like
alright well I need it should I join
these two tables first because they're
on the same node a partition in the same
way and therefore that can be really
fast even though if I was on a single
node I may not want to join those two
tab
first so that just could now included in
your cost model to have you help me make
a decision
about again what's the right this query
planned a most optimal query plan for
the for the system again just as I said
before doing query optimization on a
single note is hard this is just even
harder okay and like we you know
sometimes you can make a decision on a
single node and centralize the location
sometimes you can make it into
distribute across all the nodes but now
again you had this you have to make sure
all your statistics and all your nodes
are updated as much as possible to help
you make decisions about what the best
plan could be it's just everything just
much much harder when it's distributed
but now same way we have now a query
plan what do we actually want to send to
our different nodes that are that are
going to participate in executing a
joint query so there's two approaches
one is we could actually send the
physical plan or plan fragment to to the
node for it to execute by just taking
the query plan that we've generated on
you know on the base note of the home
node and then carving it up to say well
I know this portion of the query plan
needs to execute on this this node this
other portion the query planner needs
actually on that node you just share
those physical operators to the other
nodes they just take them and
immediately execute them without
reasoning about whether that's the best
thing to do for the local data and then
sending back the results so as far as
they know most most ribbity databases
that are doing analytics do this first
approach well the generate the run the
query plan through an optimizer once
generate a global plan for the entire
cluster for the query then carve it up
into two plan fragments and divide it up
another approach is to actually take the
Seco query that came in and then rewrite
it to have it be on a per partition
basis have a C query each individual
partition and then send that out then
when the when the node that that where
the partition is located it gets that
sequel query then it runs it through its
own query optimizer to generate the
physical plan that it wants to execute
the idea here is that
if we can assume that the if we did a
global plan on a single node the
statistics and information about what's
what's best at each partition is not
going to be up to date or you know or
fresh and therefore rather than me
trying to reason at my home node what
the best thing to do at this other node
I'll just say to this other node hey I
think you need to execute this query or
I need to react to this query for me and
then that that node can then do all the
local optimization and all local
planning when that psycho query arrives
so again look at example here so this is
my query like this and so I could in
this case it there's you know there's
there's no joint odor ah well it's
either RS or SR but I just say alright
well I know me actually the query and
need such data at these three partitions
so I'll rewrite my sequel statement to
now include a where clause that says
here's the here's the portion of the
data you need to look at which matches
what the partition key is or the
partition ranges then the node gets gets
this each each node gets these
individual query plans running through
its own optimizer and then they can
decide Oh based on the data I have here
is it better to join our than SRS then
our shut you a hash join so do a sort
merge join I can make a local decision
here because I have the best view of
what's what date I'm actually storing
whereas the home node again could be out
of date so the only database something
that actually that I'm aware that
actually does something like this is is
mem sequel everybody everybody else
sends the physical plan I don't I mean
to me this seems convincing that you
could do this I think you still have to
make a higher-level decision of the
possible join order at you know if you
have multiple tables more than two like
I 5r s and T should I join
RNs or TNS first like I think there is
some information there that you may have
the reason about at the upper level but
when it comes time for the local node to
make this decision
you know everything it doesn't worry
about communicating with anybody else
I'm not saying one is better than other
I think this has interesting
implications that have not been explored
in the research
okay so now we want talk about joins
again joins are those expensive most
important thing you have to do in a
single node database and just you know
also in a Toshiba database for
analytical workload the large portion of
the time that the system is going to
spend executing a query where I be
reading data from disk or doing doing
our joint as we said reading from data
from disk there's you know there's there
are some methods you can do to speed
that up but in the end of the day you're
usually bound on how fast you can get
things off off of the physical device
but for joins we can be smart about
things so as I showed in the first
example the easiest way to do a join is
just get all the data we need to do our
join put them on a single node and run
our joint album but as I said you lose
all the extra parallelism actual
resources you have by dividing the data
across multiple nodes you lose all those
benefits and you also you know you may
not be able to actually put everything
in memory to run things fast
so there's before different approaches
actually how we actually or affordab it
scenarios you need to handle when we
want to do it should be to join and
again a distributor join is gonna be the
exact same way we would do a join on a
single node system but the idea is that
we need to figure out how to get the
data we want to join together on and on
us on a node it could be one node to be
multiple nodes such that we can do a
join locally without having to
coordinate with any other node while
we're doing the joint so when we do that
local joint it's all the same algorithms
the server's join nested loop join the
hash join that we talked about before
all the same optimizations apply it's
the step you have to deal with before
you do that join of how to get the data
to a node that that's gonna need it so
again we're gonna talk about four
different scenarios if you've already
sort of come up in our earlier examples
and we'll see how we actually wanna
handle them and again the main takeaway
is that there's no magic here that we
can actually do there's no magic
industry to join algorithm that's gonna
form so much better than a single node
one it's all about how to get the data
to where needs to be
I say the best-case scenario would be
one where the the table is one of the
tables for joining us partitioned on the
join team and then the other table is is
is replicated in its entirety at every
single node so in this case here the our
table is is partitioned on the on the ID
it's ID field which is in our join
clause and then the s table is
replicated in every node again this
could be the fact table this could be
the dimension table that this is small
enough where we could split it up or
small enough where we could replicate it
on every single machine so in this case
here again all we need to do is have
every single node do a local join to
produce the result for the data that it
has you know store and local storage and
then we just need to transmit the the
output of one of joining one node to
some centralized location so that we can
combine the results that produce a
single single answer to our application
all right again this is the best-case
scenario is this transfer to get the
join result from this node to that node
is unavoidable we have to do it but when
we I should get the join we didn't need
a coordinator or communicate with any
other node because everything we needed
was local to us so this gives us the
benefit of a distributed database
because now we can run this join in
parallel on every single node without
any coordination and then everyone just
sends the result back to the head node
next best-case scenario is where the
both of the keys are partitioned above
the tables are partitioned on the join
key again in this case here the again s
ID on the last slide it was partitioned
on today was replicated this one is
partitioned on the ID field and the
range that's in this in this partition
it's the same as the range of sorry the
range of the partition for s is the same
as the range for position on R so again
just like before we compute our local
join give me a hash going to be nested
loop could be sort merge it doesn't
matter and then this guy's transmits the
result to this other node where we
combine it together yes so this question
his question is about data skew so in
this example here I'm showing you that
the ranges are the same one to 100 and
101 to 200 but it doesn't necessarily
tell you how many tuples exist in this
range or this partition so like say this
ID is the primary key for R so there's
exactly one hundred tuples for R but say
this is IDs not the primary key for ID
for s I could have a billion entries
within this range and then a billion
entries for that range how do I handle
that well in that case you've not you
would not want to have the same range as
the ID field so in that case you will
have to shuffle some data around talk
about in a second there's the best-case
scenario these are uniform uniformly
distributed exact same range I don't
need to corny I'm sure it doesn't
I agree but it won't have a real-world
I'm saying best-case of worst-case
scenario and we'll see how to handle as
things get worse all right so so related
to him so so the next issues gonna be
let's say that one of our tables is not
partitioned on the the same attribute
that we want to join on so in this case
here s is partition on the value field
so in this case
can't compute our local join because for
every single value of our ID here I
don't know whether it's it's you know a
matching tuba will exist on my local
partition then maybe won't over here
with the same ID so in this one this
case this is called a broadcast join and
the basic idea is that you copy the the
portion of the table that's missing from
from each partition to every other
partition so that now this node has a
complete copy of the table and then now
you just compute your local join and
then send the result over to the other
guy again this assumes that s is small
enough that it could you reside in
memory or not to cook not overwhelm this
machine or does note here you try to
copy everything here write the broadcast
means that you're basically generating
every node would end up with a
replicated copy of the table sometimes
just see you ever heard to as a
broadcaster owned a broadcast broadcast
partners join it just means they're
doing this initial step where they
transmit the data across to different
notes that everyone has a complete copy
and then you do the join the last
scenario is the absolute worst case
scenario is where both tables are not
partitioned at all on our join key and
now we need to reorganize the the layout
of the data so that we compute our join
more more efficiently so this will be
called a shuffle join trouble hash join
so basically we recognize that we'll
really want things to be partitioned on
the ID field so let me just start
copying the data that I need from these
two tables to lean these two different
nodes if this has to spill to disk run
out of space that's unavoidable so we
just go ahead and do that and then once
I know I have everything purchasing the
way I want to partitioned then I can
keep my local join and generate the
results yes
what so his question is and the space is
limited what can you do
so the point I'm trying to make here is
like Teemo what you end up doing here
right so I have to now make another copy
of our on on you know and store it on
this node and so if it doesn't fit in
memory just as I said like it's it's it
gets spilled as a temporary result for
the query could get spilled a disk
that's unavoidable right but the more
important thing is that now when I
compute the join I want that to be fast
as possible because that's the most
expensive thing so by copying data
around when I do the join everything is
partitioned nicely the way I want it and
it's more efficient we this question is
do we always assume that the disk is
enough for our class yes in the real
world no what will happen is the
database and recognizes that if I get to
here and I can't copy any more data to
this node here the query would fail just
just say I run out of swap stays for 10
space and you throw an errand the query
fails and actually related to his
question but about the dispersion of
data if say it was partitioned on the ID
field but the the distribution was
highly skewed sister that most of the
data was on this node for s instead of
that node I can still do this
reshuffling to to realign my data maybe
move some data from R and s over here so
that things even get balanced but still
it's still called a shuffle process
question how does a lot more compact oh
sorry
yes of course how do you manage what sir
our question is how do I make a decision
about what data to send because if
things are replicated I don't want to
waste
you know waste network transmission of
sending data that's that's that I don't
need to send you know everything ahead
of time right sequel is declarative we
know what the query is we know what data
are trying to access we then look in our
system catalog our system Callao is
gonna tell us how this data is actually
partitioned we know this ahead of time
so the query planner can make a decision
oh well this data partition this way and
it's this size and it's in on this node
so therefore and either move or not move
it or copy here don't copy there I can
do all that ahead of time it's not like
as I'm going along I say oh well yeah
maybe I should copy this you figure out
everything ahead of time except for the
issue he brought up or like I ran out of
disk space you know you just fail
nothing you can do and then the the how
efficient the the database system is in
making those decisions about what the
copy are not the copy depends on how
good your query optimizer is which is
why people pay a lot of money to have
people like work on query optimizers
question your question is what if the
data is sorted on the partition ID
beforehand but it's partition ID or
joint ID so if it's sorted for what I'm
showing here who cares right cuz what I
care about is the locality of the data I
need to join our ID on s ID so I want to
make sure that when I do that join
locally I have all the data that I need
to ever you know for you know to join
the outer table at the inner table is at
my local node it can't be at some other
node that I don't know about and that
could end up with a false negative or
false positive so sorting doesn't matter
sorting would matter when we can make a
decision about do I want to do a cert
mergers as hash join word like a step
above this we're designing how do we
move data
or not yes okay so question is what if
what am I actually transmitting here and
be clear I'm not swapping this I should
shouldn't have a divider line so this is
the permanent data on this node it does
not go anywhere I just make extra copies
as temporary temporary data to do my
joint and then I throw it away when my
queries over so even though I'm
shuffling here on ID the I'm still going
at the end of a partition or name and
value here this this stays but then your
other question is what am I actually
transmitting am i transmitting the whole
tuple or am i transmitting the summit
some identifiers next slide okay we'll
get to that yes your question is it on a
local node if the data is not sorted how
do I make sure that there's no
duplicates duplicates of what I want for
the join ha is a partition ID the
primary key or a unique ID what the well
yes all right get to questions that so I
think what you're asking is actually if
I have a primary key then I need to
guarantee it's unique but my my
partition key is not the primary key how
do I make sure that I enforce that so
that that is a transaction right that's
not us we're just doing analytical
queries we assume we don't like we
assume that someone else has solved that
for us when they inject and stored the
data as a part of a transaction so in
your example if I have a partition key
that's not the same as the primary key
then I insert a new record
how do I make sure that's unique while I
eat IVA need to maintain a sort of
centralized index that I
look up and see whether this key does
party exist or at the broadcast the
query to every node to say hey I'm
certain this key do you do you already
have a copy of it I'm saying you could
write help me how come in me how could
how could that be ID there's a node
here's an index we're building idiots we
do have every one right we can do this
again like I don't care about in this
world for these queries I'm not
enforcing integrity constraints I'm just
running this read query is analytical
queries to figure out you know how to
compute the joint efficiently on a large
a large data corpus the transactional
side it cares about integrity
constraints when you because you're
you're modifying the state of the
database no notice so so going back to
my initial example here like for this
ETL thing so this thing of this like
your bulk loading a bunch of data like
this is sort of streaming it's not happy
it's not like all at once here's a bunch
of data but you're streaming
incrementally updates from the front end
to your back end data warehouse and the
back end data warehouse could choose or
not choose to enforce those integrity
strains as it comes in but but it won't
be on the critical path of when we
execute our queries because I'm running
a selects David I'm not checking to see
whether my primary key is unique so now
how you enforce that integrity
constraint as you ingest the data into
your back into a toe warehouse well
that's the same thing we talked at last
class how to do transactions because
that is a type of transaction you know
insert something make sure it's unique I
need to coordinate across multiple nodes
if I'm not everything's not on a single
node to make that check it does everyone
agree that we can go ahead and make this
change so a lot of times in these
analytical data warehouses they will
have they will sort of have a separate
engine or a poor
Gorge area that is designed to do
efficient more are more efficient
updates than what a you know a
traditional comm store data system would
do if you take the advanced class we
will cover that we didn't cover that
here right so again for our purpose here
today we don't care about enforcing that
integrity train we assumed that it was
already handled for us some database
systems I mean some data warehouses they
just turn all that crap off they turn
off foreign keys they turn off unique
keys your data is a little dirty who
cares for analytics right so this
question is you have your bank account
or what it whatever your your your game
information you you update your user
account on the front end o to be
database because that's what that's the
users are touching this part they don't
touch the back in data or house they
make updates here that update gets
propagated and you want to go update the
record here has that happen advanced
class in general what I'll say is like
you buffer a bunch of changes in a sort
of right optimized storage layer or
execution engine in these data warehouse
and then they periodically merge the
change into the data warehouse or into
like the the main column store tables
for the for that for the new analytics
different systems do different things
okay
so any other questions about about this
stuff here
yes go ahead yes her question is I said
here that if when we go to copy this
thing here for this particular query if
we run a disk base and the query crashes
couldn't the query optimizer figure that
ahead of time and say oh I'm not gonna
have a disk space let me let me make
sure that maybe not run a certain way
here the query optimizer is usually do
not reason about what our other queries
running at the same time it assumed your
query runs in isolation and that it it
could reason about certain things like
some sort of some systems you can
specify how much temporary buffer space
or temporary displace the queries
allowed to use and then if you exceed
that in your query fails and it throws
you back hey you know creases parameter
if you want to keep running so it could
potentially figure out at planning time
oh I'm gonna copy over more data than I
have space for for this particular query
and throw an error but if like you dis
physically runs out of space even though
you're not within that you know you you
you haven't exceeded that limit on a per
query basis the query optimizer usually
does not think about or cannot reason
about what queries are running the same
time cuz that just makes your life
harder cuz like this query first-years
up I plan it I say all right nothing's
running now let me go ahead and and
choose one kind of plan because I'm
running by myself and start running and
then this other query now shows up I
don't want to go back and modify that
other queries plan to say hey now you're
also be running another query at the
same time that's way too hard
my comment was that sometimes you see in
data warehouses so the the database
system itself could support schema
enforcing integrity constraints foreign
keys primary keys referential integrity
and stuff like that it could support
those but the application developer the
person building the data warehouse may
say I don't want to pay the penalty to
check for foreign keys let me turn all
that off this question is I said that in
the previous slide that in general most
shared-nothing actually shared disk
notice distributed OLAP databases do not
support query fault tolerance or query
query resiliency where if a query if
they know crashes that's a response for
executing query halfway through the
query execution they are not able to
recover the enemy results of that query
it was had or computed and then picked
the query up where it left off in
general they just killed the whole thing
through an error or maybe restart it
silently for you that has nothing to do
with logging and recovery we absolutely
still need login recovery and we still
do that this is this is this is more
about while the queries running do I can
I take snapshots as I go along so that I
can pick up I can pick up midway where
the query was running if I know Goes
Down and I'm in the the statement I made
was that to the best of my knowledge
most distributed OLAP systems do not
support that query resiliency because
taking the check points the snapshots of
the mediary result is expensive logging
of what so what logging of what
the query of the database we're still
all the fault on all the the D the D and
acid stuff that we talked about before
we are still doing that we are still
making sure that if we ingest data from
the outside world up to our database we
don't want to lose that and so what they
will all provide durability guarantees
again I am I have a hundred petabytes of
Walmart they don't want to lose that
data all right and the days of them will
guarantee that they won't when you say
operation again what do you mean like
the UH nup date to it or we are queer e
I got like a select query let's take us
let's go let's sit down afterwards guy
I'll go through this I think there's
something you're missing here okay so to
his question about what am I actually
sending when I do these to ship it
adjoins am i sending the whole tuple or
am i sending them sending sending an
identifier and I always say the answer
is that you're sending at the very least
you're sending the minimum amount of
information that you need in order to
compute the join and then the worst-case
scenario you're sending the entire tuple
and in general again the the high end
the good distributed databases that are
doing analytics will minimize the amount
that data that you actually need and so
they're petite have a query would be
called using what is called a semi joint
a semi joint is like a regular join but
the idea is that we're not really gonna
do a join on the on the right table or
the inner table we're only gonna check
to see whether if we dare to join a
tuple would match so the query optimizer
can recognize that it may not need all
the old any inmate may not need any
values or attributes are from the
columns of the inner table
and therefore it can rewrite the query
just as do an existence check and send
the middleman information back and forth
of he knows to do that semi join rather
than copying the entire tuple again like
a natural join you would cut you would
do the join and then the output would be
all the result in the combination or the
the concatenated to post on the right
and the left table and a semi join it's
just the attributes that needed to
compute to join from the outer table so
in this case here say I have a query
like this select our ID from from are
doing outer join on s and we'll just
match my IDE oh and then this is a
poorly written query because they're
basically saying where our ID is not
null then match up with what on s so if
we didn't do a semi join we either have
to copy s over here or or R over here
again we're copying the entire tuple
that would be expensive but we could
rewrite this query to be like this where
we just check to see whether there
exists a tuple in s that has the same
ideas our ID and then if that's true
then we just spit out all our our IDs
that match so in this case here the only
thing I need to send over is just maybe
just the our IDs because that's the bare
minimum information I need in order to
compute this join so the some systems
like Claude hours and Paulo actually has
an explicit semi join keyword you can
give it otherwise you can try to fake it
with it exist the high end systems can
check to try to rewrite your query into
a semi join again it's part is figuring
out what data I need is transmitted
between between the different notes and
includes that in its cost calculations
in the optimizers cost model or to
decide how much data might transmit in
between different nodes as one plan
better than another so like I could have
I could say select our ID from our semi
join on s ID explicit sequel that does
that says hey you're doing a semi join
or I can rewrite it as this most systems
you have to do this because they don't
have I don't think semi joins in the
sequel standard
questions who does who does this work
and this example here this is the
application programmer the the high-end
enterprise systems that have good query
optimizers could figure out how to
potentially rewrite this for you they
can do that for you Oh quite your
question is the query optimizer another
node another like what do you mind node
even so this is like a partition that
you think it doesn't matter doesn't
matter what the query optimizer is
running this node here or another node
doesn't matter
did for more talked about here this is
just sort of like the semantics of the
semi joint
so from relational algebra standpoint it
just looks like this I'm joining R and s
and then the output this is the semi
joint operator the output would be just
skin to be a ID be ID that I used to
compute the joint and nothing from from
the the inner table so is this clear
there's a home a question on it all
right so we have ten minutes so as I
said this is to sort of crash course on
on crash course on the main design
decisions in the issues in tuning and a
little database if you're not going to
be building a you know an illiberal
database min root system actually
working on the internals of the system
you just want to be a user of them the
main issue you're going to deal with is
that partition key how to pick that in
such a way that most your joins can
operate on a local node without having
to do a broadcast or our shuffle and the
the the various systems that are out
there mostly the enterprise guys have
tools to help you try to figure these
things out for you okay all right let's
talk bout Claudius's so the definition
of comp cloud database is a bit nebulous
no pun intended the the
typically what it means is if some
vendor offering you what is called a
database as a service from dbaas the
idea is that you give Amazon whoever
your credit card and they will say
here's your JDBC or no DBC connection
port number and and and hostname that
you should start shoving queries into it
and you don't worry about how to manage
the nodes you don't worry about how to
do backups they take care of all of that
for you and so I already sort of
mentioned this before but the the in
these some major cloud vendors people
that control the whole stack like Amazon
like Google like Microsoft the lines
between what is a shared disk system
versus a share nothing system is
starting to get really blurry because
they can push down database logic up
between up and down the different layers
of the system stack in a way that you
typically can't do unless you control
the hardware yourself so for example
Amazon has something called Aurora
Aurora is a shared disk version of my
sequel in Postgres but they actually
push logic to do transaction management
down into the storage layer in the EBS
again at the shared disk level and so
now it's not pure pure shared disk
system anymore it starts to look a bit
more like a shared nothing system so
alright so I think in the next ten years
I think the cloud systems will receive
the mote you see the most innovation in
the cloud systems and I think it's
really really interesting what they can
kind of do alright so I think I've
really talked about this in general a
cloud system could either be a managed
database or a cloud native database so
managed database would be just taking an
off-the-shelf database that system that
was written to run on premise on
dedicated hardware and now you're just
running this for you as a service take
my Seco take Postgres and then you plop
it into an ec2 instance and then have
people connect to it and they don't know
and don't care that you're managing ec2
for them that they could have done that
themselves but you're just providing a
service to do all the backup and other
management stuff for them so most of the
times when you see when you get a cloud
database it's gonna be it's gonna be the
first one
now there are some systems where though
they'll refer to themselves as being a
cloud native data internet system and
these are ones where they're designed to
operate in a cloud environment and
typically they're going to be a shared
disk architecture because they don't
want actually have to build you know
replicate EBS or s3 so they'll build on
top of the existing storage
infrastructure that these cloud vendors
provide you and they're providing the
the compute layer on top of it you know
Stefan do query planning you still have
to do all the fault tolerant stuff we
talked about before but they don't worry
about actually how to you know persist
things to disk they just let cloud
vendor provide that for you so there is
now also a new class of systems that
label themselves as being serviced yes
yeah question is what would it like what
is it what is truly the difference here
so this would be a manager this would be
just using my sequence example I take my
sequel I didn't run it without making
any changes to it I run it in a
container or I run it in a VM and it's
the same software that I would run on my
local machine but just now I'm running
it in a you know in a cloud for you
right and then old and then the the
service provider will then also do the
backups and recovery and all the other
stuff for you this would be like I'm
building a new database system scratch
or I take an existing one and I make
heavy changes to it to be designed to
work in a cloud environment so up here
running my cycle my Seco doesn't know
anything but s3 doesn't know anything
about the performance implications of
you know reading PBS and things like
that just have a disk it has these
properties this would be like oh I've
designed the system's explicity to work
on s/3 s/3 provides me these guarantees
provide me these properties that
information now permeates all throughout
the system like my query optimizers cost
model can reason about you know what's
the speed of writing s3 or what you know
what can you do a nester you can't do on
EBS
stuff like that alright so there's a the
the buzzword going around now is
serverless
so of course there's server list
databases and so it's the same
everything's the same that we talked
about before
it's just that the idea is that when
your machine goes idle your data has
connection those idle because your
application is no longer sending queries
they will try to then deeper vision or
have you you know not pay for hardware
that you're not actually using so let's
say that I have again a managed database
system I have a single node it's running
my sequel and so I pay for I pay for the
instance I pay for the storage and I
have to provision it to be running all
the time so my application sends queries
to this guy and you know and gets
results comes back but now if my if my
application goes to sleep or walks away
goes the bathroom does whatever then I'm
paying for these resources I'm not
actually using right because I have to
provision the hard right that provision
the ec2 instance I provisioned the EBS
storage right so I'm paying for the
stuff to run and not actually do
anything so the idea with the serverless
database is it's almost always a shared
disk architecture is that I can do my
all my queries that I had before but now
when I go to sleep I decommission the
compute side of things this goes away
but before I do I basically take a
snapshot of what pages are my buffer
pool I take a checkpoint then record all
the page IDs or what's in my buffer pool
write that out the shared disk then kill
off my computer and so now the only
thing I'm paying for is storage just
paying for my data to rest at idle on
disk and then if I ever wake up and come
back and execute a query the very first
thing we're gonna do is say alright well
before I shut down the last time what
was in my buffer pool and got it trying
to fetch that in and make it as if I was
still running all the time
so this is one way to do it if you
assume that the there's only one
customer I'm running on a single node
another common setup would be you run
multiple customers or multiple tenants
on a single node and then you just
recognize that this customer has not
sent me to query in a while and then I
write out its buffer buffer pool page
contents out the disk before yes
so this question is why am I doing this
section chef why am i actually writing
the buffle blade page contents out to
disk before you know why do I care about
this because you want to make it as if
like the the most expensive thing is
fetching things from disk so ideally I
want to have you know my query the next
query shows up a minute later I don't
want to have everything all now evicted
from my buffer pool and I have to pay
this big upfront cost of warming all my
data I'm bringing into memory so you you
record all this information so that when
you come back again a minute later it
looks like the thing was still running
and you don't like you still paid a
penalty case you have to fetch it in but
you don't have to wait to like fetch
everything in you try to maybe prefetch
some stuff
you pre-warming with creamer in the
cache yeah every database system does
this when you call shut down do it like
a correct shot down they're already
doing this correct so his question is if
I don't do this step well this still
work yeah it'll be corrective it'll be
slow right this is this is just an
optimization to to can warm the cache in
a cigarette like we're just storing the
the cotton we're just turning the page
at ease we had in the buffer pool at the
time we at the moment did a shutdown so
then the first query shows up and and
then say the first query says go give me
page one two three it says oh I also had
four five six seven eight nine also in
there let me go fetch them and fetch the
Nolan yes this question her question is
how does it like to be stateless as in
the server lists it's usually what
people mean my service is stateless but
it isn't isn't right so if it's service
from the perspective of the end user
meaning like I don't have to say
provision me this machine so a lot of
cloud vendors they're not doing a
service architecture
you basically say
I want to be key I wouldn't you know I
want to pay for this dedicated resources
to be available for me at all time if
you're not using them they're so
charging you they're happy right but if
my I mean I have one query a minute I
don't want to me you know I don't want
to provision a whole machine just to
send X 60 queries an hour whereas in
this architecture I can still have my
database still as if it was running all
the time but I'm not paying that pending
so I pay or not I paid on a per query
basis plus whatever I'm storing over
here so the main vendors that are in
this space would be Amazon has a server
this version of my sequel and then fauna
DB is a as a separate database startup
that does so Amazon will try to all
these guys are doing
not exactly this where you kill the
machine they're just recognizing this
customer has not sent a query while and
and then they they write everything out
to disk so Azure can do this and then
Google I think it's these icons are so
useless because this like doesn't say
the name I know and I second what this
says I think it's the Google fire store
so not spanner or not the bigquery stuff
it's only for fire store all right so
another interesting thing about this is
that you could potentially build a
database system without having to write
every piece of the system yourself so
there's enough open-source software
that's out there now or services that
are out there you can cobble bunch of
these things together and make a new
cloud database without having to write
everything from scratch so we've already
talked about like as I said her question
was what is the cloud native database
well it's one where you assume that you
can write you know you the sulfur is
written to assume you're writing to s3
and you take those it's guarantees or
performance implications into the design
so that would be sort of one example
you're not the write that you know disk
manager you just let s3 handle that for
you you may not have to write your
catalogs right you can get metadata
service get metadata as a service
through these bunch of different types
of software you may not the manage your
cluster you can relies on kubernetes or
yarn or these other tools that the
vendors have to handle all that for you
and then you may not even have to build
your own query optimizer so there
actually are some open source
sort of optimizers as a service
where its runs on a separate node you
just feed it a bunch of XML or JSON
metadata to say here's what my data
looks like here's my query plan looks
like and then the separate machine will
then crunch on it and spit out a
potentially optimized plan for you I
don't know how good these things are
actually are I'm there has been any
study actually to evaluate them yet we
looked at Orca when we were building our
system and we passed on it because at
the time the documentation was terrible
Cal cites written in Java so that was a
non-starter for us as well all right the
last thing I briefly talked about is
file formats so pretty much until very
recently every single database minute
system always had their own proprietary
binary file format meaning like my
sequel writes a bunch of files a disk
you can't read those files into Oracle
well because Oracle has its own file
format can you do the same thing when
you built put your projects on bus tub
bus hub has its own page formats that
can't be read by anybody else so this is
problematic now if you're in a cloud
environment where you have a bunch of
different services that may want to
share data like a bunch of data I want
to generate my old to be databases and
maybe I want to run that data through
spark or learn that data through through
Vertica or some other Shiva database so
there right now if everything's based on
a pie chart format the only way you can
get data out from one system and put
into another system is to make copies
and put it into one of these human
readable text readable formats and so
now instead is that there's these open
source binary formats that a bunch of
cloud vendors or and distributed
databases or data science ecosystem
tools are now supporting to that I could
use right out to s3 or EBS or my
distributed file system a bunch of these
files in this format that might get my
data a system-generated and then I could
suck them in and read them into another
database without having to do that any
destabilization or conversion so some of
these you may have heard of but these
are just these are sort of a main ones
Parkay knork applied two most common
ones
Parkay Kemetic ladder and twitter and or
came out of hive and again think of
these are like binary column store
formats that are not tied to any one
pacific data system like an open
specification that anybody can modify
their database system Armada
by their application to read this data
natively Carbon data is a newer one
actually 2016 ish I think that's like
orc and the parkade that came out of
Hawaii in China iceberg is another new
one from from Netflix that I've just
notified recently by somebody I have
looked into much into yet but they claim
that they can support schema evolution
like I can do change columns and you
know change memes change column types
the way these other guys can these other
guys are read-only like I create the
file and then I freeze it and I can't go
back and change them hd5 is not
typically used in cloud systems or in
sort of traditional Silicon Valley
database for tech companies this is
mostly found in HPC in the scientific
world this is for like a Rea data like
you can have your you know your your
particle collider can can well spit out
bunch of these files in this type and
then arrow is an in-memory column format
that came out of pandas and gem IO that
think of this is like it's like parkade
orc but it's for in-memory data so our
data is more building here at Carnegie
Mellon our native stored format is
actually arrow so you could take data
that our data system generates dump it
out and feed it into pandas or whatever
it's I can't learn you want anything
that reads the arrow format so I think
this is the right way to go it is sort
of you get to the lowest common
denominator like there's you know the
compression scheme and all these these
different these formats may not be the
best for all possible applications and
certainly if you write a custom one you
could probably get much better
compression or better performance but
this this provides you interoperability
ok all right so just a finish up overlap
it means if you if you need analytical
database that needs to scale then you
have money because you're getting data
right people actually using whatever
application you have and you're actually
able to process it but the more data you
get and more problems you're gonna have
because because these two tivity
databases are you know all the
additional management concerns and
problems that you have with the
distributed system you do have to
account for all right so here's question
last time can I can i names what are
some interesting or
now these weren't good but what are the
main oh that systems you could possibly
look at well in the cloud red ship and
snowflake are the key to two players
Oracle and Microsoft and Google also
have their own Pacific services I think
these two are the probably the biggest
ones so this is run if you're running on
a cloud if you want to run on premise
the one that I'm actually super
interested in is click house so
distributed in memory column store
system out of Russia from the Yandex
guys and when you read their web page
the list of the things that they support
it's actually amazing and it's open
source to presto is runs on top of I
think SPARC and Hadoop splice machine is
HBase plus SPARC greenplum is a fourth
version of Postgres that somebody made
distributed it was a startup back in the
2000s they got bought by EMC the EMC
says we don't wanna be a data based
company so then they merged with VMware
became pivotal but in May open sourced
it Vertica was founded by my advisors
when I was in back back in New England
they got bought by HP the guy came gave
a talk a few weeks ago or the semester
so the way to think about this is like
if you have no money start here if you
have the money you could start over here
like Oracle data and tear data are super
super expensive like Exadata I don't
think you can buy a machine for less
than like you know two million dollars
because you're buying custom hardware
okay alright if you don't want to go
down this route its setting up a whole
distribute database there's a newer
system and I was all very excited about
called duck DB it's out of Europe think
of this duck DB as like sequel light for
analytics so you can run it as an
embedded database it actually you can
connect to it through the sequel like
terminal but it's a column store ranking
and can do you can do analytics on in
the same kind of way you can do here so
if your data can fit on a single node
duck PD might be the right thing and
it's open source okay
so that's it for the the main material
and the semester the next class after
the holiday we'll have a guest speaker
from Oracle and again we'll have the
final review and the the potpourri
session on Wednesday so at this point
again you should be confident enough to
go out in the real world and either
manager database or user database and
know enough about to opine whether you
know it the system you're working with
is making good ideas okay
we've covered a lot and you guys
hopefully you guys okay okay don't know
you can't