[Music]
they're an event I'm missing on campus
or what what is today free cake that's
pretty weak all right dude you drop
tables negative always all right all
right let's those are here let's look at
through this so again this is just the
the the outline for the many things for
you guys in the semester again these
dates are all available on the website
and then the extra credit for the the
first feedback review of the extra
credit what we do this Sunday and then I
also post on Piazza last night if you
haven't done this to already please go
vote for what database systems you want
me to cover on the last day yes result
of what sorry the result of what sorry
result
oh yeah right yeah no I have not heard
back yet
I will try if it comes in I will
announce on the last day of class I send
a send until Monday I don't it takes
whatever week or two or something so
well see any other questions related to
class again I don't think it looks like
me
alright this is say my wife lives a
certain lifestyle where I would have
questions ok so last class we talked
about it was an introduction to
distribute databases and sort of the
main three things we focus on was what
the system architecture of a system
looks like right we talked about shared
memory shared disk show nothing and I
said that most distributed databases are
actually every distributed race that's
out there is either gonna be shared disk
or sure nothing shared nothing is
traditionally the more popular approach
people take with distributed databases
but shared disk is becoming more
prevalent in cloud architectures
then we talk about are you partitioning
a sharding the hash partitioning rate
partitioning round robin just in a way
to take a database to break it up into
disjoint subsets that we assigned to
different different different nodes and
then we talked a little bit about the
end about how we want a new transaction
coordination of whether we have a
centralized approach that has a global
view of what's going on throughout new
tire system in the context of what
transactions are trying to do or a
decentralized approach where the the
nodes themselves are responsible for
figuring out you know whether things are
allowed to commit or not so the last
class all these topics are sort of with
accepted me for transaction coordination
but it for the most part everything I
talked about last class or applicable to
both trivedi databases that are designed
to run transactions or de juvinity races
that are trying to run designed around
analytics so for this class and then
Monday's Monday's class next week we're
now going to buy it up talking about
specific issues for each of those two
classes or workloads because there's
different trade-offs that they're gonna
make that may be good for transactions
but not good for analytics and
vice-versa it's again just as a reminder
for for what I mean when I say
transaction processing we're just an
analytical processing oil to be OLAP
again I think we've covered this a
couple times throughout the semester
just to reiterate this the dichotomy so
that everyone's on the same page and all
three workloads we're worrying about
operational operations that are trying
to update or read a small amount of data
in the database so again using Amazon as
an example when you go to the Amazon
website you add things to your cart you
make purchases for your account you
update your payment information all
those operations are transactions that
are only touching you know as we know
when you invoke those changes they're
only touching your data so the Amazon
database is quite large but for your
transactions to update you know do your
operations the amount of data you're
touching is is small and essentially the
database system is doing the same same
set of operations over and over again
because you're going through the the
website application code that you know
when you click on you know Add to Cart
that invokes a function on the
application code which then goes through
and execute so queries to make those
changes in OLAP workload this is where
we're now started doing analytics
to try to extrapolate new information
from all the data we've ingested on the
older TV side so again using Amazon eggs
example an analytical workload would be
something like trying to figure out what
was the most popular item for Carnegie
Mellon students during the month of
November when that when the temperature
was was you know above 30 degrees so
that's not something you do in LTP
because that's you know that's not a
transactional thing this is something
you do in the OLAP side
so these workloads are the queries much
running longer because they're touching
more data they're doing joins and doing
aggregations and oftentimes they are
one-off queries because someone's trying
to say you know answer that question oh
what's the most bought item for a
particular group of people and you know
they're filling out some dashboard or
using a analytical tool to compose the
query and then firing that off and maybe
the data that may never see that query
ever again so again for today's class
we're going to focus on the first part
oh it's P next class we'll talk about
overlap so the again just to go at a
high o discuss the what we're talking
about in distribute database so we're
going to focus on today we talked to the
set up before we have some partitioned
database whether it's logical
partitioning or physical partitioning
meaning is it shared nothing or shared
disk we you know I'm not explaining just
yet it doesn't matter what we're talk
about here today but the scenario we're
concerned about is we have we have a
application server that wants invoking
transaction it picks some partition node
to be the master one so it tells that
guy hey I want to execute a transaction
then it goes ahead and does a bunch of
updates or reads a bunch of data on our
various partitions and then now when a
transaction complete it goes to the
master guy that it started off with and
says hey I want to go ahead and commit
and assuming this is a decentralized
architecture meaning we don't have that
middleware we don't have that the TP
monitor that's coordinating all our
transactions now these notes at the
figure out amongst themselves whether
they're allowed to commit this
transaction so last class I was very
vague about this step here how to
determine whether it's safe to commit
and what does it mean to say hey we're
all going to go ahead and commit this
transaction so this is what we're
primarily going to focus on today this
this last step here and so essentially
what we're trying to do is we're trying
to have in our database system we're
trying to have all the nodes agree that
we should commit a transaction and if
everyone agrees that we commit this
transaction and we go ahead and commit
it we don't want any sort of weird
anomaly a weird reversal of you know one
node set is gonna commit and then an all
sudden it doesn't that transaction got
rolled back once everyone agrees that
we're gonna go to commit then we go
ahead and commit this so now there's
much issues we have to deal with in
order to make this happen correctly and
safely when we were on a shared
everything system meaning we our
database system was running on a single
box and we wanted to do our you know
validation protocol for OCC concurrency
control
the all the participants in deciding
whether this things a lot of commit was
running together in a single machine all
in the same memory possibly and it was
really fast and for us to figure out
whether we're allowed to go ahead and
commit and then if we said commit and it
truly was committed because we know
everything was on that single box but
now in distribute environment we have
the issue of let's say we go ahead and
say to commit everyone comes back and
says we go commit and then maybe I you
know during that time one--not goes down
what should happen I know all the same
asset properties we talked about before
then we don't need partial updates that
you're persisting to our database all of
those things we have to account for so
if an O goes down or I've got to deal
with that but what if the node doesn't
go down and instead our commit messages
just shorter show up late right the
packet got delayed somehow on the
network on the way over or which is
probably more common say our database
system was was you know buting the JVM
like it's written in Java written in
scala it's using the JVM and all sudden
the JVM decides to do a real expensive
garbage collection sweet and now our
process pauses and so we're gonna look
like we're unavailable why during this
GC GC pass and then all of a sudden we
come back after the GC and now our
messages are arrived and it's you know a
second has passed and then what happens
if we decide that how we determine how
many nodes have to agree that we're
gonna commit a transaction to decide
that we committed the transaction should
be all of them should it be some of them
right so these the things that we're
gonna we're gonna worry about today so
one important sumption we're gonna make
about this entire lecture is that we are
going to assume that the software
running on the arm nodes in our
distributed database or our friends
meaning gonna be well behaved
they're not gonna trying to screw us
over right there it's software that we
we as the database system developer
software that we wrote and that we've
deployed on the same administrative
domain so we asked a transaction we
asked endo to commit a transaction and
they come back so yeah we're going to
commit that we assume you know a modulo
harbor failure or you know software bug
we assume if a node tells us they're
going to commit a transaction they will
commit that transaction all right that's
going to simplify in some ways how we're
gonna do our commit protocol if you
assume that the nodes could be bad
actors right if they say yeah we
committed that with our screw you we're
not actually do that then you don't need
some of the things we'll talk about
today you actually need what it's called
a busy team fault tolerant protocol and
this is essentially what the blockchain
is under Bitcoin right a blockchain is
essentially just a distributed database
it's just a law your pen thinks but
transactions but in that environment you
soon because there's Bitcoin mining
right or whatever you're trying to do
that the participants in your
distributed database are not your friend
and they can lie to you so you need a
way to deal with that we are not in that
world most database systems durability
systems are not in this world most
refrigerators can assume that everybody
is gonna be is gonna play along
correctly most people don't need a
blockchain very few things need a
blockchain so if you think you're
building something and you use a
blockchain you rethink your life ok all
right so the things were talked about
today are listed here so yeah I didn't
say this last class I wanna sort of say
it again I'm trying to cover in three
lectures what would normally be like an
entire year of studying distributed
databases so we can't obviously cover
everything in detail and I consider my
goal here so just to expose you to like
the issues the problems the difficulties
of building a distributed database even
using a distributed database system so
that you know when you leave CMU and you
go out in the real world if you find
yourself in a situation
where you think you either need a user
Trivedi database or you think you want
to build one usually snow what are the
issues you should be thinking about and
so you can reason about you know whether
you're doing the right thing and also to
say upfront that most people probably
don't need a sugar database there's
obviously some useful cases but I would
say I mean I can't prove this but 90% of
the world's databases comes running on a
single box now I should have replication
and once you bring that in that becomes
a tribute database but most the times
you don't need a partition database most
workloads can handle be handled on a
single box right alright so let's talk
about time of commit protocol is how do
you get everyone to agree that we're
gonna commit how do we handle
replication to make sure that we have
multiple copies of our data so we can
always stay online then we'll get into
the cat fear I'm talking about
consistency issues how do we you know
what kind of guarantees can i distribute
database and provide for us
given our commit protocol and then we
have time at the end well quickly
talking about federated databases the
idea of composing dispair databases
together and to make a single database
instance okay alright so that example I
showed in the beginning of when we went
to go ahead and commit the transaction
and then the the one know how to talk to
the other nodes and say hey is it safe
to commit this is what is called an
atomic commit protocol yet idea here is
that we want to get everyone's feedback
that participated in our transaction to
decide whether it's okay to commit that
transaction and then if if one node or
enough nodes depending what protocol are
using if a certain amount of nodes above
the threshold that we're gonna define in
our protocol all agree that we should
commit this transaction then we tell
everyone we will commit this transaction
and then it then it becomes committed so
there's a bunch of different variants of
atomic commit protocol that you can use
so the two that we're going to focus on
is two-phase commit and Paxos two-phase
commit is probably the most prevalent
one right goes back into the 1980s
paxos has certain guarantees that
two-phase commit cannot provide some
systems can use this but it's this is
sort of a degenerate case of this
there's also a three phase commit that
was actually developed by Mike
Stonebraker the guy had invented
Postgres in the 1980s no one actually
ever does this it's too
there's too much you know too much
network traffic there's actually a four
phase commit as well from Microsoft they
using in this just to be a base called
form they have to do that because
they're using our DMA sort of special
remote memory access again we're not
going to cover that okay Pat so so we'll
talk about raft is was developed by
Stanford about ten years ago as a more
easily understood variant of paxos but
it basically provides the same
guarantees raft actually shows up a lot
more often in newer distributed systems
because there's a lot of existing or
that people basically wrote like Lib
raft right they were at libraries that
implement wrap that you can then
incorporate into their database for a
ton of different languages like there's
no Lib Paxos that everyone can use
Zab was developed for Apache zookeeper
and the view stamp replication is not
that common but this actually turned out
to be the first purely correct atomic
commit protocol it actually came out
before Paxos but people didn't recognize
that the properties of this thing had
until pax s came along much later so
again for distributed databases that are
not in the blockchain that are actually
you probably an encounter in the real
world use mostly you most likely see
two-phase commit or paxos and then from
new assistants apply wrap but for this
lecture I will just cover those two
they're the two base commit impacts
those so actual quick show of hands who
here has ever heard of two-phase commit
before alright
less than that okay so two-phase commit
sounds exactly the way you know it
sounds like it's a two-phase commit
protocol has two phases
so let's look an example here where
we're gonna have everyone agreed to
commit a transaction so assume at this
point the application server has
executed whatever queries that it wants
to to make changes on the database or
read whatever did data once on our
different nodes and it wants to go ahead
and commit so it's gonna send a commit
message to this guy here assume this is
the master node so under two-phase
commit a vernacular we are gonna say
this guy is going to be centered the
coordinator so that's in charge of
asking around to its friends involved in
the transaction whether it's allowed to
commit this transaction and then the
other two nodes here we call
participants now
I'm not going to show examples of this
but the node that participant node
itself
can also be a participant right this the
this note here could also have been
modified by this transaction and then
it's involved in this two-phase commit
process or simplicity assume that this
transaction here only modified data on
the on the two other nodes so in the
first phase called prepare phase we sent
out a network message to our
participants from the coordinator to
participants to ask them hey here's this
transaction we think you know about it
is it okay to commit and they're gonna
do whatever validation or whatever they
need to do to determine whether this
transactions live commit and if they
determine that it's okay then they send
back an okay message then now once you
get back the okay's from all the
participants the coordinator goes into
the second phase called the commit phase
where it tells the all the participants
hey good news everybody said we can
commit this transaction go ahead and
commit this and then likewise these guys
now have to send a response and say okay
we did that this transaction is
committed and then at this point here
when we get back and in the second phase
the okay's from all our participants we
can then go tell the outside world that
our transaction has successfully
committed so there's one thing I'm not
showing here and I think that the
textbook talks about this is that at
every step of the protocol on every
single node involved in it we're writing
out log messages to keep track of what
messages we got and what message what
what responses we sent out so at this
point here when I sent hey we'll go
ahead and commit this these guys are
gonna write a log message and say hey
for this transaction I saw I got a inter
of the commit phase and I said that was
okay to do right so that way if we crash
and come back we would say oh we were
involved in this transaction how far and
in the two-phase commit process did we
get to determine whether we need to undo
it or redo it
and so another point indistinct about
this and this will differ from taxes and
a few more slides is that all of the
nodes prevent all participant nodes in
the commit protocol for this transaction
they all have to say we have to commit
this transaction
it's either everyone or no one so we go
to the next sample here of one we
already have an abort it's again the
same thing Mike transaction finishes I
send a commit request to my coordinator
the coordinator enters the first phase
sent the prepare message to the to-to-to
participant nodes let's say this bottom
guy here for whatever reason you know
for its concurrency or protocols the
size that we cannot commit this
transaction so it sends back an abort
message so as soon as the coordinator
gets the first abort message from any of
the participants it is no longer in the
prepare phase and now it medially goes
into the next phase in this case we're
for the abort and so at this point we
can really go back to our client our
application and say hey this transaction
can't finish we're going to abort even
before we and go to the second phase or
even from before we hear back from
anybody else one abort message will kill
this entire thing so now in the abort
phase we say hey we're aborting this and
then everyone comes back says oK we've
aborted and at this point the the
transaction is done so the idea is here
that we need to network round trips to
get everyone to agree that were to
commit this transaction and then we go
ahead and our commit or abort this
transaction and we go ahead and then
apply that change yes so this question
for the abort commit the question is do
I need this second round here to tell
that the do I need to go to the nodes
here and say yes you've committed before
I tell the application run before I tell
so his question is same here I'm in the
prepare phase this rule action should
commit a semi semi preparer request
these guys send back okay is do I really
need to wait for the next round trip to
say okay go ahead and commit this and
get here back
from them before I can tell the
application I need to commit in practice
no for absolute correctness yes because
like if I can fight if I crash at this
point here right there's a trade-off
between the time it takes to recover and
the time it takes to send the response
so in if I'm logging everything to disk
then you're right
soon as I get back here if I crash at
this point here I have my two okay's
from my participants I'm gonna log that
to in the coordinator so now if I crash
I come back and I would say say save
been the coordinator goes down it would
come back in look in the long say oh I
solved this thing you know I got these
messages did I commit or not
okay well make sure I'm applying any
exchanges if one of these guys goes down
they would come back but they men they
would still need to know whether you
know whether it actually truly committed
free before they get actually you know
redo everything so for at the
correctness you asked for performance
you don't have to do that yes so this
question is if I'm here and then I send
back so I got I get to this point
everyone agrees that we're gonna commit
we're gonna write on disk in the
coordinator that we've committed that
everyone agreed to commit so therefore
we can enter this the the second phase
and go actually go ahead and do the
commit but then I crash before and then
I come back and I can reapply the change
and I didn't tell this guy he committed
so that's so that is actually not a
guarantee that we can provide in our
database system if this is true whether
it's single node or distributive so if
we get to the point where everywhere you
know we flush the log to disk we
everyone agreed that we're going to
commit but then before we tell the
outside world we've committed we crashed
and that never gonna Versa doesn't go
that tractions actually still gets
considered to be committed and it's up
for the application code to then come
back and figure out whether the double
question it asks actually committed or
not we can't guarantee that right
because how do we know like
in this case here that this message
could get could get lost the app the
database server it shouldn't be
responsible for figuring that out yes
from which one like for this one for
this one this the second phase no you
can it's just like just like mommy
aboard the transaction on a single node
as soon as I notes
I'm aborted why wait to flush any CLR
anything out the disk I just tell the
outside world immediately you'll board
it and who cares right because that's
it's as if the transaction never
executed so we tell it right away do you
have a question or no okay so actually
related to his question earlier about
the comment like do I really need to
wait for the okay's before that I tell
the outside world that I committed this
is this is actually two of the
optimizations you can actually do to
speed up the protocol and in exchange
for having a longer recovery time well
that that's the second one here that's
what he proposed
so the first optimization you can do is
caught early prepared loading so this
would be where if I know that my my
application is sending the last query
that is ever going to execute to one of
the participant nodes then in addition
to it to me sending the query I also
piggyback another message it says oh by
the way I'm never coming back you ask
you to do anything else so go ahead and
send me your response as if we were as
if we were in the prepare phase for
two-phase commit so now it's one network
message to exit the query and run run
the prepare phase and then my response I
get I get the result of that query plus
the result of the prepare check so this
obviously requires you to know and the
application server that you're never
going to go back and run another query
on the on that on that node what he was
proposing is the it was called early
acknowledgment after prepare so once you
know a known the coordinator that
everyone agrees ever to commit this
transaction then you can merely tell the
outside world your connection
transaction is committed and then you
take care of the of the
commit phase so again just visually it's
like this I do commit prepare phase
everyone votes that it's okay and then
now at this point once I get my two
responses for my participants I can go
ahead and tell the application I I
committed and the idea here is that the
likelihood that I'm gonna crash for this
round trip here is low so therefore I
it's okay for me to go ahead and do this
if I now crash during this you know say
before I hear back from this over for a
head back from B's then I have to do
extra work to figure out whether I true
actually committed and resolved the
thing correctly but that's okay yes this
question is if a transaction if we're in
this phase here and prepare I get my
prepare message participants says okay
I'm gonna commit this your question is
what do they logged at this point yes
yes yes yes okay so his question is so
I'm here I I send back my okay I tell
the application okay you've had your
go-ahead and committed but now this
participant crashes in the log it says I
told the correlator I was gonna commit
what do I do want to come back well this
do you assume the coordinator would know
all right well this guy crashed now he
comes back and I'm in my in my log here
I would I would then say all right well
I saw commits from everyone this
transaction should commit so you would
have quoted or fill in the missing
information as needed on the participant
participant when it comes back up right
so you would get here the commit message
and then that would never never show up
so the mister then it dies so this
requires you to have so we're not gonna
it does this is more distributed systems
stuff but it's you care about that we
need to hear
this one you can use like a heartbeat
just to keep track of like is the note
up to have this thing determine whether
like I I haven't heard back from them in
a while go into some recovery mode or a
failure mode to handle that case yeah
yes sir your question is why do we why
do we send the so that's when I should
question is why are we not sending the
success message after the commit phase
yeah so that's like the the original
two-phase commit protocol that's how it
works right
but think about in I'm not saying also
where these notes are located could be
in the same rack and the same data
center it could be across the world so
rather than me waiting for this the next
round trip which could be 100
milliseconds maybe longer I'll just go
ahead and send that hey you're actually
committed because I assume that I'm not
gonna crash during this time and I had a
copy magnet mechanism that are necessary
to then handle a ferritin error that he
mentioned to recover myself if I come
back after a crash yes your question is
if if you're here so you've told the
outside world you've told the
coordinator you want to you want to
commit what is actually what is this
note actually doing could you just keep
everything in memory questions instead
of I'm being vague here but like in the
original two-phase commit protocol like
I I logged a disk then sent my response
but nobody does that right so in theory
you could just buffer the log messages
if it gets flushed out as a group part
of group commit who cares but I know
that if I crash to come back and maybe
some of those log records that told me
what I was how I voted for committing
this transaction get lost
I could
come back and the coordinator would have
could could put me up get me up to speed
where I let you know fill in the missing
details that that I lost yeah you could
do that as well yeah I don't think
anybody does the hard core like flush
every log record on every single node
every single time nobody does nobody
does that so far as I know okay so just
to reiterate everything we talked about
tonight so the as I said the the nodes
can record what happens and each phase
and what messages they receive what
messages they send out to it to a log
and that allows them to fill in the
missing details when you come back after
a crash so if we're in while we're
running our transaction and the
coordinator crashes before we tell that
you know before we resolve what actually
happened it's up for the participants to
decide how to how they want to proceed
so the simplest thing to do is like if
the coordinator goes down assume the
transaction aborts and we just you know
you roll back any changes but you could
have the participants recognize our
coordinator is down and our transactions
still open so somebody could become the
new coordinator and then figure out how
everyone voted and then decide whether
you want to commit that transaction or
not yes so her question is what what if
we're here and say this guy sends the
commit message that arrives at no.2 but
before it can send the other one to
node3
it crashes what happens right so again
the first option is I write if we can
recognize the coordinator crash whether
it's a heartbeat or timeout or whatever
we just say this we had open transaction
we're gonna abort but at this point
we've told once we the coroner says one
one note hey this transaction is
committed that is the the ground truth
of what actually happened so it's now
let's up for this node then corn ate
with everyone else or tell everyone else
hey this transaction I the coordinator
said I transaction committed we should
actually go head and commit this
right again this is what I'm saying that
like we this doesn't work if our notes
are malicious it only works that like
everyone's on you know playing on the
same team so we hear we hear one commit
message from this guy and that should be
enough to validate everyone else and
tell them yes we should commit this okay
so then now if a participant crashes so
for this one under two phase commit we
just assume that the participant is gone
and we replace their missing response
with just an abort and we go ahead and
abort the transaction right that's sort
of the best thing to do so the key thing
to point out here what's happening is
that the nodes have a block until they
find out what's supposed to happen and
the wait you know to avoid blocking
forever you just have a sort of a
timeout but how long you set that you
know can vary depending on the operating
environment you just have a timeout and
say all right I haven't heard anything
about this person on time so we get we
go ahead and abort this transaction so
you could have a you know live block
issue or an issue we're like just not
making any forward progress because your
nose are sitting around and waiting so
an alternative to two-phase commit
choose Dubey scheme it is probably
certainly any distributed database built
in the 1980s and 90s is amusing
two-phase commit the newer ones can use
variants to two days commit or could use
Paxos a raft to base commit is a sort of
a subset or gender of a case of paxos
and hopefully it makes sense when we go
through it so with paxos it comes from
the distributed computing world so said
I'm calling this an atomic commit
protocol they'll call this a census
protocol but the idea is the same you're
trying to get a bunch of nodes to agree
that this is the correct behavior this
the correct change to our state machine
so what's gonna happen is under Patos is
that you can have a coordinator propose
whether transactions allowed to commit
and then a bunch of participants are
going to vote whether it's gonna succeed
or not whether that transaction is
allowed to commit but under paxos we
only need a majority of the nodes to
agree that committed to transact
in two-phase commit we need all of them
right so now what happens is that long
as you have the majority of nodes but a
green Commission's action you don't have
to block the entire system or block the
entire protocol you can still make
forward progress where again two-phase
commit you would have one one having one
participant become unavailable blocks
the whole thing so paxos the story
passes is quite interesting so the the
first description of paxos is in this
paper written by Leslie Lamport who won
the Turing award a few years ago called
the part-time Parliament so I think this
paper is dated
it says 1998 but he actually invented it
in - in 1992 and what he was trying to
do he was trying to come up with a proof
by contradiction of an example that
shows you couldn't have a consensus
protocol with this fault-tolerance
property and they end up in the process
of actually inventing one so if you ever
read this paper it's the craziest thing
because it's it's written as if he's
like an archaeologist and he finds he
goes this greek island a Paxos and he
finds this stone tablets and he derives
what the actual the algorithm is from
these ancient civilization like it's not
a computer science paper it's all like
this this this illustrative story so the
story goes is that he wrote this paper
92 with all this like the Greek island
stuff
the reviewers hated the story want him
to put you know rewrite it to make him
more of computer science he he refused
and he didn't make any change so he
retracted the paper put it in his his
filing cabinet it didn't touch it for
like six or seven years until people
started publishing papers that look a
little bit like Paxos so then he pulled
out says aha you're you're all way off
or you're close but I've already solved
this problem so that's what that's the
story you get when you read it from
Pleasant lamport's website when I was in
grad school one of my I took a class
from Maurice Herlihy the guy then menon
linearize ability transactional memory
he's being professor here at CMU and he
said he was actually one of the
reviewers of this paper and he said they
were they were okay back in 1992 with
all the Greek islands story they just
wanted him an avid add an appendix with
just an algorithm to show what the thing
actually was and like you know brief
description of it
and Leslie Lamport was so stubborn he
didn't he thought the paper is so
perfect he didn't change anything so but
it's an interesting paper you should
definitely go read it it's a it's
probably if you read you reason read
this for amusement you're not gonna
learn anything from it at least I didn't
um
and then he has a follow-up paper called
Paks photos made simple
that doesn't help either it's the Google
one paxos made live for me that was the
one that actually forget clicked and now
I understand what the protocol actually
was so let's go through a brief example
so for this we're now gonna introduce an
additional node right because we need to
have a voting majority and then the
difference is gonna be now when we got a
commitment crest under the paxos
parlance instead of on our to base
commit we have a coordinator Pat those
calls as a proposer
and then a set of participants they're
going to call it acceptors so this the
the proposer is going to say hey we want
to go ahead and commit this transaction
is that gonna be okay so now let's say
in our example here this middle node
here crashes and goes down so now the
first two nodes come back says yes we
agreed to go ahead and commit this so
under Paxos we just need a majority so
two out of three nodes in this example
here agree to commit this transaction so
that's enough that's enough for us to go
ahead and try to commit this on our two
phase commit if this guy goes down we we
have to abort the whole thing so now we
get the majority to agree we go ahead
and commit and they come back and say
yes we accept to make that commit and
then now we have to send back our
success message so we actually for this
one we have to wait until we get Beth to
the second phase response back we can't
shortcut it in a way you can in
two-phase commit because we actually
could come back and get rejected in in
the second phase so let's look at a
different example let's look at it in
terms of a timeline here so let's say at
the exact same time there's two
different proposers in our distributed
database and so the first guy is gonna
say hey I want to come to this
transaction and sort of think of what
they're really doing in the state
machine they're just appending a log
message and say here's the change we
made the state machine is the database
so they're proposing that this
transaction should commit and
for each changes should be applied to
the database so I'm moving the state
forward so it says I want to commit the
change for a timestamp n so girls lots
of acceptors right and then they come
back and say yes we agreed to go ahead
and commit this change but now there's
other propose that comes along says I've
other transaction that made a change and
it's timestamp is M plus one so it's a
logical time stamp so now what will
happen is if this guy comes back and
says hey I want to commit n cuz you guys
all agree to commit this let's go ahead
and commit this they're gonna reject it
because they stole n plus one so even
though they don't know what the outcome
of n plus one is going to be just the
mere fact of seeing a new proposal for
committing a transaction or changing the
state of the database that requires them
to all abort a reject the the one they
all agreed to before so then now we send
the agreement to commit and plus one and
then he goes says I all right great
let's go commit n plus one and then once
we all accept this then at this point
here the transaction is actually
committed yes our question is yes so
it's your question investigation what is
this n and so if I come along with n
minus one would that be be immediately
rejected yes
now how you actually have a logically in
a a globally valid timestamp or counter
that everyone agrees to go you know go
up in the correct order so that I can
always move four in a time the simple
way to do that is you assume your clocks
are reasonably in sync and you you could
you could append a logical counter to it
maybe prefix the hostname so that you
can break ties right there's standard
tricks to handle this yes
all right so her question is could this
go forever I mean theory could couldn't
be to proposer just keep clobbering each
other back and forth yes well we'll
handle that next slide yes so your
question is does it matter if there's
say stating it there's a majority of
acceptors or yes okay how would that
work yeah so if one guy if one of these
acceptors sees n plus 1 they have to
reject n yeah I think they cover packs
us in the distributed systems class
right the guys in the X you have to
implement it so I'm being I'm going
through this very briefly just to show
the distinction between two-phase commit
and and Pat says that like yeah the
hilum idea is the same except that under
Pat says yeah you still get rejected in
the second phase and you have a majority
have to agree so now her question is or
her observation is it could not get
starred forever if I just have two
proposers clobbering each other by
posing you know n plus 1 and plus 2 n
plus 3 and everything just keeps getting
rejected absolutely so the way you
handle this is called multi Paxos so the
idea with multi packs s is that you you
select some node to become the leader
for your Paxos group and then it's the
sole node responsible for for proposing
changes to commit transactions it's the
one that they think of this it could
delegate it or designate it as the
almost like the coordinator or the the
middleware piece that everything
everybody has to go to to determine
whether they're allowed to commit or not
and you have a lease on being designated
as a leader like you know some 60
seconds or so and then after that 60
seconds is up you do a round of voting
which is another another round of Paxos
to determine who the next leader is
going to be and then once that that's
resolved then you go ahead and have you
know that that new designated leader be
the responsible for all
for applying all the changes so this
report this avoids that that starving
starving issue because the leaders have
been the only one proposing changes yes
correct so she's like isn't just moving
the problem because now couldn't get
started for the leader election right so
yeah we assume our nodes are friendly so
we just have right in our and our
database system you say all right well
the after my lease is over I'll try to
be the only one to to you know vote
myself or propose that I can be the new
leader how do you handle two guys
clapping same time yes but you serve
back off so I tried I got rejected so
MIT said to me Miele trying to reject or
merely try to propose it something new
maybe I'll wait 10 milliseconds if I
propose again I get rejected maybe I
wait 20 just do it that way yes the
question is how many proposals can you
have and then as you want
yeah algorithm doesn't say anything
about limitation in practice it's like
getting for it they'll call in a pack so
this group you typically would have one
under multi taxes to avoid this start
starvation issue if we cover spanner at
the end of the semester of an assistant
potpourri which every year we always do
I'll show you how you can do taxes with
that question over here so the the main
takeaway from this is that so with with
two-phase commit and paxos you can both
use them to commit transactions so to
determine whether everyone agrees we
want to go ahead and commit transactions
in practice usually for distributed
databases that are local to each other
like meaning they're running under the
same data center where they're not like
you know or widespread geographic
regions two-phase commit it's what
people mostly use because the the number
of round trips could be less and you
assume that maybe the nodes are going to
are going to be crash less often
okay there's much extra failure scenario
Cody you have to deal with ferret handle
code to deal with like you know the
coordinator goes down participant goes
down so it's you know even though it
would be slightly faster than paxos
it's still there's so much of your stuff
you have to do to make sure that you
don't the whole system doesn't go down
and you don't lose data
as I said before the the inventor of
paxos Leslie Lamport and Jim Gray the
guide have been two phase locking they
had a paper in early 2000s before Jim
disappeared that showed that two base
commit is a degenerative case of two
phase locking right - sort of like I was
talking to Jennifer case of paksas right
the the coordinator it's the same taxes
round of a voting it's just everyone has
agree rather than the majority okay all
right
so let's talk about replication now as I
said in beginning most people don't need
a sort of a partitioned attributed
database to handle the workload most the
data says you play and count the real
world while probably using you know some
kind of replication and I would say that
still counts as a distributed database
so the idea here it should be a database
replicated with application is that we
want to make multiple copies of every
object whether it's a page or a - poor
table whatever you want and store them
on multiple nodes so that if one of
those nodes goes down we have a backup
available for us so we don't have to
wait for the system to reboot and replay
the log to put us back in the correct
state we could just failover using paxos
to decide who to failover to to
determine what becomes that you know the
new location for writing data so there's
a bunch of design decisions we have to
think about when we want to build our
replication scheme so we'll go through
each of these one by one
so the first first issue is what however
after you can configure the system
configure the replicas in the systems
and where do the reads and writes go to
so the most common approach is used what
is called master replicas replication
sometimes called called leader follower
used to be called master slave but
people try to try to avoid that term and
the idea here is that there's some
designated master for that form for a
given object in the database and all the
rights are going to go to that master
master node and the master node is then
responsible for propagating those
changes the
updates to its replicas and all the
reads can go either to the master or
some systems that can also go to the
replicas so you can offload the work you
have to do in the massacres the rights
could be could be very expensive and so
as I said if now the master goes down
then we hold up axis around to do a
leader election to determine which
replica becomes the new master and
that's where all the rights go to
question this question is well this is a
venture persistency no we'll get there
but not necessarily no no no not true a
few more slides
okay the other approach is do
multi-master where we have replicas
stored in different machines and
transactions are allowed to write to any
of those replicas all right some
sometimes called multi-home and then now
that it's the replicas are responsible
for determining if you have two
transactions that try to update the same
thing running the two different replicas
how do you actually coordinate from
decide which one should actually commit
which one should abort how do you
actually with conflicts so let's look at
these visual ease again master master
replicas yeah you have a master node all
your rights go to this guy and in in
some systems all the reads go here as
well and then this just then propagates
over the network
the update information to it to its
replicas so that can get applied and for
some systems again you can have the
reads go to the replicas so that you
produce the amount of work you're doing
on the front end so if your reads don't
need to have the most up-to-date latest
information then you can all flow them
to to these other guys here all right
this is still be potentially consistent
by meaning like I can if I have snapshot
isolation I can be guaranteed that I'm
not seeing torn updates or partial
updates from transactions still running
on this guy here so I still can
guarantee the consistency are the data
I'm reading on my replicas it just may
be the case that I'm not seeing the
little latest information that's on the
master the multi master approach is that
again we have transactions can you read
the rights to any copy of the data and
then there's some procedure
to resolve the conflict again using
Paxos or two-phase committee to decide
you know to have overlapping changes on
these two replicas what should be the
latest version so just as a quick
anecdote Facebook originally used to use
this Malta
master replica setup for their giant
data center right the the main data
center was I think you know in
California and then across the different
around the world they would have
replicas that would fall along the the
you know the the the master and get
updates to you know to propagate the
changes so that you can see things and
the way they would fake it out to make
it look like your changes happen real
fast locally like if you updated your
timeline they would store that as a
cookie information in your browser so
that if you refresh the page you would
see your update even though have may not
been propagated to the to the replicas
where you're reading your timeline from
right cuz it takes a bit of is late for
the right to show up here and then
pushed out to the replicas and now
probably five six years ago now they do
the the multi multi master set up so an
important concept in our with replicas
yes you could react so there's a there's
a lot of pumpkin permission map this
four years ago so the way like if I
write a post like you know in my
timeline if i refresh the page and if
I'm saying I'm in Brazil and I'm reading
the Brazil my local data center has a
replica of the master so now if i
refresh my page and come back I wouldn't
see my post because it has been
propagated from the master to the
replica because there's there's always
delay for this so people would then you
they want to avoid the issue of someone
posting in their timeline hitting
refresh and then thinking they're their
post went missing because now you're
reading from this right so the way they
would handle that is they would actually
store what she wrote in your browser
cookie and then fill that in as if it
was coming from the database it's not
yes if they quit their browser and
assuming the cookies got got blown away
and you cut but even
better scenario I make a change my time
on this machine and I have another
machine right next to it and I hit
refresh on that machine it would go to
the replica database down in Brazil it
would not see your post you know it'd be
a couple hundred milliseconds before
they actually got propagated but they
would say you know we'll still like to
hurt someone could hit refresh on the
two machines they're exact same time yes
correct
question is is that in my scenario with
Facebook if the replicas Brazil this is
in California when I actually did the
post does that mean the application
server needs to communicate with the the
data is back in California from Brazil
yes David is that's a huge bottle
absolutely and that's why they did the
cookie thing to hide it because doing
this is this is hard right they had to
build that and to get that right is not
easy yes his question is receiving again
using the Facebook example if someone
comments on that post I will never see
that no because again it's just the deal
with you at the person writing the post
if you hit refresh it would pull it from
the cookie so that you would think you
got it from me from the master but you
really got it from the replica it fills
in the missing information that knows it
should exist for you eventually it the
bastard will get propagated to the
replica and then now if I do a refresh
instead of coming at the cookie I'll
come from my replica so Zimmer and post
my comment i it'll be a delay before I
can see it correct in the in the old in
the old system yes and the new system
yes everything is now we're getting the
GPD our world which I don't wanna get
into like where can data actually live
but in generally think of yes like think
of this is like Brazil America u.s.
everyone has a complete copy in entire
database whether Facebook actually does
that anymore I don't know
again this big think of this as this is
a good example of it's sort of like mp3s
right mp3s take advantage of AUSA's
humans of what we can proceed
in audio and they they can compress down
you know wavelengths that we can't see
by a throws away data that we humans are
never going to be able to hear to
compress the the you know the the actual
file so it's sort of like the same thing
right they know that if it takes me a
hundred milliseconds to get to get up
from a comment on my post get from the
master the replica who cares
if it takes me a hundred milliseconds to
see your comment about my stupid picture
right the thing they were trying to
avoid was someone posting and then
immediately not seen what they posted so
that's why they were doing that cookie
trick but for everything else you do
have to wait till gets propagated and
again if it's a hunter milliseconds to
see a comment from from your friend who
cares comment in the comment use case
someone in California comments on like
if I posted Raziel or something yes yes
so just repeat his comment like for this
one I'm showing p1 the partition P one
and I'm assuming everyone has a complete
copy of this but now you can think of
like in a really large large trivia
database with a lot of data I'm gonna
maybe want to replicate p1 multiple
times so there be multiple copies of p1
and so maybe if all my data is down in
if I'm down in Brazil then I'll keep
more copies of my data in down in Brazil
because I can update them more quickly
if anybody's posting my comment Brazil
now if anybody updates something in
California that has to then get
propagated down to Brazil so that when i
refresh i can see it yes they handle all
that yeah the facebook architecture
actually means it's all based on my
sequel at the end that is like the the
core storage engine of their giant
distributed database system is is my
sequel they're getting rid of inner DB
and eventually replacing with rocks DB
but all the layers above that are sort
of independent of what the actual
underlying storage is but the azure
storage doesn't look all that
coordination stuff of like keeping the
multi multi master stuff in sync that's
all written by Facebook
all right so an important property we
care about in a replicated environment
is this notion of K safety and the idea
here is just keeping track of the number
of copies of an object you have to have
in order for our system to remain online
so I don't know whether KP is a
standardized term this is something that
Mike Stonebreaker uses when describing
vertical TB and basically it's it's a
human defined threshold to say I need to
have at least K copies of particular
object at all time in my tribute a
database and if I ever go below that K
then I grind the system to a halt and I
stop until either I can bring up a new
new copy of that data or you know Hughes
or the human comes in and makes a
correction the idea here is is that we
want to avoid losing data so obviously I
want my K safety beat to be at least 1
right because if I have if I lose one
you know if I lose one node that has the
only copy of that of a piece of data
then I'm screwed now I could have false
negatives or false positives for
different queries and my database is
incorrect so what this threshold
actually is depends on you know how
paranoid you are about keeping things
online and then you can also you know
vary this by saying like in my example
what like I have more copy down in
Brazil maybe one copy up in up in and
you know in the US because I want to
make you know I care about keeping local
copies down in Brazil all right so now
we want to get it what what are we
actually propagating or how we're
actually propagating our changes to to
have replicas and he sort of asked about
this like does this mean we're doing
eventual consistency and I mention was
no you'll see why so the propagations
team is is is when should we how long do
we have to wait or how many when should
we tell the outside world that our
transaction has committed and this is
somewhat independent of the two-phase
commit stuff right this is saying like
with my replicas should I wait until the
replica acknowledges that they got my
change and have safety safety stored in
a disk before I tell the outside world
that I've actually committed and in
general the two approaches of use
synchronous or asynchronous synchronous
will give you what's called strong
consistency which means I can guarantee
that if I tell the outside world of my
transaction has committed if I go read
that data from any replicas I'm
guaranteed to see the changes of that
turn
action with eventual consistency the
idea is that the change will eventually
get propagated to my replicas so if I go
if I hear back my transaction is
committed and I immediately go try to
read it on a replica I may not actually
see it so again look at this visually so
with synchronous we have say two nodes
assuming we're doing a master replica
set up we we say we want to commit on
the on our master and then we have to go
to the to the replica and say hey yeah
we sent you a bunch of log messages or
updates about this transaction made go
ahead and flush it and then we pause and
we wait until we hear a response back
from our replicas to say that our
transaction has has successfully been
committed and then it's durable and disk
and then once it done it's done flushing
we send back the acknowledgement and at
that point we can tell the outside world
that we've committed so again at this
point here when we get back the Siq
knowledge meant if we try to read
whatever this thing modified we're
guaranteed to see that change correct
you know see that the change we'd expect
on both the master and and any replicas
with asynchronous you don't wait for
that response so I go ahead say I want
to commit then I say hey go but go ahead
and force the change but then I can
Neely come back into the application say
my transaction has committed and then
now at some later point you know this
thing with eventual get flushed but I
don't really need to be told on the
master be nice to know but I technically
I don't have to be told so this is one
of the good distinctions between
distributed database sorry that the
traditional transactional relational
database management systems and the no
sequel guys in the transactional
database system we don't wanna lose any
data we don't want to have any
inconsistent reads so we would always do
synchronous replication denote the no
sequel guys would do this one here
because the idea is that eventually this
thing I'll get propagated to my replicas
and so maybe in the small window like 50
milliseconds I can maybe get a stale
read on my replica that's who cares
maybe it's a website of like stupid cat
food cat photos with comments
you know I can't see the last 50
milliseconds of Cat Cat comments it's
probably probably good enough
I have money certainly I want to use
this because what could happen here
I tell my transaction commits I tell the
outside world I committed but then this
guy crashes and this guy crashes and say
this guy didn't flush anything to disk
and this guy didn't get the get the
message yet or didn't apply it now I
want to come back my transactions gone
so as an aside come and I'll say that a
lot of the the no sequel the no sequel
systems from 10 years ago that all said
we were a shoe sequel they were going to
avoid joins avoid transactions a
majority of em have added transactions
the majority of them have added sequel
and joints right so all the the me it's
not to say that the certain aspects I
know Segoe systems are invalid
there are certainly use cases like
website we don't really need to have
strong consistency but in general I mean
there's enough application out there
where this this this matters a lot cuz
you don't lose any data so let's say
like if I get this commit message here
and I immediately come back and say I
acknowledgement and I don't wall get
anything here actually see anybody did
log something right say I woke to disk
that we come into this transaction but
now this this machine catches on fire
those discs milk-like so now this this
guy crashes to it but he just crashed he
comes back he looks in this log he
didn't get the flus message so that
didn't show up in time so I told the
outside world I committed but this guy
never solved the change and I crashed so
I come back now the transactions gone in
that
if that's your bank account with that
money transfer you're pissed all right
so it's up to the application to decide
what trade-offs they want to make do
they care about
alright are you super conservative and
don't lose any data then synchronous
replication is the way to go if you're
okay with maybe losing the last ten five
you know 50 milliseconds of data and
this is the way to go okay
the next issue is when do we actually
when we actually sense in there send our
changes oh and what do these changes
actually look like so one approach is to
have the master continuously send all
the updates that transactions make as
they occur think of this is like it's
it's like a it's attached to the right
ahead log so anytime I create a log
record that I'm gonna put you know I
want to write out the disk I also send
it out in the network to my to my to my
replicas and they can start applying the
changes as they come in of course this
means now I not only don't need to send
a commit message but I also need to send
an abort message just as just as they
would if I'm replaying the redhead log
because I need to know what changes I
need to roll back the other approach is
to only send the log messages when the
transaction actually goes into commit so
we just buffer all our log messages in
memory on the master node then to begin
abort who cares we just drop it we don't
send it send anything over the network
if we go ahead and commit then we push
everything to to our master I started to
to our replicas alright and the
advantage of this one is that you're not
wasting time sending log messages that
are gonna get aborted from transactions
they're gonna board but of course this
means now if I need it if I'm doing
synchronous replication and I need to
wait until this guy acknowledges the the
replicas knowledge is that it's applied
all this changes then if I'm sending
this huge batch of updates all at once I
have to wait till they all get flushed
whereas in this one I can do it
incrementally so far as they know most
systems will do do the first one here
all right the last one is a bit more
nuanced but it's it's it's what it's
determining how we're actually going to
apply our one of the
changes were actually gonna apply to the
system on our replicas and so again in
new databases a lot of times the
terminology is vague or people use
different things or to describe
different things but I think active
passive versus active active is
standardized enough that this makes
sense I don't know what I don't know
what the textbook covers this so think
of this is like with active active the
idea is that our transaction who's gonna
run independently on on each of our
replicas so say Mia but we have a
transaction want to update four tuples
we're gonna run that transaction on the
master I run that transaction on the
replicas or if we're doing multi master
again it runs on each each each copy of
the note and so they're gonna when they
commit all we need to do determine
whether we've committed correctly is
that we use need to check to see whether
they all produce the same same result
now this is not easy to do if you're
doing an non-deterministic control
scheme like two-phase locking and and
you know time-saver learning all the
things we talked about before because
now you can be guaranteed that the
transactions are running in the same
order on our two replicas without
checking for every single query so we
talked a little bit but the partition
time same ordering scheme when Prashant
talked that tell that lecture in that
case that's a term you can use that for
deterministic virtual and guarantee that
you know transactions run their
operations in the exact same order on
both sides so active active is not that
common because you have to do a better
exercise a run exactly the same what is
more common is active passive where the
transactions can execute on one location
the one master node and then they're
gonna propagate their changes to the
replicas and these these changes could
either be like no right ahead log you we
can either send out the the physical
updates to the actual 2 plus themselves
or the bytes the low-low bytes we
changed or we could also stream out the
sequel queries that they did and just
replay the single queries and our
replicas there's advantages of both of
them just as we talked about before
between you know for the recovery time
physical replication is usually the most
common because all you're really doing
is just sending up a lot the redhead log
just and then the the replicas replay
down so is this clear
yes question is if you send the yeah his
Christian is yeah I actually would agree
that a statement is if you're sending
the sequel queries isn't that the same
thing as as as active active I'm
thinking in terms of active passive
where I run the sequel query on the on
the the master and then the log message
comes out as the sequel query active
active in context of store procedures
think of like two transactions running
in their entirety independently on the
two replicas but in your example yeah
that this what I'm saying the terms are
like nebulous I would agree that would
be active active even though it's it's
done after like active passive as I I
run it on the master and then only after
I run on the master and then I sent to
the replicas but you could you could say
alright I've run this query and then
right before you run it on the master
you you send it over to the to the
replicas is that active active mmm-hmm
I would agree yes alright um we have
like eight minutes left and this is like
one of the hardest things let's roll the
dice let's see we can do it okay so
there's this thing called a cat theorem
that people apply for the trippity
databases and this is a way to
characterize and understand what are the
properties or guarantees that a
distributed database can provide for you
and it's broken up to three parts
consistency are consistent always
available and never partition foot
tolerant so this was this was originally
posed as a conjecture by a berkeley
professor named Eric Brewer in the late
1990s and then it was formally proved at
MIT that this is actually correct this
is this is a true theorem in 2002 and
the basic idea is that all these three
things if you're going to have it
asserted tributed a Bayes you you have
to pick two of these you get two out of
three right it's kind of like if you
want it's like you know
you're looking for a husband or a wife
you can pick someone's either smart
good-looking or not crazy but you can
get me a two out of three of those
things right
same thing for drippity databases so
let's go feetsies one by one
again the idea is that it's this sort of
Venn diagram where you have CA P which
you can never be in the middle here you
can never get a system has guarantees
all these things so the consistency just
means linearize ability thinking this is
a stronger version of serializability
availability means that at any given
time we can access any node and get any
data in our system and then partition
tolerance this means that if we start
losing messages because the network goes
down a machine goes down that we can
still process any response that we could
ever want
so the no sequel guys they are going to
be AP they're gonna they're gonna try to
provide availability and partition
tolerance in exchange for giving up
consistency like that's the eventual
consistency thing like I can't guarantee
that if I tell you I made your a I tell
you that you're right it's exceeded that
I guarantee that everyone's gonna see
that right in the sort of new sequel or
the traditional transactional district
of data systems they're gonna try to do
CPU or CA and then their award if like I
can't talk to a node rather than keep on
running I just shut the whole thing down
and in that case I give up I give up a
bell Doty all right so let's go through
these one by one I think we've covered
most of these already but just to show
them visually to understand what what
they actually mean so again with kiss
assistance II the idea is that if we do
a write on one machine that everyone
should see that right before we tell the
outside world that are right it
succeeded so our transaction is running
on this application server here it wants
to set a to two and then we're going to
propagate that change to this replica
and then we can tell the outside world
that we did acknowledge there right and
at this point whether we read a on the
replica or on the master will see a e
equals two right so another application
server can immediately see no after this
right has succeeded I can see a equals
two and I get back the correct response
partition tolerance our availability
says that if this replica it goes down
then either the mat the this application
server or this other application server
can can read and write to anything that
at once here all right and then the last
one is partition tolerance the idea here
is that say the network goes down the
network that I'm using to communicate
between these two machines goes down the
machines don't go down but it never goes
down or my messages my packets are
getting lost in the network so now
what's gonna happen here well soon again
before we had master replicas set up and
I said with master up like I set up you
run patos to decide who then who the
master is and then that's where all the
updates are gonna go so at this point
there's that there's a network partition
so these guys can't communicate but they
know they're so up like you know you're
still alive so now you run paxos and you
find out oh I'm still alive now I'm the
new master all right so now if my two
application servers send at the exact
same time updates to my database this
guy's sets a equals to this guy's says
eight all three both of these notes
think that their master because they ran
packs those that was fine you know no
one else about loaded us where the
master so we said okay it's okay for me
to go ahead and make this change we send
the acknowledgement that we made that
change but now at some point the network
comes back and I need to reconcile this
change in synchronize and now you're
screwed because now one guy says I
equals two and this other guy says equal
three and we told the outside world that
those rights succeeded so yes correction
is when can you have CP you mM you can't
really take the back
yeah so this what I'm saying it's sort
of so what would CP look like CV was
says what the network goes down I can't
communicate communicate these two nodes
what should I do
so if I'm doing like a kay safety thing
where I say I need to have three copies
of the data at all times and say I have
another I have another node over here
so these two guys would you say hey we
have at least two copies we're fine we
do leader election this guy says he's
the master
so now anybody can do writes here and
then that's fine
this guy over here say well Mike a
safety is is two but I only have one so
I have to shut down I can't run anything
so therefore I'm giving up availability
so in that case I can have I'm
technically handling the partition the
partition in the network by being not
available on that side but this sides
okay so this is called split brain
initiative systems like I have two sides
like two brain size the brain can't
communicate and they both think they're
their king of the world so again in a in
a traditional transactional database
system they basically stop the system
when you realize you can't communicate
with everyone right or if you have a
majority then you say I'm the new master
and so in this example here if say this
guy came back up well assuming that
seeming this guy
if this guy was allowed to make changes
because it had its case a factor was
enough then when I came back I would
have to have a new human come in and
resolved this change we can't magically
just do that in our system and in that
case we again we stopped the world and
we go offline until someone comes in and
fixes us yes yes correct so his calm is
how do I avoid the split brain well if
your case safety factor is half the nose
plus one that means that at least you're
always guaranteed to have yeah only one
side could be could be the be the master
and the other guy fails yes that's it
there's no the magic right and again so
going back to the nocebo guys in their
world again they're dealing with like in
it traditionally with dealing with like
websites that you want to have be online
24/7 so in their world they they would
rather have system be available and
still serve request
albeit maybe they're there they're
slightly wrong or delayed in getting
that all the changes but that was better
than being completely online if you're
dealing with money and you can't you
don't want my I don't want to give out
you know a million dollars to you that I
don't have and again a million dollars
ever hear from you know because I have a
split brain in their role they can't
have that happen so they'd rather take
the whole thing down so I'm not saying
one is better than another I'm saying
for certain application scenarios one
one is prefer preferable but it's just
sort of good understand like when you
start design you should be data system
what trade-offs are you actually making
okay so let's just finish out quickly
about federated Davis so the cap theorem
again it's it's include to be correct in
the late 2000s there was some if you go
if you go google the phrase like
defeated cat theorem there's a bunch of
people making wild claims about how
their database is defeated a cap theorem
and they were presently put down as
being stupid its second you can't have
it you should be database you can have
at your videos that can do everything
you can do a bunch of extra stuff to try
to mitigate the bottleneck sort of the
issues you would have by having these
various these you know machine know down
and things like that so redundancy so
that you can you know reduce the the
likelihood of a network partition or
things like that but in the end of the
day they're unavoidable at some point
you're gonna run out of money or the
it's isms gonna get you slow and you're
gonna be you're you're gonna become
beholden to it
all right so let's just finish up
quickly so I just want to briefly
mention what a federated database is so
that if you ever see one or think about
think about building one you just know
what it is so in all you know all this
tribute davis's we talked about so far
we have assumed that all the nodes are
running the exact same database system
software right it's in here it's my cell
just ripping a version of my C code
attributed version of cockroach TV or
whatever but sometimes in some systems
and sort of large organizations you have
these sort of one-off applications that
are using you know this kind of database
system and then it's other applications
using this other type of data system and
they need a way to sort of do maybe
transactions across all
do queries across all of them so they
appear as a single database instance
even though underneath the covers
they're running quickly different
software so this is what a federated
basis is designed to hope designed to
solve the idea is that we provide a
single logical database instance and we
know how to take a single query that own
that single database instance and break
it up into plan fragments that we can
then possibly execute on the separate
machines and we have a way to sort of
put it all back together so this was a
big thing in the late 1980s early 1990s
right as companies and organizations got
larger and there was more database
deployments you think would it be great
we had a single interface for all our
databases it didn't pan out because you
end up dealing in a designing a system
that has to do with a lowest common
denominator of all your systems
all right this system doesn't do
transaction or this doesn't do these
type of queries so we can't do that for
other systems all right so again people
try this people still try this it's
usually a bad idea it's not gonna end
well you do simple things but you know
having this is beautiful all in the one
federated database it's not gonna work
so again basic ideas like this you have
your application server you have your
middleware system and your separate back
in databases so single query goes to the
middleware and then it recognizes what
all these different systems can actually
support and so it rewrite the portion of
the query that you want to run on these
different machines for their different
api's right so my sequel does sequel
MongoDB does JSON queries Redis does its
own thing in the subway is whatever
alright so it knows how to take all
those queries break it up and run on
those separate machines and then you get
back the result so these things are
usually call connectors like they have
the ability to communicate with these
different databases and pull them into
the single system the one database that
Pike is the the best positioned to do a
federated database architecture is
actually Postgres so Postgres has this
thing called the foreign data wrappers
think of this is like a an api oh you
can plug in different data sources that
are outside the normal Postgres storage
so there's there's there's
de foreign data wrappers for you know
for for and all these other
systems so I write all my sequel queries
in
to Postgres then the foreign data
wrapper news how to go out to these
individual systems and suck the data in
which i think is pretty cool okay so any
question about any of us as I said yes
the bat
alright serious question is can I
recommend any distributed OLAP or OLTP
system oh that let's take this offline
because it's a complicated question
depends what are you trying to do
what does your data look like how much
data do you have do you want sequel or
not no sequel why I mean there's like
you seen DVD die oh there's 680 basis to
some 260 whatever like there's not gonna
be this one magic thing that like solves
all the world's problems you have to
look at your application requirements
and end up making compromises about what
you know what features you need what
features you don't need how much money
you will spend right so let's cover this
net class is a popular video that system
will come at an x-class some popular
distributor ltp systems so all the the
major vendors sequel server db2 and an
Oracle
they all have their own distributed
systems all right there's newer startups
like cockroach Tidy be yoga buy fauna
Mongo's distributed right they all make
you know they all have different
trade-offs well covered I'll list out
some overlap subsonex class and actually
let's talk let's talk offline maybe
there's some of your cover at the
potpourri in the last class all right so
again the main takeaway I saw from
beginning is that we assumed all our
database nodes in our system are
friendly that makes our life easier of
how we do commits and transactions and
replication if they're not friendly then
that's what the blockchain is and the
projection worked if they do to prove
that when we say commit transactions we
want to create a transaction that
everybody actually committed transaction
and in case a Bitcoin that's all the
hashing stuff they do with the Merkle
trees ok
all right so Monday's class next week
will be the last lecture on the sugar
databases will cover just rip it all app
systems I think that'll be the end of
the material for the for the semester
that'll be covered on the final on when
we come back after Thanksgiving that'll
be the guest lecture from Oracle and
then the system potpourri in the final
review okay any questions all right guys
[Music]
ricochet jelly hit the deli food
naturally don't fill out drinking only
two you can't and if the sink don't know
your phone can tap a