[Music]
sloping I love it
alright let's get started alright let's
talk about let's let's get right into it
again
thanks for DG drop tables hold it down
that was awesome Peggy how are you are
you still having that police problems or
everything okay do you need a good
lawyer in town because I have one well
my pc students got in trouble for legs
leg whatever minor so we have somebody
we can help you out okay no never
okay good all right so let's let's how
about David so real quickly the we have
a talk today engaged May 4 at 4:30 p.m.
so this is one of the head engineers
from Vertica is come to give a talk so
vertical I believe it not has a small
development branch here in in Pittsburgh
and so Steve is gonna come and talk
about some of the things that they've
been working on Vertica is a disk based
distributed column store database you
gots a bunch of words we've been thrown
around throughout the entire semester
but it means it runs multiple nodes it's
a column store and it soon as the
primary search location of the database
is on disk so this is one of the it's
not the it's one of the first column
stores that came out in the mid-2000s
that sort of that began the wave of
column store dead business so comstor
databases aren't really that rare now
but back in it back when Berger came out
in 2006 ish that was considered a that
was a sort of a major tech not
technological breakthrough so Stephens
good guy if you want to talk about the
kind of things that they're working on
and for that one that'll be fruit
they're not pizza
so again plan accordingly all right so
today we want to continue our discussion
on talking about tree indexes so I want
to spend a little bit time in the
beginning doing some demos and
discussing more about B plus trees to
finish up the things that we we left out
last class and then we'll talk about
different ways we'll talk about more
ways you can use indexes beyond the
you know straight key mapped into a data
structure that we've been talking about
so far and then we'll talk about an
alternative to B plus trees tries or
radix trees and we're getting we'll go
through what makes these unique what
makes them different and how are they
better or worse than B plus trees and
then we'll finish up really quickly with
a sort of a brain dump of inverted
indexes I'm not going to teach you how
they work we have courses here at CMU if
I can do that this is just so you know
that these things actually exist so when
you go out in the real world and you
realize that the thing you want to index
can't be indexed in a B+ tree you want
to use one of these inverted indexes all
right so the the last class we had a
couple questions about how do we
actually going to handle duplicate keys
in our B+ tree index so I showed you how
we would handle duplicate keys inside of
the node right we could have we could
duplicate the values in the node and
then or just have a mapping from a key
to a valueless inside the node so now I
want to talk about a data what I
realized I missed out was discussing at
a higher level actually within the tree
itself how do we gonna actually maintain
these duplicate indexes or duplicate
keys so there's two approaches to do
this so the first is that we're gonna
make every key unique automatically by
appending the the corresponding tuples
record ID to the key that we're
inserting into the index so instead of
destroying the keeping of the copy of
the attribute that's in the table I'm
also gonna prefix or sorry put at the
end as a suffix the record ID for that
tuple so now that makes every single key
automatically unique so the reason why
we can do this in this still works is
because we're using a B+ tree memorize
said it would be plus tree we can do
partial key lookups and and still find
the things that we want so if I if I
have an attribute an index one
attributes a and B if I want to do a
look upon a I can still do that without
having B so in our case in the B plus
tree because we're not gonna have the
record ID we can just do the regular
lookup we as we would with it with a key
but we just scan along the leaf nodes do
we find all the matches for that given
key you can
do this in a hash table right for the
hash table you have to have the entire
key so in order to do this approach you
have to have the when you do a lookup
the key you want and then the record a
is the record IDs they correspond to but
that seems stupid because if you had the
record IDs why would use an index a
lookup the record IDs yes so these
questions what is what is this record ID
it's the page ID and all set we talked
about in the very beginning right that's
the unique identifier for every physical
location of a tuple now it may change
and therefore that we have to deal with
that and Postgres is most famously the
one that what this won't work because
they can move things around but when we
tell about multi versioning we'll see
different examples of why this works
from post but it doesn't work replace
graphs with arcs or other systems but
this assume it's a page 18 offset or
indicates a sequel server an Oracle it
was like file number object number of
page ID and all set like a more complex
thing the other approach is to somewhat
violate the sanctity if you will of the
design of the B+ tree and actually store
the duplicate keys as overflow leaf
nodes so instead of expanding the leaf
nodes horizontally to accommodate new
entries we're actually gonna ban them
vertically or then what for then a given
leaf node will add these overflow pages
almost like the chain hash table we
talked about before and is add all the
trippity he's down there so as well see
in a second I'll again provide over use
what this looks like
this approach is gonna be more complex
because now we have to handle the case
of where I'm skinning along my leaf
nodes I have to know how to follow those
you know follow down the overflow pages
if I'm skinning reverse direction you
know what where do I start my scan when
I jump back in the other direction
so most people implement this one this
has the advantage that again we don't
want to make any major changes to our
data structure whether it's a unique
versus not unique index everything just
still works the same
the downside is now we're actually
storing there's record ID as an
additional key element of our key and
that increases the size of our of our
index you know the amount of data it
takes to actually store the index with
this case here we're not storing any
redundant information unnecessary
early to make things unique but now we
have this management issue so let's go
through both them so this is our simple
B+ tree that we talked about before and
so the first approach is again depend
the record ID so either I'm showing just
like the key value assume there's an
adjuvant a and here's all the values for
them
in actuality what the database system is
actually storing is a combination of the
key and then that record ID so now when
I do a lookup and say I want to cert key
key six I would in this point here I can
do a prefix search in my in my B+ tree
because I don't have a record ID as I'm
inserting this why should I take it back
you do have a record ID but I'm not
gonna find an exact match for that so I
would Traverse down here and I would
land at this page the real I mean the
real thing I'm starting is the page 18
upset but I land here
and now I know I want to go into this
page so because now I don't have
overflow pages I have to go exactly in
sorted order so assume whatever this
original six is its record ID is less
than the one I'm inserting so it needs
to go between the six and seven so I
just do the normal split process that we
talked about before I slide everybody
over seven and eight move here and now I
can I can update pointers and house six
goes in here right it's just works
exactly the same that we talked about
before so I'm gonna do a lookup alone
six again I just do the prefix search I
do the just look at the first element of
the key just the six and I can find down
here now I scan along my leaf-nosed to I
find them what I want the other approach
is the overflow pages so now again I
want to start six again I know I want to
go into this guy I can't I don't want to
split across right I want to I don't do
what I did before I have seven eight
move over I want to go in this page here
but I can't because it's full so I just
add now an overflow page where I insert
my new six and now I have my pointer
down to it now remember I said before
that that in in most textbook
definitions of a B+ tree you assume that
the keys are always gonna be in sorted
within the node in this case here we
could do that we could sort them but
it's not actually wrong just to leave it
unsorted we just need to know when word
looking for the element we're looking
for we can't use binary search to jump
around we have to do the linear search
to find that we want so now let's say I
want to search seven same things seven
goes down there
I insert six same thing six goes here
it's it's on order and that's okay
so now here's what needs to happen so
physically this is stored across
multiple pages logically from the index
perspective this just looks like one
giant leaf note that has the month in it
so now if I'm scanning across I do the
same thing I follow this pointer I land
here and now if I'm scanning across
instead of jumping over to this node I
no need to follow my overflow page you
keep looking there and eventually if I
find what I'm looking for I'm done if
not I need to go to the next page then I
just follow that pointer over there so
now I may be thinking why not just have
this guy should' this guy really be
pointing to that one right because that
would actually be correct but now the
problem is every single time I add a new
overflow page now only do I need to
update you know my pointers internally
for these two note these nodes over here
I now need to go update this one as well
but if I just leave that pointer alone
and let it point to the beginning of my
page the topmost leaf node in this
vertical tower then I would just land
there and say oh well I'm going over
search I really need to jump to the end
of my overflow page and work backwards
there's much extra logic we have to do
to accommodate this yes
so I said sorry you haven't reviewed
what sorry oh every doubt okay so this
question is if someone if the data
systems using the index and we're trying
to find the tuples that have the value
six for this particular key so what is
the index returning well if we turn the
record id's so you would say you
basically have an iterator I traverse
down and get to my leaf node and now I'm
looking calling next next next on this
iterator and I'm looking at every single
element until I find the ones that I
want and I new iterator knows to stop
what says I'm looking for everything
that where key equals six so soon as I
see maybe a nine over here I need to
stop
but this what I'm saying if you know if
this is unsorted then I know I need to
scan to the end of all my overflow pages
because I if this the last six might be
here if I want to keep them sorted then
you know now I'm certain this six here
now I got to go update this guy and this
guy whereas before if I disappear only
its updating one page so this is a
really good example of why you know why
trying to understand these data
structures in the context of a real full
system is important you take an
algorithms class an algorithms class
will teach you yes this is the way to
start a B+ tree but now because we're
inside of a database system we know we
have these things called record IDs and
we can exploit them to make to
facilitate different aspects or
different operations that would not be
otherwise easy to do yes correct
if this thing overflows we just keep
continuing yes correct I think it says
to a certain point you actually want
rebalance so yes so that could be a
criteria it says all right well if I go
beyond this number of overflow pages
then do a split but if these are all
sixes right in a single page then you
can't you can't quite you know easily do
that without depending the record ID all
right cool so let's do a demo because we
didn't get to do this last time so we're
gonna do Postgres and these want to show
the difference between a B+ tree and a
hash index all right turn this off all
right cool and you're logging over here
so I'm gonna have a table this live yeah
okay so this is post rest I'm gonna have
a table of email addresses so it's gonna
be a simple a simple table with an ID
with an auto increment key and then a
bunch of email addresses so this is a
file that you can find on the Internet
this is a list of 27 million email
addresses from if you don't know what
that is it was a a think of like tinder
before tinder that it was an adult
hook-up site in Canada they got hacked
and then eventually people release the
email addresses so this is real it
shouldn't take that long to load but I
should do this before now but that's
okay so what we're gonna do is we're
gonna create two indexes we're gonna
create a hash index so in Postgres you
can actually just say well I want to
create index I want it to be a hash
index and then you can then say I want
to create index and I want to be a B+
tree index of course yeah
well this is that a good demo right okay
so maybe we'll come back to this let's
go to my sequel sir about that okay it's
the same thing this is my sequel
secretary select count star from emails
alright Postgres finished actually let's
go back to post press because it's done
I took a minute so I told you I inserted
27 email addresses so I first I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna create a hash index so
in in deep by default in sequel and most
systems if you just create an index
you're gonna get a B+ tree you know or
some tree data structure in Postgres I
can say using hash I'm forcing it to use
a hash index and so now we can see
things like of course not gonna load
this I should have warned it sorry
this shouldn't take too long but the the
we can see how if we try to do certain
queries we won't be able to find the
things that we want let me look at all
this in sorry
PG warm so this is that same function I
used last time just to warm the cache
and then now when I call create index in
theory this should be faster because
everything is just loaded then but we're
gonna run queries and we're going to see
how the query planner is not gonna be
able to pick the index for some queries
but it be able to pick indexes for other
queries right because the hash index
again you have to have the entire the
entire key or the tower elements of the
key you can't do partial lookups and you
can't do range scans mmm sorry
well this sucks all right why this is
going on - I'll then create the the
Depot Street index in the background I
had everything working and then I
dropped to the table before class start
and I forgot to rebuild it all right
we're back okay so it took 50 seconds
all right so now I can do say queries
like select star let's find a user first
select star from let's find the minimum
use email address from emails yeah there
we go
whatever that is someone correctly used
a fake email address so if I want to do
select star from emails where email
equals this thing again if I add that
explained keyword purse will tell me
what it's gonna do so Postgres is gonna
tell me that hey I had this hat thing
called a hash index and I can do and do
a lookup because I know I can do exactly
the thing I'm looking forward evil that
text right well ignore what a bit bitmap
scanner heaps can is that'll come later
on but in but we know this is gonna be
fast is it's gonna go find exactly the
the one that we're looking for right but
now say if I want to do something like
where email like and then this thing and
put a put a wild-card at the end can you
use this hash index no right because you
have to have the entire key I'm not
gonna run it cuz I probably take the
whole time but but you can tell you when
you asking explain its tells you it's in
default to the sequential scan matter
the sequential scan is always the
default operation or access method for
the database system they can't find what
it wants using index it always defaults
to a central scan so while this is going
on let's let's build the tree index but
we can see some other things to it right
so let's say we want to find we want to
count all the email addresses where the
better greater than this right
can I do that no again right because we
have to have the partial key we can't do
anything that's not in the quality
predicate it always has to be an exact
match all right it can do some things
though right so let's say we find the
there's say somebody else also did this
one too is it quite of that because I
didn't find that actual that was pretty
fast for a special scan no wait sorry
that that's an index in let's find
another one let's find another one let's
find the something who somebody who
starts with an a so like a star and then
we'll limit one and this basically says
just keep find me the first one that you
get that matches that right so there's
somebody's email address let that books
but that's okay but if we can do other
things like this or email equals like
that
and it was able to actually to do two
index scans so notice has an or clause
and you can see I'll do one probe in the
index try to find what I want do another
program index and try to find what I
want and then it combines them together
and that's that's what the bitmap or
means they think it was happening here
is the bitmap index means that it's
trying finding all matches and then the
set of storing a record ID maintains a
giant bitmap and the mender stores the
the up you know it sets that bit of that
offset to say that that record matched
and then it combines them together and
then it produces the output so that's
why it has to do this and then another
lookup over here all right so now our B+
tree is done so now we come back to our
original query here yes your statement
is didn't I say last class that it would
do the search once and then organize
this is a hash index this is a beat
that's not that this is the B+ right
there's the hash table this is not a B+
tree okay like going back to well now I
just added the B+ tree but yeah right
there
so this is explain explain is telling
you what the query plan is going to be
so it tells you I'm going to
scan using idx emails hash that's the
name the hash table index I created okay
so now my hat my my I have my I have my
my B+ tree index so if I do something
like this just do this lookup we had
before this fake email it tells me it
once you the hash hashed using hash
index but as soon as I add this I add
the range predicates down here is gonna
use the hash table no it's gonna use the
an actually do sequential scan all right
good example so this guy is the smallest
key that we have in our index so it
knows that if I want to use the index
and all I'm really doing is jumping to
the far left point and the scanning
along the leaf nodes and so therefore
the traversal of the index was a waste
of time the air force is better for me
to just do a scrunching scan but let's
say if I change that to Z a bunch of Z's
and now it says that alright well I know
that if I use my index I'm going to
throw away a lot of data so now I can
use that they treated jump down to the
right side of the tree get a starting
point and then a scan along the leaf
nodes right so this is an eternal cost
model thing that's going on in Postgres
so we'll talk about later that allows it
to decide when's the right time to do
these things so is this clear
so for a quality predicates the hash
index is me pretty good but for the for
these range predicates if it's the right
location again we know something about
the division of values then it will
choose to do a index leaf scan so now go
back here again this guy was doing the
index scan doing exact point great
lookup if I drop that index drop index
emails hash comes back right away and
now I do that predicate now it's smart
enough to know oh I no longer have that
hash index I have but I do have this
tree index so I can use that for this
quality predicate so is this clear all
right the other thing we talked about
last class briefly was was table
clustering so table clustering is the
where we're going to
use the index to enforce the sort
ordering of the of the of the table
themselves the to pose themselves Samara
post grass is unsorted or started
relational models unsorted so as we
insert things into post grass it's just
putting them and the essentially the
order that that it was told to put him
in as we do the inserts and we saw
examples where I could update things
delete things and can reshuffle some
depending on how I you know what you
know what free slots are available in a
page so if I go say do a select query
here a select star from emails and I
just say give me the first one alright
we get some random Gmail account but now
if I say if I called this clustering
command this will take about a minute
but what this is doing this is this
command is forcing Postgres to
potentially re sort the entire table
based on the the sort ordering defined
by this index but this is a one-time
operation so as I as I modify the table
and maybe things get out of order it's
not you know it's not gonna match what
it was when I first set it up here some
systems like in my sequel and sequel
server and oracle you can say i want an
index clustered table or an indictable
clustering on the index and therefore it
ensures that no matter how you insert
values into your table in what order you
insert them the underlying physical
storage will be sorted so in some cases
this allows us to do binary search
directly on the table themselves which
is still login without having to go
through the index itself so this is if
you take a long time so what does let
this go but I quickly want to jump back
over to my sequel so again same email
address load it into my sequel I can do
the same kind of queries select star
from emails where where that fake one
was email equals that so the the my
sequel explained is not as good but
basically it's not a tree structure be a
bit is reading here it says this is
here's the index I could possibly use so
notice I have a hash index and I can use
that
and then if I do change that to be
greater than this still uses it no but
it it says here the kind of hard to see
it's small its rolled over here but see
the there's a column here called Rose
this is my sequel telling you how many
rows is gonna I think I'm at the reading
so that's twenty seven million wrapped
around around here so it could use this
hash index but it's gonna fall back and
do a simple salento scan whereas the one
up above it could do it in X and X probe
to find exactly what it wanted alright
alright so Postgres is now done we're
coming back here so now if I do limit
one right I get that first guy that I
had before right so this is saying it
give me the very first tuple you find
for this for this and this is the min
one that we found before because this
guarantee that this was inserted order
so if I if I do this now if I say I
delete that email address delete emails
where email equals this thing there you
go ask for the first one now I get a
different fake email address but now let
me start another one back in insert into
emails values default because it's a
auto incrementing key insert my guy back
in right it's still not in sorted order
because it only did that operation once
any questions this question is it to
enforce sort order I'd have to run
cluster over and over again for Postgres
yes for other systems you do not have to
do that you can say I wanted to be all
to automatically cluster by the index
this question is does the comm need to
be indexed before we cluster no so my
sequel it's sorted by the primary key so
in my sequel the leaf nodes are actually
the tuples themselves so as I'm moving
things around splitting and merging the
leaf nodes always be in that sort of
order so if I want to do a sequential
scan on the table I'm basically always
following leaf nodes and so in other
systems like
and sequel server db2 you can say create
this table and sorted by these columns
and I'll do it for you nope sorry
yes yes this question is I said that we
could use the physical ID sorry the
physical location the page ID and the
slot number as the record ID to
determine to make the tuples unique
instead why not use the timestamp of
when the tuple was inserted because so
in Postgres this is an issue from my
sequel this won't be an issue what's the
problem a timestamp he said in tribute
of setting the times aren't going to be
synchronized yes even more simple that
is an issue leap second leap years right
so now again they repeat the second now
what happens
I insert something now they have the
same timestamp or clocks can drift by
clocks are horribly inaccurate so you
know I run NTP every so often and now it
slowly just the clock but occasionally
has to do big big steps you might repeat
a second yes this question what's there
between doing the record a versus
milliseconds versus the unity yeah so
he's right milliseconds since the unity
file particularly beer it won't help
drift right if the clock has to get
stepped back you repeat seconds nobody
uses a time stamps in that way you can
use logical time stamps which we'll talk
about later on you always want almost
never want to use hard physical clocks
you used in conjunction with other
things yes
a question is when would you want to use
a clustering index when if you already
have an index so again like in the case
of my sequel I should show an example in
my sequel it's always a cluster Munich's
when I call create table it's always
clustered on that there are some cases
where for certain queries it for certain
queries you can be smart about like
alright well if I'm clustering on the
only logical time stamp one of us
inserted like the application told me
the time stamp then now maybe I can say
well take the last days worth of data
and put it on the fast disk and the
older stuff puts on slower disk there's
ways to do like disk partitioning that
way and data says we can enforce that
all for me underneath the covers so you
say this if if I have if I'm if I'm
clustered on email next on email and
that's my primary key and then primary
keys ID so if you have a primary key
we'll see this in a second you always
have an index on that on that on that on
that ID or all the attributes to cut
yeah so they hit update the index guess
depends how you store your indexes we'll
get to that later
like in if we'll get that one called
version so you the the pointer could be
the primary key or it could be the
record locations record ID you can do
different things
Postgres does record ID so we have to
update all the time my sequel does
primary key all right so we actually can
poke around and Postgres real quickly
and see what the see what the you know
what's roughly what the tree looks like
right so this is just an extension
Postgres that allows you to get
information about what's in the tree
right so I can say I had this index
called you know on the unbe plus tree
and I can say you know give me
information about it tells me how many
levels it has tells me how many elements
it is storing and the root block size so
then we can go even further and we can
actually get inspect the contents of the
treating with this command here and you
know the actual details doesn't matter
but there's a bunch of hex stuff right
so this is the root node so we can go go
a bit deeper now and show you you know
for a single node here's some
information about it but then we that's
all hex but we can decode it and then
here's a know here's this proving that
it's actually storing these emails so
this is saying that here's a record at
offset 3 in my root node or in this
particular node in the tree here's the
you know page number and all set where
it's located here's the hex form form of
what's being stored and then there's the
actual email address right so again the
the Davises gonna store tired copies of
these keys on the inside all right we're
gonna stop now and keep going to bunch
other stuff we want to get through but
that's just getting to show you that you
can by default you're always going to
get a big cluster e but you can for some
systems to tell you I want a hash index
and there's different trade-offs for
doing this
alright so now related to the point he
said about the the primary key you know
and the vs. the clustering index so if
you create a primary key the database
system will automatically create an
index for you actually for any time you
you declare a an integrity constraint it
will automatically create an index for
you and you think about it has to
because otherwise the only way to
enforce that is do a sequential scan so
in my one my auto increment key if I had
it to enforce the primary key uniqueness
of it every single time I inserted that
you know you need to blow up I didn't
have an index I had to scan every single
tuple all over just make sure there's
nobody has the same same key so again
every day.you system will do this
automatically for primary key and unique
constraints it and it so basically again
when i create the table if i have
primary key unique it's the same thing
as running these commands i'll create
the table then it goes heads and creates
these indexes
for foreign keys it doesn't actually do
this so if I create a new table here
called bar and has a foreign key
reference to this value here every
database system that I ever try this on
will always throw an error because it's
saying I doesn't have a way to enforce
this referential integrity constraint
without an index right you think it
could make all matically create one but
it doesn't do that because it doesn't
know because this has to be unique right
so it won't actually do this instead you
just replace that with it as adding
unique calls here and that that that's
builds an index automatically for you
that it can then use to enforce this
right because think about basically the
way foreign keys work is that every
single time I started a tuple into bar I
have to have his ID thing so then to
make sure that it matches to a tuple in
my biz table I can do a lookup in that
index and see whether there is a you
know parent referential match so now
let's talk about different ways to
actually use indexes beyond the you know
copy the whole key that we talked about
here today so the first thing that we
can do is called a partial index so when
you normally call create index on a
table it does a sequential scan across
the entire table and looks at every
single tuple but in many cases for a lot
of applications maybe you don't need to
have an index when the entire table and
instead you always want to maybe almost
you know some subset of the data so this
is what a partial index is you basically
modify the create index command and you
add this where clause at the end that
tells you what - match b2b in
order to be put into this index so now
if I want to do a lookup like this
select be from foo where a equals 1 2 3
and C equals whoo tang so I've built the
index on a and B my where Clause has
references a so I can still use this
index but I can also look at this thing
and say oh we're see it was wu-tang but
I know this is exactly the index I want
to use so then this allows me to do a
more the index is leaner because I'm not
storing all the information for all
possible tuples i'm only storing exactly
whatever it matches
we're closed so but somehow the query
doesn't have this e equals mu tang I
can't use that index so this is very
common when people do things like they
want to separate I have different
indexes for different date ranges like
you know per month I'll have it index so
I do look up quickly on all the orders I
want for that you know for that month
and again I'm trying to not have to
pollute my buffer pool cache with a
bunch of data that I don't need by
having a partial index now the heights
gonna be lower and I quickly find the
data that I'm looking for
so in this particular example here for
this query we were doing a look-up on a
using C and we want to turn B it turns
out actually for this particular query
all the data we need is in the index
itself so member I said normally the
index would for a given key would
produce a record ID that you could then
follow that to in the table heap and get
the tuple that you were looking for but
for this particular query here we don't
actually even need to even look at the
tuple because we need a to do the lookup
that's in there we need B that's in
there and C's already handled by the
partial index where clause so to answer
this query we only need to actually look
at the index we never actually need to
look at the underlying tuple in the
table so this is what is called a
covering index a covering index means
that the all the fields that are
necessary to answer the the require
result for the query are produced you
know art can be found in the index
itself I so you don't declare an index
as a covering index this is something
the database system figures out for you
automatically I knows of your query as
it notes a new index that says
everything I need is in here
so again just using this example simple
example I can get the B field from that
from that the a and B field can be found
exactly from this the index and I never
need to look at the actual tuple I can
do this work for a bunch of different
queries I can do this for aggregations I
can do this for joins and the advantage
here it's one less you know page ID
lookup and the page table and maybe one
glass disk IO to not have to go look at
the underlying tuple for this so the a
bunch of different data systems support
this all the commercial guys do
does
I don't think my secon Postgres to I may
be wrong about that but this is a big
win right if you can do this this is a
huge deal okay
I don't think Postgres can do this for
reasons we'll talk about later so for
this simple example this is great right
I need a and B a B confounding the index
but what if I have now another I have
another attribute that I want to be able
to do a look-up on or get for my query
but I don't actually want to build the
index on that attribute all right so my
table has column a B and C maybe I don't
want to index on the seat but it'd still
be nice to have a covering index not not
have to go look at the tuple so this is
what the include columns allows you to
do basically include column allows you
to say for all the keys that I'm storing
in my for my my leaf pages my leaf nodes
also include these additional attributes
so this case I'm building NX on a and B
all the inner nodes only have keys a and
B and when I do lookups I only examine a
and B but when I land into the leaf
nodes I can also get the C attribute
value for every single entry in there
right so now again if I go back to my
other query here select B from food
where a equals 1 2 3 and C equals whoo
tang
I do might look up on a follow that down
then as I'm scanning along the leaf
nodes I can look at the values at C
that's packed in the leaf nodes and also
value my predicate it produced my output
so this one is also this one's more rare
than the covering index support so a lot
of systems support the partial indexes
slightly fewer systems support the
covering indexes this one is even more
rare I think this is Postgres 11 has
yeah post press Elevens gonna add this
or has it now sequel server has it but
my C code doesn't support this and
Oracle does not support this so again
the key thing about this is that
although we can do a look up and see in
you've got where clause it's not in the
internet sort the we're not you know
greatly increasing the size of the
overall index the last kind of and next
one talk about our functional expression
indexes so again everything we've shown
so far anytime
we declare index we're always creating
an exact copy of the key that's in the
tuple and putting that in our index but
there may be some kind of quick some
queries out there where we don't
actually want to do a look-up on the
exact value of a key we want to do a
look up on some value that we derived
from the key so let's say I have a
simple example here I have this users
table and I want to do a lookup and find
all the users that logged in on the
Tuesday so this extract function takes a
timestamp and you pass in what element
of the the date or timestamp you want so
do W means a day a week and so this is
saying extract the day a week from the
login timestamp field and find the ones
where it equals to its Tuesdays to
Sunday zero Monday one Tuesday two so if
I create an index like this as we've
shown so far right this won't work why
yes so this one who says he says you
have to know how to extract our pull out
exactly what ranges will correspond to
Tuesday and so you can kind of be smart
say oh well my crave looks like this I
could say well here's the here's the
ranges of timestamps where Tuesday can
be found but as far as I know no system
actually does this so instead we which
you can just do is not use this and
create a functional index or expression
index where the actual the the
attributes your your indexing on can be
any arbitrary expression anything you
can have in a where clause you can you
can build a index on all right so now
what I'm gonna do a lookup and for this
for this predicate I know how to exactly
satisfy it by did you know you know do
look at every feed that just getting
along here finding all the the the twos
that match what we want
what's another way we could we could
speed this query up to then we've
already shown before the partial index
way right so instead of creating an
index for exactly in this way for
exactly for the extracted day a week I
instead just use that as my my where
clause to say put only the elements
where where the extract value produces
two right so let's do a demo this in
Postgres so Postgres has the partial
indexes it has the doesn't have covering
indexes and then the version I have here
is 10 so it doesn't have the include
clauses but we can play around partial
indexes verses the functional indexes
alright so for this we're going to
create a table make sure we turn off
parallel workers and timings on alright
so we're gonna create a table that has
an ID field and a login timestamp and
then this is going to be a simple this
insert query it's just going to insert a
bunch of records a bunch of unique
timestamps since 2015 - now at
one-minute intervals right and this is
gonna generate looks like to two million
records so in sake of time makes us go
fast so we'll PG warm everything now
everything's in our buffer pool so say
this is the query we want to run we want
to get the average ID of users where the
the day week is they logged in on the
Tuesday right so in this case here when
we run explain it has to do a sequential
scan there's no index so the first index
we can build is the expression index and
this shouldn't take long so now when we
run explain we can see that it's able to
pick out and use that expression index
we just built all right and again the
weight the way it did that it said oh I
know you're trying to do a look-up on
this you know extract function where and
where the output is - so
I just need to do a look up and say find
me all the values where it equals to so
then we can add the partial index again
this is now creating a smaller index
that only contains the ordered a it only
contains the the records where that
extract function equals to so now if I
go back to my function here and I see
now it actually wants to pick that index
because that's gonna be a commute
smaller less it's a the trees is is has
a lower height and I just find exactly
what I want immediately so again the
database system can figure out on its
own which is the best access method to
use for all these different choices all
right so any questions about this yes
okay so he said so let's try it out
right so drop index so save it is what
happens if my expression is a it's based
on some some difference or using the
current timestamp isn't that gonna
change every single time I run it so
look I think what post rest is gonna do
so let's let's do the let's do the
expression index where is that yeah so
he's saying do this take a login and
again I can put anything I want here
long as long as a valid expression so I
can say take my login and subtract out
now the current timestamp doesn't let
you do that okay how to do this in
yeah forget this forget Henry
subtraction in Postgres
can you do that that works okay
okay could you do this okay
nope now let's just do it let's do some
more so let's take a login subtract 100
from it didn't like that either yeah all
right so basically what happens when we
call create index it'll run the
malfunction once and whatever that
timestamp is now that now now later on
it doesn't change it's not dynamic it's
- as it builds the index so now if I
insert something again in theory it
should now use that the correct current
now if it's smart it could say well
wasn't now at the time when I built the
index I don't know whether it does that
or not but again so you can't do certain
stupid things like you can't do like one
build an index on one but I should be
able to do ID plus one now wait what am
i what am I missing here oh he's this
yeah that's what it was write them
double parenthesis so yeah so now I
can't and won't let me do this I don't
know I already user
log in expr let's try has a other
example functions an expression must be
mark immutable there go yeah but I
should be able to do this right like no
times that right anyway let's get my
point
yeah there's this thing called well cut
snapshots later on but like there's like
the now at the time the query runs and
it has to be guarantee that's consistent
for the snapshot would be index SL yes
so this question is when we create an
index what kind of index is going to
create so I so by default it's going to
create a B+ tree if I add that using
clause from before so this this is a
Postgres idiom this is not in the sequel
standard
so like if I add this using hash this
tells postgrads make me a hash index by
default everyone use you're gonna get a
B+ tree your question is when you add an
index you can make me put yes so when
you say you don't you don't need to look
at the leaf nodes of what they index all
right so I think your question is if I
have an index and if I do a lookup for
some queries I don't have to look at the
actual tuples I get to look at the
indexes yeah you were calling like the
tuples are you know in the table heap
don't they're not leaving
leaf-nosed are in the index right so I
always I always have to look at the
index because I in a B+ tree I always
have to go to the bottom okay so you for
some queries if you can do a covering
index lookup I never have to look at the
table the tuple I can get all the
information I need to compute the answer
from the index itself not all database
systems support that though for so for
what we talked about so far other than
covering indexes the idea is that we can
quickly find the the tuples that have
the keys that we want to look up one
without having to do is sequential scan
so so switch the scan is n if it's a if
it's a hash index I can do a 1 if it's a
B+ tree it's log n right so if the idea
is cutting down as much data as you can
to not look at not too wasted work
correct saving is if we create a table
and there's no index we always have to
do a special scan yes we told that in a
very beginning yes question is if I
create an index where does it live well
again if it's backed by disk it goes you
know it gets written out that you know
if it's backed by the buffer pool it
goes out to disk and I want to do that
because it's made my index might be
larger than the amount of memory that's
available to me so again I could have I
could have an ephemeral data structure
that's in memory and I have to blow that
away my sequel does that for for their
hash table because it has to be in a
memory but the B post tree is backed by
disk so as it gets too large I patient
things out we might separate hey they
could be the same buffer pool it could
be different of a pool instances it
depends on implementation again the
buffer pool manager doesn't know what's
inside the pages it says you want page 1
2 3 here it is and then whoever is is is
accessing it is responsible to know how
to interpret those bytes buffle minute
doesn't know doesn't care in the
high-end systems you can say here's the
buffer pool manage for indexes
has certain replacement policies and
here's one for tables they have another
replacement policy proposal SMI sequel
it's all the same okay so um let's now
jump back and finish up with tries okay
so in all the examples that show for the
people's tree so far the the inner nodes
and the leaf nodes always had an exact
copy of the keys yes you can do prefix
compression or suffix truncation as we
talked about last time but in general we
have the entire copy of the key
replicated multiple times throughout
throughout the the tree structure and so
the other issues gonna be also into
people's tree is that in order for me to
determine whether key exists in my table
I always have to get to the leaf node I
always have to traverse all the way to
the bottom right because again the inner
nodes may have copies of keys that don't
no longer exist because when I delete
them from the leaf node depending on how
I split merge I may have left my
guidepost up above so in order to
determine whether I know exactly this
key exists I always have to go to the
leaf node so this you know again it's
login instead of set of Oh n you have to
do to central scam but it's still not
great and I may have you know depending
on how much memory I have and how I'm
using my buffer pool manager I may have
a page miss right they do a lookup on
disk for every single node as I'd
reversed down so for some applications
it might be nice if we can actually
figure out at the top of the tree
whether our key exists without having to
go all the way to the bottom so this is
what a tribe does for us so quick show
of hands who here is her to try before
okay perfect
who here has heard of radix tree fuer
excellent okay so so radix tree is just
a specialization of a try and nobody
uses chives everyone uses radix treats
and databases so what we'll go through
this so a try is a tree data structure
where instead of storing the entire
copies of keys in our nodes in the tree
we're instead going to store digits of
key and by digits I don't necessarily
mean Arabic numerals I mean some some
subset atomic subset of our key like a
bite some or some a single bit and so
what happens is that we're basically
gonna decompose all our keys and store
them down the digits down you know
different levels one by one and then now
because we could have duplicated keys or
duplicated digits we only need to store
that once at each level so a really
simple example here would be a try like
this where I have three keys hello hat
and have so in the first level in the
root node all three keys begin with the
letter H so I sort each once and there's
a path down to the second level where
now I see I distinguish between hello
and hadn't have hello has an e hat and
have have an A for the second digit so I
have separate entries for that and then
now I have separate paths down to handle
for you know each each unique path in
the key so now if I want to look up say
I want to look up hello
I guess decompose it the key into its
digits and I look at the H I have a
match here I find the E and then I
tourist down ello oh and the bottom is
just like our and our B plus tree this
could be a record ID that points to the
actual tuple that we're looking for so
tries are old tries are older than B
plus trees or D plus trees were embedded
or in like 1973 at IBM tries are
actually from invented in like 1959 by
this French dude and he didn't have a
name for it and then there was another
CS researcher the famous guy ever defend
Caen and then a year or two later he
proposed the name try which is short for
retrieval tree and he was using that to
distinguish from from a regular tree
data structure so this is why they're
called tries and apparently this F M can
guy is actually seeing you faculty to
get a look at the you know the the CS
website the directory he's listed there
he's like super old I've never seen many
faculty mean I don't know who he is I
don't he's actually still here but
that's the guy that invented the term
try he's actually here at CMU supposedly
so sometimes you also see these things
listed as digital search trees or prefix
trees as far as I know these are all
these are all the same thing so tries
are really interesting right in the
concept of databases
all right you know now that we
understand people streets so the first
thing that's super interesting about
them is that their shape only depends on
the the key distribution of the key
spaces and their length so what I mean
by that is it's a deterministic data
structure so no matter what order we
insert the keys we're always going to
end up with the same shape of the
physical data structure all right that's
not the same thing as in a B plus tree
because in B plus tree if I insert a
keys one way and then I shuffle them
around and then and I sort them to
another tree depending on how I do is
split the merges I may end up with
different layouts of the note the keys
might be in one node versus another note
in a try it's always it's always the
same thing all right the other thing
about them is that they don't actually
require any any rebalancing like we had
in the P plus tree so we'll see you know
there is some rebalancing we could do
that at the vertical level but
horizontally we're never actually gonna
potentially rebalance so an unlike in a
B plus tree where all the operations
were login in a try the operation
complexity is K where K is the length of
the key all right this is totally
different than gonna be plus tree so
going back here so if I want to look up
hello I by the time I get here I know
that there's no you know I keep going
down the bottom but so the number of
steps I have to do is dependent on the
key that I'm looking up but say I'm
gonna look up and II am dy the first
letter is a I look up in the root node I
see it only has an H I immediately stop
and I know the thing I'm looking for it
can't be anywhere else in the tree and I
don't have to always Traverse in the
bottom yes your question is for the e
here do I have to iterate across the
entire block so this game is if this
thing is super wide does that does that
mean I have to switch the scan across
the entire thing you presort them as you
do binary search to find what you're
looking for well when we see actually
how we actually do this in like for like
bites you you can just jump exactly to
the position you want it's either there
or not there
yeah this is not really you know
physical diagram I thought I was
actually stored this is just a high
level overview okay
so again this is super interesting
because that the fact that like the the
complexity is based on the key that
we're trying to look up on the length
it's also interesting because now the
the we're not storing the exact copy of
the key you know directly in any single
node it's implicitly stored by the path
so if we if we want to reconstruct hello
we would Traverse down keep track of our
path on the stack and that that's how we
can put the key back together
whereas now this makes sequential scans
more difficult because although I can be
in sorted order
I got a backtrack and you know go back
up and go back down unlike in the B plus
tree where I can scan along the leaf
nodes so tries are gonna be faster for
point queries then a B plus tree but
they're gonna be slower than first of
her scans all right so now we get bit
more formal talk about the definition of
a try so but we would use the term
spanned to the same way in a B plus tree
for of a node just to say the span is
the number of outgoing branches is
essentially the number of digits we're
going to represent in in you know each
node in each level so if a digit is
gonna exist in the corpus then at the
level at each digit we do have to have a
pointer now to another branch if it
doesn't exist in our corpus at a level
then we just or null like a little bit
or something so now this this span is
gonna use B to determine the fan-out
just like again in a B+ tree and that's
can then correspond to the physical
height of the try so the parlance you
would say I have an N way try you would
say you have a fan out of order N and
it's the number pass coming out and
that's going to Turman the size of the
the digit you're storing at each level
so the most simple try you can store is
a one bit try right so they eat each
level I'm gonna discriminate the a digit
for of a single bit so let's say I want
to start these three keys 1025 and 31 so
it's a 1 bit tries I mean at each each
level we're gonna we're gonna look at
one bit so I'm showing them in you know
the binary form of these two numbers or
the three numbers again normally these
would be 32-bit or 64-bit but for
simplicity reasons I'm showing them in
in 16 bits so at the try would look like
this and I'll go through it each level
so at the root node we're gonna examine
the first digit position the first bit
and again it's a it's one way it's one
bit so it's either 0 or 1 so in this
first position all three keys have have
bit set to 0 so at bit 0 I have a path
going down at bit 1 is null because
there's no key that matches that then I
go now down to the second level and for
simplicity reasons we're just gonna
repeat this think of this repeating
across 10 times right but it's gonna be
the same thing I have a 0 all my all my
tuples are keys have a 0 at every single
position and have a path going down and
one doesn't have anything but now when I
get to this position here now I see that
there's a difference so for key 10 it's
bit this dish at this position is 0 so
there's a path going down to this side
for the other two it's a it's one so as
the path going down here so now if I
look at say the remaining part of this
key again it's a single path going down
and it's you know it's 1 0 1 0 and same
thing if it's null I have there's
there's no the bit if not said at that
position it's null otherwise it's a path
going down and then the leaf node again
this is just a record IDE that points to
the corresponding tuple same thing for
the other side right at this point here
they're the same but then they split
here and then now I have separate paths
for the other parts right is this
covered you know you know so we can do
this in 1 bit 2 bits 8-bits 16-bits we
can do this at different levels
different granularities so what's one
simple optimization we can do for this
there's actually two optimizations how
can we reduce the size of this tribe yes
exactly so he says we don't need spaces
marked zeros and ones because what is
this saying right so again this is this
is the value at this digit in this
position and then here's the pointer for
it so this is redundant
so all I really need to do is just store
the pointers right because if it's if it
at if the bid is set to zero and one
offset zero the better set the one I go
to offset one so this is horizontal
compression this is reducing the size of
of the tribe each try node what's
another compression weight where I could
compress us in the back
he says repeating the numbers there are
ten times for this one you actually have
to have so once I get down here these
parts here there's no other key that
matches this and sort of what he was
saying but but but up here breather
right we had to keep this is because
we're gonna split here so we need to
know how we got down to here so but
after this we don't need to store
anything mean stack into store well if
you go down here at this position at
this level if the bid is zero I only
have one key that matches so let me
destroy the tuple pointer to to that key
and then same thing over here so this is
vertical compression yes your question
is incentive story city instead of
storing the website yes this is like a
low mark opposition there's like CPU
instructions to get you can run in a
single structure in for like a for a bit
bit map a bit sequence find either
finding the the value at this offset in
some instruction you don't have to
iterate or like you find me you count me
the number of ones in my in this bit bit
field right there's a CPU instructions
to make this go really fast so it's not
like you're just doing like an in a for
loops quench like scanning over this
it's not as bad as you think it is okay
so again this is like low-level bit
information but it's showing you at the
extreme case you wouldn't actual
try usually you want to store them as
eight bits or
and a bite but for me this is the
easiest way to understand this and so
even now if it's eight bits same thing
for every single position I just have a
pointer or not and then quickly jump to
the one you also that I want so this is
fine and dandy if everything's static
but actually how do we how do we modify
this thing every do inserts and updates
and deletes so there is no standard way
to maintain a try in the way that there
was for a B+ tree different
implementations do different things so
I'm going to show you sir one brief
example I'm not saying this is the only
way to do this but just some of the
things you have to be mindful if you're
actually trying to build one let's say
again this is the hello hat and have key
set we had before so I insert hair again
I just reverse down I would find this
slot here and now I can serve this into
this alright so now let's say I want to
delete hat well that's here I go ahead
and delete that and rather than
reshuffling everything maybe it's okay
for me to leave an empty space here
right because then I don't throw the cap
action but now let's say I do lead have
and now I remove this and I say well now
I have this this note here by itself and
so if I want to you know actually find
hair I'd have to you know do an extra
hop to go down I are but I know I'm not
gonna have any other match so you could
decide just to roll everything up and
put it up here different again different
implementations use different things if
you take the advanced class will cover a
bunch of these things yes yes yeah you
mean real clear the radix tree is one
that's vertically compressed uh yeah I
should I should align without more
carefully yeah I don't on the slide yeah
radix tree is is a is one where you
remove all the path yeah positive I
don't know what I don't use to be a
slide here is defined what a radix
treaty I don't happen to it sorry okay
no this is it sorry this is the radius
tree
sorry it's when you do the vertical
compression to remove any any nodes
where there's no other distinct
differentiating path below it
sometimes called Patricia tree but
usually the call radix trees and again
it's a subset of a try okay so he
covered markets and the last thing I
wanna PP talk about is actually how we
do comparison actually the sake of time
I'm gonna skip that let's the last one
sideways inverted indexes again tries
are super interesting no commercial data
system as far as I know supports them
out of the box hyper is a system out of
of from Germany that tableau bought that
runs in you know tableaus its post was
compatible there they're all in on try
we do some research here on tries
they're super interesting but right now
the B+ tree is still the dominant data
structure everyone uses but there's a
lot of interest in them alright so so
real quickly everything that we talked
about so far have for these indexes have
been satisfying or handling index or
point queries and range queries so I
want to find out you know record where
it's people that live in zip code one
one five two one seven
all right that's an equality predicate
to find exactly the thing I'm looking
for or if I'm trying to find things
within date ranges right that's a range
scan okay again I can use user people a
street for that where the Bevo's tree
and the hash index hash tables are not
good for us when we want to do keyword
searches so for example say I have the
entire corpus of Wikipedia I'm gonna
find all the blue key bead Wikipedia
articles that that contain the keyword
Pablo I can't use a hash table index for
that and I can't use a B+ tree index for
that because I'm trying to find a sub
element of above value for an attribute
right and the candidate for the B+ tree
and I had to have the exact key I can't
do a partial key you know I can do a
partial key lookup but the if the key is
comprised of multiple attributes but
within single attribute I have to have
the entire value of it I can't have like
the first 16 bits so this is the problem
we're trying to solve here so quickly
just again just remind everyone what
wikipedia looks like the main thing we
care about is that there's this
revisions table that has a has a tech
that's my bookie sorry that has big text
field
all right and we want it we want to be
able to find all the matches for Pablo
for this so if I try to create an index
on the content field this is me a really
bad idea because again it's gonna take
the entire key an entire contents of
this this attribute in our table and try
to build a because people Street on that
all right and in case if we keep Peeta
this would be really stupid because some
articles can be kilobytes and now I'm
storing the entire key in might and my
index and yeah the only thing I could do
to look up someone is you know if
someone gives me the entire article back
which is stupid all right and so in
order to do this kind of look up like
this I I want to do a set of you know
something equals something I want to do
a keyword search like when the like
clause with wild cards and say find me
all the matches where the you know the
keyword Pablo's inside of it actually
and this is actually knotting the rights
equal going either way because this is
gonna match for things that have Pablo
as a prefix like Pavlov ugh them for the
famous Russian scientist and I'm gonna
find exactly where my name is being used
so this predicate itself is not gonna be
useful for us so this is what an
inverted index tells for us so an
inverted index is gonna map words and he
works as we describe them in the you
know English language or in natural
languages not like byte sequences in the
processor there's gonna map words to the
records that contain them and then it's
gonna louse it then do lookups on this
index and say find me all the records
that contain this keyword or have this
you know key word of this certain
property so these are sometimes called
full-text search indexes and just like
with when I created index and I told
Postgres I wanted this thing to be a
hash table index you can do the same
thing as some databases you can say I
want to create an index and I wanted to
be I wanted to be an inverted index well
full-text search index so sometimes in
in the theoretical literature these are
called core dances and this is because
there was this old lady in the 1800's
who sat down for 16 years and built an
inverted index that mapped every single
word used by Shakespeare and his entire
body of work alright but if this is
nobody calls him does everyone instead
calls him first full-text search indexes
are verted in texas so all the major
database
will support some variant of this
internally as I said when you call
creating index you can say I want to
have a full-text search and search index
and they all vary in the sophistication
of the of the indexes and what kind of
queries you can run on them
there's also a bunch of specialized
database systems that are that are sold
or marketed as full-text search
databases so the most famous one is poly
elastic search and this is built on top
of leucine leucine is like a library
written by the guy that invented Hadoop
that does like a you know does the
search it says it does indexing and then
elastic search provides like a server
interface to to that index so there also
uses the scene I think Sphinx does as
well I use these HP in which is like a
standalone C library that does full-text
and search indexing because this is
better than the my sequel full-text
search indexing but ideally you know
these are all these would be internal or
sorry external to like post customize
sequel whereas these other guys are sort
of like it's built inside of it the
system itself so the we're not got time
to discuss implementations but basically
all the hash table index stuff we talked
about so far in the B plus trees that's
what you're going to use to build one
these full-text search indexes so the
thing that there's a lookup and find me
all the you know the records that have
containers word I could build that as a
hash table I can build that as a as a B+
tree but I'm gonna augment it with
additional metadata that provide the
context about how that word was being
used in the in the tuple so the kind of
queries you can do that you can't do
want to be plus tree at a full-text full
or inverted index you can do phrase
searches so I can do again find all the
records that contain the word Pablo I
can do proximity searches so find me all
the records where the word Pablo is in
you know within five words or three
words from you know criminal or
alcoholic or something like that right
because I'm maintaining the context
information about how that word was
being used then I can also do a wildcard
searches that's more complicated than
the like stuff I can do regular
expressions or complex pattern matching
to find things I'm looking for
so the things we do care about slightly
is that how we're actually gonna build
this thing and again the different
systems will all do different things the
thing they're gonna bury the most own is
what they're actually storing again this
is the context information about how the
word was found in the attribute so at
the very simplest form you just have you
know the word itself and then map to a
record IDE but I can also include you
know what other words are around it how
many steps away from other words and
that will determine how how complex
queries I can support on this the other
tricky thing is actually when you update
these things so if it's built inside of
the system you could in theory on every
update make sure you update your your
search index or inverted index if is a
fist external and you can run this as a
cron job or push updates to it a lot of
times people will stage updates in
batches and then apply them every so
often because because potentially
updating the inverted index is super
expensive and again I realize I'm going
to over the super fast I just want you
to be aware that beyond B plus trees and
hash tables that we talked about here
it's a whole bunch of other database
indexes that are available that can do
things beyond point queries and range
queries that we've looked at and
actually the the other class of indexes
that we didn't talk about are the
geospatial between indexes so things
like our trees quadtrees KT trees these
allows you to do multiple dimensional
mock-ups like in your geometric spaces
and things like that these are very
common now in like video databases and
image databases so there's a whole class
that Christos falooda is the other Davis
professor teaches 15 a 26 he teaches it
in the fall and spring now so if you're
interested this kind of stuff I'll be
teaching it in the spring so the main
takeaway for all of this is that the for
our most of the time the B+ tree is gone
what we want that's the go-to index
that's that's very that's resilient and
solve many of the problems that people
have in databases inverted indexes we
can go you want to go more detail
there's a whole nother class and I think
an LTI 442 or 642 I think it's called
search engines right but in a search
engine only for covers is basically an
inverted index so it's the same the same
technology the same methods okay
so next Wednesday we're now gonna go
looking at how we actually make our B
plus tree thread-safe so we've sort of
washed all over this or we've not talked
about avoid the problem that actually
how do we allow multiple threads update
the index at the same time so now we're
spend more time talking talking about
that okay any questions ricochet jelly
bottle I can't say don't know your phone
can tap a