[Music]
[Applause]
today is our second lecture on query
optimization so again the high-level
idea or what we're trying to do here
today is give it a sequel query we want
to generate a physical execution plan
for that query that is both correct
meaning it will generate the correct
answer we'd expect as well as has the
lowest cost of all the query plans that
we we could examine the again we said
last class that this is super hard to do
because the the problem trying to find a
query plan is proven to be np-complete
and therefore even though the name of
what we're trying to do is called the
optimizer we're not really ever gonna be
gonna try to find in most cases form
useful complex queries the true optimal
plan so we last class we looked over a
bunch of different approaches to doing
this search we first talked up talked
about how to take use heuristics where
you just have these if-then-else
statements that are bacon the source
code looking for certain query patterns
and applying changes to to the query
plan to put into a different form then
we talked about how to do a combination
of the heuristics from the first
approach as well as a cost based search
approach that came from the system or
from IBM that allows us to find a
optimal joint ordering and the key idea
here what makes the cost model base one
different here is that the cost model is
guiding our search it's a way for us to
approximate the cost of a query plan and
then use that approximation to compare
one plan versus another we then talked
about how to do a randomized search with
simulated nailing or the gener algorithm
from Postgres and as far as I know again
Postgres is the only one using this
third choice here
but they only use it for queries that
are have more than 13 tables otherwise
by default you get the second approach
and then now we talked about
the movement in late 1980s early 1990s
towards these optimizer generators where
instead of having imperative code we
didn't see or C++ to do all these steps
for the query plan lien instead write a
our optimizer rules in a high-level
language than have a compiler generate
the optimizer for us so Starbucks was
sort of the first one in this space from
IBM and it was using a stratified search
which which is like this the heuristics
plus the cost base joint search and then
the unified search is doing the sort of
the logical and logical logical
illogical physical transformations
all in one and this is what was used in
Cascades for the paper you guys read so
again just to reiterate in the last two
points just repeating myself the
stratified search is where we're gonna
have these rules to do that the logical
quad plan transformations and the the
idea of way this is going to work is
again there isn't like there isn't just
a list of rules where we apply them one
after another there's this rule engine
for us that it's gonna look at the query
plan figure out sort of patterns that
would match what what is what rules we
have to find and then fire them off to
to make make our change but again in
this first step it's entirely done
without any without consulting a cost
model cuz there is no cost model then
after this we do the same cost based
search to map the logical plan to the
physical plan and again that was the IBM
technique but you know if I'd search
again the idea here is that rather than
having these two separate stages you
just have a single single search process
or a single search procedure that can do
both the logical to logical and logical
physical transformations so no longer do
you need the separate stages because
you're just doing everything all at once
right so the and what we'll see when we
talk about cascades is that the this
approach is going to generate a lot of
redundant transformations
because again like in the stratified
search once I get past that first stage
I'm never gonna reconsider those rules
again but in the unified search it's all
combined together so you may be trying
to evaluate the same rule over and over
again and so you'd have to use
memorization to to identify that you're
doing redundant computation or add
redundant transformation and use a cache
cache result rather than applying it
again again what we'll cover this in
more detail about when we talk Cascades
the in addition to whether you want a
unified versus stratified another
another sort of design decision you have
to make in your query optimizer is
whether you want to do a top top-down or
bottom-up optimization so top-down will
be Cascades and that's where you start
with a final outcome that you want okay
I want to join these three tables
together and then you Traverse down into
a search tree and start adding in the
operators the physical operators or
logical operators you need to get to
that end goal and you can use the
classic branch about pruning technique
to recognize that if there's a branch
that has a the current cost is greater
than the lowest cost you've seen from it
from the current off-the-book current
best plan you know you don't need to
burst down into it the the dynamic
programming technique these fall from
the system are is an example of a
bottom-up optimization where you start
with nothing at the bottom and you start
it early adding in the components or the
operators that you need for the query
plan to get to that end goal right again
this is this is the dynamic web eutectic
so the current literature suggests that
the dynamic programming bottom-up
optimization is better we'll talk a
little bit about today why that's the
case the in my opinion from a software
engineering standpoint I feel that I'm
able to reason about the unified
approach and the top-down approach
better and this is what we implemented
in our system
again there's like the research
literature and then there's what
actually gets implemented in real
systems so you will see for the paper in
to next week or two weeks when I order
yeah next week next Wednesday that
sequel server actually has the best
query optimizer and they're using a
top-down Cascades approach but the
literature shows that the dynamic
reading bottom one bottom-up one is
better because again there's a lot more
going on than just you know whether
you're going in.i these directions the
cost model matters a lot how you
collecting that the cardinality
estimations all that will contribute to
the overall efficacy and quality of the
query plan so generate and not just what
algorithm using it alright so for
today's agenda I want to spend some time
beginning talk about how we're gonna do
logical query optimization again these
the things we'll talk about here are
applicable to whether you're doing a
stratified or unified search then we'll
spend time talking about what the
Cascades how the Cascades optimize it
looks like and we'll do this in the
context as described in the paper ahead
you guys read which say master's thesis
from the late nineteen eighty nineteen
90s on a query optimizer based on
cascade called Columbia the reason why I
had you read that paper instead of the
original Cascades papers because the
original cascades paper is not very good
it doesn't really describe what they're
actually doing they keep banging on
about how great it was that their
object-oriented because that was in
vogue and in the early 1990s whereas
those thirty pages from that columbia
master's thesis
lays out in my opinion the best
description of how cascades actually
works and how its implemented well
briefly talk about why some things that
dynamic programming can do that maybe
Cask use Cascades can't do very easily
at least in the moderate implementation
as you've i've got the hyper guys in
germany then we'll talk about a bunch of
other sort of optimizer implementations
that are out there again these are be
categorized as whether they're doing
dynamic programming or Cascades
but again I just want it should be we
want you to be aware of what's out there
and then we'll finish up with a quick
overview of what's expected starting on
Wednesday this week for your project
three code review submissions so
and we'll do two rounds of Coast
missions equip of use so I'll sign you
to another group on Wednesday you sweep
your code on github doto code review of
your code and you do a code review of
their code so I want to talk about what
sort of expected for you as a student
participating in this project for the
stuff yeah all right so again there's
going to be two types of optimizations
that we can do there's the logical
optimization and and physical
optimization logical optimization are
changes or transformations that we could
apply to the logical query plan that we
get from the binder right or a further
up in our in our front-end stack that we
can apply rules based on matching
patterns or certain yeah certain
patterns that we would see in the
logical query plan and we can make
changes to the query plan in such a way
that we can potentially set ourselves up
so that when we do the plan enumeration
in the the physical query optimization
step that we can potentially find a the
album plan more easily so it's not
always gonna be the case that the
changes will make here will be guarantee
that we'll be able to find alcone plan
but if we know a little bit about how
our optimizer works we know a little bit
what our you know our plan a new version
album actually is then we can apply
these changes in such a way that we can
prepare ourselves I'm quoting right so
the important thing I'm saying about
this step how we're gonna stage this
between the the when we do physical
query optimization is that again because
there's no cost model we have no way to
determine whether one query plan is
better than another so we don't know
whether we take a collage achill query
plan then transform it to another
logical query plan the the optimizer
that stage can't say oh yes that
transformation was a good thing it's
gonna make a it's gonna help me generate
a query plan with a lower cost we don't
know that but we know systems since we
know some aspects about you know
relational databases or the kana davises
we're trying to run and what our query
looks like and how our system actually
performs we can then maybe direct our
transformations so
we prefer you know one plan over another
okay but the end of the day the
important thing is that the the original
plan or the new plan we generate after
these transformations has to be
equivalent to the original plan because
it doesn't help us that yes we found out
faster query if we produce the incorrect
result because people will get tests and
now your database system is considered
unreliable or there's something wrong
with the data like it's harder to debug
that so we want to make sure that any
changes we make be ensure that that
query is equivalent so I want to go
through four different examples of the
types of logical query optimizations we
can do and this actually comes from Tom
Thomas Norman the hyper guy in Germany
he actually teaches a whole class on
coordination and he goes to much more
detail over multiple lectures than what
I can do in just four lectures but some
of these examples are coming come from
from from his slides so we'll see how we
can do splits on conductor predicates
predicates push down replacing Cartesian
products with joins because again at the
very beginning all we have are Cartesian
products and then we can finish up with
during projection push down so for each
of these we're gonna use that same
example clear we have from last class
where we want to do a three-way join
between artist appears an album good to
go find all the artists that appeared on
my on my remix tape so a very beginning
what we're gonna get out of the binder
which is essentially just a copy of what
comes out of the the sequel parser is
all our predicates are going to be
combined together into a single filter
clause so we have three predicate
expressions in our where clause so we
would have a single filter expression in
our query plan again there's a logical
query plan it's not telling us how we
want to execute anything we said we
think the single filter up here that has
all three predicates combined to each
other and we do that filter after we've
taken the Cartesian product of all of
the three tables so in order to make it
easier for us to then start doing
predicate push down on other
optimizations on these individual
predicate expressions we want to
decompose the filter into
multiple filters that each have one one
conjunction of the of the where clause
so we just split it on the end and we
get it like this four ORS it's a little
bit tricky you can essentially start
duplicating the ORS if you have
different conjunctions knots or
negations or a little bit tricky as well
but a little about the high-level idea
is essentially the same alright so now
that we have these these these filters
like this we can start moving them in
different ways we can start moving them
to separately into different parts of
the query plan so this is how the
classic predicate pushdown is going to
work and the idea here is then we can we
can move the the predicate that we have
to be after the Cartesian product or at
the lowest point we can in the query
plan where we have all the information
we need or all the attributes that we
need for the filter at some point in the
tree all right so in this case here
after we do the Cartesian product we can
then apply artists ID equals appears
through our decidd
but we can't do it before on either side
because we don't have those two combine
tuples the two tuples together same
thing for this one up here but in this
case for album name equals Andes remix
we can put that immediately after the
scan on the album table because we have
all the information that we need so now
now we want to replace all the Cartesian
products that we have on a query plan
with with inner joins and this is pretty
simple right this is just identifying
that oh we have a Cartesian product
right above it we have a filter that
takes the output of the Cartesian
product from the table on the left and
table on the right and combine them
together or you know do our quality
match so we can just replace those
Cartesian products were here and here
with a within the join operator when
with the join up or specify where the
join clause is you know is that filter
that you should be right above it and we
can do this regardless of whether the
we're using the old old-style sequel
where the join is actually in the where
clause or some of the more modern sequel
syntax where you have the the join one
clause right this is the same idea works
in either one then the last optimization
we can apply is to do a projection post
push down so in in this case here you
know the beam we're being pedantic here
about the you know whatever query plan
is going to look like in a column store
you could you could implicitly assume
somehow that I'm not scanning the entire
tuple name in the scanning just two
columns that I need but you still need
some information say what actually those
columns you actually need to propagate
up into the query plan so in this case
here we can recognize which attributes
we actually need at different levels in
the tree and we introduced projection
projection operators to then only
propagate up the just the actions we
need at each step and so the way you
think about this is implicitly there's
pipeline breakers here here and I guess
up above here but like at the pipeline
breaker we would introduce a introduce
the the projection and that make sure we
only propagate the data actually need
and the reason why we don't wanna do
this all different parts because at the
pipeline if you're doing a push up
approach like in case of hyper is you
you were going to take a single tuple
and write it up as many as far as you
can up in the query plan and only
materialize it when you get to the
pipeline breaker other systems are doing
volcano are going top-down and that and
that the boundaries aren't aren't aren't
exactly the same okay
again sort of saying here like in this
case here we only need album name and
the album ID so we could have a
projection here just to filter out on my
D now name but again what will happen is
this filter action will get combined
here with whatever this this access
method here however accessing the tuple
so again we're not we don't have
projections everywhere we could write
but because so now is gonna be
implicitly represented this way
again these are all logical
optimizations again I didn't look at a
cost model I just said I know I want to
do things and I can bake the
transformation rules in my optimizer to
do this right like this one's the most
obvious one if I have a Cartesian
product and I have a filter that has a
joined clause right above it then I can
easily just write a rule that combines
that and I don't need to consult a cost
model cuz I know in my data is a inner
joins always going to be preferable to a
Cartesian product you must never really
you never want to exit Cartesian
products unless you're explicitly told
to do across join alright so now let's
talk about how to do physical free
optimization so this is where now we
have a logical query plan we have these
logical operators and we want to
transform them into physical operators
that we can then either koujun if we're
doing compilation or to actually execute
on in our execution engine so what are
the kind of transformations we're going
to want to do the most obvious ones are
gonna be things like specifying how
we're actually going to access the table
or the data and that we're targeting but
I'm gonna use a sequential scan but we
need an index scan if it's so on index
scan then which index we're going to
pick we can add additional execution
information about how we expect the the
data and be represented or sorted or
compressed choose operator invitations
for the joins like we're joint album we
want to use how we actually do our
aggregation and then in some cases also
to which we won't talk about today is
identifying when you actually want to
materialize potentially the the data for
one portion of the query so that another
portion you know another part of the
query plan could actually access it I
can be doing this sub query or views or
cities so in this stage here we now need
to make sure that we or we now have to
support cost model estimates because now
we want to be able to determine is one
physical plan going to be better than
another and the cost model is going to
allow us to do this so before we go a
little bit deeper into into Cascades I
want to talk about and how we're
actually going to do these
the physical transformations we wanted
somebody have a caveat and say that
everything we've talked about so far has
been sort of the simple case of always
doing Ecuadorians or inner inner inner
inner joins things now though become
more tricky when you start having you
know as you see more realistic queries
outer joins semi joints or Angie joins
because now we're not always going to be
able to makes have symmetrical
transformations to allow us to move any
operation around you know the or reorder
our query plan easily because there may
be some cases where you you you're not
actually allowed to do that because that
would end up with an incorrect query or
an incorrect result so let's say for
example here so say again I'm doing now
I'm doing a three-way join on a B and C
but I'm gonna do a left outer join on a
and B and then do a full outer join on C
so what we're getting into now is how we
actually explore the different join
orderings that are available to us in a
query plan so we can decide whether you
wanna join B and C first or a and C
first and so forth as we saw and with
system R but in this particular example
there's actually no joint orderings that
that are actually available to us are
possible because that would end up with
incorrect state and this is because we
have these outer joins
so in particular the outer join on a and
B the left outer join a and B is not
commutative without the outer join the
four outer join and B and C because I
don't know what the value coming out of
this joint for B will be for V dot Val
in order to join it with C so I have to
execute this first because they don't
know whether it's gonna be a real value
or null right because there's the left
outer join if is a de ID doesn't match
anything with be de ID then the portion
of B in the combined tuple will just be
null and B dot val could be null here
but I don't know that until I actually
do this join so you need a way when we
start doing these join reorderings of
the planet abrasions a look at the
different possible
choices to be mindful that there are
some cases where I can't do the
reordering and I'm is bringing this up
now because I'm going to show examples
where we assume that you everything's
commutative you assume that everything
could be flipped around but just in the
back of your mind be recognized that oh
there is an additional mechanism we need
to make sure that we don't reorder
things incorrectly the dynamic
programming is a little bit easier to do
this because you're having explicit
explicit graphs that you know you can
can can can move things around in the
case of Cascades the best my knowledge
you need to have additional property
enforcers to recognize that this this
reordering is invalid so the way we're
going to enumerate different plans at a
high level of there's two different
approaches this is the transformation
approach where you take an existing plan
and you start permuting it in different
ways to generate new plans that are
equivalent to each other you should have
to check to say make sure that you check
to make sure that the transformation
doing is valid and it's almost sort of
like a random walk except that you have
these rules to apply them and change
things and in sort of a directed way the
another approach is as was used in the
genetic program approach where you are
doing generative enumeration where you
start you take the parts of the query
that you want to execute it as building
blocks and you start graphing them alone
and constructing the query plan and can
be mindful that you don't want to add
things incorrectly to produce an invalid
query plan but you sort of start with
nothing and start adding adding things
so not saying one way is better than
another but these are just sort of at a
high level the two approaches we could
pursue so the state of the art for this
for academically for doing dynamic
programming is the method used in hyper
where you're doing sort of hyper graph
hypergraph generation where you start
with you know it's the general approach
where you start adding building blocks
of the query one by one and you're
checking as you go along whether the
change you want to make by adding a
piece in is valid or not so this is the
approach that's using hyper this is
approach that you used in duck TB I
don't know of any commercial system that
uses this approach the hyper guys might
might know but I don't know the answer
for this we in our system though we were
based on Cascades so I'm going to spend
more time talking about that so as I
said there is an original cascade paper
from 1995 but I didn't have you guys
read it because like I said I don't
think it's very good it's not that it's
not well written in terms of like
English grammar
I just don't think as from from a
pedagogical standpoint for this course
it provides a clear explanation on what
Cascades is actually doing so that's why
I had you guys read the the master's
thesis because I might get my opinion
that's the best explanation of Cascades
so what is Cascades well last class we
talked about volcano and that was a
top-down approach for doing a branch of
mountain search of adding adding
constructing a query plan Cascades is
the sort of third generation optimizer
that grits gravity had built and there's
a sort of again this this this
state-of-the-art approach that we sent
from what I'm aware of and so the big
difference we're gonna do here in
Cascades that we didn't do in volcano is
that we're gonna the the optimizer is
going to generate the transformations on
the fly as it needs them rather than
pre-computing all possible
transformations at every level we go
into as we're searching into the query
plan right so in the case of volcano
what happened is when I went from one
group to the next one down one level in
the tree before I did any evaluation of
the possible transformations I could
have each transformation I could apply I
generated all possible transformations
which will explode the search base right
and maybe the case that maybe got stuck
in a local minimum and didn't explore
the the the rest of the tree more
carefully right so the other cool thing
that we're gonna be able to do in
cascades is that we're gonna be able to
do a simple rewriting of a multi
questions or expressions within the
query plan but is having these function
and be able to apply them without having
to do an exhaustive search for all
possible combinations of how to execute
that multi expression that make more
sense and if you want a few more slides
the basic idea here is like I could have
a placeholder to say here's some lower
portion of the tree I don't know how I'm
gonna actually implement it just yet but
I don't need to search it just now I can
search other aspects of the tree and use
that place order okay all right
so for Cascades the sort of the four
main design ideas that person uses that
first is that all the all the
optimizations are going to be the simple
pair data structures when you contain
the pattern that you want to match in
your query plan and then if it matches
there's a rule to fire to do some kind
of transformation and they contrast this
with like the heuristic based approach
using Postgres use in other systems we
have a bunch of if-then-else statements
it's always these rules and you know
there's a rule and then then there's the
then there's the okay there's the
pattern and then there's a rule that
does the transformation and I can do
this from a logical the logical logical
and logical physical it's all the same
the next thing is that gonna have rules
to to enforce the property requirements
you would have on data or if they're the
enemy results produced but give an
operator and these are the things like
the the sorting order care about
compression and other things like that
like we can afford those things and then
the rule engine knows that it can apply
the transformation if the transformation
would end up violating the rule that it
has to be has to be has to maintain and
contrast this with the system our
approach where I said
that the rules to do the enumeration or
the search of the joint ordering it had
no notion of these physical properties
of the data it all had to be baked into
the cost model but now again in one
place I can define my rule that says my
data has to be sorted this way and make
sure that you don't do a transformation
that violates that the next thing is
that we can then now also define the
priority or the ordering of the rules
that we get applied based on these
promises so the way to think about this
is that rather than just randomly
picking what transfer transformation we
want to apply at a given level in our
tree we can specify an or and we'd even
get actually the dynamically so that we
can identify aspects of our query plan
and say we think these transformations
will lead us to the optimum plan more
quickly so apply these transformations
first and only evaluate the other ones
if we have more time and want to
continue searching at that level in the
tree and the last one that's important
is that they're going to treat the
predicates as first-class entities in
the system that's going to allow us to
do transformations on them just as we
would do for operators and this is how
we're gonna do all the things that I
showed in beginning like the predicate
push down projection push down and
things like that because a predicate
push an example because those again even
though they're like predicates inside
the where clause that would normally be
baked inside of like a select statement
or sorry scan operator we can have our
the engine do transformations on them
and do other optimizations just as it
would with the physical in logical
operators and this is actually something
we're trying to build now in our own
system we had a project in 7:21 last
year where they built a expression
rewriter using our cascades engine and
the student that's worked on that last
year is now working on it this year
again to help finish porting it into the
new system so we won't talk about this
today but this is allowed to do certain
things like if I have a where clause
that says where 1 equals 1 we can
rewrite that into
just to be true and instead of having to
evaluate the query tree and it's a tidy
for every single tuple now we compile
with LLVM so the Alabama compiler can
easily wipe that away by doing constant
folding but the these are the kind of
things we can do now though inside the
same cascades framework that we normally
would use for optimizing query trees all
right so the first thing we got to talk
about to understand Cascades is what an
expression is so this parts a bit
confusing because normally I've been
talking about expressions in terms of
the the predicates that are in where
clauses or join clauses or select
outputs and certainly in the in the code
of our system we use expressions to mean
there's no expression treated like one
equals one and things like that but in
cascade they're gonna declare an
expression to be a high-level opera
operation or operator in our system or
in the query plan that's gonna have zero
or more or input expressions to it so
say I have my query here a select star
from a join a B and C together like I
have a logical expression that would be
the join on a and B followed by the join
on C and then I could have a physical
expression that would be the scruncher
scan on a during a hash join on the
sequential scan on b and then doing an s
a loop join on a index scan on on c so
it's an expression would be some some
essentially the relational algebra
components for the query but if i
annotate them with these of these
subscripts i'm specifying what the
physical operator i want to use to
perform that before that relational
operator okay right so in this example
here these two expressions are logically
equivalent okay so even though this is a
specifying that the physical operator is
and this is just a logical operators
logically they're equivalent
they're both computing the join on a b
and c and so now we're going to be able
to rely on this community property
to enumerate all the different jointer
rings as part of transformations to do
exploration of the the search base with
this query plan and try to find a you
know find the optimal one and this is
what I was saying before when we talked
about left out of dueling 400 or an
example so in these case I can move
these movies operators down anyway one
because they're commutative but if I one
of these was doing a left outer join or
for doing then I would have to restrict
the transformation to make sure that I
do things in the correct order but for
simplicity in our example here we won't
worry about that all right so now now we
have we have expressions and that's
gonna be some sequence or some
relational algebra expression now we're
going to define groups so group is gonna
be the set of logically equivalent
logical and physical expressions for one
expression that that will produce in the
same output expression right so all
logical forms it's especially for a
given expression will have all logical
forms and it will have all physical
expressions that we can derive by
converting any logical operator into the
allowable physical operators from the
corresponding logical forms so what I
mean with this so this entire unit here
is a group and this group represents the
output expression of a join be join seat
and then now we have the logical and
physical expressions that are all gonna
be equivalent to this output expression
here alright so the contents of the
group are going to find based on on its
output and so I can't have a another
group with the same output right it has
me unique to to do Mike my query plan
right so I was important to note that
these expressions in here are unordered
meaning the
illustration of what's being contained
inside them
but just because this one's first
doesn't mean anything about whether we
should examine this one first that's
implied or that sort of computed as part
of the priorities you would get
your transformation the other important
thing they also point to is as I was
saying in the case of volcano for this
output expression they have to generate
all possible all possible permutations
of a lot of expressions and feature
those all possible permutations the
filter expressions in Cascades these are
sort of like you know these are sort of
computed on demand or just in time so
that I don't have to materialize every
possible logical expression in feature
those every possible physical expression
I can say I can apply my transformation
rule and it'll generate some equipment
logical expressions and I can determine
whether I even explode them further and
look at their physical expressions
alright so this you know this is so this
what I'm saying the in the case of
volcano since they were doing it all at
once the amount of state you had a
represent here it got really large and
so the on demand thing is is is the way
we're gonna sort of speed this way to
reduce that state but another
optimization we can do in Cascades is to
use what are called multi expressions
and the idea here is that instead of
instead of instantiating exactly the
verbose form of all possible expressions
for a given group we can instead
represent the sum sub expression with an
expression as a placeholder that is then
represented by or taken care of by some
group lower in the query plan and so the
they the set of redundant expressions
represented by these placeholders in a
group together is called as a called a
multi expression right so in this case
here before I was saying a join B join C
and have it's explicitly saying hey I'm
joining a a and B but now in the multi
expression I just have a placeholder
here that says hey it was a and B
they're being combined together I don't
know how somebody else below me the
query plan will tell you how to do this
but I know that I just have a
placeholder here and the same thing for
in this case here I have a scan on C I'm
not saying how to actually scan it
whereas
here I was explicitly saying you know
here that one news twins can I don't say
anything for that right so makes more
sense when you look at the physical ones
or the physical ones a mutton
I'm not specifying how I'm doing joining
a and B or how I'm actually accessing C
but I am specifying that I have a
physical join operator that's doing a
cert mode here right and so the idea
here the reason why we're doing this is
that in a top-down search strategy like
in Cascades we can then make the sames
about whether you want to traverse lower
down into the tree to understand how we
actually want to join these things
together right without explicitly blunt
blowing it all out in the the bottom-up
optimizer they're going to enumerate all
the most expressions sort of from one
group at a time and the order of the
tables that they're generated so they'll
start with a figure out how to maybe
access that and then figure out access
beam to figure out X se and then figure
out how to combine ami and together and
go for it
so it's sort of a different way of
looking at it so the before we can make
decisions now we'll see in the next
slide or the next few slides before we
make decisions about how you know how
we're actually gonna do you know for
this physical operator here we have to
make sure that for all placeholder
expressions we have below us in the tree
that we we figured out how we're
actually going to access them what's the
best physical cost or best plan with the
lowest cost for the physical operator
blue that in the tree and then we can
combine that together when we make a
decision about which operator we want to
do this for here again when we go
through the example this make more sense
so the last thing we need to understand
in Cascades is the rule system so again
a rule is gonna be some transformation
and we can apply to an expression that
will convert it into a logically
equivalent expression meaning it will
produce the same logical results and
when we actually execute it but so we'll
have two types of rules we'll have a
transformation rule which is a logical
logical logical operator to physical
operator or a logical plan to a plant or
plant subset into another logical plan
subset
and they'll have an implementation rule
that will convert a logical operator or
a set of logical operators to physical
operators and as I said every rule is
defined by the pattern will match to
identify which sub plan or find a a
portion of the plan that has a Civic
layout a configuration that matches to
our rule and then if we find one of
those then we apply the substitution
policy or the transformation that we
want to convert the the query plan
structure into the logically logically
equivalent change or logical equivalent
new plan so let's look an example here
to say this is our pattern and our
pattern is we want to match a sub plan
that has a equi-join
followed by another equi-join and then
we have these placeholder groups where
we're just saying we don't actually care
or no we don't need to know and we don't
care what these other groups are
actually doing we just care about having
sort of lefty tree where you have a go
join fall behind an equijoin so now say
this is a query that will match this so
again I have now a group here that's
combining a and B and joining us C then
I have another here another group here
that's doing joined between a and B so
these are both equi-join assuming that
you know you're doing a natural join and
then below that below each join operator
I have these get expressions but this is
somehow saying right here's how I'm
going to access the tables a B and C but
we don't care what that actually is in
our rule because we only care about
having these two matching joins like
that so the first type of join we do is
a transformation rule the first change
we do is the transformation rule where
we want to rotate the the joins to go
left to right so in this case here we're
going to switch the the the the join
below the joint at the top to now be on
the right side of the tree
whereas originally started off in the on
the left side a implementation rule
would actually now be converting the
logical operators for these joins into
now a physical operator specifies what
algorithm how
or I want to use so in this case here we
can convert these to be the joys of
useless or merge-join
so one thing with the mindful of in our
system is that or in cascades is that
we're gonna make sure that we don't get
stuck in infinite loops so in the same
way here that I have a transformation
rule that allows me to go that rotate
the joins from left to right on another
transformation rule that will convert it
from right to left so unless I'm careful
I could just keep getting stuck in if
the loop going left to right right left
and back fourth over never again so we
need a way to recognize that we've
already applied a transformation and
therefore we don't need to do it again
and possibly search what the query plan
looks like every we apply it so this is
what the memo table with a memorization
table in Cascades is going to do for us
so in the original Cascades paper I
think they use they talked about using a
graph data structure in our application
we use a hash table as far as they know
in the other open source Cascades
invitations they're also using a hash
table so what if acknowledged to do is
we can identify that we've you can
identify that we can have a group that
we visited before and therefore we don't
need to examine it again because we
already know what the query plan looks
like after we apply of that
transformation so that's good so if we
do that left to right if we try to try
to apply the transformation rule to go
back right the left we would say well we
already know what that looks like we've
already been there and we see that cost
in our in our in our memo table
therefore we don't need to apply it so
well how we're gonna do this is that
we're going to have equivalent operator
trees and their corresponding groups
store together or together into groups
and we store them in in the memo table
and we need a way to quickly hash and in
a fighh that we have we have duplicates
all right so what this memo tables can
do for us is it's going to in addition
to be able to avoid duplications and
duplicate query plan transformations we
can also use that to be identify quickly
that we've gone down now it's some part
of the query plan
and we don't need you traverse it any
further so this is tied to now this idea
of the principle of optimality that
cascades this could be based on and this
is from control theory this is for this
the Bellman's principle of optimality
and this is not specific to kept the
Cascades top-down search but this is
this is how we're gonna be able to you
converge on finally finding an optimal
query plan so all it really says is that
if I if I have an optimal query plan and
surprise of two groups then I know there
can't be another optimal physical plan
that for one of those groups because if
there was then I wouldn't be the optimal
plan it's almost like a tautology look
if I know that I know that this is the
best plan I've ever seen and I have a
best plan I've ever seen and I'm at some
point in the my search tree and now I
have a cost that's greater than the best
one I've ever seen but that if I
Traverse down into further down in my
query plan tree I'm not gonna magically
find the optimal plan that's me better
than the best one I've ever seen because
then because the way the search works is
that you're you're adding more in cost
as you go down and your automagically
going to get less than what you seen
before so this is just the branch and
balanced search method for solution tree
this is just saying that like we know
that if we get to a point in a query
plan that we have a sub plan that is
worse than the best movie ever seen we
don't we don't need to do any further
exploration on it okay so let's look at
now a full and an example of doing a
search so to say we want to do that
3-way join between a B and C and so at
the very beginning I have that this
group up here that says the output
expression should be a B and C so the
first step I need to do is fire off a
transformation rule that will generate
me a logical mult expression so here we
have now a and B combined together and
then we're joining joining C
so now what I want to do is Traverse
down into the tree and figure out what's
the cost of executing of you know these
two components of my my expression
so I'll start down here I'll take a and
B so again now I have a new group with
output it's is a and B because that
matches what my place hold or up here is
and same thing now I want to have a
logical transformation or logic
expression to represent what how to
compute this output so that's just now
somehow accessing a and I'm gonna join
that with somehow some way of accessing
B so now same thing I got to start with
this first this first component of my
expression and go down and examine how
I'm actually gonna access it so my
logical operator would just be get get a
I'm gonna access a hey they're not
saying actually how to do it so I can
have a logical to physical
transformation to then say oh I can do
an index scan on a or I can do a
sequential scan or name and then now at
this point here we have these physical
expressions because nobody below us in
the query plan tree so we can compute
the cost of what's going to take to Xu
both of these so let's say in this case
here the sequential scan for whatever
reason is is the cheapest way to execute
this this the access method on a so
we're going to compute the calls for
this and then we update our memo table
it's cut off here but this is just a to
say that the best expression we've ever
seen for the producing the output of
just a is the sequential scan on a with
the cost of 10 so now I can't even do
the same thing going the other side take
be I end up with this logical expression
be get B I compute all the different
physical expressions I could possibly
have sequential scan index scan the
sequential scan turns out to be cheap
the cheapest the cost 20
I upload 8 my memo table say to access
be sequential scan is the fastest with
the cost of 20 but now I come back up
here and I can up into that convinced
coop here and if they still start
computing more logic expressions for our
generating more logical specialists
pretty this produces output for me so
now I want to join be an egg because I
did that rotation
right the order it's a now same thing I
need to get the cost of accessing B and
then I get the cost of accessing a
before I compute the physical cost of
converting this to a physical physical
operator so but in this case here when I
go down and say what's the cost of
accessing B or what's the cost of
accessing a I've actually already done
this right I don't need to do that
because I already have the best cost in
my memo table so I don't need to do this
search again down here or plyo more
transformations I'm done and I just
reuse the cost that I've had here so I
can I could keep doing this like it's
only a joint B or B joint a there's only
two choices but now I can look at all
possible combinations of what physical
operator I want to use for computing the
join and here I'm only showing a subset
but now again if I want to get this
physical cost and you know that the cost
of accessing any of the code calls
exiting B but I already have that in my
physical plan right so the cost to save
this one here to do in the SERP
merge-join it's the cost of accessing a
which is 10 the cost of X is in B which
is 20 and the cost of the server is
joined assume is 50 and now I can write
that into my memo table to say the cost
of doing this is 80 so now here I come
back up to my according to this group
here and now I didn't need to examine
the other side access some C so same
thing jump down here I can gather do a
sequential scan or indexed and let's say
for whatever reason index scan is faster
so I record that cost to here being 5
and then now I just can I could do more
permutations of different joint
orderings of a B and C or I can start
examining be converting a lot of
expressions into physical physical
operators and examining what are the
different ways to access to do the
actual join and then I can pick one
different has the lower cost based on
the summation of what I've done below me
in the query planet all right so that's
essentially how Cascades works right at
a high level like we just keep doing
more more permutations
use the memory table as much as possible
but then we invoke the cost model
when we have enough to do a estimation
on the physical cost and now makes more
sense what we talked about last time at
the search termination you could see how
for really complex curves a lot of joins
I could heat going really deep into my
query plan and I just keep doing this
search forever so you need a way to
determine when should you stop and we
talked about how the wall clock time
just says I stop when I run out of time
right for a certain amount you know some
configurable amount I could have a cost
threshold to say like if I if I find a
look if I haven't found a lower cost I
haven't found a better plan that has
been 10% better than the best one I've
seen so far then I just should just stop
because I'm I'm sort of getting
diminishing returns on continuing the
search and then you know the last one to
be if I because also they search all
different options then I didn't stop so
cascades is as I said as far as I know I
don't think there ever was a standalone
cascade to implementation least I don't
think so I think that grid graph II
worked with Microsoft in the nineties
the emblem that cascades in single
server and it's best my knowledge there
they're still based on that but it's
been using a bunch of different bunch of
different systems as well most database
systems as far as I know are using the
dynamic programming technique method but
some of the newer ones in the last 20
years or so or using some of them are
using cascades so Wisconsin ah plus plus
was like Columbia where sort of
standalone optimizer generator that
would you know you define the rules and
we compute the or generate the cost
model or generate the optimizer for you
pivotal Orica and calcite are actually
two interesting projects we'll talk
about in a second but think of these as
standalone services that do query
optimization so you can have like your
database system running one machine your
query optimization service running on
the machine
and you send query requests over to the
optimizer service it crunches on them
and then spit you back a hospital plan
that you then execute and so these again
these are not these are not tied to any
specific database system
the ones that are actually integrated
the system against Eagle server is
pretty famous non-stop sequel is a
distributed database or parallel
database from the early nineteen
nineteen eighties that's still widely
used today in a lot of banks and
financial systems and so they rewrote
the choreographer in the 1990s cluster
expose a or is this to exist is a
distributed version of my sequel that
was blocked by the Morea DB people it's
two years ago now and according their
documentation they use the Cascades
optimizer to replace the original my
sequel optimizer and then our system
peloton which we started in 2000 we
killed it off two years ago but since
then 7:21 students have ported it over
into the newer system that you guys are
working on today so and as open-source
alright let's talk about pivotal Orca
and calcite because I think those are
like I said these are standalone
optimizer systems that are not tied to
any one database system we did examine
Orca in the very beginning days of
peloton decide whether we wanted to use
it they didn't have a look at that
locked imputation and the way it worked
was you would run the service and yet a
sent over these XML files that a
specified like the query plan and the
rules and and the catalog statistics
about what the data looks like but I
guess I wasn't very documented it's
gotten much better since than less when
we looked at it at the time it was it
was not initiate where we could I can
use it so Orca is a key annular cascades
implementation that was originally
written for green plum green plum was
one of the original data warehouse
systems from the mid-2000s that came out
with Vertica and data Allegro and Astra
data and so what happened was EMC bought
green plum and then VMware bought gem
fire single fire and EMC didn't wanna
have a database division VMware I didn't
have database vision so they both
divested their database products combine
them into a single company called called
pivotal so Orca was originally written
for green plum
but then they broke it out and had to be
a stimulant system so they can then use
it for their sequel engine on top of
Hadoop the Hadoop file system called
Hawk so again it's agnostic what the
actual data model is or what the actual
database system it is you specify
through these XML files what you you
know what rules you have and how it
actually wants to how it should actually
form the plans and then it's up for you
in your data system to take those XML
files when you get the response of
here's the optimized plan and be able to
execute it so the one interesting thing
about orca that we haven't talked about
here is that because it's a standalone
service you can imagine like I have my
cluster of database machines and then I
have one machines that's dedicated as
the query optimizer machine so that
means that can that machine can use all
the cores or all the resources that
available to it to do query optimization
so they actually can do multi-threaded
search so how would that look well in
either were doing dynamic programming or
the Cascades approach you could it's
easy to imagine that there's different
points of the query tree where I could
for call for spawn off different threads
to do exploration in them and there but
they're all using the cost model at all
examining doing their own
transformations you still have to maybe
update a global memo table to avoid
redundant calculations or update here's
the best plan I've ever seen but in for
the most part the search themselves is
very independent so they're one of the
few optimizers that I know about that
can do that can that is multi-threaded
which I think is kind of cool and
certainly our optimizers not thank our
optimizer right now could run different
queries do optimizing different queries
that when different threads but we can't
take one query and do the search on
multiple threads so there's two
interesting engineering things that came
out of the that are in the Oracle paper
that I find really fascinating that I
haven't really seen discussed in other
descriptions of optimizers so the first
is that in Orca they've set it up to
enable them to do remote debugging more
easily so greenplum
is designed as on-premise software so
it's not running as a hosted service in
the cloud
like if your corporation you download
the software that the green thumb
software in Orca and you run it on your
own machines in your own data center so
now the problem is though if now the
optimizer breaks or throws an error
there's a some problem with it
how you how do you actually debug that
if you're now the Orca developers back
and working in pivotal because they're
not gonna let you SSH into the Machine
and you know rerun the the the query
that failed or you know get a dump of
the data and run it locally because it's
gonna be way too big so what they did
was they had it so that anytime that
there is an error the system would be a
dump out its state in such a way that it
made it that allowed the developer to
take that state dump load it back
locally and be able to walk through
exactly what the state of the the system
was the optimizer was when that query
had an error so that you can easily
reproduce the problem and and fix it so
think of this as like a core dump for
your optimizer where it has additional
information like what was you know what
were all the transformations that I
applied what's in the memo table like
it's more than the quota dump it's sort
of more it's more specific customized to
doing court optimization to make their
life easier and again I have not seen
this maybe the commercial guys have this
but I have not seen this talked about in
other other optimizers the other cool
thing they do in Oracle which I find
super interesting is that they talk
about how they have this testing
framework that allows them to easily
check that the cost model and the
optimizer is truly picking the best
query plan the one that has the lowest
cost so they had this thing called taco
which is the testing the accuracy of the
query optimizer they claim it's open
source
I haven't maybe I'll find on on github I
need to email them but the way it works
is that I think of things like I think I
take my query I put into the optimizer
and then it'll spit out what I think is
the best plan but I can also have it
spit out what it what was the worst plan
and so now I can take the worst plan of
the best plan actually execute them on
my database system and see oh yes it
actually true
is that that the best one is actually
faster than the worst one now in that
case you don't want to do you know
that's to extremes the worst one
probably would be so slow that you don't
want to do it like it's a bunch of
Cartesian products it'll take forever to
run that's obvious so you ought to sort
of narrow the gap of what the worst plan
actually years or the the less optimum
plan is how many steps away from that is
from the optimal plan like you take the
best plan and the second-best plan run
them and improve that the best plan
actually truly is the better plan this
is something we want to do in our own
system we have the infrastructure and
the optimizer to potentially do this we
just haven't built out the testing you
know the testing framework to make it
happen so Orko is super cool Oracle was
one of the first standalone query
optimizer frameworks least in the modern
area era the got + + + + Columbia around
for the 90s but as far as I know in the
codes online but you know it's it's
dated and nobody actually uses that I
might have not maintained whereas orc
has actually maintained the other
optimizer framework that is actually
more popular I think in Orca at least
when I'm talking from David's companies
is this thing called calcite so again
this is another standalone code
optimization framework that where you
can specify you know what what data
model you want to use what crazy
language your support what the cost
models are and all the transformation
you want to apply and again it just
compiles them down and can do this all
all for you
so it originally came out of lucidi be
lucid DB was a Java based database
system start up out of the late 2000s
that failed as many different startups
actually fail there's a lot of them but
what came out of the ashes of lucidi B
was the actual query optimizer which
then got open sourced as Cal said if
everything's written in Java and there's
a quite a number of database startup
projects open source and closed source
that are interested in actually using
using Kaltura or we're actively using it
or pursuing the adoption of it some
examples are would omnis I heard DB
plays in sequel Apache hive spliced
machine and I know maybe two others that
have talked about they they wanna start
using this now they all use it to do
to different levels so this calcite also
provides you the sequel parser as well
so some of them is using two parts equal
and calcite has the seven dialect some
of them are using it to active you the
query optimization I have not seen
reports on how good it actually is but I
think again this seems to be a lot of
traction around this because this is
Apache project whereas Orca for whatever
reason maybe because pivotal stone owns
it that uh as far as their know only
pivotal Xin one using Orca even though
it's open source so I think for this one
this one you'll see a lot more in
systems going forward at the last
optimizer implication we'll talk about
is from them sequel it's not anything
mind-blowing the reason I'm bringing it
up cuz they do one thing that's slightly
different than the other optimizer we
talked about here and this is probably
because they're targeting distributed a
distributed database system environment
which we've not really focused on in in
the semester at all but it's just we're
sort of brick worth bringing up to and
understand you know the types of things
people can do in a query optimizer so
it's gonna have three stages it's like
the stratified approach you'll have a
lot of rewriter that is Lodge alots with
the transparent transformations but
these logical logical transformations
actually can use a cost model then
they're doing the logical physical
transformations and this is mostly going
to be a dynamic programming approach to
do the join reordering but then now then
the last stage they're actually going to
take the physical plan that you get out
of the numerator and then convert it
back into sequel but they're gonna
annotate the sequel with some additional
mem see ghosts of the commands for
moving data that in a way that sequel
can actually specify goes against egos
high-level doesn't say where the textual
data is but now we're gonna add commands
here to say like alright run this query
but then send the data to this this this
particular machine and in your cluster
so this parts is super interesting that
I've never really heard about in the
from the optimizer standpoint of doing
this I've heard about this for testing
where people take the physical plan
that's produced by their optimizer and
then reverse it back into sequel and
see if you run that to be optimizer
again does it generate the same planner
or logically equivalent plan but I've
never heard of this where they convert
it back to sequel and then actually
execute it and then parse it all over
again so this is this is their pipeline
for the query optimizer and again it
looks a lot like me what we talked about
so far you parse it you bind it and
there's the rewrite or enumeration phase
but then you take the physical plan and
then this planner thing converts it to
sequel and then you send it to all the
interval execution nodes who are then
gonna do all these same steps all over
again except for this last one here
because now the idea is that we want to
have each local node that has the data
to make a decision about how to actually
do the lowest levels of putting
optimization like accent method things
like that so the way to think about this
is like say I want to do a join or say I
want to scan on a table across five
nodes and on some nodes maybe the data
has certain different distribution
that's different than other nodes so
rather than me and a global a global
planner try to make a decision of what's
the best way to execute this query on
all five nodes I'll come up with a high
level global plan of how we want to move
data around in this first phase here and
then I send the sequel query that I've
some regenerate back from the political
plan send that to the local node who
then can now make a decision like oh now
I know since I have a more accurate view
of what my data looks like because it's
local to me
I can make a better decision of how I
want to exceed that plan on that node
again most distributed databases as far
as I know don't do this last step they
take a physical plan and then ship that
off to all individual nodes which I
think this is kind of interesting okay
so just to finish up the main takeaway
you should get all out of all this that
we looked at the dynamic programming
approach we look at the Cascades
approach these are sort of begin to two
ways to to go out searching for a
physical plan the
all of this though is gonna make me
highly dependent on having a good cost
model if you don't have a good cost
model doesn't matter when you're doing
top down and bottom up you're gonna make
bad decisions and you in their plans are
just gonna be gonna be terrible and so
we will see next week on Wednesday next
week does how bad these cost models
gonna actually get in particular we do
cardinality estimations with joins and
so there's no magic way to make this
work and so when I say sequel server has
the best query optimizer the research
shows it actually picks the best plans
and that might be because they have the
best cost model and cost best estimates
okay all right so let's quickly go
through what's expected for you for the
project three code review so again as I
said on on this Wednesday as part of the
project presentations or project updates
every group is gonna have to send a pull
request to the master branch on on
github so this will kick off a build and
Travis if that fails you can ignore it
but I'll kick off a build on Jenkins and
that one we do need to pay attention to
and also compete your code coverage so
for this one your PR needs to be able to
cleanly merge in the master branch that
means you want to do a rebase get all
our latest changes depending on when you
guys fork the code from us this
shouldn't mean that many changes and so
what will happen is you'll go to the
Google spreadsheet
I'll now non toast Piazza you put the
link to your pull request there then
I'll sign you to another group you guys
go into the I'll give you one access on
github you can go comment do a code
review on github against the other teams
pull request and I'll keep track of
who's participating and the idea is that
when the pull request is done or the
code review is done in a week from now
the the team that you reviewed will take
your suggestions to take your comments
and actually incorporate them and make
changes into onto your code and we'll do
this around again another round of code
reviews when we get closer to when we
get near to end in this pasture so above
all else we should be you want to your
code reviews to be helpful would be
courteous you don't want to be overly
disparaging or hard
to your fellow students so don't say
like this is the worst curve ever see my
wife that doesn't help anybody if you
want to give constructive criticism
about about about their project so these
are just again some general tips about
how to actually proceed with the code
review so for the group that Smith's the
code review or Smith's the pull request
you want to include a summary and
information about what files and
functions and methods that you want the
reviewing team to look at so doesn't
help us if you have this giant pull
request with all these changes and some
of these changes are a work in progress
and you don't actually want feedback on
them yet so you want to enter in your in
your summary you should provide
information say here's the list of files
or here's a list of functions that you
want the other team to review for you
now when you do the review you want to
try to limit yourself to only look at
maybe four hundred lines of code at a
time and sort of set a max limit for any
time you sit down to do the review to be
up to sixty minutes because after after
60 minutes it all becomes a blur and
you're just leaving stupid comments and
you're missing obvious mistakes right so
we're sort of limit yourself to to
looking at this amount of code at a time
and then when you go into the do the
pull request you want to have a
checklist or so when you go into the
code view you want to have a checklist
set on the side to say what did that is
that you're actually looking for and how
can you actually provide help so these
are some things that that I'm suggesting
that you should look into or be mindful
of when you're doing in code view so
above all else obviously does the code
work right there should be you know
should compile to pass any test that you
have that they would have for their code
in the pool class is all the code easily
easily understandable like it's not
something you know arcane assembly code
or weird intrinsic that are not obvious
and make sure so make sure that the code
is getting you people don't have these
giant functions that do much of things
make sure things are broken up into you
know nice composable chunks we avoid any
duplicate code and avoid any commented
out code again is the code modular as
possible ish we know global variables we
can't I don't think we check for that
but
humanly I think as a human you have to
check for this if they have any debug
output to make sure the reaction using
the this the debug functions would give
you you know print f snow standard C
outs right well the the scripts will
check that when you when you submit the
pull request on github but you know it's
in general make sure that they're doing
that these things correctly everything
should be documented all right so that
comments on the code should actually
describe what is the true intent of the
code all the functions should follow the
doxygen Javadoc format and there's a
check for this again in Jenkins make
sure you every function is actually
documented if there's anything weird
that's happening in the code that's not
trivial to understand just by reading it
make sure that's actually fully
documented what the expected behavior of
the component of the system is here if
you're using the third-party libraries
make sure that it's an understandable
why we're using that third-party library
and there's any code that single please
you know it you should have to do
statements that are actually labeled
correctly to say what it is they're
actually doing testing is super
important the overarching rule about
your your projects is that the code
coverage never go down for your tests
your tester is actually meaningful so
that means you just can't have your
tests you know run through some code and
then print a standard out and that's how
you're checking to see whether I would
actually do something correct right it
should actually do rigorous checking to
make sure that the functionality and the
behavior is operating correctly so are
the tests complete are they
comprehensive are they actually testing
what they have to be testing and we want
to minimize the amount of hard-coded
answers we have in our tests now not all
our tests work this way but you know if
there's a way to derive what the correct
expected output is without having a
hard-coded constant value then that
would be preferable so that if we if we
tweaked your test case and we don't have
a bunch of you know erroneous errors or
having spent time to figure out with
that new constant value should actually
be
all right so again I'll post this on
these updates on this information on
Piazza and what's expected of you and I
will discuss this on on Wednesday this
week at the project proposals alright so
for next class will be a new lecture on
what I call non-traditional query
optimization methods and the idea here
is to - now that we understand the
background of like dynamic programming a
cascade so the core fundamentals of
doing query optimization let's look at
different ways people can extend these
techniques or try additional things to
to improve the efficacy of our query
optimizer okay hi guys wash your hands
what is this
[Music]
won't be the same I've nice to take a
say I said a prayer