[Music]
[Applause]
today is part three for our lecture on
query optimization it's again I'm here
at my home office it's just me and the
Terrier who may or may not be asking
questions as we go along
so the the type of optimizers we've
talked about so far have been this sort
of classic query optimizers where the
query shows up we parse the sequel then
we run it through the optimizer and we
generate a plan before we even begin
executing the query this is how most
query optimizers work right obviously
you can't run the query unless you have
a query plan so you have to put it
through the optimizer but the challenge
is going to be that what maybe we think
is the best plan during the journey this
optimization phase before we even start
running it may actually be incorrect
right because there's a since we can't
actually run the query without a plan
there's some assumptions we have to make
about what the database and what our
environment looks like but these things
can change over time for various reasons
right so the physical design that
database can change because the
administrator the application could add
and drop indexes or change change the
partitioning scheme the the database
itself could get modified people could
insert tuples or delete tuples and that
could change the distribution of values
for our columns if we're invoking our
queries as prepared statements then the
the behavior of the query for one set of
the parameters might be different for
another set of parameters and of course
every time you run analyze or whatever
the command is in our database system to
recollect the statistics that we use in
our cost models every time we update
them then the decisions we'll make in
our optimizer could be entirely
different so the sort of focus today is
to understand like how can we
potentially improve our optimizers the
efficacy of our the
the quality the plans that were
generating by maybe relaxing this
requirement that we that we only
generate a plan or only revisit
assumptions or we never visit our
assumptions once we generate the plan
the beginning so to do this we want
understand a little bit what what a bad
query pan looks like a wide query plans
can be considered bad and then end up
with less than optimal performance so
we'll cover this more on Wednesday when
we discuss cost models but in general I
say the high-level the biggest problem
we're always going to have is the we're
gonna get the join order is incorrect
joins are almost always the most
expensive thing we're gonna execute in a
analytical workload and so if we get the
ordering incorrect that can get lead to
too poor performance and the reason why
we're going to make a select incorrect
ordering is because we're gonna have
inaccurate cardinality estimations
meaning we think that our join is going
to produce X number of tuples but it's
really gonna be you know X x wires you
know some some some larger multiple they
mobile it's gonna happen again we'll
discuss why this occurs more in the next
lecture but this this this issue is
gonna be a reoccurring theme that we
have to overcome and today's discussion
is sort of C techniques to do this so
but since we know things are gonna go
bad like we just know we can just assume
that our cost model is gonna mean
accurate or optimizers gonna make bad
decisions then ideally if we can detect
how bad our query plan is once we start
running it then we can make a decision
to adapt the plan to come to modify
potentially to account for these
differences and what we're seeing in the
real data versus what we assume we're
going to see and then we can then try to
convert our plan into into something
that's closer to the optimal plan so
what I mean that like that is say we
have a simple query like this it's a
four-way join between eight tables a B C
and D and then we just have a simple
where clause for the B and D tables so
let's say that we run this query through
our query optimizer and we do
this plan right it's a bunch of hash
drawings and nothing about sequential
scans but let's say that when we when we
generate this plan for this particular
join we estimated the cardinality of
that operator to be 1000 right this is
this is an arbitrary number that I'm
using for this illustration like the
cardinality is the number of tuples that
this operator all MIT but let's say when
we actually started run it we see that
were actually generating a hundred
thousand tuples so our actual
cardinality is two orders of magnitude
greater than the estimate one so the
question we're trying to deal with today
is if we knew what the district our
tonality was before we started executing
it I'm sorry
while we're executing it then could we
change some aspect of this query plan to
get us closer to a more optimal plan but
could we change the Jordan ordering
where we want to choose a different
algorithm to do our join well we want to
change maybe the access methods that
come below the join to use and maybe an
index or a different different type of
scam so this is sort of what we're
focusing on today is how to then maybe
adapt this this kind of plan when we
know something about the what the data
looks like once we start running it so
the the high-level idea again is that we
want to be able to execute but you ask
maybe the behavior of a plan to in order
to determine X maybe the behavior of a
plan to determine its quality relative
to other plans
and so the cost model is doing but the
tricky thing is gonna be back here
before I started executing us
I had to derive this cardinality from
the from my like statistics that I have
maintaining my catalog about what my
table looks like or what the what these
two tables look like when you join them
together so the stats are me based on
histograms and possibly samples that
we're collecting from the data we can
also make decisions about what the
hardware looks like what kind of cache
sizes we have what kind of maybe I
wouldn't want to use what other queries
and run into the same time like the cost
model stuff we'll cover next class but
then
main idea to think about is what we
talked about today is before we run the
query we only have an estimation of what
the data looks like and how our query
will perform and if we get that wrong we
wanted then try to be able to correct
ourselves so the technique we're talking
about today is called adaptive query
optimization and sometimes called in the
research literature adaptive query
processing right they're essentially
synonymous and into everything I said so
far the idea is that this technique is
gonna allow the database system to
modify the query plan for a query to
better fit what the actual underlying
data looks like and we leave modifying
before the query plan by just generating
an entirely new query plan like throwing
away the old one and starting over or we
could try to modify a subset of the
query plan a read query plan by
introducing new sort of sub plans almost
like a pipeline at different points
where we have to materialize people
where we could potentially switch from
you know one plan strategy to it to
another and this one here you basically
go back to the optimizer and start over
this one here is that you can try to
have the optimizer only do only replan a
portion of it or provide these
alternative strategies at the beginning
so the main the main up sort of takeaway
approach what we're doing here is that
rather than just relying on our
statistical models that our estimations
or approximations on what the data looks
like we're trying to use the data we've
collected while we actually execute the
query to then help us make a decision
about what the right plan should be for
our particular query right and this data
we're gonna collect is could be used for
helping our current query or merge it we
can merge it back into the system as
we've collected through our analyze
operation and have it be used for other
queries so again we'll cover the various
ways you have to do this but when you
think about what a query actually is
doing you know or what analyze does
analyzers doing a sequential scan to
compute some statistical models about
what the data looks like
and so these if we're doing the cilantro
scan on a table that's essentially the
same thing as analyzed and so rather
than just evaluating predicates or using
the you know the tuples as we scan them
to generate the result we need for that
particular query we can piggyback
piggyback off of those off of that scan
operator and sort of main or maintain or
update our and update our Cisco models
with new information and the question
here is whether we just update that
models for ourselves to make our query
go better Oracle you can share this with
other queries are in a global catalog
and now other queries can benefit from
from the data we've collected from this
all right so there's sort of three broad
categories that I want to cover using a
qo or adaptive query optimization one is
that we can use a qo to benefit future
invocations of our query the second
approach is to try to make our current
invocation of our query better and then
the last one would be well this is like
helping your current query this is also
helping your current query but this one
would be sort of starting over from
scratch and just running through the
optimizer all over again
this would be adding locations in the
query plan that allow you to change one
strategy for versus you know switching
one strategy to the next which again out
having to go back to to the optimizer so
we'll go through each of these one by
one so the so the most simplest form of
adaptive query optimization is as I said
where as we execute our query we also
collect some information about what the
data looks like and then we can use that
information to decide whether our query
is wrong and when we plan it or we could
then merge that back into the sort of
global catalog again when you think
about this right what if the optimize
are actually doing you have bunch of
histograms or statistical models about
what your your your attributes look like
so for a given predicate in your where
clause you want to estimate the
selectivity of that predicate because I
don't determine how many tuples your
scan will emit and the amuse that make
decisions about you
during orderings and other things above
in the query plan so the as you execute
the scan if you if you you know you
actually know the true selectivity
because you're applying the predicate
and the tuples and you know the number
the the number of tuples or percentage
of the tuples are gonna match so if you
then determined that the cost model
estimated my selectivity was one percent
but when I run the real query and I run
the query and actually do the evaluation
of the predicate my selectivity is 99
percent then I wanted to use that
information to help me decide whether to
replan my query or that future queries
come along they can you know exploit the
knowledge that I've gained so again the
the the one approach is to try to fix my
current query but the other one is just
merging it back into the into the
overall mystical cattle of models and in
the catalog so that I can then help feet
of queries in the future so the most
basic approach to do this is called a
reversion based plant correction and the
idea here is as I said is just every
single time I invoke a query I keep
track of what query plan I generated
forward I keep track of the cost
estimations I have for and then the I'll
have all my metrics of what what
happened when actually when I ran it
right how many how many tuples I
selected how much CPU and memory that I
used and I'm gonna maintain this history
inside the database itself so you'll see
this in like the commercial systems like
in db2 Oracle and Seigle server they
have this built in repository of the
history of every single query that ever
got them vocht and they can use that
information to help decide how to do
query planning in the future so let's
say that we have a prepared statement or
we have a query that that's being
invoked all the time and we have a cache
query plan so rather than maybe run it
through the optimizer every single time
we can use the cache quarry plan that
we've already generated from previous
implications so if now there's a change
in our in in the you know the statistics
or something about the database physical
design that changes and we recognize
that we maybe want it for this
queer even keep invoking we want to run
it back through the optimizer and see we
generate C we generate a new plan but
then when we run that new plan for this
query if we see that the performance of
the query is worse than the old plan
that we had before then we just want to
run back to it right if there's a
regression in the performance we switch
back to the plan that we know actually
performed better for us despite the
change in the other in the physical
design or the statistical models so we
use that simple query example that I
have a for right the four-way join say
again this is my original plan I am
doing nothing with special scans and a
hash drawing and say that my estimated
cost is a thousand and my cost
estimation is pretty good so my actual
cost actually matches up ideas just
synthetic numbers here so I'm going to
store in my execution history for my
database system that I generated for
this query I generated this plan and
when I ran it I had this cost and this
is just another database or another
table in my database system right you're
sort of eating your own dog food rather
than having an axillary store this is
just another table that you looking to
record this information all right so now
let's say there's a there's a change in
our databases on say the DBA comes along
and adds two indexes on the B table in
the D table which we're using in our
where clause so now when we invoke the
same query again we would recognize that
the design the database has changed in
such a way where we may not want to
reconsider the query plan for this
particular query right so this query
touches B dot Val and D dot Val well I
just happen to create indexes on those
columns so I want to run this through my
optimizer again and see what plan again
let's say now for the new plan it's
completely different so now we're
instead of running hash joins or running
index nested loop joins and we're doing
an index scan on beyond D which we can
now do because we have index on that
which we didn't have before and so now
we're gonna pick this plan for our query
because the St estimated cost is 800
which is less than the estimated cost so
that we had over here but when we
actually run it for whatever reason that
we think that we don't care about at
this point the actual cost is is 1200
this could be that the you know we
incorrectly estimated that the cost of
these nested loop joins would be cheaper
than the hash joins so we picked in that
nested loop joins so just as before it's
when we actually put this give me that's
not Corona um if we actually now put
this in our extra history we would
recognize that the for this plan here
again it performed worse than this other
one here so the next time we invoke it
we want to make sure that we use this
plan oh you want to look back to the one
that we know perform better so for this
approach here this is something that
Microsoft has had in sequel server and I
think Oracle has something similar in
since maybe 2012-2013 but this is pretty
coarse-grained right this is pretty
brain-dead heuristic that's basically
saying oh this query plan is bad let me
just switch back to this one I said so
it's not at all or nothing thing so the
payment you guys are assigned reading
from Microsoft is called plan stitching
and the eye high-low idea is exactly the
same where if we recognize that our
query is running slower than query plans
we saw in the past rather than
potentially this strong way the entire
query plan that the new query plan and
reverting back to the old one maybe
there are elements or aspects or sub
plans within the newer plan we actually
wouldn't want to retain because and then
that data that'll help us lead us
towards towards a better plan a more
optimal plan right and the other if you
think about plant stitch as well is that
the sub plans you're gonna borrow from
other queries don't need to be actually
from the same query like in this case
here I can only reuse the plan in the
simplest form I can only swap the team
plans if they're running on the exact
same query but with planned stitch
because I can excise out sub plans or
portions of the query plan as long as
they know that they're logically
equivalent I can take bits and pieces
from from other queries alright the
other thing too is that
if there is a change in the physical
design we're a new planet query plan
becomes invalid meaning like it defined
that it wouldn't do index scan but and
then I drop that index rather than just
getting thrown away the entire query the
query planet in its entirety I could
maybe in pull out pieces of it type so
the basic approach they're going to use
is or the way they're gonna generate
these these stitch plans is a dynamic
programming search method using a
bottom-up approach where you just you
check the see from going from one level
to the next in the same way we do a
system are going one one note of the
next to pick which which which which sub
plan is the best and then once you reach
the end goal you you find that the
cheapest path so this means that it's
not guaranteed to find a better plan
than the best plan you have so far and
it is not guaranteed to always produce a
battle plan and but there's some basic
heuristic so you use to make sure that
happens right so going back to our
example here right say that this is our
new plan and say it was working just
fine right like it was actually faster
so we always want to use this but now if
I come along and I drop one of the
indexes that I'm using this plan now
becomes invalid and under just sort of
coarse-grained reversion
I can't reuse it but with plan stitching
I actually want to figure out what
components of this sub plan of the query
plan here that I may want to use in the
new plan even though overall it's
invalid there's still portions that are
that are still usable so in that state's
case say or say this portion of the sub
plan the the sub plan of this part of
the query the extrusion cost is 600 and
we would know this because we can keep
track of every although the ratchet
runtime cost of all the operators in art
and aquarium and for this one here this
sub plane over here has a cost of 150 so
now if I combine these together into a
stitch plan the total cost of this case
would be 750 whereas before if I didn't
run this it was a thousand so again the
idea is that we want to be able to
borrow bits and pieces of different
query plans to and help us produce the a
more optimal plan
and this is being done separately from
the the regular optimizer in the case of
Microsoft's sequel server
they're running cascade - they're
actually doing a top-down search but
this is sort of this auxilary search
that's running on the side that in the
background it tries to find a plans it
can stitch together so let's talk about
how they actually do this the the first
step is you need to identify which
portions are which what cell plans in
our queries are logically equivalent
right we talked about before under live
Cascades when we have when he had multi
group multi expression groups we want to
know that the the the output of a given
some plan is is the same or equivalent
to another sub plan right and again we
have to rely on our the rules of
relational algebra to recognize which
operations can be commutative or
associative so in this case here this
portion of the cell plan just the output
is the a join be joined see this portion
of another sub plan is the output is C
join B's join a but since joins these
inner joins here are commutative we know
that these are logically equivalent now
as I said the well one one challenge
with this is that determining whether
any arbitrary logical expressions or
logical sub plans are equivalent has
been shown to be undecidable meaning
like it the questions like are these two
cell plans logically equivalent it's
it's a yes or no answer but there's no
algorithm that exists as a been proven
that can can be guaranteed to always
give the correct answer so in the
planned stitch phase they're gonna rely
on some additional heuristics to
identify things like oh I know that
these two sub plans are accessing
different tables so therefore they can't
be logically equivalent right you
obviously can do more complicated things
the optimizer itself in sequel server
also has those kind of checks in place
and so they rely on that as well so they
have their own heuristics to prune
things that can never be logically
equivalent and they rely on the sequel
server optimizer
identify that the logical sub plane
you're trying to mash together or that
the sub plane trying to match together
in the stitch plan is is invalid so the
heuristics are providing them with this
sort of sweet spot balance between the
difficulty in the implementation by it
symmetry enforcer rules the accuracy of
the of the determination whether they're
equivalent and then the performance
right it's not an exhaustive search and
exhaust evaluation of all possible
inputs to different cell plans
it's just rules based on the relational
algebra all right so now once we
identify that we have a bunch of
equivalent sub plans we want to figure
out we want to sort of combine them
together into one giant query plan that
where you're going to add some
additional operators to determine that
you can have branches to go down
different different paths in the sub
plan so this is how they're going to
encode the the all the different
combinations of the sub plans for each
stitch together so the way this is going
to work is they're going to introduce
this new or operator which is not
actually used for execution this is just
something for the search and the the or
basically indicates that the sub plans
below it are logically equivalent so we
could choose either path so starting
from the from the top we have an or
clause at the very beginning and then we
have the two for this particular query
we have the you know doing the hash join
or the the nested loop join and again
these are logically equivalent because
this is a joint B joint c.join D and
this is C join B join a John D and those
are in the joins are commutative so
therefore these are logically equivalent
so then now say go down we're gonna go
like a depth-first search going down on
this side for this one here the same
thing we do the hash join on a and B
followed by C this is the next loop
joint on C followed by C join be join a
again these are logically equivalent so
that's why we have or clause we can
choose either one and then we're gonna
keep going down until we get to our leaf
node in scheduled scan and then here we
don't see we don't there's another
option for us
in in this portion of the query plan
because the one we stitched from just
you know only had only had a hash join
so now in this case here for the hash
donor a we can do a sequential scan as
we saw on the first plan already knew
the index scan on B because that came
from the second plan and so we have an
or operator to express that going back
up here
we can only do a sequential scan on C so
that's a straight path coming back up
here for the nested loop join it can you
know only thing we knew below it is
another nested loop join and then for
this we can get either do a sequential
scan on a or again for B we now to do
the scheduled scan or the index scan
going back up here for the hash join
again we that's feeding a special scan
on D feeding in and then we just
complete the the rest of the tree like
this so this is a bit more simplified
version of what they showed in the paper
but these are actually the possible
options you can have and so what I think
remember in the paper what they talked
about is that this approach and doing
the search within this define stitch
plan that they're able to stitch about
75 to almost a hundred cent of all the
plans together but for the workloads of
it they looked at alright so now that
we've encoded our search space we
actually want to do our search and this
is just starting from the bottom and
going up in the same way we did with the
system our dynamic programming search
where we just for every single leaf node
we started off with figuring out what
the cost is for going to the next
operator we pick which one is the best
and then once we complete all the we do
this search for all the nodes at our
current level we then go up to the next
level and complete this process okay so
the say we start with a central scan on
a it only has one option first which is
just the oh it has either a hash join an
a B or or the the the necess
that's a loop over here say the hash
join is cheaper so we pick that now we
just crunch will scan a B this has an or
operator alright so this is either doing
a hash join or the next loop join and
say the hash join is cheaper so we pick
that now we do this for the index kin on
B again there's an or operator you need
the rational in the nested loop join and
so because we have an index the nested
loop join actually would be cheaper
we picked that and we just keep going
down the line and do this for all our
leaf nodes and then we're done we go up
to the next level and then again now we
have a cost for all these paths leading
up and we just pick which one is is the
cheapest for us and then we reconstruct
the we struck the stitch plan that way
right so I get I think this is an
interesting approach
I don't think Microsoft is actually
running this in production like this was
a research paper that was published in
Sigma I don't know of any other system
that's doing something similar like this
I from an engineering standpoint the
fact that you have to run this
separately from the from the query
optimizer and sort of have separate
infrastructure for that tier what are
you doing
alright so rather than having you know
separate so search infrastructure if
there's an integrated into the query
optimizer like a component itself I
think this would be an interesting
approach so there's another system that
does something similar to this plan
stitching but they're actually working
on a sort of a sort of a cogent level
rather than the called physical query
plan level so amazon has their redshift
data warehouse service and it's based on
par Excel and they use actually a they
do it's a translation engine so the
database system for a given physical
plan generates C++ code or C code which
they then compile and then they run you
know they invoke the the shared object
that comes out of the compiler and then
that's how they do query compilation so
the obviously the most expensive part of
you know cogent engine is the
compilation right in their case they're
actually forking GCC or whatever
compiled using to actually generate the
the machine code so they want to try to
avoid that for every single query so
what they can do is they say you're
doing you want you want to compile the
scan on B where you want to see what B
Val equals some some input parameter so
the coach and that piece run it through
the compiler that generates x86 code and
then they'll go ahead and cash it
and then now anytime you reinvest weary
you know you can just reuse the compiled
version of the scan on beam but similar
to plan stitching what they can also do
is they can recognize that if you have
another query with the same kind of
predicate be davao equals you know some
parameter
it'll Co gen the exact same thing so
rather than recompiling it which is
again to extent the part they can
identify that they have a cache plan
fragment for this this scan here and
they can reuse that and so they actually
can do this across all possible or press
all their customers so like this you
know this scan on a table to do one you
know something equals something on a bar
chart field that's gonna be the same
from one table to the next because it's
a column sure sure you're just ripping
through the column so they can actually
share these little fragments and stitch
these physical query plans of the
compiled query plans together from all
possible you know customers so now for a
given query that they never seen before
if it has the same pattern of access
methods and joins and other things as
queries from an another customer they
just pull from the cogent cache and
stitch it together so that's kind of
cool
alright so there another interesting
system to talk about is ibm's leo the
learning optimizer and so this is an
example of where you have a feedback
loop being used to improve the the
accuracy of the cost models in the
system i said the idea is that again if
i I keep track of what my cost model
estimates were when I want to generate
the query plan and then when I run it if
I recognize that those estimates are way
off I start recording information about
what I'm seeing in the real data and
then when my quarry completes I return
the result back to the the user or the
application that requested a quest the
query but I also go update my cost model
assistive sixth with the new information
that I've collected um so I BM is Leo
was is actually shipped in production in
db2 today but this is one of the earth
examples of a commercial system do
applying one of these debit query
processing tech
all right so the the plant stitching
stuff that we talked about or the virgin
stuff is about fixing future invocations
of a query to improve them based on the
results that I'm seeing when I when I
actually execute my query but now we
want to talk about how do we fix my
query live up my sequel query and I
determined that I have a bad plan what
do I do
all right how can I fix it because I
don't want to wait for the next
invocations I want to fix the one I have
right now so I'm calling this the
replaying the current invocation again
the idea is that if I determined that
the observed behavior of the query plan
as I'm executing it is way off or
divergent from what the estimated
behavior was that the cost models
produced then I can decide to
potentially either stop the query and go
back and generate a new plan or I can
decide to maybe how much smelled
recognize that I've already produced
some work for me
and keep that portion of the data that
I've already processed and then return
back to the optimizer and ask it to just
just generate a sub plan so again you
know just start with a scratch and you
know you decide that continuing with the
same query plan that I have now is gonna
be worse than just starting over
obviously if you're at the last to put
the last operator then it's a bad idea
just let it finish so striking right
balance of this it's difficult and then
the other approaches are determining
that well I'm doing 100 joins and I've
already done one of them let me keep
that one that I have because I was
expensive and then I'll replan the
ordering for the other 99 and the whole
idea here is that you're going back to
the optimizer and saying hey generate
generate me a new plan so let me give it
a give of that so it does something sort
of similar to like this so this is from
Apache quick step quick step was it or
is a embedded analytical engine sort of
similar to duck TB but I don't think
it's supported sequel it came out of
unity Wisconsin and then it's been
it's been turned over to the Apache
foundation
I think it's been kicked out of the
incubator program because I don't think
they've updated it recently I don't know
what's going on with chicken ash and his
team but I haven't really seen any
updates in a while but they had this
really interesting approach called
look-ahead information passing where I
can do some work at the beginning of my
query and pass that along to other
operators or other portions of my query
plan and help me make a decision about
what the right ordering is for for
things up ahead so for this example say
we have a simple data says three tables
and so this would be a star schema so
this this this approach only works for
star schema we have a fact table in the
middle and then you have dimension
tables coming out of it right so it's
not for arbitrary star schemas or
arbitrary like treat tree based schemas
so the way this is gonna work is say
this is my sequel query like this I'm
doing a three-way join between the fact
table and the two dimension tables so
what I'm gonna do is before I begin the
before I start scanning the fact table
and start computing the hash table of
hash tables for my join I'm gonna scan
through the dimension tables and
generate a bloom filter we solved this
similar technique being used when we
talk about joins right this idea came
from vector wise that you can generate a
bloom filter and pass it along to to the
other side the query plan so so that
maybe avoid a hash table probe and we
said this so the joins are gonna be on
the dimension tables these are in front
of the hash tables and the fact table is
just gonna do a probe so I want to
generate the bloom filter and then check
the bloom filter to see whether the key
I'm looking for can even exist in the
hash table which is cheaper than doing
the hash table probe but we're gonna do
differently here is that we're actually
gonna pass these bloom filters and when
we pass it over here to the fact table
we're going to start do some sampling to
determine the selectivity of the of the
of the different bloom filter so for
these different tables and then if we
determine that well the second second
table here DeMint the second dimension
table is actually more selective than
the first one then I want to
shuffle the reshuffle my joins so that I
do that the probe on this hash table
first because I'm gonna end up throwing
away more tuples and we can do this
before we actually start running
anything because we've already got the
hash tables we generate the bloom filter
and we can make the decision before we
start scanning and doing the probe so I
think this is a really interesting idea
as far as you know quickstep is the only
one that does this and I don't know
whether it actually made it into the
open source version all right the last
adapter query optimization techniques
sort of category you want to talk about
is what I call sort of plan pivot points
and the idea here is that we want to
introduce additional sub plans in our
query and then have a have a sort of
special synthetic operator that we put
into our query plan that allows us to
pivot or switch which query you know
which path and that query plan we want
to do and the idea here is that we can
put conditions in our in the switch
operator or the the change plan operator
that if we determined that our data
looks one way we'll go down one path if
it looks another way what will go down
another the other path it doesn't have
to be - it can be multiple ones so the
sort of two most famous techniques for
doing this are parametric optimization
in a proactive e opposition again in a
high-level they're gonna work exactly
the same way it's just the
sophistication of their technique is
slightly different so parametric
optimization was actually developed in
the late 1980s and in 1989 this actually
came out of the volcano project again
the same one that does the volcano query
optimizer the volcano iterative model
they also did early work on adaptive
query opposition which is in as I'm
saying that work is very influential so
as I said the idea is that for each
pipeline and a query that we think that
the different alternatives we could have
that would make a big performance
difference well generate different sub
plans for them and then now in our query
will have this choose plan operator that
basically has gonna an if clause that
says if the cardinality of the operator
below me looks
way of a certain size then I want to
choose the first plan if it looks
another way then I'll choose this other
plan right and in this case here if I
know that my data is really small then
maybe I want to do a nested loop joining
because that's gonna be cheaper than
having to build a hash table and probit
but if my data's really big then I maybe
want to do the hash Tron alright how do
the hash run so again I think this is
actually interesting idea of course
obviously the the tricky thing is
determining what this conditional in
this condition should be and you know
there's it's sort of through trial and
error and as you develop the thing and
it's actually very dependent also it
won't be on the harbor but the nice
thing about this is like there's nothing
we end up like not having go back to the
optimizer and sort of replaying
everything the and we don't throw away
any of the data that we've collected
right so that we do this hash join and
then we just determine whether we want
to go down one path versus another a
more recent sophisticated approach of
this is called proactive reoptimize
ation and this is actually combining the
ability to go back to the optimizer and
generate a new plan as well as to tweak
it in the same way we saw in the
previous example so they actually can do
both and so at a high level it works
like this so crazy shows up we gender
through the optimizer
and so we'll generate different
different switchable plans just like
before we're also gonna now gonna
generate bounding boxes that allow us to
determine whether the assumptions we're
making in our decisions about whether go
down one path versus another we're
actually gonna match up with reality but
it's basically trying to put a bounds on
the uncertainty we're seeing in the data
as we run so now we start exiting the
query and just like before in in leo and
other techniques we exit query collects
as statistics about the data that we're
seeing for a particular query and then
we can switch the query plan just as we
saw before if we determine that you know
one plan path might be better than
another but then if you also determine
based on on our if we're exceeding our
estimations in our in our bounding box
thresholds
we see that we're way out of you know
way out of whack and our estimations are
way off then we just go back and can we
optimize and then you determine whether
to pin the portions of the query plan
that you've already executed because you
know they're expensive or you can just
say throw everything away and start over
so this is sort of getting a crash
course on a depth of query optimization
the I actually really like this these
techniques and there's for obvious
reasons right like it doesn't rely on
getting it right the very beginning like
you can even sort of correct yourself as
you're actually running the query so
well again we'll see a next class when
we talk about cost models of how bad
things can actually get but the way you
actually need to implement this is super
important that it's just not you know
you don't want to implement your
optimizer and your execution engine
completely separately from each other
it's sort of a symbiotic relationship
where you have to know what kind of
strategies could be employed by the
execution in the optimizer in terms of
like switching paths and throwing weight
interviewed results or not and then you
build your optimizer or you build
optimize around what your execution
engine can actually do so for this
reason I think like the I think applying
this technique for our using this
technique with sort of those optimizer
as a service like Orca or calcite could
actually tricky because there's
different approaches for how you can
actually support adapter query execution
in the system itself so the in addition
to having sort of more robust or more
more sophisticated query optimizers all
versus the open source one open source
systems all the major database vendors
now support this within the last
actually mostly in the last three or
four years like db2 had this Leo thing
in early 2000s but really in the last
three years about Oracle and sequel
server and now Teradata also included
the ability to do that the Cori
operation but it's best my knowledge
Postgres and my sequel simply can't do
this and none of this sort of the newer
open source systems that's come around
in the last decade support anything like
this so all right so
again this was just sort of to show you
that you don't have to build the
optimizer the way we described it where
you sort of plan once and run it through
our techniques to actually modify the
query while it's running and they get
feedback from execution and put it into
the system tier with doing all right
sorry um so next class will then start
discussing how how cost models work and
we'll see why they're so bad okay guys
what is
[Music]
won't be the same I've diced you take a
sake to the player