[Music]
[Applause]
right yes all right so today we're talk
about MVCC multi version control and so
this is actually the first part of a
three part lecture or three part series
where we're gonna go into really a much
greater detail than we did in the
interruption class and actually talk
about how do you how do you implement
MVC on a modern system
we're just against everyone's on the
same page at a high level what multi
version control is is a not so much a
specific incur to a protocol but it's a
way of designing a database system where
you're gonna maintain multiple physical
versions of a single logical object in
the database and so by object I'm being
vague here it could be anything it could
be a table it could be a block of tuple
a single tuple it even could be a single
attribute within a tuple and practice
most people just do it on a on a per
table basis but again the idea is that
for a single logical object that we see
in from the applications perspective
we're going to have multiple physical
versions underneath the covers so what's
gonna happen is when a transaction
writes to an object or doesn't update to
an object then the instead of overriding
the the original value of the existing
values it's going to create a new
version and that new version is going to
have the change that we just made again
the idea is that we have to keep track
of yeses pardon
all right we'll fix that later what fix
that next time all right to the end the
idea is that when we do an insert it's
obviously just the version doesn't exist
we're just putting in the database when
we do a delete or an update we need to
keep track of that we had previous
versions and we're creating a new
version and then when we try to go read
that object again at the logical level
underneath the covers the database
system has to figure out well what is
the correct version that we need to read
and it's going to be the one that is
that existed when it transactions
started so MVCC is not a new idea it
goes back into the nineteenth late 1970s
it was first proposed in this
dissertation at by this guy Reed at MIT
alright and this is sort of the first
like description of how MVCC would work
the first real implementation as far as
we know was in this system called inner
base at a deck inner base is actually
still around today it sort of changed
hands couple of times it got bought by
Borland with the ole compiler company
and now it's bought by some mobile phone
company or so it's now that's been your
sort of rebranded as in global database
but the when Borland had it they did
they did actually fork the source code
and open sourced it as as Firebird I
said that that actually exists today I
don't know I've never really come across
anybody using it but they're still
maintaining it still working on it if
you ever wondered why Firefox is called
Firefox because when Mozilla went under
and they took the netscape browser they
were originally gonna call it Firebird
but that that you know that conflicted
with this system so then they had to
rename it to Firefox right so which
interesting that NBCC is that pretty
much almost every single database system
that's been developed or released in the
last ten years including the the two
we've been working on here at CMU
they've all been using MVCC right it's
super common so it's kind of important
for us to figure out you know how we
actually want to build resistant okay
let's we should keep it like a jar as
possible yeah sorry I'll figure out how
we get a key to this all right so the
main idea of mzc
the benefit we're gonna get that is that
the writers aren't going to block the
readers and the readers aren't going to
block the writers so that means that
when we go and update a tuple
writing transaction and writing thread
is gonna update the tuple unlike in two
phase locking where you'd have to you
know take an exclusive lock on the tuple
and block anybody from doing anything
even from reading it under MVCC we don't
have that problem
we don't right we can how we can create
a new version and other transactions can
can read the older versions without them
without any conflicts now for write
write conflict well have a simple rule
says the first writer always wins that's
the simplest way to do this right that's
you know you obviously don't want that
or you can't have write write complex
but this is gonna be allow us to do some
things that we couldn't normally do on a
single version system like have a
long-running analytical query run in the
background and we told versions while
newer transactions are updating updating
database so for read-only transactions
what we're gonna get is a it's gonna
also be able to read a consistent
snapshot the database everybody's gonna
have a consistent snapshot and I'll
define what that is in the next slide
but the big advantage of this is that if
we declare our transaction as being
read-only at the very beginning then we
don't actually have to acquire any locks
to read anything because we know we can
always read a consistent snapshot in
some systems like my C code you don't
even acquire a transaction ID because
that's a for them that's a centralized
bottleneck handing out those transaction
IDs so you just skip that entirely and
so the way we're gonna use to determine
what is visible to us is through
timestamps again we'll go over this more
in more detail the rest of the class but
then we're also now gonna be able
support MVC or to call it time travel
queries so again in the single version
system what happens I update a tuple the
old version is gone right the old field
values it's in the log in case I need to
undo it but when queries run they're not
looking at the log they're looking at
the tuple but with MVC see if we don't
do any garbage collection and keep all
the old versions around then some
systems will lie to you time travel
queries to say you know run this query
on the snapshot of the database that
existed at you know two years ago or
three years ago so this a bunch of
systems claim they support this that's
not a new idea either
like Postgres had this in the 1980s you
basically just don't do garbage
collection and you do a little extra
work to allow queries to specify what
snapshot they're looking at Postgres
again Postgres inferred you proposed
this it wasn't
I actually started getting used outside
of academia in like the late nineteen
ninety nineteen nineties that they
realized that this is the feature nobody
wants and you run out of disk space for
it quickly and so this is one of the
first things they did when they they
made Postgres be actually usable outside
of Berkeley was you know get rid of this
support put a bud gets that bunch of
newer systems claim they support time
travel queries today I have yet to see
any any sort of real use case for this
alright alright so we need to find what
what snapshot isolation or snapshots
mean so in the intro interruption class
we talked about isolation levels we
actually never really talked about this
because this is actually something
that's not exactly defined in the sequel
standard but this is something you get
in some systems when you use MPC C so
the way it's going to work is that when
a transaction starts it's gonna see a
consistent snapshot of the database that
existed at the time when that
transaction started so what that means
is that you only see versions of tuples
that existed that were created by
transactions that committed before you
started so if if my transaction starts
and there's another transaction that
started before me but they haven't
committed yet and say they updated tend
to pools or they updated five before I
started and five after I started I won't
see any of their changes because that
because none of those versions actually
got committed before my my first
transaction started all right so that's
what I mean Mike assistant you're not
gonna see any torn right so many actual
transactions you only see things that
you know have committed before you
started so then also as I said before if
we have two transactions the running at
the same time and they tried to update
from the same object then we'll just use
a simple rule that says the first writer
wins right under like two phase locking
when you do deadlock prevention or
deadlock detection right there's all
these different rules to say who's older
than this when should I wait should I
abort who holds the most locks maybe I
let them go before the other guy goes we
don't do any of that so that's too
complex for us just to kind of run in in
a marine environment we just say whoever
who wrote it first they win second guy
tries to write the same object well we
needed up some tech that we're trying to
write to the same object and if so then
we just kill ourselves and abort so you
may be thinking alright well this seems
like you know awesome synaptic isolation
gives us exactly what you want yeah
we able to achieve certainly a question
yes right so this question is what I
mean by the first rider wins is it based
on the time that they started or is it
based on the time that they wrote it's
based on the time they wrote so you can
actually start before I do but if I
write to this tuple and then you try to
write to the tuple like you have but you
have to go board right didn't think of
it like it's the simplest thing you do
because I as I'm as I look at the tube
were trying to write it I would see Oh
someone got to me before got so before I
did you just go ahead and kill yourself
I don't know whether you're gonna write
to the same thing so how would I abort
before you wrote to it right that's
important question Rico question alright
so snapshot isolation is not
serializable right II and I'll show you
why because it's susceptible to what's
called the right skew anomaly but it's
it's it's sort of it has different
anomalies then like repeatable reads and
and read committed and what's also sort
of confusing about this is like if you
take Oracle for example with Oracle if
you declare that you want your isolation
level to be serializable which are
really getting underneath the covers is
snapshot isolation but they don't tell
you that unless you read the
documentation so it's sort of important
understand what the distinction is and
you'll see why this is not going to be
serializable and the next class we'll
see methods to go to actually add add
add additional things that davis isn't
to make snapshot isolation sterilizable
yes questions are faint as possible does
under this yes but in particularly it's
susceptible this right skew anomaly
which repeatable reads doesn't have all
right so the easiest way to understand
the right skew anomaly again so remember
from the interruption class we talked
about dirty reads unrepeatable reads and
and the other conflicts you can have
right skew is actually something that's
very specific to snaps snaps not
isolation that you get in a multi
version system so the easiest way to
understand this is to this simple
visualization that supposedly was was
created by Jim Gray the guy that and
then two-phase locking so let's say I
have a database of marbles and marbles
gonna have two colors it can either be
black or white and so I have a
transaction two transactions that want
to change all the white marbles the
black and all the black marbles to wipe
so let's say these two transactions
start at the exact same time right and
so again they will have under nbcc
they'll have snapped or under snapshot
isolation they'll have a consistent
snapshot of the database that existed
when they started right so they each of
them have two black marbles and two
white marbles so the first guy here he's
going to switch all the white marbles to
black and the bottom guy here wants to
switch all the black marbles of white so
they go ahead and do that there's no
right right conflicts because they
updated different things and then now
they commit but what happens now we have
two white marbles in two black mambas
they'd essentially just got reversed is
that sterilizable your shaking head note
why what you're just drinking your drink
okay so he said if it was truly sir lies
bowl then it would have to be equivalent
to a cereal ordering of the transactions
so that would either be they be all
black or all white but in my example
here right we ended up with two white
and two black so under sterilizable
isolation right this could not occur yes
your question your question is sorry
you're saying that like I'm working on
the assumption that I only need to
update but like these two here yeah well
II the query is update everything find
everything that that's white trying
everything that's black and make it
white find everything that's white make
a black right so when I looked at this
when this guy ran it when he looks at a
snapshot he doesn't see you know he sees
that these guys are white so nose knows
it doesn't need to update them but then
when I when I commit them then I end up
with that you know that anomaly yes
essentially reading all of the tuples
for turtle marbles yes and only writes
into the ones that are black or white
yes effectively wins this issue be fixed
if they just blindly broke into every
tuple and then under snapshot isolation
you get an equivalent to the
serializable since david is saving is in
this case here we would read everything
find the ones we do need to update and
that's our right set and then we then we
write that out you're saying what if we
just blindly wrote everything so this
guy was already white make it white this
guy was already black make it black and
then try to review that as our right set
well in that case it would one of them
on a billboard right it said so then
yeah so so yes it's a one would abort
retry but then your then your then your
this yeah I think so
the issue here is my this is written in
English change black marbles to white so
that could mean like I mean you can
infer that find the black marbles and
make them white you could in theory also
say I just make everything white because
that's what I want assuming I only have
two colors doesn't matter what's white
now make it white you know white make
sure that it's white no Davison would
actually do that because one there might
be higher-level semantics about what
this query is trying to do like my case
is super simple so like you can say oh
yeah of course if it's way to make it
white that's fine but for in a real
database that's probably too difficult
to do furthermore you're also keep
always in extremes if my database is a
billion or marbles I don't want to have
to write out things they don't I need to
write out because otherwise they might
just I'm better off just executing this
as a one thread after another all right
all right the main takeaway is that
again I want to point out here that
under snaps isolation this anomaly can
occur right and the end result is from
from a higher level perspective what we
how we understand what the data should
look like is wrong and that it's not
equivalent to executing them in serial
water yes
no sterilizable means that again this
was covered in interruption class
sterilizable means that you generate a
the the final state of the database is
equivalent to any serial ordering of
transactions all right so this case here
I had t1 go first of all by t2
but I could reverse that t2 Google first
of all by t1 and both will consider
correct yes questions this anomaly can
also occur in recommitted yes but not I
don't think repeatable reads has this
issue yeah so it's this picture here
right so under the like the like the in
like the textbook definition of
isolation levels and the ANSI standard
least set I think still now like you
sort of have this one path up to
serialize a read uncommitted committed
repeat over read to sterilizable but
snapshot isolation is this other thing
here with its right skew anomaly cannot
occur for this and then this is repeater
reads are susceptible to I mean dirty
reads I forget yes
and therefore that can't happen in this
you can't read you can have a dirty read
and snaps isolation because you only see
things that committed when you know it
you only see that versions of tuples
that were created by transactions that
committed before you start you can't
have a dirty read but it's again the
main point of this I would just showing
this is it like snaps an isolation is
you don't get it by default with MVCC
right so like Postgres uses MCC but
default you get I think read committed
I think same thing for my sequel but
like if you sort of follow the strict
definition of how we're gonna do
currency toll and determine versions
all right identify what versions are
visible to us when our transaction is
run as far as I know you end up with
snaps of isolation and then our next
class on on Monday we'll see a bunch of
extra stuff you can do in the database
system to make this actually be
serializable sometime
alright so the paper had you guys read
is a sort overview of the different
design decisions you have to make when
you build a modern MVCC system and so
despite having the name cartridge hole
you know that the words can hurt it's
all in the name of MVCC it's more than
just concurrent control right the idea
of multi verging actually permeates
through all we have throughout the
entire architecture of the system so
it's not this matter saying I'm gonna
pick two phase locking and then and
you're done there's all these other
things you have to be worried about and
and the the implications of these design
decisions can can be quite significant
based on what your application are based
on what your workload is that that
you're trying to support so the paper I
had you guys read actually came out of
this class so when I first first
teaching this class in 2016 we were like
you know I wanted to cover
MVCC or modern MVCC and actually we were
building our own database system here
that was gonna be multi version and a
bunch you know a bunch of questions came
up with like how should we do virgin
storage hashmi new garbage collection
and when you go read the literature and
go read the documentation for all these
other systems that are doing MVCC they
just usually just say this is what we do
they don't justify why they would do
certain things and all these different
systems were doing something you know
slightly different so the idea of this
paper was to go through and actually
understand all the different trade-offs
for these different design stations and
then eventually then do a bake-off and
then whatever turned out to be the best
one that's we wanted to put in our
system peloton so the original name of
the paper that I had you guys read was
actually this is the best paper ever on
in-memory multiverse kernel and so
papers are sort of like your children
you're not just to pick your favorites
this one is actually one of my favorite
ones I had a lot of fun writing it and I
and I think the results are very
interesting so this we literally submit
the paper with this title the reviews
were very positive but the very first
thing they said was removed this the
best paper ever right now
they were quite adamant about that so
I'm like alright well you know I
understand the point like it we we
didn't want to be sort of flip or you
know subjective in in our in our paper
you know I still think it's the best
paper but you know would always be I
don't know
so then we changed the title to if you
only read one empirical valuation paper
on a memo diversion atoll make it this
one exclamation point that one they
didn't like they came back again they
said this is subjective this is your
opinion you have to make the title be
more scientific or you know a more you
know more precise and so the third name
the paper was we think you're really
enjoying this and it's true because it's
true I did I did think they would enjoy
it that's that's a factual statement so
at this point the paper got accepted but
they were starting to get pissed off and
they were like if you don't change the
title we're gonna flat out reject it and
so I didn't have tenure I still don't
but like I didn't have tenure the
students needed the paper to graduate
and and you know get jobs so we
capitulated and so that's why that the
title the paper is is what you guys read
it was why we had to make it real dry
and boring I'm I feel like I could have
fought bit more and gotten this one but
I was I caved and it is what it is okay
all right forget the four design stages
we're gonna discuss are concurrent
retold version storage garbage
collection and index management so let's
go to each of these one by one so for a
concurrency troll protocol there's in
it's all the same methods you guys I
read about last class or we talked about
in the last lecture right there there is
not anything special that you do
differently because you're using a multi
version system right but these are just
adaptations on how you do use those
classic protocols to make them work in a
multi version system and in particular
we're gonna discuss is how do you
actually want to do this in a in memory
database system right again remember the
for the Discordian system we would
separate the locks and the locking
information from the actual tuples
themselves the extra stores because we
wanted to keep the lock information in
memory so that if the two boots get
swapped out the disk right we can still
know who holds locks on what but now
everything is in memory so we don't want
separate data structure so we're gonna
try to be clever and actually store in
the tuples all the information we need
about what's going on in Akko new
protocol in addition to all in
we need to know about the versioning of
our tuples so we want to store anything
separate so time skateboarding OCC and
and 2pl so we're going to discuss the
first and the last one
OCC as I said is just a variant of time
stamp ordering where you just put
everything in in all your rights end up
going into this private workspace that's
not immediately visible
whereas in time stamp ordering it will
be immediately visible but we use some
extra metadata to keep to make sure that
people don't read things they shouldn't
be reading okay they also think to the
but I apologize about the paper from
last class we wrote that before we wrote
this one and in that paper about the
thousand cores we described MVCC as sort
of being a single commercial protocol
that was using time stamp boarding
because that's what it was defined in
the the original MIT dissertation but in
actuality again under MVCC you can use
all these different approaches so time
stamp ordering the mvto is what we used
in the thousand core paper but you can
still use GPL all right so the first
thing we need to scoffs is water
reaction how we're actually going to
maintain information about what we're
storing in our and our tuples so the
every tuple is gonna have a header where
you store again additional metadata for
simplicity assume it's a it's a row
store but if it's a column store you
just have a separate column with this
metadata so the way that is there's some
offset into the fixed length data pool
and the first couple number of bytes
will be this metadata so the first thing
we're gonna do is gonna have a unique
transaction and identifier right this is
just what is that what is the ID of the
transaction that either created this
version or is currently operating on a
host the lock on it then we'll have to
begin and time stamps and these can be
used to determine the lifetime of the
visibility of this particular version
and these timestamps could be logical
counters like a single counter or they
could be a really high precision like
hardware clock like in nanoseconds
typically people use people people use a
counter because it needs to sort of be
followed the same under same domain as
transaction IDs then we're also now
going to have a pointer to either the
next
or previous version in the version chain
for our tuples right so again when we do
a lookup to find a tuple like say
through an index we're gonna land at the
head of this version chain versions of
linked lists that we can then traverse
to either go back or forward in time to
find the right version of the tuple
that's visible to us so we need to
maintain a 64-bit pointer in our header
to say here you know here's the next
tube or heard the previous two ball and
it was the next thing she look at in the
Virgin chain and then some other
constraint protocols might have some
additional metadata here followed by
like the actual tuple tuple datum so the
first thing I'd point out is that these
are all going to be 64-bit integers
right so eight bytes so in this example
here right if you just ignore the
additional metadata
I have 460 64-bit 64-bit values or
energies I'm storing here so I four
eight byte dice so that's 32 bytes I'm
storing for every single tuple it
doesn't seem like a lot but if I have a
lot of tuples this can start to add up
if I have a billion tuples then this
these four fields are gonna store
underneath 32 gigabytes before there's
one day to post that's a lot but it's
unavoidable right because it's just this
trade-off between compute and storage
it's sort of classic and computer
science already hit a lot this semester
so I could be a bit smarter and maybe
store these beginning and timestamps on
a block level right so I have a batch of
tuples can have begin end timestamps but
now that means that when I start doing
lookups
I'm spending more CPU power to go find
the actual version and I'm looking for
so for for this reason pretty much
everyone always stores this for every
single tuple and that that's good enough
because it gives you that the the fine
granularity you need to you know achieve
high concurrency or high parallelism
alright sorry mmm that was weird oh all
right sorry
we'll cut this out sorry this is gonna
take forever
sorry alright yup you have great paper
two bowls
okay Tyson for him alright so the first
thing we're point out it said we're
gonna store this in our table the first
thing to point out is that I have this
sort of column here of like the version
IDs this is just for illustration
illustration purposes we're not actually
going to store this in our real system
right because we use the begin and end
time stamp to figure out what the actual
version this is just for us to
understand this visually so the no there
we go alright yeah there's that
right so the transaction ID again it's
gonna be a 64-bit integer and we're to
use that to keep track of
does anybody hold the lock on this tuple
right so at the very beginning it's
going to be 0 then we have our beginning
and time stamps so this again this is
going to termina bility of our of each
version so in this case here there were
some transaction that created this
version at time stamp 1 and because this
is the the this is the latest version of
our tuple we set the end time stamp to
infinity right because it's visible to
anybody that comes after time stamp 1
all right and then for FP 2 oh we need
to also include the read time stamp
right and this is me a time stamp is
gonna keep track of the last transaction
that read this version and because we
have to use this to figure out if we try
to write a new version for this tuple if
the re time stamp is greater than our
time stamp that we our write time stamp
then we know that somebody in the future
read is to boil and what have missed our
newer version so therefore we have to
abort so this is this is a good example
of another overarching theme if we have
throughout the entire semester is that
we want to minimize the amount of global
data structures we have to coordinate
between our different transactions so by
recording the V time stamp with in the
tuple itself I don't have to do a lookup
at some you know what would that
occurred and say you know what
transaction capacity I've read this
tuple I look at the tuple and I merely
know exactly the you know what happened
alright so now we have a transaction
comes along and say it's out its given
time stamp 10 and let's do a read on a a
followed by a right on beam
so the reeds pretty easy right you go
check to see whether the the the
transaction ID is zero meaning you know
nobody is actually writing to this
transaction or to this tuple and then
you check to see whether the visibility
is is within the range that of your your
time stamp so our time stamp is 10 10 is
between 1 and affinity so we know that
this version is invisible to us so then
all we need to do now is a compare and
swap on the re time stamp to update it
with our time stamp right andthe compare
and swap fails who cares because that
just means that somebody you know either
in the after that somebody in the future
or in the past I've also read this so we
just check it again and and try to
update it right if it's less than
awesome so it's ok if this we try to
read it and say someone comes along with
time stamp 11 and we do compare-and-swap
and it fails and we come back and time
stamp 10 is less than 11 that's fine we
don't have to update it like who cares
of another thread read this read the
same thing we read all right so now
we're gonna do the right so for the
right we're gonna do it right on B so
again the first thing we need to do is
do a compare and swap in the transaction
ID so that we can take the lock on it so
that we can prevent anybody from chronic
create the new version while we are so
we do a compare and swap set it to our
time stamp
now that simplicity means that we hold
the lock on this tuple and then we can
go ahead and create a new version and
implicitly this also means we hold a
lock on it as well because assume
there's a pointer from this to this and
no one can get to B 2 without going
through b1 but I hold the lock on b1 so
no one can follow along so I can do
whatever update I need here and then now
I just flip this end time stamp to be 10
and that sets the visibility of this
transaction right and when I'm done I
really do a compare and swap well this
doesn't need me a compare and swap but
this one does I should not need to do
you just set it to 0 and you're done and
now this new version is installed if
anybody comes along with the time stamp
say greater than 10 they would be able
to feet you know see this version is
that clear yes
with what ARB okay yes now so the read
time stamp is always going forward in
time so that's time since you're back
here the reach time stamp is one say I
do a compare and swap right compare swap
says you have to read the value first
then you do compare and swap and say I
think the value should be one if it's
one set it to ten
so if I do that and it fails because
fifteen came along then I would loop
back around see that now the value is
fifteen right then that's 15 is greater
than ten so I don't try to update it if
it was eight ten is greater than eight
so yes the new value of the entire row
back in I guess I'm just kind of
confused it's like toilet you actually
go through this link imagine a case
where like if you're like reading
through these memory locations and then
somehow some other thread comes along
and like jumps around you in exactly the
right order so you read the right thing
okay so these question is how am I
actually doing this atomically right and
it really starts off with this
transaction ID so if I do compare and
swap on this I said to my transaction ID
then nobody else can come along and do
the right the same time I do right I
hold the lock and the whole thing so I
don't this is 64-bit so I just you
compare and swap on 64 bits the I think
what you were proposing is sort of
taking a lock on the entire piece of
memory for this tuple and for that one
you would happen and that's essentially
what this is doing right you can't do a
compare and swap more than 128 bits on
Intel so this is thing is way larger
that so you can't do a Tomic stuff at
that granularity so by setting this now
this will prevent anybody else when
writing a new version you know before
I'm done so now you say well what if
some comes along
and tried to read this well the first
thing the reader would do is see that
this thing is not zero and back away
because it's it's this thing is under no
it's being written to now and I don't
know what the end time stands gonna be
yet so I don't know whether I should be
reading this version or the next version
he's about to create so now you say all
right well what if the reader comes
along see zero right and then starts
doing the read then this thing does ten
and while the other guys still reading
what happens well who cares right
because this version this person is not
going away
that reader who got him before I I did
they can still read this right and we're
fine because this is not gonna corrupt
that data or do anything weird
it could it'll miss potentially this new
version but then meets my next question
how do we actually know this how I'm
actually keeping track of this thing
actually committed right because all I
should was that when I update the
virgin's I flipped the transaction ID to
zero that means I released the lock but
now how do I know whether I should if
this transaction is actually going to
commit and therefore I should actually
read this version right so what's
missing here is an auxilary data
structure that basically has to keep
track of the status of transactions so
that when I go do a read and I say I
read in this case here I would well you
keep track of it I read this version
here you need a way to know later on oh
the transaction that created that
version did they actually commit right
because you the begin timestamp was the
same transaction ID that I set up here
so I'd know that transaction at
timestamp 10 creating this version when
I go to commit I need to know whether
they committed as well because if they
don't they haven't committed and I read
something I shouldn't have read I need
abort so what's missing here and what
we'll see in hackathon on Monday next
week for Microsoft in their version of
MVCC is that there's a separate data
structure that you have on the side
think of a giant hash table we just keep
track of what are they all what are the
different transactions that are running
and whether they've committed or not
this question is if I did this if I just
left this as ten then wouldn't that
somebody like so but for that basically
holding the lock on this version forever
until I commit by releasing it now
anybody come along and read stuff
because you're assuming transactions
aren't going to conflict or are not
going to abort and therefore you won't
you want to use speculative reads yes so
this question is why not embed another
commit ID so that's what Microsoft's
gonna do it's two ways to do that so one
you just have another commit IDE but
that's another 64-bit field and now
you're adding a way more space what
Microsoft is gonna do we'll see you next
class is that they'll piggyback off of
the I think I think the end times damn
though actually use one bit in the
timestamp to say this transaction
actually has committed or not and that's
how they that's how they avoid you
should have to go back and update things
but that avoids having a separate column
all right so I wanna jump ahead to two
phase locking there's still a lot to
cover so with MP 2 PL we get rid of
three timestamp but now we're gonna add
this recount and the recount essentially
is gonna act as a the shared lock on on
the tuple right so my transaction comes
along and it wants to read a I'll do a
compare and swap on these two fields at
the same time alright so these are both
gonna be 64-bit fields x86 allows you to
do 128-bit compare and swap so I'll
check to see that transaction ID is 0
and then I'll and I'll also atomically
update this to be 1 so the way you do
that is you set this also to be 0 and
then you increment this by 1 as the
result right so if I do that then that
means I have a shared lock on on this on
this tuple right and I can read it along
with other reader other readers running
at the same time but now when I do the
right same thing I'll do an atomic 120
bit compare and swap to
set the transaction ID and the recount
to one I actually don't think you need
to set the recount but you definitely
ought to set the transaction ID so now I
have the exclusive lock on this tuple I
can go ahead and create a new version I
update the end timestamp with my
timestamp and then a new
compare-and-swap to revert it back to
zero and that unlocks it yes I think the
starting what are you saying sorry no no
no no today's lock acquire locks as
needed you acquire them in the growing
phase but it doesn't necessarily mean
you're gonna acquire them exactly when
the transaction starts how the last
writer win the first writer wins it's
always first writer wins yeah
how would it win this guy got to this he
wrote to it anybody else that would come
along in this case here like so if
another transaction comes along and say
they have time-stamped five well they
would see that the this versions
visibility is one to ten five is in
between one to ten so that it knows that
there's some other some other version
that came after timestamp ten that
physically got wrote before I did
although logically logically it's in the
future but in actuality it's in the past
in physical time so I might intersect
with this this range therefore there's
another writer before it got here before
I did and I have to abort first writer
wins these timestamps tell us everything
okay so in the paper ahead you guys read
then when we wrote it originally the
transaction ID in the recount we're
actually set to be 32-bit integers right
because at the time when we wrote it
I don't list x86 we were looking at
didn't support 128-bit compare-and-swap
so we put these two together right if
you think about it there's probably not
going to be two to the 32 minus one
threads reading the same to board the
exact same time so setting this to be 32
bits is is kind of an overkill but we
still would want this thing to be you
know a large as possible so we have to
make this thing be you know at least 32
bits maybe 48 but even then although
it's a large number on if your system is
running for a long time you can burn
through these transaction IDs pretty
quickly
all right and what's gonna happen if you
if if you get to the end of transaction
IDs you wrap around right and then you
start to have problems all right so
let's say that we have a simple table
with one tuple and we have this this
this one version here so we have some
transaction ID that's gonna get
transactions of insurance actually be
two - 31 - 1 so it does it right on a
break and do all you know set the
transaction ID do all the lock stuff
that we just talked about and then it
creates a new version here right and
that sets the the the range now to be
232 to the 31 minus 1 except it's the 0
but now another transaction comes along
and now it has time stamp 1 because it
wrapped around and now I create a new
version but now the the ranges that are
all messed up because this is between 1
and infinity and physically that's in
the future but based on these timestamps
it's illogically in the past so now
someone could come along try to find the
wants to look for this version and it
could end up you know going nowhere
right because this thing is in a
disjoint range right so this is
problematic and so if you have a 32-bit
integer for your transaction ID which
Postgres does you can wrap you get
through this pretty quickly even if it's
a 64-bit integer at some point you'll
run out and you need to wrap around and
handle that so there's a couple
different ways to do
I like describing what Postgres does
because it's so simple and easy to
understand and some way that makes it
sort of elegant so what they're gonna do
is that they're gonna add a additional
bit in the header of every single tubule
right usually four tuple headers they
always Pat it out as symmetric bit space
so like if in the future if you decide
oh we need to keep track of some
additional information about each tuple
we just add an extra bit in there we
have space for it so they're gonna add
extra bit that says that a particular
version or Pickler tuple is instead of
frozen and any any version that's
considered frozen means that it's always
gonna be deemed as in the past no matter
what transaction ID you have timestamp
you compare it with so even in this this
case here even though this one could
have a timestamp that's greater your two
- 31 - 1 is greater than 1 if I set the
frozen bit then then this will always be
deemed older than this so the way they
do this is that they if they the system
recognizes that you're gonna about the
wrap-around they'll run the vacuum their
garbage collector scan through and find
old versions and set this bit flag so
there's a lot of there's not a lot of
there's a couple posts on the internet
you go look around for like Postgres
trent transaction rep transaction ID
wrap around problem there's a bunch of
cases where people will actually turn
off the garbage collector on Postgres
during the day because it adds some
overhead so you trying to get the system
running as fast fast as possible during
the day because that's when you have
most your customers using your website
and then all sudden you start hitting
this wrap around problem and the system
freaks out because it has to stop
holding you know accepting new
connections inspecting new transactions
because it doesn't it has to wrap around
but the vacuum you can't run because
you've turned it off and then you
basically have to run the vacuum
manually and that that can do a you know
full compaction or full vacuum pass and
that can take hours and hours or even
days right so the post goes way it is
pretty pretty simple like the vac and
you'll do what you wanted to do and
unless you turn it off so this clear
okay
so when you read the academic literature
about concurrency show
or transactional database systems the
emphasis really is always on these
concurrent protocols right it is two
phase locking better than OCC II or
timestamp ordering but what we actually
found out in his paper was that it's
actually the other things that actually
matter a lot more in in particular what
mattered a lot was the the Virgen stores
mechanism or the architecture the
virtual storage component of the system
so again as he said that we have for
every single physical version we're
going to search every single logical
object will have multiple physical
versions so there's different ways we're
also actually store these versions but
at a high level they're gonna be
organized as a latch free link less
single direction and the head of the
link link list is always going to be
what the indexes point to or sort of
what if I'm doing a look-up on a tuple
I'm always gonna land at the head and
then that can you traverse along the
version chain to try and try to find the
right the right version that's visible
to me so the again the index always
point to the head but the head could
either be the oldest to the newest
depending on what what what approach are
using so the the different schemes will
talk about here will determine where
we're gonna actually store and what Rex
you're going to store for each version
that we create all right sometimes will
store Delta sometimes we'll store the
actual entire tuple so the three
approaches are append only time travel
storage and deathless storage and the
spoiler would be that that the Delta
storage is the best way to go but
there's still a lot of systems like
Postgres in particular that do append
only so what's gonna happen here because
we're in an in-memory system again we
want to avoid having global data
structures so we want to avoid having to
allocate space for new versions in some
you know in a global space of global
memory chunk so instead what we'll do is
as threads create new versions they'll
create the versions inside of like
thread local storage or memory that's
allocated for just that thread you know
that means the Virgin chain could
traverse the storage across multiple
threads but that's okay right because
everything is always always just in
memory so the other thing we also need
to think about too as we describe these
different approaches is you know not
just how fast they are but also how much
storage space they're gonna require to
store these versions
and what's the engineering effort to
actually implement it because some are
obviously easier than others and we need
to think about it's in both in terms of
what is the overhead of finding the
right version that we need for our query
but also the overhead of actually
cleaning up older versions over time as
they accumulate like in the garbage
collector all right so go to each is one
by one so append-only storage the idea
is that we have a single table like a
single physical space where we're
storing ro tuples and any time a
transaction updates a tuple what does
create a new physical tuple in the in
that same tablespace right so say our
transactions can update a 1 right we
just make a copy of a1 append into some
new space or a free slot in the table
and then we just update now the pointer
to our version chain to say you know
here's the new version right so it's
pretty simple to do and this is what how
Postgres originally designed it in the
the 1980s think interbase did the same
thing
the downside obviously is that you know
I'm making a lot of copies right
you know I'm copying the entire tuple
even though it may only update a single
field so another important thing that
was a point out too is the order in
which were traversing the virgin chain
for our tuples so in this example here
I'm going going oldest to newest so I
started off like this I have a 0 a 1 and
then a 0 was the head of the chain and
it pointed at a 1 and then when I
created a 2 a 1 now pointed at that but
I would still have my indexes still
point a 0 so they want to find a 2 I
have to jump to a 0 check that there's
begin n time stands to see whether it's
visible to me if not then I jump to a 1
do the same thing and they jump to a 2
so that may not be the best approach
depending on your application right so
again that was oldest to newest you
always have traversed the the chain to
find the newest version you could also
go newest to oldest where the head of
the version chain is always the latest
version that just got created so you
know you don't need to update any
previous versions you just add your new
version and then have its pointer point
to the old version the head of the
version chain
what's one obvious problem with that so
it's faster doing lookups obviously
right because you it's it's you want the
newest version I'll and the head of her
G chain and I'm done yes no yes I'll
bear the indexes correct yes so again
we'll talk if you more slides but like
all the indexes are pointing to the head
of virgin Jane if for every single
update the head of version change
changes because its newest to oldest
then I have to update all the indexes
now to point to the new virgin Jane
right and actually that's what purpose
does and compared to my Siegel that's
problematic so again I'm not saying one
is better than another in most cases
newest to oldest poly is the better way
to go because most of the times most
transactions most queries want the
newest version if you care about doing
depending on how you do garbage
collection or depending how you do like
look if you have queries that look at
old data this actually made me maybe
better yes so that so it's a way to
avoid this overhead having to update
every single index every single time by
lately doing no because that could give
you false negatives and then the other
picture is what if you have an
indirection layer we'll see in a second
that will avoid that problem but you
have to maintain that that's additional
you know again additional storage
overhead it to have that indirection
okay again so again the in practice I
think this is the better way to go if
you're doing a pen only but this does
have have some benefits that you don't
have to update the indexes all right so
the other that the next approach is to
do time travel storage and the idea here
is that as we create new versions
instead of appending the new versions
into our main tablespace we will have
this other table that looks exactly the
same as the first one but it has the
same scheme on the same allocation of
columns
and rows but that's we're going to put
put virgins as we create them so in this
case here we're doing newest to oldest
so a2 is in the main table space and it
has a pointer to a one in the in time
travel space so now if I'm going to
update this guy I first gonna copy it
into the time travel space have the
pointer point back to a1 and now to
overwrite the master version with the
new version that I wanted to create I am
and again first writer wins I don't
worry about two transactions trying to
update this master version the same time
I do the right here and then anybody
tries to update the same thing will have
to get aborted because they'll conflict
with me alright so then now if I rights
and then update the version pointer to
now point to a2 so this is actually
which what Hana does and this is
actually what sequel server does well so
we'll see sequel server how they do
login with NPC see in a few weeks and I
think they do it this way because it's a
byproduct of the system was not
originally designed to be multi
versioned and so by adding this it
requires the least amount of changes in
the overall architecture the other
engine thing you can do to also is that
you could have the tank that the the
main table actually be a different use a
different storage model than the time
travel table right because you're doing
a lot of updates into this you could
have this be like a roast or or a delta
store roast or and then the time travel
tape because these are like older
versions you can maybe over time convert
them to a column store and that way if
you need to read old data right you can
you can access it through a columnar
layout which is faster all right and
again so the last one is gonna be what I
think it's the better approach is to do
Delta storage and the idea here is that
instead of having to copy the original
version every single time and then make
our change to it we only need to record
what was the change we made and
destroyed that information right so if
I'm gonna update a one and set a copy in
it
I'll just have a Delta record in some
some space in memory that says here's
the change that I made so here's here's
the old value for
for this for this table and update that
and now the pointer points to that sit
again for this Delta information I'm
gonna maintain the same begin and
time-stamped just as I would before and
a regular tuple but the only thing I'm
starting is this Delta information think
of like a DIF and you get that so now if
I want to do a lookup and say find an
older version I just follow that the
Virgin chain and replay all the log
entries or the Delta records to put me
back into the state that I should have
been for that version so again if I have
a thousand say or sailor got a thousand
columns in my table and I only update
one of them then instead of having a
copy all thousand columns every single
time I can just store the the one
attributed one column that got changed
so this is what Oracle does is what my
Siegel does I think this this is and is
what we now do in our system this this
is the better approach right these again
computationally it's more expensive
because I got to essentially replay the
the log or the deltas to put me back in
the correct state I should be for my
tuple when I want to do a lookup most of
the time though you only need to read
the latest version and that's just you
know all the data is just there you're
done but you ended up also storing less
space which also can improve your cash
cash locality or have less pressure on
the cache keep much data in memory as
possible so there's a big benefit to
that yes the question is what if a lot
of my transaction are doing scans and
some of them are updating why would it
be very slow so again like so in a real
database system most of the time the the
you're not updating every single tuple
so say I'm doing special scan across the
entire table most of the time I'm just
gonna rip through the main tablespace
and I don't have to follow the Virgin
chain in the event I have to follow the
Virgin yes on the pay a little you know
computational penalty to now follow this
pointer and replay the deltas to put me
back to the correct state most the time
I don't do that
right I would say also two of the I
think depending on any architect the
system but like you went to do an update
anyway you're already started generating
this Delta and actually this is what
you're gonna log out the disk anyway so
you might as well just just record that
you know in memory as a Delta record so
you not to do any extra work to make the
copy when you you know when you create a
version so there's this trade-off
absolutely right that like resources
right which ones you want a favor I
think the science turns out that that
this approach actually it'll make the
rice go faster and the pen or you're
paying for reads is not is not
significant then it's not worth it to
get the right benefit plus you have less
storage space garbage collection is also
easier in this world too because I only
need to go through this thing clean this
up I never touched the main table
because that's always the latest version
yes so it makes a good point
so if say I have a thousand tuples and I
have a bunch of Delta's that each update
a separ attribute do I need to go back
in time super far to find the correct
version so way you handle that is
garbage collection you try to you trick
down the or compact even the the Delta
the Virgin Jane as quickly as possible
we'll cover that next week yeah yes
question is if you're training multiple
adroit skeet sure that it's one Delta
yes so I'm there's only one actually we
would value but yes for every single
attribute I modify it will be within one
one does a record yes so so this could
be uncommitted right and this also could
be written in the future that's not that
I haven't but I shouldn't see cuz it's
not my snapshot so therefore I have to
go back a time if I'm what is actually
visible to me all right cool
so um so one additional problem though
if you're doing a pen only and this is
why I think the Delta story is better is
that if now you have if you have string
values that are stored in the verbal ink
data pool every single time I create a
new version I I have to make a copy of
this tuple or that sort of the the very
length data so that my next my next
version can have its own pointer because
if I start if I start doing garbage
collection and I clean up a one cuz a
tuna is now the latest version if this
thing is pointing to this and I go clean
that up then now my pointer points to
nothing and that's bad right so that
sucks right so that means for every
single time even if I don't update this
I don't take this string at all I'm
still making a copy of all the string
values so one way to handle this
obviously is just add a reference
counter in the verbal link data so that
when I know that how many pointers how
many versions actually pointing to this
so if I go clean up this this the first
version and I decrement the counter and
still greater than zero that I know that
someone out there is pointing to this
this string my very unlike data pool and
I shouldn't go ahead and clean it up the
downside though is and this is actually
what we tried in in our old peloton
system the downside is that because now
I keep track of the if I had multiple
versions pointing to this
I actually don't know where they are so
if I ever need to move this this piece
of data around in memory like I started
compacting my my favor length data pool
then I have to do a sequential scan and
try to find the one version of the tuple
or the book version of the two are
actually pointing to this so this
actually turns out to be a bad idea it's
something we abandoned pretty quickly
this is a synergy sort of what
dictionary compression does as well
because instead of storing the pointer
to something in the very like data pool
I would have a dictionary code that I
could then do another look up and find
find what the actual value was but at
least in that case you know if you're
compressing the data then it's it's it's
usually cold data and therefore you're
not gonna you have to clean things out
very often
yes No so again member last class I
talked about how there's the fixed
length data pool and the verbally dated
pools so all our tuples
alright I'm gonna try to reside in the
fix link okay I have to reside the fixed
length data pools that's like the
location of them but because we want all
the size of every single tuple to be
fixed length anything it could be
variable length has to be stored in a
separate data pool so inside my my fixed
length data instead actually storing the
string I store a pointer to the string
right and that's another piece of memory
that's managed separately and the point
I'm trying to make here is that one on
one hand we could just duplicate the
string over and over again every sperm
is single note version because each of
these guys need to have a unique pointer
but that's obviously gonna be wasteful
because if I don't update the string
that I'm copying for no reason and if my
string is huge then that's gonna get
expensive very quickly so you could try
to share pointers by adding a reference
counter into that to the reference to
the fare blank data pool for every
single thing you're storing but now the
problem is if I ever try to move this
data around I don't know what else is
pointing to it and I could have you know
broken pointers yes
say especially couldn't use a logic
warrant that's what dictionary
compression essentially does we'll cover
that in like a few weeks it's hard for
me to balance like like when you guys
need to know now which what's going to
come in the future
so the dictionary confession you solve
this okay probably need to get two
carbons motion so the idea of carbon
suction again it's just like GCE under
under for the JVM we need to find
physical versions that are reclaimed
bold and physical version is one where
we know there's no active transactions
running that can see that version right
because it's in the past and and all new
time stain all new transactions have a
time Sam in the future and they can't
get to it or the version was created by
transaction that later got aborted and
we know and no one's gonna read it we
gotta go ahead and clean it up so the
much different design stages we need be
mindful of how to find the expired
versions what to do how to determine
whether it's safe to reclaim a piece of
memory and where to actually look for
them so we're gonna focus on this how
how to look for them we'll cover this a
little bit but we'll do next Wednesday
Wednesday next Wednesday next week we'll
spend the entire lecture discussing on
how we actually do garbage collection in
MVCC and go to more details about this
right so the two ways to do this is at
the tuple level or the transaction level
so the tuple level the idea is that
there's not going to be any central
location that says here's all the
versions of the tuples that we can go
clean up the idea is instead we're gonna
have threads run and do scans and when
they come across data or come across
versions that are we claimed a little
they go ahead and we clean them up we
can either do this with separate threads
or cooperative threads as a running
queries and then transaction level the
idea is that each transaction is gonna
keep track of every single version that
they that they invalidate and therefore
could be reclaimed and then when they go
to commit they hand off is this set of
pointers to this garbage bucket says hey
by the way here are some things I
invalidated you should go ahead and
clean them up and that's a voice having
to do that the sequential scan so let's
go through tuple level first
so with back I'm vacuuming again the
idea is that there's separate threads
that are gonna run that are going to do
special scans and try to find old
versions so when the vacuum starts
we have to look and say well what are
the actual transactions what are their
time stamps and then now when we scan
we're gonna we're going to compare the
beginning and time stance for all the
versions that we see and see whether
that the range is specified them do not
intersect with any active transaction so
in this case here we have transactions
with time stamp 12 times at 25 so we
know that for the range 1 to 9 these two
transactions can't see that so therefore
no one can see this and therefore it's
safe for us to go ahead and reclaim this
memory right so this can be expensive to
do likes winchell scans across the
entire system especially if you want
this thing to run all the time so a
simple trick is just to keep track of a
bitmap that says here's all the blocks
that got modified logically since the
last time I ran so therefore when I just
need to scan through that and I can skip
anything that wasn't modified so I mean
by logically is that depending on what
I'm doing oldest newest renews to oldest
I may update say I have two versions in
two separate blocks and it's almost the
newest and I add a new version that's in
the second block but now I could reclaim
that old version that's in the first
block so I need to know logically that
back going back in the version change
here's the block that has the thing I
should examine all right whereas newest
to oldest you would know I add my new
version I know but I need to point to as
the previous head so I know where that
thing is located and I can update that
bit easily so cooperative cleaning the
idea is that we're not gonna have any
separate threads potentially if we're
back on the beckoning it's just now as
our transactions or query start running
if they come across all versions we go
ahead and clean them up alright so say
this guy runs he's gonna do a lookup and
the index to find key a and we're gonna
get to the head of the virgin chain so
then now as I'm scanning along to find
the right version that I want I check
the time stamp which I'm doing anyway to
see whether it's visible to me but I
also know what is the sort of the
high-water mark for the or the low-water
mark for the oldest time stamp of any
active transaction and if I know
that thing is not visible this tuple is
not visible to that oldest transaction I
can go ahead and Garba collect it right
there and I keep scanning along and can
print out anything and I also then have
to update the index now point to the my
new version chain so the benefit of this
approach is that you don't have to
maintain these separate background
threads but now your queries could
potentially run slower because they may
come across a long version chain and you
had to clean things up before you can
actually finish running your action your
query what's another problem with the
cooperative cleaning yes correct
well one it says that there only were
stores near us but even then there could
be another problem
bingo yes so let's say I create a new
version and then no one ever goes back
and reads that logical tuple again but
now I had that over and sitting around
that no one's ever gonna get so
Microsoft calls these dusty corners and
basically the way to handle that is you
peer out if he also had stuff to run the
background thread just go find things
that could be still sitting around yes
yes overstatement is is there a notion
of cleanliness in our system it could
quantify that so the example I was
saying before like the the garbage
suction takes time right so Microsoft
roughly estimates in their paper that
garbage suction adds but a fifteen
fifteen percent overhead if during the
day I want Mitra's actually run fast as
possible I could maybe potentially
disable garbage collection the system
becomes more dirty and then when I want
you know maybe in the day then I run the
garbage cutting and burning more cycles
but I have spare ones that you know I
can use to clean things up it's usually
the storage overhead people care about
the you run out of space pretty quickly
if you have a lot of virgin in your
turning through them I always say that
like the the the notion of cleanliness
would be something better to have to be
human to find like I usually use fewer
threads from garbage question because I
want queries run faster but then there's
sort of a push back
to say while I'm running out of space
especially if I ran memory so I want to
be more aggressive and cleaning things
up so with the overhead like that 15
percent is that like what about yeah
because think about it like my careers
are running slower now because this guy
could have just said well I don't care
that these versions aren't or reclaim a
little let me just go get what I want
but it's implemented such that you clean
things up as you find them okay the the
other one is transaction level again
we'll discuss this more on on Wednesday
next week again the idea is that my
transaction runs I'm creating the
versions because I think the tuples so I
know what was the old version before and
so I just record to say hey by the way
here's this transaction or here's this
this version here's the beginning end
timestamp which I know because I had to
read it I if I commit go ahead and
reclaim this and then we put this in a
queue and then the garbage collector
will go at some kickoff and some some
background threads to clean this up over
time so for this one the garbage dungeon
is no longer on the critical path of
queries like it is in cooperative
cleaning so that means that our queries
gonna run faster it could end up
creating order verges more quickly than
before so we actually may need to use
multiple threads and make sure we clean
things up and in timely fashion so in
our current system today we do this but
we only can do a single thread garbage
collection and in some of the
experiments that man has done we can
burn through transactions pretty quickly
and we started running out of space and
the single thread actually can't keep up
so we'll discuss more about this next
week all right the last one is super
important is index management and we
sorted our talk to us a little bit but
basically how do we find the right
version and this depends on what the
version scheme is and how much work we
have to do to baby replay deltas or what
the ordering of the version chain is so
the primary key index is always going to
point to the head of the virgin chain
doesn't matter whether it's oldest to
newest or newest oldest or time travel
or Delta storage it's always the head
right and so that just means that
depending on what what you know whatever
we do we
they end up on exactly the right away
the first version that we want is the
head or may have to traverse the whole
thing so now if any transaction tries to
update and the attribute in the tuple
that's in the primary key rather than
trying to get clever and trying to
maintain different versions or or you
know different version chains for the
same logical entry in the index we're
just gonna treat this followed by as a
delete followed by an insert so even
though sort of conceptually the same
tuple its from the database systems
perspective it's now two discrete
logical tuples secondary index is more
complicated because as I sort of already
said before cuz depending whether
reporting the Virgin chain or not every
single time we create a new version that
could get really expensive and so
there's this great blog article that
came out actually exactly when we were
writing this paper from uber and it
talked about their journey from going
from Postgres to my sequel the true
story was they originally start with my
sequel they hired some guy that really
loved Postgres so he switched a Postgres
then they realized it was a mistake and
had switched back to my sequel so that
was super expensive they just took this
course they were saved a lot of money
right so they talked about a bunch of
different things about how Postgres does
things different than my sequel but one
of the main things they stress is how
they actually manage secondary indexes
in a multi version system because
Postgres would actually point to the
head of the virgin chain whereas my
sequel uses a logical pointer right so
that's the two difference so a logical
pointer would be some kind of identifier
that's fixed for the tuple that we can
then don't have to update in our
secondary indexes anytime the the
physical location of the version change
changes and you can either be a primary
key or some kind of synthetic tuple ID
like in case up so primary key is what
my sequel does but if you don't declare
a primary key my sequel they will
actually generate one for you called the
row ID or we just have some kind of
global counter says you know this tuple
one two three four five six and then
have an indirection layer to do look up
to get the physical address write the
physical point is what I said is always
pointed at the head of virgin chain so
let's look at this visually so so assume
we have a we're using a penalty store
oldest we don't look up on key a and the
primary index again the primary index
always points to the physical version no
problem just jump here and then scan
along to try to find the version we're
looking for the secondary index if it's
using a physical pointer right same
thing you land here and scan along if I
only have one index then it's no kind of
no big deal every single time this thing
changes because I just go update that
one index but if I have a lot of indexes
and they're all pointing to the physical
address any time I create a new version
and going newest to oldest I gotta have
to update all of these and this is what
Postgres does in the case of that the
example with uber their application had
a lot of secondary indexes and it got
really expensive to update the Virgin
chain every single time you created a
new version of a tuple so how can you
handle this well if you have an
indirection layer either by drawing the
primary key and then now just do a look
second lookup in the primary key index
that get the physical address now if I
update the the physical address I only
have to update this index and nothing
else so if your primary key is not that
big if it's like a 64-bit integer no big
deal but if it's a large text field
you're storing that as the value in your
and your index over and over again and
that can be expensive
the alternative again is to use a
synthetic tuple IDE but now you need
some kind of hash table or some one kind
of other lookup table to map that tuple
ID to a physical address so now anytime
the physical address changes you just
update this map and you know you don't
update the the symbols themselves just
like yeah
this question is for doing time travel
storage let's I think the next few
slides actually into a question like is
there a way to avoid having to to update
this is there anything what you're
asking right
well short of time will take it outwards
all right all right
so another new nasty thing this actually
wasn't in the paper that you read but
this is something we've encountered
actually building our own system is that
the NDB it'll support
duplicate keys that could exist in just
disjoint snapshots so the issues gonna
be is that in our indexes we're not
actually restore the version information
about our tuples right so for our B+
tree we don't want to store like here's
the key for Virgin one here's the keeper
version two because that would be super
expensive to maintain every single time
I update the version I've got to go
update the index and I have the storage
Nishal metadata so nobody most systems
don't actually do this if you're using
an index organized table like my sequel
in ODB where they store the tuples in
the leaf nodes of the index themself
then you kind of get this for free but
most systems don't don't do this so the
issues gonna be now I could have a the
same key could exist in different
different snapshots and therefore in my
index I need to store that same key
multiple times and have have but
pointers to different version chains so
the middle certain example so I say
every simple tuple with a have a single
version my first transaction comes along
and does a read on a we'll cover what
beginning end time stamps mean in a sec
next last next class but just assume
this is the time say it's given to one
to start him so this guy does a read on
a no big deal I follow the fellow might
my my pointer in my index and I land
here this guy does an update on a same
thing I follow the pointer I create the
new version and update the virgin chain
right so that's fine
but now I do a delete or net
and so what needs to happen well I'm
gonna mark this thing is deleted right
there's a little bit you can set in the
header as well and Tibet so that's fine
this guy who goes ahead and commits we
update our our timestamps to say that
you know here's here's when this thing
actually finished so this is setting the
begin time attends time is 25 they're
the same so this is saying this thing's
been deleted right so now this other
transaction comes along and he does an
insert on a a timestamp 30 so now I have
to create a new a new entry into my
index and now points to this other other
this new version chain here because I
can't give it to the old one because
this guy is still running a timestamp 10
so now when I do a read on a on the
index I've got to make sure that I get
this one and not this one even though
the value of the end of the key is
exactly the same and this is allowed to
happen because this guy committed so
he's gone so he starts after this guy
committed so he can he's allowed to do a
write on a conceptually it's not a
conflict because a is gone at this point
for this snapshot so I'm creating two
entries for a in the same index so
that's kind of weird right that's the
idea that the same key can exist
multiple time even though it's with your
unique index because it's the primary
key index but at different snapshots so
the ways one way to handle this you just
to remain you could you maintain you
could maintain some like that actually
how do we do this but how do we have two
entries for the same key I don't think
so
anyway but it has two different virgin
Jane's I think we store some extra
metadata in the key right to say that
this is unique
we don't okay yeah what do we do this is
the problem then they come back to
discuss this next time or maybe we don't
he knows we're broken
we had this different hit department
peloton in the old system and I think
the way we got around it was we would
store we were we were oldest to newest
so he could store the you'd have to
store I know I know how we did this so
the same key could produce even though
it's a unique index so unique index you
would think all right for a single key
has one value you would get back a list
of values and there's list of values we
different pointers different virgin
chains and then you have to traverse
every single virgin chain to find the
version that is actually visible to you
all right that's how we do this so it's
H they shouldn't be should be on top of
each other so if we're single key you
get back a list of pointers and put you
have to traverse each of those pointers
virgin chains the fly man tree that's
invisible to you yes even though this
guy got deleted why not just have this
thing pointed this thing and I can
traverse that because you need a
sentinel value right that says don't
like you need a way to say there's
nothing else comes after this virgin
chain you don't need to skin anything
more but I guess if this is not no you'd
still do that yeah that you might work -
I'd have to think about that though this
is what you actually maybe yeah he's
right you may actually either think with
a certain mayor should be need to need
to do this I think what we do is we give
you back multiple pointers we don't
wonder at all
but you're not you're not updating the
attributes you deleted the entry like me
to not pay pay act we didn't update the
key we didn't updated the tuple
somewhere and then you delete it it gets
marks let's delete it and then this guy
inserts
I thought we added we add a new add
another entry the details not important
you just understand that this issue can
occur right because the act this guy
wants do a redo make sure we get the
right version all right wherever time so
I'm gonna skip all this just come to the
evaluation well quickly so again this
was came out of his paper pal town is
dead because it had a bunch of other
problems which covered many times this
semester but the main experiments
basically just trying to bake off the
different Alliance Asians and then the
goal was whatever which one was the best
one we would keep that in peloton this
pissed me off because we did not do that
right like if you look at this graph
here I'll come back to this right this
is this is the main graph that don't
understand so this is scaling up the
number of threads running TPCC
and what we did we implemented based on
this previous table here for all these
different systems for u21 we we
configured the system to match what real
systems actually do and so Oracle neo DP
and hyper actually do it the best way
Postgres actually does it the worst way
and it's not just you know progress and
new DB are doing the same comrcio
protocol the verge of storage and
garbage collection and the index
management are different and the other
things actually matter more so I was
like fantastic Oracle new DB a hyper the
best let's do it the way it they did it
the student that was writing the paper
just left us with this and he went back
to Singapore and didn't actually finish
it so he ended up after all this work we
ended up in pals on was the worst way of
doing it not the best way the new system
is the best way right right so let's go
back to this real quick game this is in
the paper this is just showing you that
all these different systems are doing
all these things differently and the day
I think the main takeaway was the virgin
storage and indexes turned out to matter
the most and current retool not so much
okay so
not saying because of our paper I think
Postgres recognized that they had some
issues but there's a blog article came
out in 2018 that I think I think this
link is our paper but they basically
said that oh this the way we're doing a
pen Nolan kind of sucks cuz you have
this vacuum and it's a lot of overhead
and this guy is one of the main
developers opposed to us now so they
talked about how they're heard they're
gonna switch to dental storage in the
newer versions I don't know whether it's
coming out in version 13 or 14
they're called Z heaps and this is
something that they want to get you know
get to so alright we're well over time I
can briefly talk about project 1 before
you guys run just do it now and then
we'll release this on on on later today
ok target 1 the idea is here to get you
comfortable to the system so we're
asking you to welcome someone very
specific part and that's to do
sequential scans or parallel or current
sequential scans so the task itself is
not overly difficult we'll have sort of
different levels of complexity that you
that you can try to achieve it's mostly
teach you how to actually work in the
system and actually do profiling and
performance measurements in the system
okay so Matt covered this yesterday
here's what our system does Beauvoir
right so we're gonna bind you with a
bunch of super close benchmarks written
in G benchmark from Google but there's
one in particular called concurrent slot
iterator micro benchmark that this is
the bottleneck or the thing that you're
going to investigate basically when we
when you deal with a a scan in the
system you get this iterator and it has
a latch on it and so if you start
scaling up and adding more threads and
they all try to acquire the same latch
and this becomes a bottleneck so the
idea is that we will ship we will learn
how to use perf and call grind to
understand what are the main conflict
points in the system and then you try to
try to fix it so this is a single
project system but it expose you to you
know give you the full system you want
try out different workloads and threads
and access patterns beyond with just
what the the micro benchmark that we're
providing you okay so the way we're
gonna do grading is that your grade will
be bait your score will be based on how
much faster than you are then our
implementation so we're we will have a
basic implementation that tries to
improve this
all right we'll have the before and
after so your score read based on how
much faster you can get over what Matt
writes okay Matt talked about yesterday
- we either on clang formant Clank tidy
you make sure that your code is all
clean you you want to use Google
sanitizer stuff as much as you'll get
this automatically and make sure you
don't you don't have any memory leaks we
talked about this before it runs on
anything greater than 1804 for Ubuntu in
OS X you can also do a vm on docker this
is CMU I assume that I want to has
access to a machine the new development
locally if not email me and we can fix
this the main important thing though is
the way our new grading is not going to
be like your suite upgrade scope and
that'll do it like a smoke test to see
whether your thing actually compiles but
you're not going to identify this
bottleneck if you try to run it on a
machine with less than eight cores most
your laptops have you know four cores or
eight cores or less so what we're gonna
give you is 50 bucks on Amazon that you
can go get one of the c59 x-large it has
I think 32 cores or 36 cores and you can
do the your analysis on on that machine
because that that's how you be able to
identify the bottleneck okay so everyone
get 50 bucks if you go get this
on-demand one it says all at fifty an
hour if you get the spot instance which
means that like you're saying hey these
machines are idle I'll use them they
could take them away from you at any
time
but you pay a fraction of the price so I
encourage you to use this because if you
blow through your 50 bucks you I can't I
can't reimburse you okay
so I'll send an email out to everyone
who's enrolled in the class like here's
your code for Amazon you need to have a
credit card to sign up for Amazon for
ec2 or a AWS if that's a problem let me
know we'll figure out how to fake one or
something like that right like but
anyway all right so this we do the 16th
we'll post this later today and then
next class we'll discuss more and easy
implementation okay bye guys see you
wank it in the side park
what is this
[Music]
and my hood won't be to say I think it's
a prey