[Music]
you didn't buy your opening I heard ok
lets you ever some people christmas for
the holiday okay okay so alright what's
up for you guys
alright so this last week classes the
project for still do home 5 what we do
and then on Wednesdays class we'll have
the system potpourri and the final
review and I'll also be announcing the
result of the fraternity test about my
kid and well we're not two mile away
alright so I'm outside at the end of
class on Wednesday as well all right
before we switch over to Vegas speaker
any questions about what's remaining
progresses the semester for you guys yes
now you're gonna do the same day as
project for it should be on the website
it will send off the feedback for the
extra credit flight tomorrow or
Wednesday okay any other questions hi
guys so we're super excited today to
have Shashank from Oracle come and give
a guest lecture and again like I said
the reason why I like having him here is
because it's gonna make me not seem
crazy that I didn't tell you all these
about databases and just didn't make
things up he's gonna say oh yeah there's
a real system there making lots of money
it does all the things that we talked
about this the semester but he's gonna
talk about it in the context of an
in-memory database which is not what we
talked about but it's going to apply the
same concept in a different environment
and if you're interested in the kind of
things he's talking about today this is
what the advanced class 15 7:21 will be
entirely about next semester okay so she
shank is a vice president of a memory
database technologies is that correct
that's correct so he has an
undergraduate and a master's degree from
UC San Diego and he's been an Oracle for
six years nine years nine years nine
years okay and again like
a real dude working on the system isn't
some marketing this is real so by all
means stop and ask some hard technical
questions it's push him and see whether
he actually knows what he's talking
about
awesome all right hey guys thank you for
coming so again my name is Josh shank
Yvonne I come here every now and then I
guess there's a PDL lab that they come
here for the retreats and I think it's
like winter and spring I think and and
he's kind enough to invite me so thank
you again for inviting me here so
today's talk is gonna be on this top
five innovations of Oracle's database in
memory so this talk was initially given
to folks actually know about the
database in memory product I kind of
changed it a little bit to kind of give
you guys a background on what database
in memory is like Andy said please feel
free to stop me at any point in time any
time you have a question of no problems
I as I was telling Andy I usually have
more slides and I have time before the
talk so sometimes I talk too fast
so just interrupt me any time you want
to come okay so let me see I just wanna
make sure I'm following the slides
appropriately okay great so that's my
next slide all right so I like to start
off with this motivation slide this is
talking about real time enterprises need
in memory innovations now okay so this
was the the slide that I have currently
what I really wanted to show was this
slide with our presidents tweeting in
the morning called the arms real time
enterprises needed memory innovations
now but I was told would be too
political so I opted for this instead
but I actually like this one better cuz
it's real it actually is very true he
literally said that no no this is
actually when the impeachment trial
started I think is when we put the slide
together but the reality is following
real time enterprises our enterprises
that need access to data now their
data-driven
they are agile they're efficient they
want to be able to react instantly to
data so you can imagine they're a bunch
of enterprises that fit this category
right like insurance companies retail is
manufacturing process these financial
services people need to do fraud
detection in real time actually this
just
happened yesterday I was buying some
speakers that Best Buy because they're
on sale and literally after I made that
purchase I got a text message that says
are you certain that you want to make
this purchase did you make this purchase
blah blah blah because they immediately
know that I'm not the kind of person
that makes a 500 purchase you know on on
the spur of the moment that's just not
me so anyways that that's real time and
so in order to achieve that we need a
lot of things to come in place so we see
the demand that's coming from
enterprises companies right so what's
actually making this possible so if you
look at the hardware trends okay you're
starting to have larger cheaper memory
so DRAM everybody's familiar with memory
P man I don't know how many of you are
familiar with persistent memory I talked
about that and the last bullet there so
I'll get to that then you have larger
CPU caches so now we're talking about 32
megabytes of shared l3 cache on Intel's
latest processors you have larger
multi-core processors so 24 cores with
Intel cascade Lake larger SIM D vector
processing years
show of hands the folks who know what
Cindy is you hear that before single
instruction multiple ADA excellent okay
so now you have 512 bit sim D registers
that can paralyze your operations
essentially in the sink in a single
cycle faster Network so you have 100
gigabit per second rocky versus the 40
gigabit per second that you have with
InfiniBand
Numa architectures so that you have now
you have to concentrate on local memory
versus remote memory there's a bunch of
factors persistent memory is really the
biggest in my mind and at Oracle and a
lot of our group we think is a big-time
game changer in the memory technology
space so persistent memory is basically
like DRAM it's just like memory except
it's a lot larger about 3x times the
size of DRAM
it's got availability because it's
persistent you pull the plug you're
doing you put the plug back in the data
still they're sitting in these
persistent memory dims and it's it's
fast it's not faster than DRAM but it's
way faster than flash so it's got a lot
of really cool qualities and all of
these things combined
help us move towards meeting the
requirements of real time enterprises
[Music]
Aries so you're writing your ability to
write out dirty pages in your own pool
persistent memory you don't want to do
project for work exactly okay
where do we have in memory to that in
case we have different tiers so the top
tier here is application tier this is
where you care about an immediate
response time so imagine you have an
application and you're gonna link this
database directly into your applications
shares the same process base the memory
space everything is shared and so you're
gonna get immediate response time this
is extremely important if you're like
oil TP sensitive and you want to do an
insert very quickly or read very quickly
you're just getting a value for this
particular key so that's times 10 times
10 came out years ago was one of the
first in memory did I think it was the
first in memory database I think it's
what Oh No maybe 20 years ago so it was
Chris 96 okay much long enough so that's
that times 10 that's in the application
tier database tiers what I'm gonna talk
about that's where we have Oracle
database in memory and this is where we
really care about analytics but will
also mix workload performance and it's
embedded directly into a real working
enterprise database and then you're
processing things that billions of rows
per seconds when you're looking at
analytics then there's also the storage
tier so I'll talk about that as well and
by the storage chair means where the
data is actually residing whether it be
on on disk in some persistent store on
flash or something close to basically a
persistent store
so yeah the application to your database
tier storage tier and I'll talk mostly
about the database tier and the storage
tier Ken okay so I'm gonna start off
with a background on what Oracle
database in memory is okay let's start
with some basics okay so before we had
calmer databases which is in the next
slide we basically have row databases
row wise databases are fantastic if you
care about transactions okay
so as an example your an ATM machine you
have you ATM card
you wanted the duck 25 $20 from your
account that's a transaction that you're
applying you're going to quickly search
through this gigantic database of you
know millions or billions of users not
billions but certainly many millions and
search for your particular account find
your balance and deduct $20 from it so
that's like looking for a specific row
and potentially top potentially
accessing multiple columns within that
row that's great for it that's
transaction processing so row base is
very good for accessing a particular row
and then touching multiple columns
within that realm so as an example here
if you're running this query like select
column 4 from my table what you have to
do is you basically have to process each
row and hop to column 4 to get to it
right so the problem is when it comes to
analytics is you're basically visiting
every single row but on top of that
you're going column by calling call them
touching multiple cache lines to get to
the column that you care about so it's
again fantastic if you want to get to a
specific row and access a specific
column that's row format now column row
format is fast for analytics ok
analytics is where you say I actually
care about visiting all the rows but I'm
only interested in certain columns right
so in this case now if I just want to
say select column 4 from my table
all I need to do is visit column 4 ok
the data is stored in columns in
contiguous memory each column here is in
a contiguous piece of memory any
questions so far the difference between
row format and column or format we don't
do that ok great awesome okay so the the
innovation on art and what Oracle
develop for our in-memory product is we
decided that you can't just have one or
the other
it's just not feasible really for
enterprise companies enterprises are
basically more interested in mixed
workloads sometimes the running
analytics sometimes the reigning
transactions sometimes and it could be
very mix sometimes they run ad hoc
queries use gigantic queries sometimes a
very very
simple queries so it's a mix and so we
basically decided that you're not you
can't Jessica Lee choose one format we
basically want to have both formats and
so that's why we have this thing called
dual format architecture so with dual
format architecture we basically
maintain both the traditional roast or
that's sitting in your buffer cache as
well as a columnar representation that's
sitting in memory okay we maintain both
and both of them are simultaneously
active and consistent with each other
all the brains goes into the optimizer
the optimizer decides when it sees the
query which path it should take so for
example if it sees a query that says I
really want to get to this particular
row this key and extract that value and
I have this old TP index on it the
optimizer will say go to the buffer
cache and fetch the index block for it
and read that row and that's how fast
it'll get that row if the query is an
analytic query and you're doing some
kind of crazy aggregation or group by
somewhere some joins or whatever it is
it'll use the column store okay so it's
for us when we develop this database in
memory we built it natively into the
database so it's not a separate storage
engine it's part of the existing storage
engine it's basically just a think of
the the color representation as if it
was an index an index that resides in
memory okay any quick question so if it
depends on what the percentage of writes
are to do your workload so I'll cover
that in second in terms of how we handle
writes or updates or whatever or DML in
general if you're doing let's say 1% of
your workload is rights ok
that's not a problem that's basically a
mixed workload ten even five to ten
percent is fine when when you start
getting to a higher percentage or like
twenty thirty forty percent maybe let's
say this is not the right solution for
you because now as you'll see you're
basically oops I'm sorry I don't know
how that
advanced ah you know I'm probably you're
probably running with the timer yeah
okay
so what you're doing is you're basically
maintaining both right you're
maintaining this column store and the
rows store and that could become
problematic okay so I'll describe how we
handle that very efficiently any other
questions next week all right cool we
move all that out awesome
all right let's go into some of the
details okay in terms of how we store
this data so what you see here is a
table we store the data in a very impure
memory calmly representation so sales
table continues to sit on disk doesn't
change right it's exactly as you guys
know it to be it can be pulled into the
buffer cache if it's accessed that
doesn't change but what you do is if you
stay bring this table into in-memory we
will basically bring it into in memory
we'll take the rows transpose them into
columns and then store the columns into
blocks of contiguous pieces of memory
okay there's no changes to the disk
format we were Oracle so we support all
platforms you can enable in memory at
any level okay at the tablespace level
at the tables at a column level even you
can specify any level and the only thing
you do need to do is you need to tell us
how much memory you want to reserve for
your column store okay that's as I'll
talk about some of the future stuff
we're working on but that's a the only
thing you really have to do is tell us
how much memory now if you dive in
deeper into us okay we basically block
out these rows in something called IMC
user in memory compression units okay I
am see you in memory compression units
and in IMC you basically has about a
half a million rows half a million to a
million rows and within each IMC you you
have all the columns for that table so
here in this sales table here you have
the employee ID name Department salary
okay we also have this row ID column now
this is really important this is kind of
the little trick that we have that row
ID column maps to the actual locations
of those rows on disk which is this
bottom part here so on disk we basically
store data in extents which are
basically contiguous pieces of blocks
and this extent says extent number 13 as
blocks 20 to 120 extent number 14 as
blocks to 80 to 180 - and in each block
you have like you know some you know
hundreds 100 or thousands of rows and so
this imc U is mapped directly to the the
physical locations on this and why this
is important is because when you have a
modification to a row it's very easy to
say which I am see does that map to and
I'll go through a another slide that
talks about how we utilize this when we
talk about DML so the only other point
to make here is you can specify how you
want to compress this column so you know
you don't think you guys talked about
compression yet or different data
formats and you guys heard a dictionary
encoding before or prefix encode okay so
well I think I have a few slides on this
but you can specify what compression
levels you want you're limited to on
memory so you can bring it into memory
and compress it however you which way
you want to okay so that's how we store
things as I'm shocked here's the slide
on on compression so how do we actually
store this data okay so imagine this was
your column okay this is your
uncompressed data and I have Cat Cat
fish fish horse horse horse horse dog
cat etc okay it's not actually sorted I
have dogs here and cats here but this is
just my example so the first thing we do
is we dictionary encode this so
dictionary encoding means is it
identifies the distinct symbols in that
column pulls out those distinct symbols
and then sorts those distinct symbols
and then assigns a code to them so you
have cat dog fish horse that's all you
have in this in this column I sort them
and I sign them codes at 0 1 2 & 3 and
and you just have to replace the values
of Cat Cat fish fish etc with the codes
themselves and we take it one step
further we actually bit pack those codes
so because they're only four distinct
symbols there I only need two bits right
to represent each one of those symbols
so 0 0 0 0 1 0 etc ok so far so good
so that's the dictionary encoding the
next thing we do is we apply orally or
run length encoding run length encoding
is basically saying let me see if I can
identify a run of the same symbol and
number of times and replace all end
copies with a single copy along with the
run write account so here you notice
that we have Cat Cat and fish fish or
rather zero zero zero zero and one zero
one zero where I can replace that with
just zero zero and one zero and then I
have a run over there is this little
button the yeah there you go perfect so
then you can see their names basically
maintain some runs that just identifies
how many runs there are for those
symbols so far so good
okay then we take it one step further we
apply something called a zip or oracle
zip local zip is very much it's pretty
much a fancy dictionary encoding
algorithm but it's fantastic because
it's very simple and it's it's hardware
friendly to decompress I won't go into
too many details before describing
what's happening here so what it's doing
is it's now finding patterns within the
the encoded the values now so here you
have 0 0 1 0 1 1 0 1 and you see the
same pattern of 0 0 1 0 1 1 0 1 so
you'll replace the set of of 8 bits now
with a single code of 0 or sing a bit of
0 and you'll replace 0 1 with 1 and now
you've compressed it even further so
you're building and yet another
dictionary on top of the encoded stream
so far so good ok so that's what we do
we take it to kind of an extreme and
then you can actually take this and you
put Z Z Lib on top of it or B zip
alright at a higher level
on top of it okay
all right one more compression form I
want to talk about is something called
prefix encoding so we talked about that
dictionary write a cat dog horse etc
notice how they were all sorted well so
once it's sorted you can actually remove
a common prefixes from adjacent symbols
and store them separately so the example
I have here in this dictionary is used
used useful usefully usefulness etc
right and they all have used but some of
the symbols can actually benefit for
something more like useful so what we'll
do is we'll basically take out maybe
like a block of eight symbols and then
from those eight symbols we'll find the
the common prefix across those eight
symbols in this example I think I'm
using two symbols so use for use and
then D is the suffix for used so I just
maintain the prefix along with an empty
suffix here for the first symbol and D
for the second one and then the next one
we'll use useful because the third
symbol here is useful and the same thing
and then our grabs the suffixes so this
just gives you some more compression so
far so good okay problem with this stuff
is the following right
you have to decompress it and that could
take some time
you can't just point to use and D
because you have to stitch them up at
some point and give it back to whatever
operator wants the actual symbol so
there's a cost associated with
compressing and then decompressing as a
result for the coms
we have specialized formats where we
like we know what the format is you
don't have to decompress it we have some
tricks too
like for example for a dictionary
encoding for a prefix encoding we have
tricks that use sim D that that allow
you to not have to ever stitch things
back together when you're doing a scan
when doing a projection you do roast or
roast or has a compressor very much like
dictionary encoding but it operates
across multiple rows and it's far more
complex so you're right when you
actually
have to project back it's a complicated
stitching algorithm to bring it back
together again
alright so far so good
okay alright so we talked about how we
bring the data into memory we talked
about how we format it and compress it
now we're going to talk about how do we
scan how do we actually use that data
and actually scan fast how do we get to
this billions of rows per second versus
the millions of rows per second when
you're looking at a buffer cache in a
row store
so this is where sim D comes into place
so sim D again for those of you don't
know stands for single instruction
multiple data and what that does is a
lot of most modern processes now now for
last I don't know 15 20 years maybe and
well since 96 I think have a in the
processor have a vector a vector ization
unit where they have very fat registers
and not only do they have those fat
registers they have a sequence of and
they have a instruction set that can be
applied on those registers registers
that allow you to paralyze data
operations so let's just go through an
example to make things clear here you
have again in your column store and you
have a column called state right and
your query is fine sales in state of
California so what you're gonna do is
bring the state column into a register
now you guys we just talked about
dictionary encoding right so these state
columns can all be packed into how many
bits do you guys think quick thinkers
exactly okay that's a good answer that's
right so you got with that five bits or
six bits thank you six bits so six bits
coming in here but you have a register
that sets 512 bits so I can bring in 64
of these assuming all of them are 8 bits
let's just say right I can bring 64 in a
512 bit register 64 states can be loaded
at once
that's one instruction some number
cycles depending on whether it's in in
your CPU cache or not but let's suppose
it is in your CPU cache okay so it's one
cycle I've loaded them in here the next
step is to bring in
California whatever bit representation
California is and splat that across
another register California California
California California cetera then I
planned that's one cycle okay then this
is where I use the the instruction set
for vector for vector registers here
where I can do a vector compare all
values in one cycle so this state will
be compared to California this state
will be compared to California etc etc
and in one cycle it will apply
sixty-four comparisons resulting in a
bit mask of 64 bits and that tells me
which of these 64 states or equal to
California you cannot do that in a
single cycle right to go do 64 tuples
would be you know next call 64 times
this is super phantom this is why you
use a vectorized model just what they're
doing here
you can punch of crap all at once and
then do the filter review the predicate
evaluates your very quickly that's why
they're getting 100x faster make make
you feel really good that's why you guys
100x slower learn okay um but but but
but Andy's right that we actually apply
vectorization techniques to all of our
operators okay so because there's magic
in this it's it's complicated not when I
have a slide on this I think but so
let's move on here okay so that brings
me to this slide here so we're really
looking to improve all aspects of
analytics so we talked about scams just
now with vectorization joins we look at
vectorizing joins as well there's all
sorts of nifty techniques when you're
dealing with a columnstore and you're
dealing with dictionary encoding you can
leverage the format leverage the
hardware to again process at the at the
billions of rows per second here we make
joints faster by simply making something
called bloom filters faster show of
hands of folks who know about bloom
filters excellent awesome
excellent excellent bloom filters are
magic I love
okay so that's how we make joints faster
initially with our first release from
five years ago and then reporting
aggregations group by some things like
that okay yep yep this is using sim D on
top of it okay let's move on here okay
so now we finally get to the top five
which is what I wanted to get to so top
five I just want to list five things
that we have done in the in the last
five years I guess that I think stand
out in terms of what makes database of
memory kind of cool for us at least and
by the way a lot of these most of these
resulted in academic papers that we
submit to various different conferences
so I'll point them out to you as we as
we move along so the first thing is the
dual format architecture fast mix
workloads and faster analytics why we
think this is pretty innovative so let's
explain how it works okay so the dual
form and architecture enables fast mixed
workloads and faster analytics so if you
look at your right that was our eye
drawing I showed to you last time now
you can get very fast in memory DML
because the invalid row is logically
removed from the column store so I'm
going to walk through this example let's
suppose that a row was modified okay so
that row was modified for whatever
reason maybe I call him in there or some
number of columns but it was updated or
deleted whatever it is that happens on
the normal path okay like it normally
does like Oracle has been doing for the
last 3040 years now when that happens
that tells us immediately using that row
ID see you remember how I told you we
map from disk to the Consular we can
immediately just set a bit that says
that row is invalid that doesn't take
that long you guys have all set bits if
you've done if you create a bloom filter
it doesn't take long you do have to find
that I am see you that's a little bit of
a lookup but not that long and then used
to set a bit so that's how DML is work
super simple you just say this row and
that column store is invalid so now what
happens when you want to do a scan
you just ignore the invalid rows okay so
here's my example let's say I'm doing
the full table scan I just go route and
I just sidestep that invalid row and I
keep going now
what happens I sidestep that row but
that's not giving me a consistent result
now I have to actually process that row
so just for that row I will go to disk
or the buffer cache to fetch that row
okay now in all likelihood is probably
in the buffer cache because I've updated
it or I've done something updating it
brings that block into the buffer cache
and so I'm still technically processing
at memory speeds because the buffer
cache is in memory but I'm going against
the row store right now I am Sue's not
covering invalid rows are unaffected so
that's when you break up your data into
blocks it's got a lot of value to it the
blocks aren't affected they'll still go
through a nice you know proper vector
scan the cindy scans that we just we
just talked about okay this is an
important point
mixed workload performance can suffer if
the number of invalid rows accumulates
in your IMC's which goes to to your
point over there earlier if the rows
start to get really dirty then I'm just
going to the buffer cache all the time
I'm not leveraging the the common
representation
so this is where fast repopulation
techniques save the day
so let's go through let's explain this
for a second so we do something called
continuous intelligence okay this is
actually an analyst herb continues LH
intelligence just means that we will
track how dirty your eye MCU is how and
how frequently it is scanned we do a
combination of it and I'll explain why
we care about both how dirty it is and
how frequently does it scan if your
iamsu is super dirty lots of updates are
happening but you're never scanning it I
don't necessarily care to refresh it or
repopulate it no one's actually
accessing it so it's some combination of
it that we have an algorithm for that
decides when we should refresh it so the
first technique we have is something
called double buffering
so with double buffering the idea here
is when you have an IMC that's dirty you
need to refresh it so we keep the dirty
one around and in the background we'll
create a new one
that brings in those dirty rows
repopulate sit and now has a nice fresh
copy of the IMC you and once it's ready
we do that switcheroo and the old one
goes out and a new one comes in right
the main reasons why we want to do this
is because we don't want your queries to
suffer by taking it offline every
operation if you if you learn a few
things I guess in database classes you
really want to try to keep everything
online you never want to bring something
down and then suffer a slower
performance while you're refreshing an
index or in this case refreshing the IMS
you anybody understand that double
offering okay the second thing is
incremental repopulation what we call
incremental population the idea here is
you can construct a new column
leveraging the information from the old
column so for example when you do a
track when you're actually going from
rows store the column store is very
expensive population we call that
population to bring it into the memory
the it's very expensive to identify the
distinct symbols you basically are going
to use a hash table or an art you guys
heard of art adapted radix tree and very
okay okay
an index or something yeah great extreme
you need something to identify give me
my distinct symbols it's expensive to do
that and so what you want to do is
leverage the fact that hey I have
already created a dictionary before I
just have some some dirty rows here so
you leverage that to build the new C or
the new column column C you okay so
that's incremental repopulation and the
last thing here that we do as a little
trickier is oftentimes when you are
invalidating a row invalid means you're
updating and deleting or whatever you're
really just touching a column or some
number of columns you're not actually
touching all the columns and so if you
run a query that's unaffected by by the
columns because
you're only accessing those columns that
were not affected then you can still go
columnar right you don't have to worry
about the accessing the invalid grounds
okay so these three kind of techniques
here allow us to really run mixed
workloads faster and it gives us this
best of both worlds there's no there's
no paging no so that's so from the very
beginning Oracle
we've always said that you can't assume
that everything's gonna fit in memory
that's just it doesn't not realistic so
so what happens is if you have a limit
of whatever memory you have you'll
populate that bringing it to memory
anything that doesn't fit will stay on
disk now you like I said you have the
ultimate control you can say which
columns you want you can say which
partitions you want whatever this no no
it's a it's a store it's a column store
so it's not a cache now well I'll talk
to you about how we're transitioning
over to actually making it a cache when
we're doing storage tiering and things
like that okay all right so far so good
doing all right on time this is a very
quick slide I'm just gonna skip through
the animation here and this is just
telling you how question I'm sorry go
ahead
yes yeah so let me okay so I think the
question was is that if you bring you
sounds like you're bringing both the row
row format color data and the column
their data into memory and it sounds
like that's inefficient to basically
have two versions of your data and in
memory
and you need to keep them in sync and
up-to-date right okay so so that okay so
let me see if I can answer this
appropriately if you're depending on
your workload you might be an analytic
heavy workload if you're an analytic
heavy workload you're never going to
bring the row formatted data into the
buffer cache make sense you're only
going to leverage what's in the column
store and you're done if you're an all
TP heavy all you're doing is
transactions inserts updates deletes
you're not doing joins or aggregations I
think you're never going to even bring
it into the column store that makes
sense
so so that's the the two extremes now
the middle ground is when you have some
percentage of DML some percentage of
scans now where in memory is going to be
beneficial is of course if you're more
heavily towards the scans than you are
to the DML now the DML is going to bring
thing blocks into the buffer cache but
it's not going to bring the whole table
into the buffer cache so that makes
sense and so you are going to
occasionally go down the row store
because you're just looking for a row
and you're gonna use an index to get to
that or you're gonna do analytics and go
through all those so that's the
difference
got it okay question good question so
the question is is that since we don't
bring it you don't have to bring
everything into memory what happens when
you're doing a full table stand and
you're actually they access something
that's not in memory that's your
question
so it's no different than what I was
mentioning about the invalid rows if you
have an invalid row you have to go to
disk to go get it so it's the same
concept imagine you have so you filled
up 50% of your data in memory and you
have those in IMS use imagine you have
the other 50% as empty AIIMS shoes or
dirty IM shoes just you know if you can
envision that then you're always going
to disk to fetch those 50% of the rolls
that's the behavior that you'll have so
you'll get everything that you can from
memory
the columnstore and you'll get the rest
from disk or the buffer cache got it
remember and you can compress the hell
out of these things so you can fit as
much as you can see you say so I didn't
say that per pile but you can't give you
let's say what I want okay okay all
right
there it is but you can you can compress
it bringing it in until you want it
bring everything you can into memory if
you can okay
moving on all right so this is I'll just
blaze through this but this is a very
kind of a knob somewhat obvious point
for me because I explain it all the time
but may not be so obvious to others how
do we get mixed workloads to run so much
faster without doing much but just
having a calm store so normally when you
have a mixed workload you'll have here's
a table you have one two three old tepee
indexes okay old to be index again
indexes on columns like key columns
primary key columns that you really
quickly trying to get to the the values
of and then you have 10 to 20 analytic
indexes because for all the columns that
you want to run analytics on you're
gonna have a separate index for that now
you can basically fill away those
analytic indexes all together and just
maintain the column store and anytime
there's an update as I mentioned you can
very quickly mark a bit that says this
guy's been update this guy's been
deleted so because the memory the the
updates are very quickly
to indicate a DML has happened okay and
that's how and so now you don't pay the
cost of updating all of these analytic
indexes for every update that you have
to your to your table all right number
to vectorize analytics so we touched
upon this briefly right with the sim D
scans I'm gonna walk through that a
little bit more in detail in terms of
how that works so paralyzed predicate
evaluation load eval store consumers all
these are the steps that you take when
you want to evaluate a predicate so
let's just go through a quick example so
let's say you have this select count
star from table T where a is greater
than 10 and B is less than 20 right so
the first thing you're going to do is
you're going to load a and you're going
to
for values into a sim deregister right
then as I mentioned you're gonna splat
10 across that Cindy register then
you're gonna do a comparison greater
than greater than greater than greater
than all in one cycle and you got you
know a bit back that says 1 1 0 1 then
you do the same thing for B you load B
you compare it to 20 and that's the bit
vector that you have for it and now you
just need the and those two bit vectors
together and now you have the final set
0 1 0 1 now that is actually not
completely done because that's stored in
a sim D register 4 bits are stored in
128-bit register I don't want to waste
128 bits to store 4 bits so you
basically pack them that's another
instruction that the the Simeon
structure set support that packs them
into just four bits literally four bits
and then you store that you know
wherever or utilize that on and then for
the next predicate so that's you know I
a little more details of house m.d.
operations work ok so not just scans but
we're also making joins faster so bloom
filters you guys are familiar with bloom
filters the way we make bloom filters
even faster it's a combination of things
we apply the bloom filter on the
dictionary first that's the first thing
because you only need to run it on two
distinct symbols you don't need to run
it on all the values and once you run
out on the distinct symbols you need to
map them back to those symbols that map
to those codes second thing that we make
bloom filters faster is we vectorize the
operations we use sim d to basically do
a set membership lookup this says within
the bit vector find determine if this
value is set in this in this bit vector
this slide doesn't talk about bloom
filters this takes it to the next level
this is saying if you can tell me which
two columns across two tables you plan
on joining against okay and that's what
we call this join group if you say hey
you're going to join between vehicles
and sales on this name column now once
you tell me that or tell us that we will
encode both of these columns using the
same dictionary okay
without this we will we don't know that
these two are related and so we'll
basically have a separate dictionary for
this guy a separate dictionary for this
guy and they can have different codes
depending on how the item sewers are
broken up and so once they have
different codes they don't relate to
each other anymore like code five here
doesn't match code eight here even
though five and eight are both out BMW
or whatever this is vehicles name that
BMW whatever so once you tell us this we
will use the same dictionary to map the
codes and now you're just doing a code
to code match you're not doing a normal
join you guys implemented a join yes
okay
so you know you guys a hash hash join
hash drilling involves building a hash
table you're gonna have to hash the key
you got a insert into a hash table when
you do a probe you guys again hash the
key you gotta do a key comparison you
got follow chains all of that right here
it's just a ok code ten index into an
array not null there's a match and
that's it and that whole thing can be
vectorized it's a very simple operation
to do a lookup that makes sense yes yeah
good question so there there cases where
we do things automatically and then when
I talk about the future we're gonna go
to an extreme on this okay so that's
joins aggregations we do the same thing
that this the slides very detailed so
just follow my words and not necessarily
look too much at this but we have two
forms of aggregation pushdown this is
single table aviation pushdown this is
something it's called vector
transformations doing aggregations above
a join and it's kind of a you know this
is complicated right this you can't make
much meaning by just looking at this
graph but let's talk about this first
what we're doing here is imagine you
have a select sum from this table with a
predicate right normally again with that
volcano model right you're sending back
every passing row to another operator
and that operator is then
and adding and adding and adding one row
at a time maybe there's a batch of rows
at a time right but it's taking it's
doing a couple of things one is it's
doing it it's copying the symbol into a
buffer the other operator is reading
that buffer then it's looking up and
aggregate and it's adding it it's it's
quite expensive what we're doing here is
we're saying you know what let's
leverage the format this was dictionary
encoded and if it's dictionary encoded
we can use the dictionary codes and
aggregate against the dictionary codes
and the distinct symbols and then we can
do that all at the scan layer and then
only project back a partial aggregate
result to the higher-level operator okay
so that's that's the techniques that
we're doing aggregation I have an
example this vector transformation I'm
not going to go into this all I'm gonna
say is again this is a paper that we
have in I see de 2018 I think it's a
very novel technique that basically
pushes aggregations down and joins down
into the scan layer so basically instead
of actually sending all these rows back
up up up across the operators to join
operator aggregation toppers we do
everything in the scan operator and
that's that I'm again I'm not gonna talk
about that but I'm gonna talk about this
this is kind of cool something that you
probably don't think about but we have
to think about in industry very large
numbers anybody know how very large
numbers are encoded there's a variety
different formats and by very large I'm
talking about like let's say there are
30 plus digits you know it's something
that doesn't fit in 64-bit and a 64-bit
register Oracle supports a software
implemented type for a number you might
think of a number is just the register a
six an int or whatever right or long we
treat it as a sequence of bytes okay
when each set of each byte represents a
digit up to 100 so it's it's its base
100 so you have the first byte indicates
like an exponent as well as a the sign
plus a minus
right numerix okay so this is but the
and how its implemented you know how you
guys it puts it okay so so we basically
have a in each operation on a number
type is like hundreds of cycles
literally hundreds of cycles as opposed
to one cycle for doing a simply a
register operation so let's walk through
an example of how we support very large
numbers so imagine you have a select sum
of a from table T where grouped by J
comma K okay so you're doing a someone a
grouping by J comma K and let's suppose
this is your table okay
these are your grouping columns J and K
and that's your measure column a okay
what we do is we create this frequency
table and this frequency table on the
x-axis are the dictionary codes
these are imagine these are dictionary
codes okay they they map to actual
symbols just for the for to illustrate
this example here so you're gonna have 0
1 2 3 and this is 10,000 and 1 all the
way to 50 1000 here 19 cetera okay
that's the x axis on the y axis you have
the groups the distinct groups so the
possible combinations of groups are 0 0
0 1 1 0 and 1 1 if you look at all these
values over here right now what we do is
we walk through each row and we add a
count so if I go to 0 1 that map so this
group I index into 50 1819 and I bump up
a count here that says I've seen it one
time and I do the same thing for each
one of these values 51 8 or 9 again for
the other group I bump it up I do this I
bump it up and in the end I basically
have this table that says how many times
have I seen these dictionary codes for
these different groups everybody with me
so far
ok now what we do is we will aggregate
across each group by multiplying the
frequency times that dictionary symbol
so it will say code 0 shows up 0
times so I don't need to multiply it but
this guy shows up one time so I need to
grab its code look it up in the
dictionary and multiply it and so this
is basically the operations zero times
the symbol plus zero times the next
symbol and so on why do we do this
question mapping are you saying if the
number groups is too large or if the
number of dictionaries okay got it
absolutely right so you bet you've
identified some of the weaknesses of
this so the question was I think if I
understand your question right it's it's
possible that you might have one
everywhere here for example because it's
so diverse I guess it's the right word
and so you know every one of these codes
only shows up one particular group or
maybe the show in all the groups or
whatever it is and so you basically end
up multiplying everything and that is a
weakness of this it's it depends so it's
it's a it it depends on the data and how
the data is actually organized in the
case and also it depends on how many
groups you have if you have many groups
and this table stuffs become very large
because you have many distinct symbols
and many groups it's gonna be a very
expensive operation to go through this
for every single group but just just to
finish off where the idea here is is
we're basically replacing addition with
multiplication right every additional if
I have to add each one of these values
up and sum up the same value and if I
can replace that if it let's say it's
ten times five I'd rather do ten times
five as opposed to adding up five ten
times and this is like an obvious thing
you would think about in terms of
factoring but it's very important for
software implemented types because each
one of these operations is so many so
many cycles 80
some cycles so as you were saying it
does depend on the workload in terms of
when this actually kicks in or not so
that makes sense if I understand that
one question again the group so the
groups can be analyzed by what by by
walking through the columns of J&K
so you will as you walk through J you'll
identify how many distinct symbols are
in J you walk through K how many
distinct symbols are K you multiply the
two like kind of like a
multi-dimensional array to get the max
possible code and that's the that's the
table that you create and then when you
want to index into it you take this and
this multiply them together and that's
how you index into the table good okay
all right I'm gonna skip through several
slides here in interest of time so
numbers joins are made faster remember
expressions I'll skip over here dynamic
scans I'll skip and I'll move over
straight into this thing called a memory
plus extra data so this is number three
where we bringing in memory into the
storage tier so with Oracle we have
something called Exadata Exadata is a
database machine that we build from
scratch
utilizing basically the best of reed
hardware so the fastest networking the
best SSD drives a lot of memory a lot of
flash right we build that from scratch
and we build it to run Oracle as fast as
possible that's a good question it's
definitely in the millions we've sell
them in various different configurations
but it's definitely in the millions but
it's amazing how many people buy them
it's like amazing it's a it's a
billion-dollar business for achill ok ok
so on exa data you have the compute
notes and you have storage nodes ok
compute nodes is where all the higher
level sequel operator processing happens
joins and aggregation
and sorting and all that jazz happens
there on the storage nodes is where you
are closest to the data where it sits in
the SSD drives so that's where you can
actually do some fast filtering here and
then only send back the rows that pass
through the network to the compute nodes
right correct okay so what you had
without in memory is we have also some
flash that's sitting on these storage
nodes and how we use that flash as we
use it as a cache and this goes to what
Andy was talking about earlier is that
there we actually have it as a cache in
the sense that the hottest data that
you're accessing will be moved from the
SSD drives into the flash cache and now
you will and it will also be stored in a
columnar representation now the beauty
of this is that on the compute nodes
you're limited to how much DRAM you have
like one and a half terabytes of memory
which you might think is a lot but in
again real enterprises that's nothing ok
it's like a drop in the bucket you
really need the hundreds of terabytes
that flash gives you and once you have
all of that memory you can basically do
some really nifty storage tiering now
you can have some most of your hottest
data sitting on your compute and if you
run out of memory no problem it will
automatically get populated into the
flash cache sitting on the storage nodes
now how does a query work ok so imagine
you're doing a scan a full table scan
says you know select from my phonebook
all people in my address that live in
California whatever it's going to go
through here it's gonna say ok I've
exhausted everything that's over here
the rest of my table is sitting on my
storage and it's gonna say everything is
cached into my flash cache it will
utilize the same vectorization
techniques that we've talked about the
same improvements that we make for joins
and aggregations and so on it leverages
all of that it's just doing it from
flash and so you have to bring it from
flash into the D
that's local to that storage node but
then after that you do the same
techniques and then you send it back up
maybe that makes sense and this is just
the form of storage tuning gives you a
much larger column store it allows you
to place data where it belongs
hot data in the most expensive memory
that's the fastest warm data in the
flash cache and cold data sitting on
your persistence store right on your on
your disk okay these are just some
performance numbers I think we can skip
that and we'll skip this anybody
interested in fault tolerance okay good
okay so let me tell you about how we
achieve fault tolerance okay on we
basically maintain a cluster of nodes we
call it rack
okay on the rack you can have many
different nodes let's say four nodes in
this example and you have a column store
on each one of these nodes each one of
these nodes has memory you can put a
separate you can put a column store in
there what you can do is you can bring
your data into this column store and you
can duplicate it on any one of these
other nodes so for example this red eye
MCU is duplicate on this node and this
blue is duplicate on that and black is
duplicated there and you can have at
least two nodes that you can duplicate
it against so that if anything happens
to this node queries just need to be
redirected to the node that has that I
MCU right it's really simple it's as
simple as that you can do even better by
having full duplication where this red
eye MCU is stored everywhere and that
gives you both availability as well as
performance performance because every
access now when you go to it will be
local you're not doing a remote access
to another node to fetch its contents to
and run that query everything is local
okay
so that's how we achieve photons is it's
it's fairly simple and straightforward
every is the IMC you level every IMC you
which is that half of a million rows
gets duplicated I'm gonna skip data
guard and I'll move straight to
intelligent automation Andy how we doing
on time okay okay all right all right
number four is intelligent automation
this is where we're trying to be a lot
smarter so far everything I've told you
for the most part is the DBA or you you
know do you the user has to direct us in
some way says hey bring this table and
turn memory or hey create this join
group right we want to be a lot smarter
you guys were all work with Andy Andy's
the creator of self-driving databases
Larry Ellison stole the name I said we
made money out of it so anyways so
that's where we're moving towards right
self-driving databases I have a separate
talk later on today that that's talking
more about how we achieve this but the
idea here here is here's a picture of
this DBA poor DBA and the DBA saying I
have to manually manage what to put in
this column store and what to keep out I
don't know what tables are hot I don't
know what's cold I know it's warm I have
no idea what queries you're gonna run
right but as I as I mentioned earlier
it's a column store so once this store
becomes full of tables that's it the DBA
has to decide what to Vic tout what to
bring in right and the desired outcome
here is you want to keep hot objects in
memory and remove the colder objects
right so that's what we had okay
what we have now is something smarter
right here we will observe the access
patterns we have something what we call
a heat map heat map basically says at
the very smallest granularity which for
us is a block and the block has some
number of rows at the block level we
will say how often has it been
just how hot is it and how it's been
accessed well the access because it
scans a DML what how right so we observe
the access patterns once we observe the
patterns will classify the data right
we'll say hot intermediate cold cool
data and once we classify the data then
we take action we'll bring in the hot
data in will remove the cold data very
simple very straightforward we take it
to an even more complicated level where
we'll do it we'll do it not just at the
table level or the partition level but
even at the column level so we'll say
something like this column is being used
to aggregate on its a measure column and
this column is being used to predicate
on okay now if I know that this columns
for predication or for predicates
predicate evaluation and this column is
for aggregation I could format them in a
different way I might use dictionary
encoding for wine and maybe another
compressed format for the other because
dictionary encoding in order involves
getting the code looking up in the
dictionary getting the symbol it's a
couple of levels of indirection and
that's expensive but it's really fast
for scans because I just need to look at
the bit codes I don't never I never have
to decompress it whereas aggregation I
need to actually go get that symbol from
the dictionary and then I need to add it
so why should I dictionary encode that
maybe I should just keep it uncompressed
so I have the symbols right there so
this is where you can start becoming a
lot smarter about knowing how your your
data is accessed how the columns are
access how they should be formatted
maybe remember these maybe these four
columns are never accessed get rid of
them compress them or if you want to be
safe compress them or evict them out of
the column so all together
okay so anyways so that's how we're
trying to remove the guesswork out of
the picture and just start being a lot
lot smarter and this gets complicated
because you guys all work on with the
buffer cache imagine you have a mixed
workload where sometimes you're going to
run a little two-piece sometimes you're
gonna run analytics how much memory do
you dedicate for the column store versus
how much do you dedicate for the buffer
- right how do you determine that how do
you know what the behavior is gonna be
today versus tomorrow versus the next
day and so on so all of these factors
have to come into play and you have to
be very elastic and being able to switch
from one to the other and you have to be
very very fast and accurate no customer
wants to move over to Oracle's
autonomous database and all of a sudden
they experience worse performance and be
experience like inconsistent performance
those like those are two terrible things
if the very least you want to be
consistently bad that would be my sister
if you're gonna be bad be consistently
bad so that the user knows like okay at
least I know what to expect today and
tomorrow and so on all right so um I'm
gonna skip through some more things I
will talk briefly about question yes so
this is this is a finer grain this is
saying for example when the column store
is full the action we could take is just
evict out cold columns that's it we
never will decide what should go in to
replace it that's just based on your
query whatever you touch you bring in
that's one mode another mode is now will
be smarter will evict and tell you what
to bring in and yet another mode is an
extreme mode that's where like hands off
will do everything will decide from the
get-go what should be in the column
store from the get-go what columns
should be in there or how to compress it
and so on we we just look at we we just
look at frequency ndv right that's all
we really look at you could we do look
at if it's a date column for example
let's give a date column if it's a date
column we could be smarter in terms of
how we encode it we can code the month
separate from the year from the dates
and get better compression if it's a
number column we can impress them with a
binary representation JSON we can do so
we do look at data types to compress
them in a much more efficient
representation but we don't look at it
to derive meaning
out of it now that's kind of another
level once we once we have the queries
together in the repository and we have
the data and we have access patterns we
can do things like that I don't know if
we're like I say we could do it so we
haven't actually done anything like that
yet because we'll see here's the thing
is the data likely will be encrypted as
it is and so you know we can't do
anything I'm not even an NDB even is
difficult you can do it from the
dictionary but other than that again
any other questions question great yeah
great question so that is that's kind of
our expert system I don't it's not
machine learning but it's like it's an
expert system it's taking to account
again but let's just take simplest
metrics are how often has it been
scanned how much space does it consume
and how has it been scanned those are
kind of like the three very simple
metrics and from that you can divide
design an equation that meets a
threshold and you optimize for the other
part of it that's missing is time I
think when wine has been access you take
all those into account and you've got a
pretty smart system without anything
more complicated than that
this you can go further you can look at
correlation between multiple columns
correlation across multiple tables etc
question in the back yep good question
so the question is how do you determine
when to bring it into the columns for
automatically right but and when these
opposite okay good question
so I'll answer the first and when to
bring it into memory is again it's
similar to what I was saying those
attributes if I know it let's say
there's a table that's not in memory and
counselor is full how often has this
table been scanned not that often how
often these tables been scanned at our
memory very often doesn't make sense to
replace them once the number of scans
for this table has increased above what
any of these are the tables have then it
makes sense to evict something out from
the column store bring something in but
it's tricky right because you have to
know is that just for a short period of
time and then it's not gonna be accessed
again and I paid all this I spent the
last CPU cycles to transpose it bring
into memory and now I'm done like it's
midnight and I don't need to run these
reports again so we try to be smart
about identifying the access patterns
before we take action we're actually a
fairly conservative system and we will
slowly make modifications it's it's it's
like any other system its expert system
that you design you're gonna have
feedback mechanisms in here right you're
gonna say did I make the right decision
that I just did and if I didn't like I
learned from that I remember that and
the next time this situation comes again
I'll be smarter about what I would I
bring in I'll be honest with you this is
not a perfect system and there's a lot
of work that needs to be done here and
that's where we're we're trying to
figure out what's the how do we get the
80% of the benefit with 20% of the work
so we can quickly get to it it's a
question of it okay yes yes yes so what
we'll do this so the first thing we do
let's say 0 & 1 are both hot that's what
you're saying right they're both high
you don't have space for both 0 & 1 what
do you do first thing we do is we say
which of these columns are not been
accessed okay normally you have a table
that's a very fat table or a fat table
okay let live like anybody familiarity
PCH okay t PCH is a benchmark the data
warehouse bench mic
okay TP CH has a table called line item
line item has a column called L comment
L comment is never used okay in the in
the queries that are in that particular
benchmark L comment for Oracle takes up
about twenty percent of the space in
memory it's a gigantic varchar not
gigantic varchar but it's a large
varchar' string and oracle is very
aggressive
we will dictionary encode it which
doesn't really make sense because
they're all distinct symbols why the
hell am i dictionary encoding I'm not
gonna leverage it but we do that because
we assume you might scan against it and
if you can scan against the dictionary
encoding is the smartest thing so going
back to your example here is L comment
is never used line item is hot that's a
hot table but that column L comment has
never used so will evict it out or
compress it just to be safe and just
that act of compressing your victim out
might allow you to bring this other
table in that make sense so we will try
to first be very conservative and try to
get both of those tables into the into
the column store by compressing columns
okay if that doesn't work we take the
next bigger action if that doesn't work
we take the next bigger action it's very
so for example tables are usually
partitioned right you can partition by
date maybe the old dates partitions are
needed and you only care about the
hottest date so you keep that in mind
when you Vic the old dates out that make
sense now if you're in a situation where
both of these are hot then then we stay
conservative we're not going to
constantly populate we pick populate a
vague that's just gonna add more cycles
to do the population so we'll choose one
and live live with the consequences okay
all right I know I'm like running our
time here so I'm just going to up sorry
sorry I persistent memory okay let's
just talk very quickly about persistent
memory new silicon technology capacity
performance and price between DRAM and
flash this is a nice little picture here
that shows as you go from disk to flash
to persistent memory the DRAM you're
going faster faster faster faster faster
but at the same time you're going higher
cost higher cost higher costs per per
gigabyte okay
eventually pmm is really expensive right
now it's really expensive eventually
this will reduce in price but flash is
going to be even cheaper also so it's
very interesting how we put systems
together with all this technology to get
the the best performance Intel calls
this obtain DC persistent memory DC's
data center I believe they're pretty
much the only game in town right now
okay there's a there's others but the
only game in town right now
reads that memory speed much faster than
flash right survive power failure unlike
DRAM okay you can imagine building as
and you're saying building a brand new
storage engine built on top of
persistent memory right it's tricky as
heavy a key here you guys he's gonna
give a talk tomorrow on how you can
leverage persistent memory it can be
tricky because it involves leveraging
some new instructions to make sure that
data is properly flushed all the way
back to to memory I won't go into the
details of that I will just bring up
this slide here on how we are planning
on using persistent memory for our a
memory column store so today as a
baseline
you cannot necessarily fit all of your
data in memory that's the example or
some of us we've been talking about so
assume it doesn't fit in memory so
you're gonna have disk disk plus memory
the queries then have to go against the
column store endear am as well as the
roast or on disk right and DRAM dims can
go up two hundred twenty eight gigabytes
no one buys it at that it's very
expensive so that's today's baseline
with P mam you can conceivably fit
everything inside of a pea mmm
Adam okay it's 3x more denser something
called memory mode this is really cool
memory mode Intel supports it allows you
to have a your persistent memory dim and
a a dram dim sitting on top okay so when
you access data the DRAM dim serves as a
cache so your hottest data sits in
memory Indy Ram and if it's not in that
cache then we'll bring it from the
persistent memory dim into the D Ram den
so the D lambda just serves as a cache
it's wasted space in the sense that it's
a cache it's not like extra memory that
you have but the benefit is you are
accessing PMM almost as fast as SDRAM
okay so that's called memory mode the
hottest tables are cached in DRAM for
the fastest access and these DIMMs can
be quite large the 512 gigabytes and
then this just talks about using our
latest Oracle 20 C and some of the
techniques and the reason why I mention
this is we ran this this benchmark where
we use SS B's is SS B's another
benchmark called star schema benchmark
it's kind of based off of T PCH and
there we showed D Ram about 380 4
gigabytes the table didn't fit entirely
memory this was a progress bar but that
completed we process 18 billion rows and
took 130 seconds okay when it didn't fit
entirely in memory and then we use
memory mode with persistent memory and
it like dropped by 10 X right and 10x
faster and took 12 seconds to go to 18
billion rows and then we just added
Oracle 20 C which has some cool
techniques for making joints faster and
we just showed that that can go an
additional you know 4x faster than that
and the main point I want to mention is
this really is a game changer for us
we're looking at at persistent memory
more as expanded memory larger capacity
so now you could fit everything into
memory and gone are the days where you
need to put everything on disk
okay you got terabytes and terabytes and
terabytes of memory okay
I'm gonna skip the converged analytics
and I'm just gonna open it up to
questions but the main I'll just talk
about this slide here the main thing
about Oracle one of the things that
we're trying to push more cool is you
don't need to have a separate storage
engine for a document store or a spatial
store neo4j or graph or AI or IOT or
you know treat your databases the file
system Oracle is trying to position
itself as a one-stop shop right you can
do everything on a single database and
it's got a ton of benefits one being
security you don't want to have to
migrate your relay
data out to bring it into yet a graph
database just so you can run graph
queries on it right there's a customer
or is it the next day the customer in
Europe that they have a they build a
graph database and they use a graph to
represent transactions between different
people on their on their PayPal or a
system and they every every edge in
their graph node is a transaction but
they have to take their data out of a
relational store bring it into the the
graph store and then they run their
query and that takes one sometime and
second there's always this security
violation now because you're taking this
unencrypted data out of the database
same thing for a document store with
MongoDB this MongoDB but you can also
store JSON nicely inside of your your
relational database okay so I'm not
going to talk so much about this I'll
just sort of skip through this and leave
it at that
okay so last thing is just this is this
innovation summary I want to make it
very clear that you know this is 2014
when we came out all of these little
bullets here are like kind of massive
projects and Oracle is kind of committed
to in memory and you know our roadmap
going up so I'm kind of drawing it up
higher from 20 to 21 scenes so on we're
super committed because we feel like
now's the time in memory is becoming
readily available it's becoming cheaper
it's becoming larger the hardware
technology is all there the requirements
again from the real time enterprises is
there and so as a result our features
need to be there and the main drivers
for us are the self managing in-memory
database everything needs to be
autonomous really looking at everything
not just relational but spatial text
graph etc and also vectorizing all of
our operators is not just our simple
scans and so on ok I think that's it
I'll skip that I'll skip that I'll skip
that and open it to any questions you
may have if you have any
yeah great question so the question is
how do how are we representing this as a
single representation of your data when
you want to use it for a graph Corre
versus a relational query or is it like
a you know multiple representations I
had that right okay so I went through
those slides very quickly but let me
explain so what we do for graph or let's
say I'll say JSON initially right now
for text okay so the techniques that
we're doing for text spatial JSON
whatever it is is representing the data
in a much more efficient manner in a in
memory in a column store so it's kind of
like think of dictionary encoding doing
some tricks like that to represent your
data more efficiently yeah like this how
important you're looking to hire
somebody would be he would have a
background maybe testing database
systems or query optimization oh yeah a
great question okay so when I when we
look to hire people okay so first thing
is this I always look for people that
are enthusiastic smart and excited about
the technology that's that's first and
foremost because we have we have
mathematicians we have a mechanical
engineer we have a chemist we have all
sorts of people that working on database
systems the folks that actually have a
solid background in database systems
however they that's like I don't know
it's what's the word the Holy Grail in
some in some ways
because we interface with we're the core
storage engine team but I interface we
interface with the optimizer team we're
going to face with the exudative team we
interact with the hardware team I have a
background in compilers in computer
architecture so I didn't have a
background database systems at all okay
you have two candidates equal background
honking one is a JavaScript programmer
okay
[Laughter]
[Applause]
[Music]
son ricochet jelly hit the deli photo
put one naturally bless ya
rap is like a laser beam the pores in
the bottle or sippy go don't fill out
drink it and only to you can't and if
the sake don't throw your phone can tap
a thing