[Music]
all right again
Thank You Gigi easy drop table for keep
things fresh all right
so we'd love to talk about real quickly
again for the assignments project three
hits been put out and that'll be due on
Sunday November 17th and I'll talk about
that briefly at the end of this class
and then project or say homework 4
should be four not three or will be
released next week and that will be then
better we do on on the thirteenth okay
and as I said my wife is going we're
going to hospital tonight it's gonna
happen like nine hours from now so I'm
gonna be gone for two weeks I won't have
office hours next week or the following
week and then next week we will still
have classes my PhD students will what
we take take care of those classes then
the following Monday we'll be getting
one more PG student and then we'll have
no class on October 30th and then the
schedule correctly reflects this okay so
any questions about any of this and that
would make arrangements with my my admin
about having all the midterms in her
office and then we'll figure out some
time you'd go come her office and check
check out your your midterm again just
bring your student ID so she knows who
you are okay and then if you have if you
want something regraded take a photo you
can't take your midterm with you just
take a photo the page you want me
created and email me and we'll take care
of it okay all right so we're right now
in the course is that we've covered the
entire stack we've covered how to store
things on disk we covered how to put
things in a probable the access method
scans how to execute operators and how
to do query planning so now we're gonna
actually can look look at for the next
four weeks we're gonna go back and look
at the entire architecture all over
again and now consider two important
components concurrency control and
recovery and these concepts actually
permeate all throughout the entire
system we kinda need to understand the
basics first and that's why we went
through without discussing any of these
things and now we're going back and
seeing how we wouldn't you know if you
want to enforce concur cheat or make
sure that our databases can be stored on
disk safely
how do we make sure that we had we
modify what we've already talked about
to account for these things and take
care of it
so again courage call and recovery are
all you know they're not like should be
separate things on the side with a
problem manager or an index the entire
system needs you aware of how it's gonna
be durable how things are gonna be how
transactions are gonna run safely and so
that's why we're going we're covering
this at the at the second half of the
semester and I would say also to once we
have these two things that you can go
off the world and build your own
database system but these are the last
two things we need to actually build an
AV system that can run transactions
correctly and make sure that everything
is safe so we're almost there so to
motivate why we want to talk about
Kikuchi on recovery let's look at two
simple scenarios so let's say that I
have an application where I want to have
two threads try to update the same
record in the same table at exactly the
same time how to make how to make a
decision about which one should you
succeed well should be our final change
and there's a race condition here I
would have want to come slight before
the for another the other scenario is
that let's say that I have an
application that for my bank and I want
to transfer a hundred dollars out of my
account into your account but let's say
you know before I you know after I take
the money out of my account but before I
can put it in your account the the
building the data center gets struck by
lightning the the lose all power our
machine crashes or database system
crashes so when we come back what should
be the correct state of the database but
what should we actually see so the first
problem that I'm talking about here at
the top this is an example of a lost
update or I have two transactions two
threads trying to make an update to the
same back at the same time I couldn't
have end up missing one all right how to
make sure that doesn't happen and the
way we're gonna use ensure that these
things happen correctly is through a
concur tool mechanism occurred stroke
protocol for the second scenario where
my machine Meador my data center catches
on fire and I you know my I lose power
and my machine crashes we're gonna use
the recovery mechanism
in the database system to ensure
durability so these two costs of control
and durability are one of the main
selling points of a database management
system this is why if you're building an
application whether it's in the cloud or
on a cell phone or on a desktop you
don't want to be in the business of
doing these things yourself in your
application because you're probably
gonna get it wrong and you can have
losing data or have incorrect data this
is why you want to use a data internet
system because they can have they have
really smart people that have been
spending a lot of time to make sure that
these things happen correctly if you
also think about it to it like if you're
a startup you know the if you're
shipping an application it doesn't
matter you know the end of the day
what's with what's not gonna sell your
product is oh I can I can recover the
database after a crash right you need
that as a feature you absolutely have to
have but that's not a differentiating
aspect of your application versus your
competitors all right so you don't want
to get if you don't want any business of
writing a database minute from yourself
unless that is your job for everything
else
people should rely on you know high
quality software David system software
that is that is vetted to do these
things so the core concept that we're
going to use through the next four weeks
discussing this these you know running
the our system to make sure that things
are running in the correct order or
running that all our changes are so
durable is this idea of transactions
that are that are gonna run with asset
guarantees or asset properties so
there's a quick show of hands who here
has heard of the acronym asset before
all right
about half okay so we'll cover that so
before we can sell an asset let's talk
about what a transaction is so in our
world today if we're talk about in this
lecture the transaction is gonna be the
execution of a sequence of operations on
a database system to before some
higher-level function and so these
operations you can sort of think about
as sequel queries or the reads and
writes we're doing to the database and
by higher-level function I mean
something like that reputation you know
some some some feature we want our
application to perform the steps
transfer money from my account into your
account that would be a high-level
function because it's suppity program in
a transaction in our application no
database systems gonna have that did
that feature that like that single
function can call no move money this is
something you would write in your
application up above so transactions are
going to be the basic unit of change in
our database management system meaning
this is well how all changes are going
to occur in the in the wrapped inside of
a transaction right whether it's if it's
multiple queries or a single query it's
always going to be a transaction I
suppose you can have a zero query
transaction but that doesn't really mean
anything right but it's assumed that
it's one or more operations we want to
do and so the key concept though about
transactions is that we're not going to
allow for partial transactions where
transactions are always going to be
atomic
but that means that if I have a sequence
of five updates I want to do either all
five occur or none of them occur I can't
have you know some like you know maybe
the first three out of five secede and
the other two fail right it's either all
or nothing and even if you have a single
query transaction a single operation
transaction say I have an update query
that updates five to pools all right
still one query but within that I'm not
getting five things all five had to get
updated not not some subset of them so
the transaction example would be that
the one I talked about before work I
want to move a hundred dollars out of my
bank account into my shady promoters
account so the database system doesn't
provide this functionality in my
application code I would write the steps
to perform this right so in the first
step I would say well check to see
whether India has $100 he probably
doesn't write but then if I do then you
can take the hundred dollars out of my
account and then put the hundred dollars
into his account all right again these
are separate steps there's no magic way
to just materialize money in in a single
at the lowest level the harbor to
automatically update something and
another thing at the exact same time all
right there's a bunch of extra stuff we
have to do to make sure that this
happens atomically but from the
applications perspective you know they
vote this transaction and this will all
happen or none of it happens
so let's talk about a really simple
database system we could build that
could could could do this for us so
let's say we have a database system that
has only supports a single thread
meaning only one transaction and only
one query can run at a single time and
you know if multiple queries are
multiple transactions show up in the
system it just puts them in a queue and
there's one thread pulling things off
that queue and running them one by one
so now before transaction starts
executing what they're gonna do is
they're gonna copy the entire database
file or set of files what however it's
architected it's gonna make a second
copy of the database make all the
changes that wants to make to that copy
and then if it succeeds and we want to
save all our changes then we just flip a
pointer to say now the new version of
the database is is the second file I
just created all right so this
guarantees that Adam is to be propagated
is mentioned because if I make the copy
to the database and then I'm doing five
writes but then the first three happen
and then I crash when I come back I
still have my original copy of the
database because I didn't affect that I
said that you know so everything is
still correct there that's fine things
are being written to disk so if I crash
I could come back and those my disks
didn't die all my data is still there so
would this actually work he says yes
would this be fast says no y-you said no
so why if something to the UH please
doesn't matter right the amount of the
matter updates I'm doing in my
transaction it doesn't matter because
I'm copying the file every single time
so I copy entire file and make one
change versus a thousand changes like
that copy cost is always the same but
you're right the clock the copy part is
expensive if it's a one kilobyte or
starting a four kilobyte page for my
database who cares that's one Hardware
read and write I can I do that pretty
quickly but if I have one petabyte of
data now for every single transaction
I'm copping one petabyte every single
time making my changes and then updating
the pointer so this is a good example of
where we
design a system that had the properties
that we want and particularly acid
properties that we'll talk about but
this is going to be super slow to do it
this way the other issue is that we're
also running with a single thread so I
didn't say anything about whether the
the the database fits in memory or not
right so now if I'm running with a
single thread and tries to touch data
that's not in memory but it's in disk I
have to stole my thread until I go fetch
it and I can't run anything else because
I only have one thread that can do this
at a time so we're gonna talk about
today and and and for the next couple
weeks is a potentially better approach
where we're going to allow transactions
to run simultaneously at the same time
and then we're gonna come up with a way
to try to put potentially in or leave
their operations in such a way that we
maximize our parallelism but still get
all the safety guarantees that they want
and correctness guarantees that we want
in our database system right and again
it's obvious why we want to do this
because we talked about two before when
we talked about latching we talked about
query execution if we can get we can
allow multiple queries that run at the
same time we're gonna get better
utilization of our Hardware better
throughput meaning we can do more more
work in a same amount of time and then
the system's gonna look more responsive
and snappy because now I don't have to
wait in that single queue until my to my
quick transaction gets to the front and
then I can run I could potentially start
running right away but now Kristin the
tricky thing is gonna be is that how do
we actually do this interleaving you
know such a way that we don't violate
any better correctness guarantees of our
system and that we don't starve any one
transaction you know from from taking
all the resources and other transactions
can't do anything so concurrent reto
we're talk about today is a is an old
concept that goes back to the 1970s oh I
when I BM built system R this is one of
the first things they also invented and
so in a disk based system back then of
course because memory was limited and
any time it turns actually could touch
data that's on that's on disk and on a
memory and therefore it would stall and
then now you could let other transaction
to run at the same time in modern
systems today usually for all it to be
applications they're not that big the
databases aren't that big
so we have enough memory where we could
put the entire database in memory for
analytics you still go to disk but that
we're not doing transactions there so in
a modern system most mostly ultimate
databases can fit memory but now Intel
is giving us more and more cores so now
we're gonna allow transactions around in
different cores at the same time and
then we still need to guarantee all
these things so even though the hardware
is different from when how people first
invented cooker to scroll back in the
day we still have the same problem so
you still want to maximize parallelism
and as I said a couple times already
this is gonna be really hard to do and
as I said last class this is probably
the second hardest thing to do in
database systems to do concur control
and this is part of the reason why the
nocebo guys when they first came out ten
years ago they were like we're not doing
transactions okay that's too hard
because they want to run faster so it's
gonna be super hard for us to guarantee
correctness which transactions all right
so what happens if I we have $100 in my
bank account and I try to give money to
people at the exact same time what
should happen because I don't want to
you know assuming that banks not gonna
let me overdraft I you know I don't
wanna be giving out money I don't
actually have and then it's also gonna
be hard to execute this very efficiently
because again if I do the serial
execution case that I talked about in
the beginning then that's gonna be
always correct because only one
transaction is running at a time and
then how many worries about any
interleaving but for now I do want to
interleave them
I want to bet to be as efficient as
possible to be to figure out whether I'm
running correct still correctly I just
there's me some overhead to figure these
things out so what we're essentially
trying to do today and for the next
three let three or four lectures is
allow for these interleaving the
operations of transactions and that well
as we see is that when we start doing
these interleaving we can end up with
inconsistent databases and sometimes
it's okay sometimes it's not okay
so some inconsistencies will be okay
because they're temporary so for example
if I'm taking money out of my account
putting in your account again I can't do
that atomically at the Harvard level I
have to do that with you know multiple
instructions or multiple operations so
there will be a brief period in time
where I take the $100 out of my account
and then before it before I put it in
your account
that hundred dollars it doesn't exist
anywhere so that's okay because that's
temporary it's unavoidable the outside
world will not see potentially not see
that inconsistency and we'll do some
protection mechanisms make sure that
they can't see this and so because that
because we're gonna allow this this is
gonna last actually make this all work
but the thing we want to avoid or
permanent inconsistencies where again if
I take the hundred dollars out and then
I crash and I come back that hundred
dollars better not be missing all right
a better it better be in the other count
or Maya County it can't just disappear
so in order for us to understand whether
we're doing the right thing
whether we're coming out with the
interleaving of our transactions that
are actually correct we need a more
formal definition of what actually means
to be correct because it's sort of
obvious for us right yeah if I take a
hundred dollars of my account and before
I put it in your account we crash like
that sort of obvious we know that we
don't want to lose a hundred dollars or
any amount of money but from the
database systems perspective it doesn't
know that it's operating no money
just sees a bunch of bytes and it's
moving them around so we need a way for
us to reason about whether we're doing
the correct thing so the first thing we
need to find what is what are these
operations that we're actually doing so
as I said already a transactions Macross
of one or more operations but at a high
level the database the application could
be you know update this insert that make
these changes but from the database
systems perspective it doesn't doesn't
know about those high-level queries it
just knows that I'm doing low-level
reads and writes and so the only thing
that we can reason about are the things
that happened to our database so that
means that if they're our transaction
involves additional steps or procedures
or operations that aren't reads and
writes on the database this is outside
our purview this is outside our control
and we can't do anything about it so to
give an example let's say that I'm gonna
take a hundred dollars out of my account
I put it in your account and then I send
an email to you to say the transfer
succeeded and that we want that to
happen in the transaction but then
before I can go commit and save my
changes there's a crash so I've sent the
email but then I crashed before I
save all the changes that email is gone
up on the network it's outside the
database now it's gone out in the real
world we can't retract that so we can
only reason about and roll back and and
and and persist things that are these
low-level reads and writes to our
database if we make a call to you know
to an outside system or whatever like
that's that's beyond us no system can
handle that at least we're talking out
here so far okay so the database that
were going to be worried about today is
going to be defined as a fixed set of
arbitrary data objects that are each
going to have a label or a name so in
this case here we'll just use ABCD but
we'll just use alphabet characters so
the two new things to point out here are
one I'm not defining what a database
object is it could be an attribute it
could be a tuple could be a page could
be a table could be a database it
doesn't matter all the same things that
we'll talk about today and for the next
couple couple classes they're all still
work on different granularities in
practice most the time it's going to be
based on a take on a tuple but we'll see
in some cases you can take locks you can
try to protect databases and tables
nobody exercise protect single fields
that becomes too too too expensive the
other thing to point out too is that I'm
saying the database is a fixed size so
that means that the only operations
we're gonna do or reads and writes reads
or updates of existing things we're not
gonna talk about inserts today we're not
going to talk about deletes the Davis
always has the same number of things
because that's gonna complicate things
and we'll cover that on Monday next week
so for today just assume that we've
always have the same number of X and so
now what the database is gonna see is
just the sequence of read and write
operations on these names opposite up
above so we're to say we use the
function R for a read and the function
of W for a right so this is the only
thing that we can see in our database
system we can't see anything else any
program logic that the application may
be running for the transaction and
that's gonna limit the amount of
parallels and we're be able to get
because we don't understand main any
some kind of high-level meeting with
what the transaction is actually trying
to do we'll see one case where if you do
you can get better parallelism but in
practice nope nobody does this and we'll
get to that later so now from a
practical standpoint how do you actually
implement or use transactions and
applications and database systems today
so in the seco standard you have these
extra keywords begin commit and abort
some systems use roll back instead of
abort
I think postcards are my siglo support
both so we're gonna explicitly start a
new transaction with the begin keyword
and then what happens is we make we any
queries we then execute or a part of
that transaction and then the better
call I want to commit or abort so if the
user says I want to commit then two
things can happen either the transaction
does commit the database saves all the
changes that you made and returns back
in acknowledgments is to say they're
successful or the database systems can
say you can't actually commit I'm not
gonna let you make those changes and I'm
gonna go ahead and shoot you and abort
you and you have the rollback and you
get a notification that your transaction
failed right so just because the
application calls commit doesn't mean
you're actually gonna commit again
that's a very important concept that we
can rely on later on if the transaction
gets aborted then any changes that we
made since we called begin will get
rolled back and it'll appear as if the
transaction never ran at all so that's
how we guarantee if I'm moving hundred
dollars out of my account to your
account if the thing fails before we put
the money in your account the
transaction gets a border to come back
and if we go back to the state we were
before we started our transaction right
this is how we guarantee that there's no
partial transactions yes this question
is why would do we want to tell the
Davis entity one of abort so a lot of
times there's application code where you
say take take take for example take the
money out of my account or I'm
transferring money so I go look at my
account first
I read that do I have $100 yes now go
take a hundred as my account but then
I'll go read your account and your
bank's your your accounts my flag fraud
so now I want to abort and roll that
back right the simple reason
I don't know how often that occurs I
always say I mean most code I want to
commit they want to go to commit right
but we have to be able support this so
again the main thing to point out here
is this abort could either be
self-inflicted meaning we tell us if we
want abort or the data system tells you
you have to abort and then if you
tennyson comes back says you have to
abort are you got aborted then it's up
for you in the application code to catch
that you get like an exception back and
says you know your transaction failed
and it'll suggest that you retry it and
you have to go back in application code
if you actually care about this and
retry again all right so the correctness
criteria we're going to use now for this
lecture and going forth through the rest
of the semester is going to be defined
in terms of this acid acronym so as it
stands for atomicity consistency
isolation and durability
so atomicity is what we already talked
about where we say all that the
operations of a transaction have to
occur or none of them occur right no
partial transactions consistency is sort
of a weird one I'll briefly talk about
it but it's it's very handy how it
actually means at least for a single
node database system
so it just says that if if the
transaction is consistent like doorbell
sorry I forget the if if the transaction
is consistent and the database system is
consistent then when the transaction
executes then the database and state
will be consistent so now you're like
what is consistent mean well at a high
level it means correctness but then what
does that mean
so again we'll cover this in a few more
slides this one again as it was
originally defined by the guy that
invented this this acronym this one was
always a really handy one it's some
people feel like he sort of forced this
one in here in order to get that the
acronym to work out the other thing too
is that the database lor is that he made
this thing up to make make fun of his
wife cuz like his wife didn't like candy
or she was like a bitter woman or
something so he named it after her I
don't know whether that was true he's
Germans and maybe but there's another
one called
base which is for distributed systems or
no single systems and we'll cover that
and a few more lectures so there's acid
is what we care about here base will
cover later isolation is another
important one that means that the when
our transaction executes it should have
the illusion that it's running by itself
even though other transactions may be
running at the same time and the data
isn't one well will provide that that
illusion for it and then durability is
wet if our transaction commits all our
changes get saved and we get back at on
acknowledgment veterans actually
committed then no matter what happens to
the database whether you know it the
Machine crashes it's not oh s crashes
the machine catches on fire then all our
changes should be persistent maybe she
always could be able to come back and
see our changes our changes may get
overwritten that's okay but for least
for our transaction you know we know
that all has changes got persistent so
another short shorthand way of looking
at these things you would say
Adam isn't he just means all or nothing
no parts of transactions because since
he means it looks correct to me and
correct will be in quotes isolation
means you're running as if you're alone
and then durability means that you're
going to survive all failures so for
today's class we're going to go through
each of these one by one and describe at
a high level what it means to determine
whether we are achieving the asset
guarantee with a given property of each
letter we're gonna mostly focus on
atomicity and isolation I'll briefly
talk about consistency here it doesn't
really make that much sense for a single
node system it matters more for
distributed systems and then for
durability we're also not really going
to talk about it too much because we'll
spend that whole two lectures after
after I come back on on checkpoints and
volume because that's how they're gonna
achieve that okay and I'll say also to
that acid is what you would get in a if
a relational data cement system says
they support transactions this is
typically I mean the no sequel systems
that don't do transactions
they're typically going to sacrifice
often Adam is to be isolation and kisses
actually some of them do get rid of
everything but we'll take that offline
all right let's talk wait atomicity so
as I said already there are two outcomes
of our transaction either it commits
and all our changes get get % or get
could apply to the database all at once
or it gets aborted because of some you
know either data says so or application
says so so again what we're providing
the guarantee were providing to our
application is that that any transaction
that we execute all the changes will be
atomic meaning they'll all appears that
they happen exactly at the same time so
again it just means that either
everything happens or none of it happens
so no matter what happens if I say I
commit then I know everything got got
saved so let's look at two scenarios
where we could have problems atomicity
and then we'll see how I actually want
to solve it so again my beloved example
I'm taking a hundred dollars out of my
account and putting it to another
account but then we we take the money
out of my account but then the
transaction gets aborted the machine
doesn't crash the data says noes crash
we just get aborted the second scenario
is when you can take the hundred hours
out but now there's a power failure and
everything that the data systems running
is lost we come back and what should be
the correct state of the database all
right so there's two ways we could
possibly handle this the most common
approach is to do logging so nice a
logging I don't mean like you know the
log debug messages you're using for your
projects right I mean something like
right ahead logging but we're actually
recording our file on disk here's all
just that we're making so what will
happen is the David Simmons gonna run
and as it runs a transaction every for
every change I make to the database
every update or write I do to the
database I'm gonna make a copy of what
the old value was that I'm overwriting
and then that way if I crash or my
transaction gets aborted I had the old
value sitting around and I can go back
and put it back in place so that when my
transaction gets cleaned up after an
abort all the original batteries were
still there and so the way this is going
to work is that this is going to be
we're gonna maintain these undo records
both in memory and on disk and that way
again if we crash while if the
transaction is aborted while we're
running then if it's in memory we just
go reverse things real quickly but if
stuff
written a disk and then we crash then we
have our log records on theirs on disk
that we can then load back in when we
turn the data system on and and
reconcile put us back in the correct
state so in a high level you can sort of
think of the log as the black box and an
airplane like if there's a major any
airplane crash as a major crash but if
an airplane crashes what the government
goes and looks funds looks at the black
box all right because that's gonna
record information about what actually
is you know what happened in the plane
at the moment that it crashed and then
it tries to figure out what was the
error what was the malfunction now in
the in the airplane case they can't put
the airplane back together and the
database can okay so we can put it back
together
all right that's that's what we're gonna
use that form so logging at a high level
right will be used by almost everything
we'll make data system that's out there
any database system that says that
they're adorable to disk chances are
they're using log so in addition to you
know having the ability to roll back
things and guarantee atomicity logins
gonna provide us additional benefits in
terms of both performance and high level
concept of high level criteria we may
have for application on organization so
it's going to turn out that when we
start talking about logging since no
discs are expensive right - we can turn
random writes into sequential writes
through a log all right and that'll make
the system run faster and then for other
applications the log is actually
essentially going to be you know a audit
trail everything a single thing every
single thing your application did then
you can use that to figure out what was
happening if you ever have an audit or
to have questions about know my
application did this at this time
because and then there was a breach what
data I got red or what data I got you
got got written so in a lot of financial
companies they maintain me they have to
maintain the the log that data students
generate for the last seven years
because of a government regulation so
this is this is a good example where I
can use the log for atomicity but also
get additional benefit from it so the
other approach to guarantee atomicity
that's less common is called shadow
paging and this is actually the example
that I mentioned the beginning the class
where I said for every single
transaction I'm gonna make a copy of the
database file on disk all my changes go
to
copy and then when my transaction
commits I just swing a pointer and say
this is now the this is now the master
version so that's essentially what
shadow paging is but instead of copying
the single file every single time
they'll just copy the individual pages
that the transaction modifies when it
runs and then when in transaction
commits again you swing a pointer and
say all right all of these shadow copy
pages are now the master copy pages so
this is the one of the oldest ideas in
database systems this was event about
IBM in the 1970s and system R this turns
out to be super slow and problematic for
managing data on disk and when IBM went
to go build db2 which is the second day
the relational data system they built
after system are they didn't do any of
this they went with the logging approach
because you end up with fragmentation
and it with unordered data sets and it
gets and it gets slower so as far as you
know today the only two database systems
that actually do this is shadow paging
approach is CouchDB and LM DB they say
it's for performance reasons it's not
that common everyone else is gonna do is
gonna do logging so this is question yes
oh yes this one keep going this one so
for this one this one is it's the same
operation take money around account put
in your account this is like we get a
Bourdon like the user says abort my
transaction everything's still in memory
how do I roll that back this is like a
hard crash how do I come back from that
and so the point I was trying to make
here was the the log information is
gonna reside both in memory and
eventually also get written out to disk
because if it's in memory then I can
quickly go get it and flip you know flip
back the old buttons right if I pour it
if I do a hard crash if it's on disk
then I can reverse things potentially
right when I wouldn't want to load the
system back up because again after a
hard crash all the contents of a buffer
pool are gone and we in you know we need
to figure out what was happening at the
system at the time
crash to put us back in the correct
state yes so this question is does this
require writing to disk reads
transaction yes if you care about this
okay if you care about not losing data
yes we'll cover that later
LM dB
this question is is there any why would
you ever watch you want to do this I'd
if you it doesn't work right so we so we
a few years ago my first my first PC
student he and I started building a new
system using like the new Intel
non-volatile memory devices and we
thought at the time that with really
fast storage like non-volatile memory
he's like almost as fast as DRAM with
really fast storage to do random access
that shadow paging would actually turn
out to be a better approach like taking
an old idea from the 70s and running on
like today's hardware it doesn't work
right ahead of all games always move
faster because you can do these
sequential writes you know you can batch
a bunch of things together and then
shove amount all the disk at once with
shadow paging it's all this
fragmentation you're copying things
every single time it becomes very
expensive well see multi-version
concurrency troll which is sort of like
this but you instead of copying an
entire page before I make a change I
maybe just copy a tuple or a subset of
the tuple so shadow paging is sort of
how multi virtual control works but its
shadow paging as defined by IBM is
nobody does except for these guys yes to
their login stuff yes so I don't spend
too much time on running out the desk
but the question is is it the case that
I if I do much changes I create some
some undo undo records that are in
memory but then I crash before it's
written out the disk is that a problem
no because when I come back all my
memories gone
and the therefore I'm going to load the
database back up based on how it was on
disk and so because those changes never
got persisted to disk they're there as
if they never happened so his question
which is which is a good point is that
do I have is this mean have to do if I
know if I want to say my transaction is
committed do I have to do an S Inc do I
do a flush every single time my
transaction commits and I answer is yes
but you don't really do it on every
single commit you batch a bunch together
and then do a group commit when you
flush them out all together that
advertises the F sync costs over time
but if you dare if you want to guarantee
that your data is actually durable you
happen you have to write the disk well
seem so but the tricky thing is gonna be
in what order you write to disk it's
gonna matter a lot to so you have to
make sure you write the log record that
correspond to a change to a data page
first before you write the data page to
disk
we'll cover what's in a whole day on
this as well and at the point of
checking make I made about like oh well
the no sequel guys don't always provide
acid some of them would actually not
even flush to disk when if they had
transactions they would not trust a disk
exactly when you say you know complete
my transaction they were sort of every
do it every 60 seconds so that means you
could crash and lose the last 60 seconds
of data some systems were even worse
than this I'll just say it straight up
right the early version of
is when you do it right it would mean Li
come back and say yeah I got your right
but in actually being do the right it's
a network Lera said yeah I got it and if
you wanted to make sure that you're
right actually occurred yet to come back
a second time and say did you actually
do that that was the default for them
for like four or five years and their
early benchmark moments were amazing
because like they would do these rights
and of course it's like yeah I get it no
problem right but didn't actually do it
there's some fix that company fall
anymore okay so any questions by
atomicity
again what we'll cover that how we
actually guarantee this in a second so
consistency as I said before is this
nebulous term about correctness of the
database so at a high level the way to
think about this what a database
actually is is trying to model some some
concept or aspect of the real world like
my my database for my bank is trying to
model the old days of a bank where
somebody would sit in a ledger and
record how much money you actually had
in your account right it's modeling some
some process in the real world so we're
gonna say that if we have our database
be logically correct meaning we don't
care has actually actually physically
stored but the data integrity the
referential integrity all those things
are correct then any questions we asked
about that our database will produce
correct results and again that sounds
very vague so let me go in or detail
there's two types of consistency we
could possibly have now database
consistency and transaction consistency
the spoiler would be database
consistency is the one we actually care
about we can actually we can't do the
second one and we'll see why in a second
so again the our krampus criteria is
that our database actually reflects what
the real world looks like and so how do
we actually enforce that well we provide
the data system with integrity
constraints to say this is this is what
it means to for us to have correct data
so for example if I have a table of
people or students and I'm keeping track
of their age I can have an integrity
constraint that says nobody's age could
be less than zero all right there's no
negative negative ages and so the data
system could enforce that it sometimes
insert something with a negative age you
can say that's you can't have that in
the real world I can't let you insert
that data the other way to think about
to also is that the so now in addition
to these have experience now as
transactions to start making changes to
the database that any transaction that
excuse in the future should be able to
see the changes the correct the correct
changes that a transaction in the past
made so what does that mean so if I of
transaction say I want run transaction
right now and I make some change in the
database if you now run a transaction
one minute later long as nobody has
overwritten my changes I you should be
able to see my updates so in a single
node database this is not that big you
know this is not that big of a deal
all right so my transaction commits I
give back the acknowledgement that I
committed then you come along and now do
another transaction on that same machine
and you read might you should we're
gonna read my rights right away
so for a single no database this is not
that big this is not really an issue
when this matters more is the
distributed databases so now if I'm
trying to guarantee strong consistency
in my distributed database if I do a
write and I update some some account and
then you come one millisecond later on
another machine for the same logical
database but on the separate physical
machine and you start you now do a read
you should be able to see my change if I
if I told the outside world that my
transaction committed alright so this
will matter more then for the Shiva
databases because the no sequel guys
will have this thing called adventurer
Kristin C will say I'll propagate
changes eventually and not guarantee
that everyone sees the exact same state
of the device at the exact same time but
for our purposes today a single new
database it doesn't really make sense it
won't be an issue so the other type of
constancy is transactional consistency
and this one again is very hand wavy but
it basically says that if the database
is consistent before transaction runs
and our transaction is consistent then
after we run our transaction the N state
of the database should be consistent all
right so what does it mean to be you
know consistent or correct right that's
a higher level concept that we can't
reason about in our database right we
can try to enforce some some integrity
constraints and we prevent the
transaction from doing you know making
some changes but you know if if my
application says there should be no
customer with an account that has you
know at CMU edu email address and my
transaction go ahead goes ahead and
actually tries to do that I I can't stop
that in my database that's not a bad
it's not a good example because I you
know it's me rephrase that let's say
there's the application says that nobody
taking this class is allowed to have an
account on my on this one system but my
database doesn't have access to whether
you're enrolled in this class or not so
the transact
allowed to go ahead and do that and the
DA says okay sure you want to do this in
sir I'm allowed to do that but that's
this high level concept this higher
level constraint but the data stuff
doesn't know anything about it so
therefore the transaction can consistent
and therefore we can't stop that so you
know this is this is something that we
can't simply just can't do in our
database system we can we can enforce
integrity constraints a referential
integrity constraints we can't afford
level things because we just don't know
because it's a human value judgment that
we can't codify in our system so there's
there's nothing really else to say about
this like if you understand the high
level what I'm talking about and that's
it right that's all that matters okay
all right so the moment the other one we
care about today is also isolation so
isolation again is saying that if our
transaction if we if we have our user
submitting users many more transactions
we want each of them to run assuming
that they're running by themself and the
reason why we want to provide this this
guarantee is that it's a it makes it way
easier to programmer application our
logic in our transactions if that's the
case we assume that we have exclusive
access to the database we don't have to
worry about any intermediate data we
could be reading from other transactions
then you know we just write our
single-threaded code and that's fine and
it makes life easier so we can achieve
that we can achieve this by doing again
my straw man approach in the beginning
where I just have a single thread
actually one by one but I said that we
want to be able to interleave
transactions to achieve better
parallelism at concurrency and so we see
if you want to be able guarantee this
illusion property but we still want to
interleave this that becomes difficult
and so the way we're going to provide
this way we're going to do this is
through a concurrent roll protocol so
we've already talked about control
protocols slightly when we talked about
index latching maybe we would have a
single data structure and allow multiple
threads to access it at the same time
and we use our latches to enforce the
the correctness of our data structure so
now we're gonna do the same thing but
for our database objects this is why I
was making the distinguish between locks
and latches so latches are protecting
the internals of the data structure
locks are gonna protect these database
objects so you think I'll call as like
the traffic cop for for the database
system right it's it's sitting saying
this we can let this operation go this
operation has to wait or this operation
has to abort it's it's trying to figure
out how to interleave things in a way
that we end up with a correct state so
there's two categories of protocols that
we're gonna care about and then this
will this always cover on on next week
right Italy both of these so the first
one is a pessimistic protocol where
we're gonna assume that our transactions
are going to conflict to cause problems
so we require them to acquire locks
before it allowed to do anything right
you assume that you know you're
pessimistic we assume that there's many
problems so you you you you make sure
that there's you make sure that things
go in the correct order by using locks
obstinate sticker troll is where you
assume that the conflicts are rare most
of the time my transactions aren't going
to conflict so rather than making them
stall and acquire it locks at the very
beginning I just let them run and do
whatever they want and then when they go
to commit go back and figure out whether
that was actually the right thing to do
whether there was a conflict so Monday's
class next week will be on two-phase
locking
that's a pessimistic protocol
Wednesday's class next week will be on
timestamp ordering that's considered an
optimistic protocol and optimistic
encouraged goal protocol was actually
better here at CMU in the 1980s all
right so let's look now at some some
real examples start understanding what
it actually mean to have complex so
again this is my bank account example
where we have two accounts a and B it's
Andy and is bookie and so we want to
transfer 100 dollars out of my account
into my bookies account but then at the
same time the bank runs action where
it's going to update the the monthly
interest of all the bank accounts so
we're going to update every account with
an add 6% interest I so transaction one
is taking hundred dollars out of a put a
hundred dollars and B and then
transaction two is just computing
you're incrementing both accounts by
adding six percent so if we assume that
again both bank accounts have a thousand
dollars
and we want to EXCI at these two
transactions what are the possible
outcomes we could have for the state of
the database
all right zooming we have arbitrary
interleavings well many right because we
could have t1 maybe go do run run in one
query then switch over to t2 then back
and forth right there's a bunch of runt
ways we can end up with these
interleavings but the important thing to
point out though is that at the end of
the day after we execute transaction t1
and t2 in any possible order to know
that our database state is correct the
final result when we add both the
accounts together should be 2120 because
I have a thousand dollars than a
thousand dollars to be add that together
that's two thousand and then the second
transaction wants to add six percent
interest so we want to guarantee that no
matter how we order or interleave our
operations we always at the end after
executing t1 and t2 we end up with 2120
so this is a very important property
about transactions and database systems
that's gonna be slightly different than
maybe how you you you know or have
experienced parallel programming before
so in a database system that we're talk
about here even though t1 may be
submitted to the data system first
followed by t2 there's no guarantee the
database system is gonna run t1 first
right and the reason why we're gonna do
this is because because we can have any
possible interleaving or any any
possible ordering then this is gonna
allow us to open up more opportunities
to do interleaving to get better
parallelism if I care my application
absolutely had to care say well t1
absolutely has to exit first then
followed by t2 the way you would write
that code is you admit t1 and then only
when you get back to your knowledge
meant that t1 committed then you submit
T 2 coz the you can't guarantee that now
in practice if you if you submit t1 and
if you know it takes a minute then you
submit t2 that's basically the same
thing but if I sit vice with them at
exactly the same time then the data's
could enter leave them and it anyway it
wants
but what we're gonna care about those
that for any arbitrary interleaving we
want the end state of the database to be
equivalent to one where we actually
execute these transactions in Syria
order with a single thread either t1
followed by t2 or t2 followed by t1 the
end state of the day this has to look
like Val so now that means that the the
number of possible outcomes we could
have are for the state a and B could be
different right so if I have say t1 go
first all by t2
I'll have 954 dollars in a and and 11
$66 and B but I go the other order
I'll have 960 and 1160 but again if I
add both of these together I always get
2120 and that's again that's equivalent
to one where the xu2 in serial order
this clip all right so let's actually
look at what the database sees so for
this this is this is called a schedule
for our transactions in a way to read
this is that going from the top to
bottom for time and then for each of
these columns here we have the
transactions and we have the operations
that they're actually doing so I call
began on t1 I take a hundred dollars out
of a take put a hundred hours and B and
I call commit and then now annex --an
time I do a context switch over here and
now I call it t1 and it computes the
interest in these guys so for this
assume that we only have a single thread
that can with a single program counter
and we can only actually one operation
at a time like we can interleave them of
these different transactions but at any
given time step we going do one thing so
in this case here if we x2 t1 followed
by t2 we end up with this this amounts
for a and B if he asked you t2 first
followed by t1 we end with these amounts
here so again a doesn't match as 954
over here at 960 over here so they're
technically different from what you know
from a from a finite exact amount but
from a databases assistance perspective
for what we're caring about with
transactions you add them both up and
you always get 2120 so both of these
interleavings are both of these
orderings are still are equivalent to
each other they're correct
yes sorry your question your question is
if you know that you have you to
transactions exactly the same time could
you do it we're like you could you
combine them yes but nobody does it that
way and I think that would complicate
things right now let's just assume that
this is the case also say to what I'm
showing here or like yeah here's why
here's why you can't really do that so
when I'm gonna talk about here today are
like the the schedule is fixed meaning
I know ahead of time exactly what all
the transactions actually want to do in
a real system it's not like that in a
real system you have like you know
transactions are showing up they're
calling you know a client opens
connection calls begin and then it
starts executing a bunch of queries and
you don't know what the next query is in
this case here sort of to reason about
correctness you see everything all at
once
right so on Monday when we talk about
two-phase locking
that's a dynamic conquerer protocol
where you don't know what the queries
are gonna be ahead of time now there's
some cases where if you have some
introspection but with the applications
actually trying to do then you can
actually do what you propose but that's
hard nobody actually does that will get
that too so case question is which is
correct I said before the data sent only
sees reads and writes water of this 8
equals a minus 1 right yes that will get
translated to a read followed by right
I'll see that in a sec yes yes yeah
we'll get to that yes question is so
this 8 equal a minus 100 what is it
actually gonna look like well in the
program logic I would say do a get on a
you're reading a have a copy my local
variable then I can manipulate it and
and write it back to the database so
each of these transactions would have
their own local variables that aren't
shared these questions can you believe
the operation between transactions yes
we'll get there exactly yes the question
is if I have two transactions that are
touching completely different objects
not to post objects do I need to still
serialize this what I mean so for this
one I'm just tryna show equivalency if
they touch clearly three things and
there's no conflicts then you can
interleave them any way you want
absolutely yes her question is how do I
know whether another transaction is
touching the same thing I'm touching
again but this is a high-level example
the database seeds and reads and writes
so I do it I do a read on an object a
you do a read an object a in order for
me to serve your read request ask me to
read it for you so I see everything but
I don't see high-level things like I
don't see that your your that you're
going to take the value of a and then
add 6% to it
so again what everyone's sort of getting
up to now is be able to interleave these
these transactions really the operations
and we've already covered this we want
to do this because this is slow and we
have a lot of CPU cores and so the idea
here is again that instead of having the
you know if we have to go to disk to get
something or wait to acquire a latch on
something we could have one transaction
stall another transaction keep on
running and still make forward progress
so we're trying to figure out a schedule
or interleaving such that we maximize
the performance of the system and we get
the best utilization of our hardware so
if we go back here now to our example so
now I made of leaving our transactions
right going start takes 200 out of a
then then does a context switch t2
starts put compute 6% on
hey then we go back and take put the
hundred dollars back on B and go back
here compute the three inches on that
and then we go commit so now again now
it's not one turns actually wanting
running in its entirety at a time right
we're now able to actually interleave
things and this example here this is
correct this is fine because this is
this is equivalent to a serial ordering
of our transactions right the end state
of the database is equivalent alright
and so the key thing to point out here
is that the reason why this worked out
okay and then we end up equivalent is
that we always make sure that we did the
operations on t1 first before on a given
object before we did that operation on
on t2 for that same object so I took a
hundred Oz at a and then I keep you to
the interest on a and then I put it on
while back and B and then a computer
enjoy some beat right so for this for
this interleaving here is if we violate
that so I take $1 out of a I compute
there's interest on a then I can fit the
interest on B then I put $200 back on B
so now in this case here the when I add
up these two values together I don't get
21 28 2014 so the bank lost you know $10
or 606 dollops all right now here's the
hundreds of dollars but it's a billion
dollars all right guys it's your account
hundred dollars is a lot but like you
know this is why we want to guarantee
that we always have correctness for
transactions especially when you're
doing and ending involves money there's
a famous example a few years ago where
some Bitcoin exchange I forget where in
the world was running on MongoDB MongoDB
did at the time didn't have support
transactions and so some hacker figured
out that you can have you can manipulate
the the API and have it drain out
everyone's account so they wiped out the
Bitcoin exchange in a single day because
MongoDB wasn't doing transactions that's
part of the story but they didn't have
transactions that's a bad idea
so came back to his point well what if
the database system actually seen again
it doesn't see these higher-level
operations it just sees these reason
right
and so essentially we're trying to do is
make sure that for any object that does
a read or does a write or read on an
object if another transaction is doing
the same thing we're always going in in
the right order to determine whether our
schedule is correct so the way we're
going to figure this out
the way we're going to find correctness
for what we're talking about here today
is well say that a schedule of any
arbitrary ordering of operations is
correct if it's equivalent to one of a
serial schedule so the Sira schedule
we've already talked about Serie
schedules just saying that we actually
transactions one after another and no
interleaving and then the equivalent
sleep policy says that if the final
state of the database is a of the of the
the objects is equivalent or it has
actually the same values of another
database state than they are equivalent
so a a ordering of a schedule well it
could be equivalent to at least one
exactly one serial ordering I'm not
exactly one one or more serial orderings
if the database is still the same
statement but a given schedule could be
correct it could still be serializable
by being equivalent to any possible
serial ordering so this is the form of
property we're going to care about for
our schedules serializability okay it
just says that a schedule is that is
equivalent to some serial execution
doesn't matter which one it has to be it
has to be one of them if that it's
equivalent that serial ordering then
whatever schedule what we're looking at
is considered to be serializable and
this is the gold standard of what you
want to get in a database net system
like this this is this is guaranteeing
almost guaranteeing all the protections
you could ever want the only one who
doesn't guarantee is that if your
transaction is t1 shows up first
followed by t2 t1 will commit first
that's called a strict serialize ability
or external consistency we don't care
about that here most systems don't
provide that the only system to provide
that that I'm aware of is Google spanner
and they need it for some you know some
some global ads thing this must don't do
that most of this if they say the
support sterilized ability they're
getting
you're getting what I'm defining here
okay
so again coming if you come over
background from parallel programming
this might seem kind of weird that I
could say all right well I can have the
you know there's not one single state of
the database that I could say this is
what it exactly should be to determine
whether it's correct right it could be
any possible thing and the reason why we
want to do this is because if we have
multiple choices for how we want to
interleave our operations and multiple
serial orderings that we could that we
get a aspire to achieve then that gives
us more options to decide how we want to
schedule our operations for our
transactions so to understand this bit
better we now need a formal way to
determine what it means to have a
conflict that could violate the serial
ordering or sir lies ability of a
transaction so we're gonna say is that
two transactions or two operations are
going to conflict if they're if they're
being run by different transactions at
the same time and they're both operating
on the same object and at least one of
those operations is a right so there's
three types on anomalies we're gonna
care about we have read write write read
and write write again y know read read
conflicts just yeah it doesn't matter
who cares like if you read something and
I read something we read the same thing
that's fine who cares it's when we have
rights and when we it's one of the
operations as a right is when we have
problems but so let's go through each of
these one by one so the first one is
read write conflicts all right this is
also sometimes called on a repeatable
read so let's say I have two
transactions t1 t2 t1 screen to a read
or knife and then read only again t2 is
gonna read on a file by a write or name
so let's say I actually run this t1
starts does the read on a gets $10 out
of my bank account then there's a
context which we start running t2 t2
reads on a sees $10 that's that's fine
but then it writes back $19 then it goes
heads and commits and we get back to
your knowledge but from the database
system to say that our transaction
committed but then now our transaction
switches back the contact switch back
over to t1 t1 now does it read and again
gets back 19 but the first time I read a
I got 10 so I'm trying to read the same
object I'm not getting the same value I
so that's I'm repeating what we try to
read something I'm not seeing the same
thing over and over again and again if
we're trying to guarantee isolation and
for our transactions it should not see
this this change over here because if
we're running this was in serie or
during t1 should've just run completely
and then finish and then t2 would iran
right so that that couldn't happen under
a serial order next conflict is write
read also sometimes called dirty reads
so so now T ones we do a read on a file
I write an A and the teachers gonna do
also do a reader name followed by writer
named T one reads egg sees $10 then it
writes back $12 now t t2 reads a and it
sees the $12 that the first guy put in
right but then now it writes back $14
then the ghost hasn't commits and then
you know we get back acknowledgment from
the database system say yeah you
committed you're good to go
but now we do our context which we come
back over here and now our first guy
aborts so he said there's no partial
transactions so this guy has to abort so
we need to roll back our update but the
problem was that this other transaction
here already read my update and then a
committed and it's hold the outside
world but yeah when I read a I sold I
saw $12 but that shouldn't have happened
because again we can't that's a
temporary inconsistent inconsistency we
made a change to a that mean we have to
make the change in order to actually you
know pilot change of the database but
nobody should have been able to see that
change because our transaction didn't
commit and furthermore because we
aborted now we leak something into the
outside world that shouldn't shouldn't
have appeared the last conflict is write
rights and this is overriding
uncommitted data so t1 does it right on
a puts in $10 t2 doesn't read a write on
a puts in $19 without reading it then
dates B inputs an Andy and then over
here t2 t1 starts running again
and it writes in beaver so now when we
go to commit what's the issue well I
have two objects a and B and so for for
a I'm seeing the the write that the T to
put in there it put in nineteen dollars
but for object B I'm seeing Justin
Bieber because that's what t1 put in so
I have a torn-up date right I have I
have data that I have two objects
they've been modified by two different
transactions when they both shouldn't
modified atomically by one transaction
and this occurred because you know this
guy got to go got to go running while
this guy was still running and that
shouldn't happen if we were trying to
guarantee you see row ordering so now
given these conflicts we need to
understand more formally you know how
did she prove whether something's
actually sterilizable so in the sake of
time I'm gonna I'm gonna skip complex
realisability or sorry we did you
definitely know calm let's turtle eyes
review I'm gonna I'm gonna skip user
lies ability complex utilizability
it's what you need to know for the for
the homeworks I'll post on on Piazza the
link to the lecture from last class last
year what that talks like we
survivability I did it's the same
material that would have cover but we're
at a time right so most eighty systems
are going to try to give you this if
they say these supports utilize what
have to nor transactions the
serializable serializable isolation
level they'll give you this nobody does
this one because this requires
high-level information about what the
applications trying to do and we can't
get that automatically all right so now
we're going to find our a new term and
say that two schedules are considered to
be conflict equivalent if and only if
they are involved in the same set of
operations and transactions running in
at the same time and then every pair of
conflicting transactions are ordered in
the same way so again a conflicting
transactions when were they're actually
trying to update turn to a read or write
on an object
rate to transactions ones either read or
write and ones either a read or write
they always have to have at least one
right so we'll say a schedule s is
conflict serializable
if it's complement to some serial
schedule so the way we're going to
figure out how to determine whether
something's complex are liable is by
just swapping the order of non
completing operations the idea is that
we can do these swapping steps on
operations and that'll to push a bunch
of operations to the top for one
transaction put a bunch of operations to
the bottom for another transaction until
we end up with a serial order so going
back to this example here so we do a
read on a file write an A and read them
a peanut B file I read on B for t1 and
t2 so we have here we want to start
swapping here so we have a read on B and
a write on a so this case here they're
not touching the same object so I can go
ahead and swap their order I can make
read a read on B happen before the write
on a same thing the next one here the
read on B can happen before the read on
a I can swap their order that's fine now
I can do the same thing there's other
one the rewrite on B could happen before
the read on a write on a swap that the
right on B can happen for the read on a
can swap so I can do that so now I end
up with a serial ordering it's got
equipment to this one here so this is
the one where you can't do this so in
this case here I have a write on a file
by write on a I can't swap their order
so therefore it's it's not equivalent to
a serial ordering right this is pretty
straightforward but of course now this
is kind of like stupid to do right like
what if I have a lot of transactions and
I have a lot of operations this is gonna
be very expensive for me to do so we
need a better way to figure out to
determine whether something is is gonna
be serializable or not without having to
do this the swapping thing and so the
way we can do this is through a
dependency graph and the textbook I
think calls this a precedence graph so
dependency graph is just gonna say we're
have a node for every single transaction
in our schedule and that will have an
edge between two transactions if there's
some operation in one transaction
conflicts with another operation in the
other transaction and the first
operation of court occurs earlier and
then schedule than the other other
transaction right and
so if I look at my entire schedule and I
generate my dependency graph if I see a
cycle then I know that it's not
sterilized well because I won't be able
to swap their ordering but if there's no
cycles than it is conflict serializable
so let's look at this example here that
we had before so in this case here I
have a right on a followed by a read on
a so the write on a conflicts with a
read on a obviously and the write on a
and T one happens before the read on a
and T 2 so I'll have an edge from t1 to
t2 and I label it for the object egg
same thing here I have a right on B for
B so I have an edge from t2 to t1 on B
and now at this point I have a cycle so
therefore I know that this this ordering
is not complex at high school again just
looking at the code this is the the
justin beiber example i have before i do
a read on a follow i run on a here then
reading a a follow right on a real don't
be fall that right on b then read on be
fall by right on B so I would have the
update to be how occur from t1 and the
update to a would occur at t2 and that's
a torn update so let's get even crazier
now we'd have an arbitrary number of
transactions so in this case here I have
a read on B and a right on B so I have
an edge from t2 to t1 on B and just keep
going down the line one by one right and
then we end up something like this so
the question is is this is this
considered equivalent yes because we can
take any arbitrary take or during t2 t1
t3 and that'll end up with the correct
zero order but we want it so but if we
generate the dependency graph just look
to see whether we have a cycle that'll
tell us whether we're conflicts at alive
or not huh all right
we have a little more time we keep going
okay um let's look let's bring back now
the operations we had before these
high-level things that the application
may want to do so now we still have our
Reason rights but now I'm showing you
like what the program actually program
logic is actually doing so the reason
rights are always going to the database
but any of these other operations like
you know B equals B plus 10 these are
happening within the applications action
state so any change I make the B is not
written to the database into I have to
do the right on B all right so in this
case here I never going to point out too
is like what we're doing and this one
here we're taking ten dollars at a one
account and then putting ten dollars in
this account the second transaction I
just want to compute the sum of the
total amount of money that are in a and
B and then this is like this fake echo
command this is not a real thing I'm
just showing this for demonstration
purposes this is just printing out to
you returning the actual sum of the two
values so in this case here right we
would we want to generate a dependency
graph we have a write on a and read on a
so we have an edge from t1 to t2 on a
bin down here we have a read on write on
B and a read on B so we would have an
edge going the other direction on B so
we have a cycle so therefore this is not
conflict sterilizable but there is
actually a way for first if we can
modern we could potentially modify this
application and do something different
than just computing the sum this way
where we could end up with something
that would still follow in the same
state as a serial ordering of a
transaction but it would actually not be
conflict serializable because of this
cycle up here so instead of just me
going reading a and then adding to my
sum and reading being added to my sum
what if instead of actually giving them
the exact sum for both accounts what do
I just want to know what are the total
number accounts that have more than zero
dollars I'm computing a counter the
number accounts that are greater than
greater than zero so if I rewrote my
application to say if a greater than
equal to zero add one to my counter then
in that case when I print out my count
sure even though I interleaved my-my-my
transaction while t1 was still running
and that money was missing assuming that
I did have
exactly $10 and they didn't go negative
then this thing would actually still
produce the correct result so what's up
with that that's kind of weird right I
said complex realisability says that I
need to end up the same stated the same
state of the database so the same result
as if I was running a serial ordering
but in this case here I'm not complex
there Eliza below getting the same
result on the same state of database as
if I was running in a Serie ordering so
this is what view serializable T is and
again the spoiler is that nobody
actually does this because it requires
us to have some reasoning about what the
hell's the application or transaction
that you're trying to do here to know
whether it's okay for me to interleave
them by plopping these guys in the
middle of these other ones here so this
what I was saying nobody actually does
this but it's actually a really
interesting concept and eventually you
know maybe 50 years from now people have
better programming models and
programming application frameworks where
we could actually do use turtle eyes
ability but it does it doesn't exist
today it's only theoretical
so let's look another example here so we
have three transactions running T
moments do a read on a a follow I write
on a and then T 2 and T 3 are doing what
I call blind writes on a so we're
writing to a without actually reading it
first which we could do so again if I
just go through and generate my
dependency graph we're gonna generate a
bunch edges and we have a cycle so we
therefore we know that it's that it's
not complex or let sterilizable but if I
just actually look at the transaction a
little bit well I see well assuming that
these are the only transactions that are
running at this right now which we said
that was the case T 1 doesn't read on a
file I write an 82 doesn't write on at a
but in the end the day the answer to
database the only thing that matters is
this last write on T 3 so this ordering
here is actually views view equivalent
to one where I xq to them in this order
like this so as long as T 3 is the last
write that get that gets persisted to
the data is a who cares how these other
ones up here about interleaved but I
need to know that in my in my
application it's ok for this thing to be
the last writer
and as I said next class when we talk
talked about two phase locking
transactions are showing up in arbitrary
orderings at different times that you
know during during execution and you
don't know exactly what they're gonna be
doing ahead of time so you can't
guarantee this so just real quickly skip
all this the way to think about the
these schedules that we talked about is
that you have this universe of all
possible orderings of schedule or all
possible schedule orderings you could
have for any training transaction in
your in your application right that's
this giant space here it's any possible
ordering but but you're not in regarding
you're not even considering what it
means to be correct or not the then you
a smaller portion here of vary ordering
all right these are ones where exiting
transactions one after another and then
around that would be conflict
serializable where again these are some
inter Lehman's that may not be serial it
includes all stereo orderings but
includes ones that aren't and then
around that will be the view
sterilizable orderings yes yes coming
back cuz again so say the this is what
I'm given and I would say run these
transactions again I'm not wearing a
transaction showing up arbitrarily it's
saying this is what I have I want to run
this right now what's the end there's
only one object in the database so the
only thing I'm gonna see after I run
these transactions is what's this what's
the value of a and so who cares that t1
and t2 wrote a because t3 is gonna
overwrite it so at the end of day all
what matters is whatever this guy wrote
who cares what these guys actually did
what correct this one not work in the
first example what is the first example
yeah taking money I don't want to count
put in another account computing the
interest yes
this is just meant to illustrate the
concept okay so I'm gonna skip all this
for transaction durability we've already
covered this that's the log itself and
we'll spend a whole week on this the
asset properties we've already covered
atavistic insisting I slay ssin today
moves to focus on these two we'll cover
this more distributed databases we'll
cover this for login checkpoints but for
next week we're gonna focus on these
these two further so the the last thing
I'll just sort of say too is that
commercial is hard it's hard to get
correct hard to get performed well this
is why a lot of newer database systems
that come along
except for more recently they initially
did not support transactions because
they said they want to get best
performance and they didn't worry about
you know running transaction they wanted
to make sure the system was always
available and you know they didn't want
to burden burden themself with
transactions and so the the thing I
always like to point out though is
Google in the 19 2004 2005 they were
sort of the Harbinger or the vanguard of
the new sequel system they put out this
thing called BigTable they said joins
are slow sequel slow transactions are
slow we're not gonna do any of that and
then like seven or eight years later
after everyone's sort of copied what
Google had done like a Sondra a
bunch of other key value stores HBase
they came out this paper called on
spanner which is their transactional
database system that they use internally
and there's this great line in the paper
that says that for their programmers
they think it's better to provide an
abstraction or programming model that
uses transactions because that's easier
for them the reason about the
correctness of the program of whether
the rachie doing the right operations in
the right order it's better for the have
baby you know the the the unwashed
masses your average you know Rando
javascript program or whatever they're
using you read them all program to using
the transaction programming model and
then instead you have a bunch of really
smart people that can do the systems
development like Jeff Dean they're jobs
that worried about how to make those
transactions go faster so transactions
are super important every system that
they didn't have them before is now
trying to start to add them
because again it's it provides all these
nice guarantees that you want to have in
your system okay
again I'm rushing I apologize but I
won't quickly when I get through a
project for you real quickly all right
so project reads out which your building
is the query execution engine for bus
tub so what you're gonna end up
implementing is the executors for the
actual query plan operators so say you
have a query pan like this then for each
of these operators you're going to
generate this executor that's gonna
follow the iterator model that we talked
about where they'll all have an X
function that shoves up you know you
call next on the OP on the executor and
it gives you back either the next tuple
that it has or a null pointer to say
that it's it's done okay so you guys are
doing it could be single threaded
execution no exchange operators and you
don't have to worry about transactions
you don't have to worry about you know
doing updates or deletes so what do you
have to what do you have to build so the
first thing we're asking you to do is
build out the catalog there's allows you
to install install tables into the
database and then go back and get those
tables back from the Cal using the name
or the internal turn-on identify ER and
then you're building executors for
insert central scans hash joints and
hash aggregation for the hash join you
can implement it first using a you know
in-memory hash table that will provide
you but the ultimate goal is that you
want to use your linear probe hash table
that you built from project two because
that allow you to do joins for on tables
that don't fit in disk so you can do the
first two tasks without having to do
that working linear probe hash table the
last one will require you to have that
one working so even up the catalog
insert an executor first because
obviously you can't do special scans
unless you have data in your database
you don't need to worry about any
transactions and then when posted this
on Piazza and I'll just emphasize this
again great scope is not meant to be for
debugging right we if you submit it and
it takes a half an hour or four starts
running we can't fix that right that's
up to great scope there's a queue of
other students with 100 unit hunter
students in the class he's not gonna run
right away so we provide some basic
tests as a framework to figure out how
to write more tests but he's you doing
as much as all the development want to
figure out what your problem is to be
done locally and then if you find this
thing timing out because it's running
too slow you should figure out why your
system is running flow locally don't
make a bunch of you know minor
changes and keep submitting them to
great scope and try to measure how long
great script takes you can figure these
things out locally so we've already
covered this don't shoot any file and
then once we give you you want to rebase
over the bus-stop master there's
instruction Piazza how to do this and
then come to office hours if you have
questions I always have to say this
don't plagiarize we will destroy you
right because what'll happen is if we do
plagiarize new copy from other people
University comes back to me say hey did
you tell your students not to play
drives and I show them the video and I
guess here's me telling you not to
plagiarize don't plagiarize and that's
evidence against you you're screwed okay
all right next class again I will be
gone yes no we go on it's how we good
all right we'll recover TV's locking and
that'll build upon what we talked about
today okay guys
it's Wednesday nights in my system I'm
blessed
let's go get the next one get over now
good never be son ricochet jelly hit the
deli for a boat one naturally bless ya
what rappers like the laser beam the
boys in the bush say nothing like a king
wrap the bottle of us a nice sympathy
goes don't feel like drinking a pony -
you drunk you can't drop me at the stake
don't know you forget a pancake