[Music]
okay let's start it hi oh it's Thank You
DJ doctor girls okay so real quick some
announcements for the course in terms of
projects project 3 will be released
today ish tomorrow ish and that'll be
due in November on Sunday I just be
doing the 15th I've updated it yesterday
announced 2 on the Sunday on the 17th
how about 3 will be released next week
so I went to worry about that yet but
that'll be due before the before project
3 the other major announcement too is
that with my as I said in beginning of
the semester my wife is pregnant I think
it's mine and so they are taking it out
of her on on Wednesday night I had him
schedule it after the Sigma deadline on
Tuesday which is the big data based
conference so it's happening on
Wednesday so next week I won't be here
DJ drop tables will be here and then my
PG students will will teach those two
lectures and then depending on what
happens I should be back maybe the
following week or so we may adjust
there's that I think we wait they told
me originated was coming up to 30th so I
canceled class on the 30th but now it's
coming out whatever this Wednesday is or
Thursday so I might adjust whatever that
that day off is but the goal is to get
all the material you'll need to do
homework number 3 and in the next two
weeks okay any questions about this I
will post this on Piazza with with with
you know more information it's real
alright alright the other change also
too is that the original schedule was
that last class before the midterm was
all about query optimization we
obviously ran out of time so I've
decided to split that lecture now into
two parts so this is part two and then
I've dropped the lecture on embedded
database logic which is not really
something we need to note in or the
build of database system it's sort of
just a
with you for you guys to understand like
oh there's other things you can do other
than than just throwing sequel at the
database so if you're curious about that
you know I'll send the postal link on
Piazza you can watch last last year's
lecture on that topic query optimization
is kind of more important so I think
it's better to spend more time on this
okay all right so last class when we
started when query optimization we focus
on this first part here right how to do
apply rules and heuristics to make
changes to the to the query plan without
having to examine the data or understand
what the what the database actually
looks like on the inside we may need to
look at the catalog to understand what
our attributes are whether they're
unique or not and whether we have
foreign keys but we don't need to know
anything about you know our distribution
of values in the tables look look a
certain way or we have this number of
tuples all right so these are all rules
that we could do without actually
looking at understand you know what are
tuples look like so today now we're
gonna focus on the second part here
which is the more complicated part where
we're now we're going to use a cost
model to allow us to assess the the
quality or the amount of work we're
gonna have to do for a query plan
without before we even actually run it
and the idea here is that we want to be
able to enumerate as many query plans as
possible and then pick whatever which
one we think is the best and so the more
accurate our cost model is the more
accurate our selection will be for what
the best query plan is but as there
seems to go along it's this is super
hard and everybody's gonna get this
wrong and then what I'll teach you today
is a way so the textbook shows it tells
you how to do it which is which is
really really wrong but we'll talk about
little help we could possibly fix these
things but this is something we can
recover in the advanced class or if you
take more you know you can do people
have done dissertations on this kind of
thing and it's still still a unsolved
problem alright so today's agenda we're
going to first talk about how to do
again plan cost estimation with our cost
model they only talk about how to do a
numeration
how we're actually going to IntelliJ
intelligently iterate or different
possible query plans in order to find
the one that we think is the best right
because again this is np-hard we can't
do an exhaustive search so we we need to
be smart about what we're at
looking at and then we'll finish up
talking about necessaries because this
is slightly different than everything
else and there's rules we can use to to
rewrite them and to make them more
efficient so we already talked about
this last class we talked this we said
that you know what is a cost estimation
what is our cost model actually doing
and again it is essentially it's a way
to approximate how much work or how long
it's gonna take to execute a query and
in general you always want to pick the
one that's gonna have the lowest cost so
this cost could be a combination of a
bunch of different underlying harbor
metrics you know because that
corresponds to the work we're actually
going to do so it could just be how much
CPU were actually gonna use this is
typically very hard to do and we don't
do this for a disk based system because
the disk is the major bottleneck but an
in-memory system would care about this
we've already talked about how to do
counting disk i/o for our joint
algorithm the sort algorithms this is
probably the major thing that we're
going to focus on we also care about how
much memory we're gonna use there could
be one algorithm uses a lot of memory
and gets faster performance but we may
not have that much memory actually use
so therefore we want to choose a slower
algorithm that uses less memory because
that'll be less pressure on the system
and then for distributed databases it's
again it's the number of Network
messages is the high pole in the tent
because sending things over the wire to
between machines is always expensive and
so in general at a high level these are
all going to be a proxy for are we gonna
use the number of tuples we're gonna
access as a proxy for all these things
right essentially determining how much
data we're got we're gonna we're going
to pass from one opera to the next and
we can use that to derive which one we
think is the best so as I said we can't
just you know the way to get the most
accurate estimation of what a query plan
is gonna do is actually just execute the
query plan but if we're looking at
thousands and thousands of different
possible query plans we can't possibly
execute every single one so we need a
way to to approximate this and this is
what our cost model is going to do and
the underlying concept we're going to
use our underlying component in our
database system we're going to use to do
these estimations is the internal Cystic
catalogs of the database system so every
database system that does has a query
optimizer
that is using a call space search is
gonna have this insistence module which
is gonna allow it to collect information
about what the tables look like what are
actually what are actually inside of the
tuples and how you collect this
information can vary based on the
implementation so all the major systems
have a way to force the data system to
collect new statistics right analyze
analyze table update status run stats
this tells the de system hey do a
sequential scan on my table and update
my statistics information some systems
also come from this and cron jobs like
every every so often periodically just
do a pass all those systems can
piggyback off of the queries as they run
and say all right as I'm doing sponsor
scan I'll also update my statistics as I
go along other systems have triggers to
say if the 10% of my or 20% my table has
changed let me go fire off the run stats
command and update things right there's
no one way to do this better than
another a common setup would be you like
if you're running an OLTP system you
would disable this during the day when
you're doing most your transactions but
then at night time you can take take
passes through and update your stats so
during the day it's gonna be slightly
off but that's still gonna be okay
because this is expensive to do because
this thing and this is a sequential scan
on the entire table so let's gabble in a
little math but it's Andy math not hard
math so everyone should be able to
follow this
so the basic main information we're
gonna maintain about every table it's
just the number of tuples that they have
and the the number of distinct values
we're gonna have for every single
attribute within our table so we're
actually gonna maintain this as a
separate counter because we just can't
assume that you know I have X number of
pages and therefore I can fit X you know
why tuples in each page and it's x times
y because again not every slot in every
page will be full and then we talk about
multi-version concurrency control we
have multiple physical copies or
multiple physical versions of every
single logical tuple so we can't just
you know count the number of blocks we
have we're actually want to maintain
this as a separate count and then we'll
talk about how we're actually going to
compute the or maintain this information
to get the the number of distinct values
for every single attribute so now with
this basic information we can now derive
a new statistic called the selection
cardinality defined by this function SC
and this is just gonna be compute the
average number of records we're going to
have or give an attribute with that same
value so for every single distinct value
I would say you know here's how many
times that it occurs so we just take the
number of tuples that we have and we
divided by the number unique attributes
that we have and that tells us for every
single attribute how many times it
occurs what's wrong with this ray says
one like so he says one could be a
thousand one could be one and this
formula clearly misses it absolutely so
this is one of the big assumptions we're
going to make throughout the entire
lecture and that is we're an assumed
that we have uniform data so this
formula basically just saying every
single value occurs every C if every
unique value that I have in my table for
this attribute it occurs it's the same
number of times as all other values but
we know that's not how the real world
works all right so take like CMU for
example see me roughly has 10,000
students it's more than that but it's
simple math and it roughly has I think
actually does have 10 colleges so if you
assume you have uniform data then you
would say for all of 10,000 students you
take 10,000 divided by by 10 and that's
the number of students that are in
college it's exactly the same for every
college but we know that's not the case
right this school computer science where
I'm in that has way more students than
the school Fine Arts it's a real-world
data is skewed but to make our math
easier for what we're talking about
today we're gonna assume that everything
is uniform but again this is another
table where the real world doesn't work
this way real world systems have to
account for this and we'll briefly talk
about how to do that all right so with
this selection cardinality what can we
do with this well the goal is for us to
now figure out how many tuples were
actually going to select during our
scans using our predicates because
that's when we need to figure out how
many tuples each operator is going to
spit out and feed him to the next
operator and then we can use that to
figure out how much work they're
actually going to do how much disk
they're going to use how much memory
they're going to use so we're using the
selection collection cardinality to
figure out for the given input we're
provided from our children operators how
much how much data is coming out of us
so if we want to get for an equality
predicate on a unique key this is the
easiest thing to do and our math will
work out great right so say we have a
simple table the people table we have an
ID column that's the primary key so if I
have a lookup says ib equals one two
three then that's easy I know the
cardinality is gonna be one I'm gonna
have one tuple that's gonna match for no
matter how many tuples I actually have
in my table because it's a primary key
it's unique where things go get hard is
now when you have more complex
predicates like range predicates or
conjunctions because now I need to be
able to combine the selection
cardinality for these different
predicates in a certain and non-trivial
ways so oh [ __ ] sorry
so the based on the selection
cardinality now we're going to produce
this idea of selectivity of a single
predicate so selectivity is basically a
function says for a given predicate on a
table what is again what are the number
tuples that are actually gonna qualify
so the form that we're gonna use to
compute this will depend on what kind of
operation that we're actually doing all
right the last one I just showed you was
an equality predicate on a on a unique
unique attribute but you know now we
need to account for the case when it may
not be unique oh we're looking at non
you know inequalities arraigned ranges
so let's look at some simple examples
here so assume now in our people table
for the age column we only have five
unique values right 0 through 4 I said
the thing of this is like instead of
storing the exact age of somebody we're
putting them into two groups like
internet advertising or advertisers do
this all the time like people under the
age 18 18 to 35 35 to 50 and so forth so
we have five distinct values and for our
table here we have these five people so
if we want to compute now the
selectivity of an equality predicate
right you know where something equals a
constant then we just take the selection
cardinality of our predicate divide that
by the number of tuples that we have and
that's going to tell us what percentage
of the two boys are going to match in
our table okay so in this case here for
a selectivity of age equals two assume
we have a simple histogram of all the
tuples we have and since we said that we
are assuming that our distribution of
values is uniform every every every
distinct age has an exact value or same
number of occurrences so to compute the
selectivity it's just taking this which
is the selection cardinality of H equals
two because it's only one you're only
looking at one value we just look in our
histogram you find exactly you know the
number of currencies of this right so
it's just one over five again so this
one here we're assuming uniform
distribution and we're assuming that you
would know exactly what this value is
and therefore this math works out great
right this is exactly what we want but
we now so do some more complex things
like getting a range predicate so now we
say we're age is greater than equal to
two well the formula is assumes here
that we're that were we're only looking
at integers that are continuous we have
a continuous range of values where you
look at so you just take the max value
divided by the minus the one you're
looking forward divided by the the range
of the max minus min and that'll tell
you what Ruffing with the selectivity is
so in this case here we're looking for
everybody that's two or greater so we
take the min and the max subtract that
that's four then we just take the the
value we're looking for and the high
value that we want and it's 4 minus 2
that's 1 1 over 2 so this is wrong right
the real answer is actually 3/5 but the
way the formula works out we get 1/2 so
this is a good example where like these
formulas don't always work correctly and
they're going to produce errors in this
case here we're under estimating the the
selectivity it should be 3/5 not 1/2 so
this is gonna be problems when you know
when you start doing
you know estimations of a complex
queries that have a bunch of different
particles and about different operators
because now we have errors built on
errors built on errors so say this is
like we're doing the scan at the bottom
of the tree and we now we have an
underestimation of the number of two
boys we're gonna we're gonna produce as
our output now when we do calculations
up above now we're taking wrong inputs
or wrong estimations as our as our input
to our operators and then doing more
wrong math on them and producing more
errors so in many cases or the research
shows that for almost actually for every
single database system they evaluated
for this one particular paper everybody
underestimates the selectivity of all
these operators and you may say oh who
cares that how's that why is that big of
a big deal but now when you start sizing
up your you know your your data
structures you like your joint your hash
tables for joins your buffers for
sorting now you're gonna underestimate
what these sizes are and you may have to
correct that once you realize I have
more data than they actually not
expected so these have real runtime
implications for in systems and also too
we're making now wrong estimations about
you know what plan might be better than
another all right the last thing I want
to look at are negation this one's
pretty straightforward right it's just
one minus whatever the selectivity of
the predicate that we want right so in
this case here the selection cardinality
of age equals two is one so the negation
is just the boundaries outside of that
right and you get 4/5 which is the
correct answer for this one right
because assuming that something equals
something so the major observation we
can make about this is that this
selectivity estimate for predicates is
basically the same thing as a
probability right it's just saying what
is worth the probability that a tuple is
gonna match my given predicate so if we
make this assumption now we can use all
the the tricks that we we learned from
you know statistics 101 to start
combining together these these
predicates in more complex ways so let's
say that now we want to have a
conjunction you know age equals to an
named like you know a wild card so we
would have this computing selectivity on
the first predicate age equals to
compute the second
selectivity on the second predicate and
then now we just combine them or
multiply B to the two probabilities
together and we get our intersection
here right this is where you know we'd
say it has to be an exact match we're
sorry we have to match both and would be
this inner part here right and so same
thing for disjunction disjunction that
the form is slightly different but
you're getting you're just assuming that
the that they're independent and
therefore you can use the standard math
trick to figure out what the union is
here so I've talked about two
assumptions so far that are problematic
but this again this is what the way
every textbook covers it
the first is that we assume that our
data is uniform but I showed a simple
example where that's not the case and
then here now we're assuming that our
data is in the predicates are
independent that's also not always the
case - there's actually a third
assumption they're always going to make
that's problematic it's called the joint
inclusion principle so again so there's
much assumptions we're making about
computing the cardinality of our
predicates that make the math easier but
are going to end up having us produce
incorrect approximations so again
uniform data assumes that everything is
always going to be the curve the same
probability the way to get around that
for for heavy hitter so heavy hitter
would be like if you if you're really
skewed data and there's like ten columns
or ten values that occur you know
majority of the time you can maintain a
separate hash table or histogram to keep
track of those guys and then everyone
else you just assume his uniform and
derive the cardia now and it cardinality
estimates based on that so that's the
standard trick to get around the uniform
data issue we then we talked about the
independent predicates so that allows me
to take two predicates and if there's a
conjunction just multiply them together
to produce the combined cardinality and
then the inclusion principle says that
if I'm doing a join the two tables then
for every single tuple in my inner table
I'll have a tuple that matches in the
outer table right but that's not always
the case but you know a way to think
about this is like why would I join two
tables if they're if there's no way to
actually join them there's no actually
corresponding values that would match
so we make that assumption but in the
real world it's not always gonna be the
case could you get you could have
dangling you know uh you could have
references that don't you know exist
anymore in the outer table so these two
are the ones that are probably most
problematic this one occurs and more
advanced things we don't need to worry
about so I always like to show this one
example to sort of emphasize and show
exactly why this is problematic and this
comes from a blog article written by a
former IBM researcher and so guy lemon
worked on like the early one of the
early IBM optimizers from the late 1980s
or 1990s there's actually still used
today in db2 it was pretty influential
so he has a blog article but he likes to
show you here's why the assumptions
we're making here are problematic let's
say we have a database with a single
table of cars and we have two attributes
we have the the make and the model so
the make would be like Honda Toyota
Tesla the model would be like Camry
Accord
you know escort and then say we have a
query that says where make equals Honda
and model equals Accord so if you make
the assumption about the week that we've
made so far the two assumptions about
the independence and uniformity of our
data then when we combine this these two
predicates together we would say one
over ten because that's that we have ten
makes and Honda's 1 so that's 1 over 10
and then we have 1 over 100 models
because we have a hundred models accord
is one of them so we'd multiply them
together and our cardinality estimate
would be 0.001 but we as humans know
that these values are actually
correlated or these two predicates are
correlated like you can't make an accord
like there's no other car manufacturer
that's gonna make an accord it's only a
Honda so if you know the model equals
accord you can then know that the the
make has to be Honda and so the correct
selectivity for this particular query is
actually 1 over 100 so we're order of
magnitude off from what the the formula
would actually tell us what we think we
are from what we actually should be
yes so a question is if you had a
foreign key would that make your life
easier
no but you would happen no whether the
the foreign key child is is unique
because it could be one to N or one to
one you have to know something about
that but even then the foreign key I
think for this pickle example doesn't
help you I think about though but if it
is one it's one table like this is just
like one table give me all the cars or
the make equals Honda and the model
equals a court when it has nothing to it
like you know we're doing a joint right
I need to think that whether whether the
joints get hurt whether foreign keys
that help of that but we can take that
offline so again like we automatically
start making estimations about how much
work we actually have to do for our
query plan and sizing up our
intermediate data structures and our
buffers and we're going to be way off so
the independent assumption and it's
going to cause us to underestimate how
much work we're actually going to do so
the way to get around this particular
issue and this is something that the
only I think the high-end commercial
systems actually do is to do correlated
column statistics so I can tell the
database system all right model is
correlated to make right I can't make an
accord if I if I know that my model is
an accord I know what my make is another
example would be like if I know my my
zip code of an address field is one five
to one seven that I know the state has
to be Pennsylvania so if you if you
declare these these columns as being
correlated now the database is we can
you know special case it's estimations
to avoid these pitfalls it can know that
these things are correlated therefore it
can use the right formula to derive the
selectivity of it but as I said only the
high end system students yes
here question or save it is it doesn't
need to know how it's correlated just
that they are correlated I have to go
look to see what the syntax and supports
I think you just say they are correlated
and it should figure it out yeah like I
think only only Oracle sequel server db2
Teradata maybe snowflake can do this but
like my sequel and Postgres can't do
this as far as I know sequel Lite sort
of I can't do this alright so let's talk
about now how we're actually going to
get this information that tells us like
the number makes a number model think
the number occurrences of every value so
I've already sort of mentioned this
before but the the database system is
going to maintain histograms on the
inside to keep track of e statistics so
the most simplest histogram would be for
every single distinct value that I have
in my column I just count the number of
occurrences that I have right so in this
case here this is our uniform data so I
have 15 unique values and you know each
one occurs five times and so now we want
to say you know what's the number of
tuples that are gonna match you know
just something equal five I could look
at this and say I know it's exactly you
know five but in real data doesn't look
like this no data is more skewed and so
now again if we have a history in like
this this is fine because now we can say
you know how many how many tuples have
five we would know the exact value
what's the problem with this though for
every single value I have in my column
I'm storing an entry and my hash table
from a histogram that's gonna be a lot I
assume that soon this if this count here
is like 32 bits so my simple example
here I have 15 unique values so you know
15 times 32 bits roughly 50 60 kilobytes
or 50 sorry 50 60 bytes to nothing but
now if I have a billion that unique
values and I'm a 32-bit integer for
every single unique value now 1 billion
times 32 bits is 4 gigabytes all right
that's just the sit that's just as the
histogram from one column so now I do
this for every single column so nobody's
actually going to store exact values
like this except for the heavy-hitter
stuff that I talked about before so
the heavy-hitter you would have the
exact value but you only store maybe
like the top 10 or 20 unique values for
every single column you're not storing
this for every single possible one so
the way to get around this is to start
combining together these values into
buckets so that we only store a single
value for the bucket rather than an
individual value for every single
element of the bucket right so this
would be called an equity with histogram
so basically was take the every three
values here compute whatever the count
is the sum of all the occurrences for
every single value in that bucket and
then now my new histogram just has that
aggregate value all right so I'm doing
I'm doing buckets a size 3 but you can
even you didn't size them anyway you
want so now the way to get an estimate
to say you know how many times does say
the number number to occur I would look
to see what what bucket is my value that
I'm looking for fall into so 2 is
between 1 and 3 and then I would say
what's the count here so in this case
roughly 9 I have 3 values so I take 9
divided by 3 and now I'm estimating that
2 occurs you know three times so again
we're saving space for saving
computational overhead of maintaining
our histogram but now we're again we're
introducing more errors in our
approximations because we there's no
other way to get around this other than
storing exact values so this is not so
great either because now I could have
going back here between this bucket
right 8 had a high count 7 and 9 were
much lower but then when I'm combine
them together I don't know which one
actually had the high count all right my
heavy-hitter could handle that we can
ignore that for now so a better way to
do this is actually use quantiles
so with this one we're going to do is
we're gonna have the we're going to vary
the width of our buckets so the last one
the buckles are always the same width
but now we're going to vary the width
such that the the sum of the counts for
each bucket is roughly the same so in
this case here I can have the first
bucket would have values from 1 to 5 the
count goes to 2 6 7 & 8
has has 3 3 values for the counts 12
sorry counsel 12 accounts
12 9 and 12 and so now I have variable
length buckets but now I could
potentially have more accurate
estimations of the the occurrences of
values within those buckets and then
this one here I'm showing quantiles you
can do the deciles and other other
grouping sizes so any questions about
this again this is what we're going to
populate when we run analyze or run
stats in our database system it's going
to generate this information for us and
store this in our catalog and it's
durable and disk when we restart the
system we come back we don't run analyze
again all of our statistics are still
there yes this question is if I add now
if I add 10 more 10 more values to 5 so
now it shoots up what will happen in my
histogram so this is blown away every
single time I run analyze I recompute
everything so yes in that case it could
could vary the now the size of the of
the bucket correct
so as far as you know in most systems
they don't maintain these things as you
do inserts and updates because it's just
too expensive because again well talk
about transactions on on Wednesday but
when I'm running a transaction I want to
minimize the amount of work I have to do
so anything that's not important right
now
I wanted I'm gonna put off till later
because I'm holding locks on on tuples
and that's interfering with other other
transactions running at the same time so
I don't want to maintain this as I go
along now you could say all right I
could have like a separate background
thread could look at recent changes from
the log and then go apply these changes
yes you can do that some citizens might
do that but in general everyone blows
away and research from scratch the one
system that does try to do the updates
on the fly was was IBM db2 Zo's leo the
learning optimizer they were big it
would run a scan they can go back and
update this thing but you know it has
issues ok
so histograms and these and the sketches
and we did about sketching but like
these histograms and heavy-hitter stuff
that's the way you know this is sort of
the most data system to do this another
alternative instead of using these these
these these additional data structures
is that we could just maintain a sample
of the table and derive our systems from
from the sample so anything about the
history bands is like it's a essentially
a lower-resolution copy of of the
database of the tables right it's an
approximation of other contents so but
rather than having these histograms and
try to derive the system's from them
what do we actually just took a copy a
smaller copy of the table itself and
then ran our predicates on that smaller
copy and then assumed that the
distribution of values within that
sample is the same as it exists in the
real table and therefore any our
selectivity estimates we derived from
the sample will accurately reflect what
the what's in the real table so let's
say we have and our people table we have
a billion tuples and then but let's say
we just take a sample we're just going
to get every other tuple and copy it
into a sample table but there's
obviously more sophisticated sampling
algorithms you can use but for a
purposes now this is fun so now when my
query comes along and I want to compute
me the selectivity of age equals greater
age greater than 50 I go to my sample
and I say well bama's over the age of 50
so therefore it's it's 1/3 and therefore
I can assume that the different values
am i my full table will match that and
in this case here just like in the
histograms we could meet we could
maintain this as we go along right as as
you know it periodically refresh it or
we could trigger it whenever you know we
know that a large portion of the table
has changed or would you all bulk load a
bulk bulk delete but the idea here again
is that rather than maintaining
histograms who may could be inaccurate
we just maintain a sample
so this only occurs as far as they know
in the high-end systems so sequence over
most famously does this and their
optimizer is probably the best one I do
they but they actually do a combination
of the histograms and and the sampling
which I think is the right thing to do
okay
yes Sandia what makes this more
difficult than what this question is why
is this the case that only like the
high-end commercial enterprise systems
actually do this versus the you know the
open-source guys good question I think
the yeah actually good question if you
already have analyzed you're gonna do a
spectral scan anyway to compete your
histograms might as well just generate
this thing you actually don't don't have
an answer it may be the case that just
like the history of ways the way it's
always been done right it's not a very
satisfying answer I mean here's here's
one thing so I think like with the
histograms you in the way you have in
your optimizer you just have this cost
model actually here's tell you the right
answer the histograms we will up way
faster right cuz again imma numerating
all these possible different query plans
I can go to my histogram real quickly
and derive is the the statistics I need
to estimate the the selectivity of a
predicate or an operator where's this
thing to compute the selectivity
estimate I have to do a sequential scan
on it that's definitely gonna be slower
than the running through the histogram
right so we can cover this in the
advanced class that the blade pilot
works in sequel server sequel some
replies says if I recognize my query is
super simple just use the histograms if
I think it's gonna be a lot of work like
it's gonna take maybe minutes or hours
to run then who cares if I spend an
extra couple seconds doing my sync my
sampling technique because that'll make
a you know
big difference one actually run the
query plus pi that's the reason the
histograms gonna be faster this one
takes more work and it's it's also sort
of weird too because like you're like
you're doing a scan on something while
you're running the optimizer it so it's
like a from engineering standpoint it
might be hard to set up like this is the
model like this is super simple like
like it's what's the subcommittee this
predicate that component of the cost
model itself is is independent I think
of whether it's a histogram versus a
sample but yeah the yeah so up above is
the formula today it'll say I'm gonna do
this man a disk IO I'm gonna you know
miss this hash joint is better than this
other join yeah if that's not of all
that other parts not very sophisticated
they may be this doesn't matter question
over here or yes so his question is how
do you actually create a sample that is
gonna be accurate for every single query
that you can ever possibly throw on it
my stupid sampling here is every other
one but clearly that's like we know it's
stupid because maybe data inserts arise
at different times and therefore the the
data that I insert today first of the
data is sort of yesterday has different
distribution and so I may want to sample
differently or I could look at my
predicate and say well I its I'm only
looking at you know data that was
inserted today so therefore I make sure
my sample only includes that this is
this is where it gets hard and probably
the reason why the advanced advanced
systems do this better than or do this
and the open source guys don't do like
there's the reservoir sampling so much
other sampling
there's a lot of sampling techniques to
try to come up with ways to do this
I I don't know what the commercial
systems actually do but hopefully can
you see why this is a query optimization
super hard because like now you need
some you know some gnarly math to figure
out like what is the right way to sample
this and after you write get depend on
the query some queries you know uniform
sampling might be perfect other sampling
techniques might be better for others
yes today hey statement from an
engineering standpoint this could be
hard because like now you have a
separate table and then you want to be
able to a sequential scan on it and
ideally use the same execution code that
you have to do spectral scans and in
order to put these statistics yeah it is
it is like a chicken for the egg I can't
run a query until I have a query plan
but I can't get a query plan until I can
run a query that can compute sample yeah
okay so this point what we have we can
now roughly you know emphasize them
roughly we can roughly estimate the
selectivity of our predicates what do we
actually want to do with them and again
as I said in the beginning this is where
we're gonna do our cost cost model or
cost based search to do query
optimization so for this one again in
the pipeline after we do all those those
rewrites with just the rules now we're
gonna run enter this this cost model
search cost based search to try to
figure out how to convert the logical
plan into a physical plan
all right the physical plan is what the
data system actually executes so the
logical plan that says I want to join
these two tables the physical plan says
join these two tables with this hour and
this buffer in this sort order and all
that good stuff so for single relations
it's pretty straight forward well
briefly talk about it the one we're
gonna spend most of our time which is
the hardest one is the multi multi
relations or anyway joins because now
it's not only worrying about the the you
know what joint Algrim I want to use but
what order I want to do my join a member
I said last class the number possible
query plans we could have this for to
the N where n is the number of tables
were
right guys again it's for all my
different joint algorithms I can again
join them in different orders and I can
join them either one with the inner
versus the outer right so the search
place explodes so because this is
incomplete and pimpy complete we don't
want to actually do an exhaustive search
because we're never actually going to
complete does it make sense to run our
query optimizer for an hour if our query
is only gonna take you know one minute
to run that's not a good trade-off so we
need a way to figure out how to sort of
shed work or cutoff query plans and we
don't want to examine to reduce our
search space so we can make this problem
more tractable so let's first talk about
how we want to handle sting relations
and the most MMOs are time talk about
multiple relations so for single
relation query plans the the the hardest
problem we have to deal with is picking
our access method right the the fallback
option is always a sequential scan it's
the slowest but it's always it's always
correct then we can maybe one do a
binary search and we have a cluster
index or pick and put pick you know one
or two one or multiple indexes to use
for index scan the other thing we can
care about also is the order in which we
evaluate predicates like I have
something and something if the second
predicate is more selective than the
first one maybe I want to evaluate that
one first so I throw away more data
sooner than later and maybe the second
predicate evaluates always you know
always true so we you know we don't we
want to put that as the the second one
so in most new database systems like
there's all these startups all these new
data cells coming along the last ten
years if they have a query optimizer
they're probably and they're you know
they're probably using heuristics that
in order to pick these things but you
don't actually truly need a
sophisticated cost model to do this I
just say you know what what index is the
most selective and that's the one I
always want to pick or what predicates
most to select them that's the one I
always want to pick so for all three
queries this is especially easy to do
because they're not going to access much
data and then you know they're doing you
know single table lookups for the most
part and so for many queries the the
query planning we're going to do is
essentially try to identify whether a
query is sergeant
and this is some terms in the 80s I
don't know who invented it all right
sergeant we'll just means search
argument Abel and all that basically
means is that there's an index we could
pick for our query we know that's the
best one to use that's it so again we
don't need to have an exhaustive search
we just look it up all our query plans
are starting we look at all of our
possible indexes that that could satisfy
our our query and pick the one that has
that has the best luck tivity because
that's gonna route us to the data more
quickly again really simple I have my
night my select star from people where I
D equals one two three I just have a
heuristic that says oh I have a primary
key on ID but therefore I have an index
done I just pick that as my I'm doing
index scan on that on that index right
again most newer systems that come along
that are doing transactions are doing
OTP stuff this is what they support
first for the joins though that for that
that's when things is hard so again the
as the number tables were going to join
our table then i'ma alternative plans
are gonna grow so therefore we need a
way to prune that down so we're gonna
rely on what I'll talk about here we're
gonna rely on a core assumption that the
IBM people did back in the 1970s with
the system are when they built the first
quarter optimizer and that is they are
going to only consider left deep join
treats so that means that any other
alternative join tree structure I'll
show that looks like in the next slide
they're just not gonna bother doing any
search or cost estimation another say
that's we're not even gonna consider it
so a left deep trees like this where
along the on the left side of the tree
that's we're doing all our joins right
so we join a and B and then the output
of this joint a B is then joined with
with the input of C the scan on C and so
forth
all right this middle guy here is sort
of a hodgepodge right it's it's it's
it's you know someone on the left some
on the right right and this one here is
called a bushy tree where I do the joins
on you know C and E and then do the
joins in a B and then the output of
those two joints are then then joined
together at the end
so IBM in the system or they're just
gonna not even consider these other guys
here they're only gonna look at this one
yes yeah this is actually again so his
statement is the result is always the
same
yes this is the beauty of relational
algebra so the join operator is
commutative so I can put I can join
these things in any way that they want
and the final result is always the same
it's always correct
so therefore ADA is perfectly safe for
me to go ahead and do this everything I
guess why they do this other than just
reducing the number of plans they have
to look at think back to when we talk
about query processing models all right
so back then they were doing the
iterator model the volcano model cells
are called what the pipeline model so in
this case here at the left deep joint
tree I don't have to materialize any
output from a joint operator right it's
always then fed into the next joint
operator so I do my joint a and B then I
take the output of that joint and I now
build my hash table to do or you know do
whatever kinda join I want to do on see
if I have this bushy tree here I would
do the join and C and D that output then
gets written out to like a temp file on
disk because now I need to go back over
here and now do join a and B and then
now I go back and feed back back in the
the joint I just did over here you know
read that back in build my hash table do
whatever I want to do and then do the
joint with this other guy here so left
deep join trees not or not always gonna
be pipelined but it makes your life
easier and back in the 1970s they didn't
have a lot of memory so they would have
to spill to disk a lot so you can
minimize them out amount of work if that
amount of data to write the disk in
order if you always go left deep right
so this is a thing I just said here so
in in today's systems not everyone makes
this assumption but again I think every
textbook talks about this that you know
they cut these things out
all right so how are we actually going
to enumerate our query plans so the
first thing we just do is name right at
the numerator at the logical level all
the different orderings of our of our
tables we could possibly join to see
Alan join our S&T I could join RNs first
maybe you know Tina's first I numerate
all those things and then if each of
those I could then now enumerate all the
different possible join outcomes I could
use hash join partners join nested loop
join and then for all those now I can
then also now in enumerate all the
possible query plans like a pop I could
have all right you can see how this is
like search space is exploding so what
the IBM guys came up with in the 1970s
was to use a technique called dynamic
programming to make it more tractable by
breaking it up into smaller discrete
problems and we solved the smaller
problems first and at the very end we
combined everything all together so
let's look at really simple example here
so let's say I want to join three tables
are an SMT so the way to think about
this is like it's a it's like a sort of
search tree that I'm showing
horizontally so this is our starting
point here for our logical plan where
none of the tables are joined and then
our end goal is end up here where we
have our s and T joined together so in
the in the in the first step we want to
figure out you know what's the first
joint ordering we want to do so we could
possibly join R and s first or teen s
first and then for the sake of space I'm
not showing all the other ones but for
all other possible join no dreams for
this first join we want to do we
enumerate them down here and then now
what we're going to do is we're now
going to have a compute the the cost of
doing whatever join were specifying here
in the first step with our different
joint algorithms so again for sake of
simplicity we're saying we can either do
a server's join or a hash join and then
now we just used all this formulas that
we talked about before to now compute
the cost of executing each of these
these joint operators in approximating
the amount of disk IO we're gonna have
to do and so for each node we have in
the first step we're just gonna pick
whatever path actually has the lowest
cost whatever joint algorithms can
actually have the lowest cost and that's
the one we retain then now starting from
each of these notes of the next step we
do the same thing and try to compute the
estimated cost for doing different
joints to get to our end goal here right
and then we just end up throwing way for
each node here we end up only keeping
the one with the lowest cost to get to
our end point here and now we go back
and try to figure out which path is
gonna have the the lowest cost for us
and that's the one we'll end up using
for this query plan this is an over
simplification of actually how this
actually works but this is the general
idea from system are that they've been
in for dynamic programming and at a high
level
there's sort of two categories of query
optimizers we're only talking about one
of them this one's the most common most
systems should operate this way Postgres
does it this way my Seco does it this
way Oracle does it this way all right
you start with the the the first node is
always the starting point when nothing's
joined and then you work from the
beginning to the end to figure out how
to get to my end goal where everything's
joined together the other thing also
over simplifying here there's no
information that tell me about what I'm
showing you about the physical
properties of the data were you know ed
we're emitting from one operative the
next so I'm not keeping track of whether
things need to be sorted whether things
are compressed a roast or a column stir
all that extra kind of information
getting you have to consider in your
search algorithm here but for our
purposes we're ignoring that all right
so let's walk through this example more
concretely so that's it that's the
dynamic approach arrived we're going to
build out our search to try to figure
out which one has you know what what
path to get me to the end goal of
everything's joined together that's
gonna have the lowest cost but let's now
start it all put this all together and
do the three steps we talked about so we
want two numerate all the joint
orderings all the algorithms and all the
access methods and again emphasizes no
data system does exactly the way I'm
showing here it's way more complicated
but at a high level you hopefully if you
understand this you can then see how to
apply it to more sophisticated
configurations and setups so the very
first step to join joint are s and T I'm
just going to enumerate all the
joyner rings that I have but we said
that for for for system or we're gonna
prune anything that is is either a cross
product but that's not a left outer join
are those things we can just drop
medially
so then for each of these guys so let's
pick this one here for each of these
query plans now we're gonna go inside of
that and now start and numerating all
the different joint algorithms we could
possibly have
right so for to do this join our NS and
then followed by T I can either do an S
loop join I could do a hash join so now
I'm going to numerate again all possible
configurations of those and those are my
edges going in that dynamic program
graph those are my edges going from one
step to the next and then we do the same
thing for all the other the joint own
routes from the previous slide so then
now we're gonna pick one of these guys
and now I try to you know enumerate all
bit different possible access methods
you can have so we can either do a
central scan or index scan and then for
each index scan become you know for each
index we could possibly have we'd have
another enumeration of that okay you
sort of keep fanning out and having more
and more options and then you use the
dynamic programming technique to figure
out what the cheapest path is okay so is
this clear roughly how this works all
right so I always like to show this
every year so again I'm gonna show you
how Postgres has Postgres has a
specialized optimizer but in general
what I've described here is at a high
level how every system are based query
optimizer works they have a cost model
that allows an estimation of as they're
doing dynamic programming search to get
to the end goal Postgres actually has
two optimizer search algorithms against
do they have the system r1 that I just
talked about but then they also have
this special one called the genetic
optimizer are the geq genetic query
optimizer GE GE qo and what happens is
that if you have a query that has less
than 12 tables they used the system our
approach and then if you have 13 or more
then you start using this genetic
algorithm because they can deal with you
know a larger search base
so with Postgres they're gonna support
all different types of joint orderings
so left deep right deep bushing doesn't
matter and as I said a and then they'll
fall back to this genetic one when it
gets too complex so at a high level this
works as your standard genetic search
algorithm
so my first generation I'm just gonna
have enumerate a bunch of different
random configurations of my query plan
right and that's the jointer uttering
plus the the index scan or suspension
scan plus the actual joint algorithm I
want to use and then for each of these
I'm gonna compute the cost and then what
happens is I pick whatever which one is
the best all right so this one has the
lowest calls I'll keep track of that up
above and say here's the best plan I've
ever seen and then I'm gonna throw away
the one that has the lowest cost and
then now do a mix up of the the traits
of the ones that weren't thrown away so
now I'm gonna do random flips of the the
genes if you will all the the components
of the query plan to produce new query
plans right and so it's sort of like a
random walk so now I'm do the same thing
in my second generation I find the one
that has the lowest cost in this case
here this one up here has a cost eighty
that now becomes the new best class I've
ever seen I throw away the one that has
the lowest cost then I do a random mix
up of the plans that are kept around and
I generate the next the next generation
and they'll keep doing this for until a
certain amount of time there's a time
out says I'm not I haven't seen anything
else or I haven't seen anything better
than what the the best one I've seen so
far and a certain mount of time wide
exhaust Mike Mike my fixed time limit
and then whatever comes out of this is
the best is that it's one I'm gonna use
yes yeah a question is for simplicity
reasons I'm only showing you left deep
trees you could mix it up with right
deep and bushy trees but you make this
is only three tables we'd imagine you
had another three tables you want to
join and maybe one part of it is right
deep one part is left deep I can I can
mix and match them as needed yeah but
it's hard to draw that
the question the first generation how's
it generate this random how many
candidates I don't know how things
probably figure well I don't know I
don't know the number is but yeah it
can't be everyone yeah it's it's it's
some percentage of big actually probably
some fixed amount I don't know what it
is but again the this cost estimation is
the same thing we already talked about
before right this is it's the same
histograms or sampling and you're just
applying this as you go across right
Postgres is the only one that I know
that actually does this there was some
work and doing simulated annealing other
techniques this is like a random
algorithm right good cuz it's looking
it's not guaranteed to converge you're
not guaranteed to see exactly the best
possible option you're doing a random
walk in the solution space and hopefully
you land on something that that's
reasonable so actually to his point you
obviously want to pick things that are
and your initial candidate should be you
know reasonably good how they actually
do that I don't know because if you have
all crap here you have ugly children and
big first step then you have ugly
children the second step it's not gonna
be good so there's probably some way to
figure out what your initial candidate
should be all right so any questions
about this yes okay so this question is
how often you often you get queries to
have 13 or more joints very often uh it
depends for OLTP you Walt for for
analytics it's quite quite often yes
all right so think about this
so in a data warehouse a very common set
up does have what's called a snowflake
schema and the idea is that you have
this single table that's called your
fact table
and then you have dimension tables that
are that are around it so a fact table
using Walmart nerds example Walmart has
a fact table that's every single item
that anyone's ever bought at Walmart so
that table is massive it's billions of
billions of things but you don't want to
store like the name of every single
product the price and so forth so you
have these dimension tables on the side
that says you know here's the product
they bought here's what store his
location so those are all your dimension
tables so when you do a joint and say
find me all the the finally the
best-selling item in the state of
Pennsylvania during the winter for this
month range for people you know over the
age of 35 those are all joins now with
his dimension tables so that thing can
rack up very very quickly the other
thing I'll say too is like I always talk
to the to the the data is companies and
I ask them like you know about the query
optimizer because that's the part I'm
most interested about and the metric
they always give me in terms of like Oh
our query optimizer is good they always
claim the number joins that they can
support and I don't think this is a good
metric but like I've noticed that this
is cars every single time I guess
Malthus so I think like mem Siegel told
me once that they could do 35 table
joins and somebody else somebody to give
you 75 and then splice machine told me
they can do 135 snowflakes at Vega new
thousands and they have customers that
actually do that it's hard right you're
ready to deeply into the ordering things
it like again joins a commutative you
can join them in any any possible order
you want you could from you them any way
you want yes
now I thought what you're going is there
like I've shown you to a joint
algorithms
like to for loops there are multi way
joins where you can say I'm joining our
SMT on exactly the same attribute let me
join them exactly the same time that's
hard and only the expensive Pistons do
that
Postgres my single don't do this yes
what the same wishes that wouldn't be
made so this is actually something
that's the human Rick urate oh I'll
cover this maybe next class or I could
send her something on its own on our
Piazza like you would like a human would
have to design the database to say
here's my fact table here's my dimension
table it's not something we
automatically figure out I'm using the
term dimension table that's that's the
vernacular for describing what that
table looks like in a snowflake schema
you have a fact table in the middle and
then the things around it are the called
dimension tables but there's from the
databases perspective unless it's our
system design for OLAP queries or
analytical queries it there's no special
designation in sequel to say oh you're a
dimension table or oh you're a fact
table it's just as humans we use that
term yeah I'll send I'll send slides
from from last class or from this
advanced class I'll post on Piazza yes
yes so the idea here is like there's
like again it's a random map to
randomized algorithm but so the
algorithm says this thing has the lowest
cost I don't know why this is the worst
but there's something about it it's bad
so rather than propagating through the
next generation wherever it's bad you
know deformed genes are right I'm just
gonna throw it away and then so
something about this one has the lowest
cost that I want to propagate forward so
that's why I'll let this thing you know
get friendly with this guy
right and then before you know you got
to go to the hospital Wednesday and your
wife's giving birth right like it's
alright yeah your question is the sorry
how is what different how's this
different than this well this is doing
this is this is right deep that's lefty
no no that's that's the outer table this
this is the inner table so I'm doing
hash join I'm building hash table auntie
and I'm probing with tea down here join
matter the order matters yes yep yep dad
should be here yeah that's mistake yeah
this is just saying that this thing this
guy is allowed to propagate forward that
should be down there I'll fix that sorry
okay so let's finish up quickly at NSSL
queries so this is something we'll cover
more in the advanced class if you take
that but the the main way to think about
this is that the it's not like a join
because it's a sub query and we want to
be smart about how we're actually going
to evaluate it all right because the
dumbest thing we could do is just
evaluate that inner query the sub query
for every single tube what we're looking
at in the end the outer query right my
sequel used to do that and it needs to
be awful so there's two approaches we
can do this and the idea here is some of
these can we can we can do these without
having to run a cost based search we can
do this in part of our rewriting phase
so the first of that we can rewrite the
query to 2d correlate it or flatten it
out or we can extract the inner query
and run that separately as its own query
and then feed its result into the first
query so let's look a more complicated
example here so this is so this query
here we're trying to get all of the say
we have a table keeps track of sailors
so this is from when we used to use the
old textbook from Wisconsin in Wisconsin
a sailing club that's what this is
problem so basically we're trying to get
all the sailors the name of the sailors
where they have reserved a boat on it on
a given date so we had this inner query
here well now we see if we're
referencing from our inner query a
record from the outer outer query so in
that case here we know that they're
correlated right because they're
referencing each other so we need to
rewrite this as a join so again we can
do this in rewriting phase we can
recognize that we have this this this
pedak up here and we can rewrite it like
this and then we just do our call space
search to figure out whether the right
join order is as before let's look more
complicated example so this one here
we're trying to find for every single
sailor free sail with the highest rating
overall our sailors get the two
reservations for red boats and then find
the sail ID with the earliest date in
which the sailors reservation was on the
red boat so we had the main thing is
that we had this inner query here where
we're just trying to get the max sailor
rating or ranking for all sailors so
worst case scenario as we do this lookup
here we're rating equals and then the
center query for every single tuple on
the outer table on the sailor table we
just rerun this thing over and over
again but that would be slow that that
would suck and so what we can do is then
extract that out or we write it to so
that we don't have to have that you know
we run that every single time so the
first approach could be just take this
out this nested block run it up here
store it in some kind of variable and
then substitute that value down below so
the main thing I'm trying to show here
is that the query optimizer doesn't
necessarily have to take a single query
and only treat it as a single query we
could rewrite it and execute them you
know one after another in order to fill
in the values that we actually need and
this is something that the more
sophisticated systems can do all right
this is saying this is the outer block
and that's the inner block up above okay
all right so the that's the ball that's
this is what we can talk about for a
query optimization for the rest of the
semester as I said this is something
that I'm really interested in and I plan
to cover more in the advanced class is
this there's something during cheating
getting involved in and when I get
started on this you know this is you
contact me because this would guarantee
a seat in the advanced class as well so
we talk about ear selectivity
estimations we talked about the major
assumptions we made about the uniformity
independence and the problems with this
we talked about how to do genetic
programming for did you join orderings
and then we we can do simple techniques
to rewrite nested queries all right any
questions about any of this so again
every single time you fire off a query
and sequel light or Postgres or my
sequel whatever database you're using
it's going through all of this which is
amazing how fast it actually is I even
though it's a really complex problem all
right so next class I will be here and
we're gonna start talking about
concurrency control so this is the
second hardest thing in database systems
this is also something if you're really
good at you can also get a job this will
cover it so we're on Monday or sorry and
Wednesday this week we'll cover the
basics of control theory again Andy
theory not real theory and then Monday
next week and Wednesday next week I'll
have the Pichichi students cover
two-phase locking and timestamp ordering
because those would be the two things
you'll need for the the fourth homework
assignment okay okay but I was gonna do
extra credit hmm hold up let me get the
slides so releasing the extra credit
assignment here today so you can earn
10% extra credit for your final grade
right now for the exams on for the
project for the final grade of an entire
semester if you write a article about a
database management system and so you
compete any database instance when you
want other than the ones that students
have written about before the way you
think about this is you're writing like
in the cyclopdia article where is that
a writing freeform text like you would
in Wikipedia it's set up so that you can
specify exactly how different parts of
the system are implemented there's
options to choose
like how it does concur to all what kind
of indexes it has and then you can write
information in like a description of
what actually it actually does so for
this one you have to provide citations
for everything you do but again
everything wiII be explained on the
website so I've created this website
called the database of databases DVD
video I wanted to DV to i/o but then
that's asking for a lawsuit from IBM so
we didn't do that so the way it
basically works is that has about
different ways to categorize different
database systems to find what you're
looking for so in this case here these
are all the data systems that are
implemented in rust and then there's
again there's an article here at the
describes exactly how everything works
and there's citations for everything
okay so I will post a sign-up sheet on
Piazza for you to spell to select what
database system you want to use again
people this is the second year we've
done this so they'll be not every single
system will active you available to you
but there's enough of them out there
that everyone shouldn't have a problem
to actually pick what you want so to be
first come first serve so when I post it
online when I post the signup sheet
online I will announce it on Piazza and
then whoever gets there first you know
get to whatever system a lot Long's have
been approved so the way think about
this that if you pick a system that's
widely known and used like Oracle then
there's a lot of documentation there's a
lot of information about actually how it
works so you expect to write something
that's very comprehensive with a lot of
citations if you pick an obscure system
then this might be problematic because
it may not be as much documentation
available so in that case I can either
get you in touch with the people that
actually implementing it and they can
provide the information I've had
previous students post on the message
boards or message people on Twitter they
askin from information how this assumed
actually works one student last year
picked a system that only existed for
three years in the 1980s and then she
reached out to the guy that actually
wrote it because he was MIT alum right
it's actually kinda pressable people try
to get get this information and so what
you get is no sign up and get an account
and it'll be a page like this you can go
edit again you can see that it's not
free form text for everything you can
select exactly how you know different
parts of the system or actually
implement it so it may be what database
system I am I gonna pick right and I'll
just say that there's enough of them
there that you should have no problem
finding one that you want so I think I
am currently I am currently aware of 636
different database systems so
distributed systems embedded systems
systems written in different languages
going back to the 1968 we have one or 65
so again you should have no problem
finding a dataset that piques whatever
your real interest is okay yes
what's up wait some giggles yeah yeah I
know it's not real yeah this is actually
it's not even all this is this is still
a subset this is probably me like 400 of
them there's another 230 that I know
about okay so how can you solve the
system you want to pick you pick the
country of origin if you care about you
know database is written in Brazil or
China or India we have those right based
on popularity so I know I keep track of
what pages get to view the most right I
can tell you which one you put you
should watch you look at there's this
one in France written in Java or
JavaScript for whatever reason Google
picks us picks us up we get a lot of
traffic for that whatever programming
language your isn't into then if you
like rust you like go you're like see we
have a database in written in bash write
like whatever you want we have something
for that you want to ship it at
databases embedded databases single node
databases we have those discourses
memory roast row versus column store
commercial versus open source or
enterprise we have it we have we have it
all if we have time we can look at the
leaderboard and see which which one
systems actually appear the most which
you know what programming language which
country all right I got to say this
because Lea shared this didn't happen so
do not plagiarize so there'll be two
parts you split it in two parts the
first part will be like a checkpoint
maybe after after Thanksgiving well
we'll look over it and give you feedback
whether you're on the right track to you
know if you're doing the right thing and
then there'll be the final submission
during finals week and that's where you
get your final grade for both of those
submissions do not plagiarize last year
we had somebody cotton pasted from
Wikipedia and they put that in there and
the reason why we caught them is because
they didn't go delete all the brackets
you know for the citations so we had to
go reporting to Warner Hall it was very
very messy okay so do not plagiarize do
not copy anything do not copy images
from the internet don't assume that it's
someone
scribes the system that their expert
they know better than you and therefore
you you feel wrong rewriting it I don't
care do not copy anything because your
name's gonna go in on this this this is
public on the Internet
so you know if you play drives we have
to go report you okay yes the question
is if you cited image I've rather not
you can get by without images yes I I
wouldn't worry too much my images yeah
yes so it's a way to work is since
students I've done this in the past
I will they're not they don't want all
had the same quality so I will provide a
list the ones you should not pick from
so yeah if I got eyes for this you
should pick the one you should always
assume the latest version right so if
they did something like five years ago
and got fixed I don't care about five
years ago just describe what it does now
you can mention they used to do in a
certain way but I would focus if you
just focus on what how it exists now yes
[Music]
I'll be dead or you'll be gone like
don't worry about don't worry about it
yeah actually we've had some companies
reached out to us and we allow them to
edit the page but again it's like I'm
like curating it I wanted them to avoid
like marketing [ __ ] like we're the
fastest database like all that crap we
keep it very scientific yes
keep it on case by case basis there any
system you're in particular tooth in
your mouth because I'm the Mongol one's
actually pretty good already okay um so
if you gotta go you can go but let's we
can quickly look at the website and all
right so what date what country has jet
has created the most database systems
USA who's number two
he said he said Russia is this China
France and India okay all right so this
the website so we go to the leader
boards actually let's do that so like
again you can click on any database
system and then over here like it has
the country of origin so somebody said
China so to tell you how many how many
do since China has so China has 28 US
has u.s. has 300 somebody said what was
that what said India what is with the
Indian code in5 Russia are you 21 you're
missing it Germany 44 right
France is less all right so again like I
can click on this and then I can click
like programming language is to
implement it so this one's written in
C++ right to 101 what what what is
probably most common programming
language used for database system
everyone sticks to missile us see the
combination C's of applause yes Java
right so we go to write this leaderboard
thing here it says a breakdown of right
so here's the breakdown of the countries
right Germany is number two
Java the most common programming
language but again if you combine C++
and and C all right then it passes it
and then also we keep track of like what
database systems use other database
systems so these are these embedded
databases there's like rocks TV a bunch
of systems like clock cockroach TV use
rocks DB as the internal storage and
then they have a go thing on top of it
there's also systems that have forked
other systems and use that as the
invitation so there's a lot of companies
that have forked Postgres and use that
and as well as my sequel there's the
most two common ones so again you see
why are we trying to keep track of all
these things right and so I'm aware of
in total as I said 630 whatever um so if
you find a system I think this would be
super helpful if you're you know if
you're from India or China or whatever
country you come from and there's a
database system that's written in that
language that I don't know about let me
know right because I want to know like
this thing just goes on forever and ever
I there's there's tons oh okay so I'll
post is the Piazza today project 3 will
be announced either today or tomorrow
and then well you know better we'll get
a great script set up for that and then
we'll have class on Wednesday and then
when next week starting starting Monday
next week will be the movie my grad
students I'll have office hours
immediately after this if you want to
see your midterm exam but I won't be
around later in the week okay guys
he's witzy nights in my system I'm
blessed
let's go get the next one then get over
dive dress good net will be son ricochet
jelly hit the deli for a boat one
naturally bless ya what rap is like a
laser beam the phones in the bush say
nothing like a chain wrap the bottle of
us a nice sympathy go you don't feel
like drinking that boney to you drunk
you can't drop cross and if the sake
don't know your phone can tap a thing