[Music]
[Applause]
welcome to 57:21
I'm the instructor for this course Indy
Pablo as I posted on Piazza I in
Pittsburgh right now I'm actually in
Amsterdam with my friend 187 Owen the
problem is that a 187 booked us a hotel
but it's actually not the kind of hotel
we'd want to stay at so right now we're
just kind of hanging out here in the
red-light district trying to figure out
what we need to do next but Owen lost
all his money and I don't have my credit
card with me right now so we're kind of
homeless so I figured now would be a
good time to sit down and cover the
first lecture for everyone so before we
get started I just wanna give a shout
out to everyone who's been down with us
since the very beginning Jael in Seattle
MC in California and Eazy E in Brooklyn
these people over understand truth for
us since the very beginning I also want
to acknowledge that this semester we are
being sponsored by two foundations or
two groups the first is the Amazon
database group Amazon is actually
surprisingly one of the largest database
vendors everything they do is on the
cloud and a lot of topics we'll be
talking about and the semester are
relevant to the kind of systems that
they are building and and so they are
helping out with course development
we're also being funded by a nonprofit
called the Steve Moya foundation for
keeping it real and again they are
helping out with paying for TAS and
lecture notes and other things so we
appreciate both of them with helping us
out and for Amazon they will become
giving a guest lecture later in the
semester sorry - today's agenda the
things we want to discuss are first the
overview of what the course and the
semester will look like if you're a
student at Carnegie Mellon and then I
just want to do sort of a fun lecture
about the history of databases just to
provide some context about what the you
know what the kind of modern systems we
talked about today what thing you know
what things that people tried in the
past so if you're not enrolled in the
course and you want to skip ahead to
this video you should skip ahead to hit
your databases everything else is just
people that
that are here at CMU so the first thing
I want to get discussed is why should
you take 15 7:21 why should you take
this course so I say this every semester
and every semester I continues to be
true right now database system
developers are in huge demand not just
in Silicon Valley not just in the United
States all over the world and it's
because that there's a lot of unsolved
problems in databases data management
processing and these companies can't
hire people fast enough so you know if
you take this course you'll be you know
any do well on it you'll be immediately
hireable or immediately employable and
that's that's a good thing all right the
other thing I'll say also too is that if
you even if you don't go off and end up
spending your career writing database
systems or building database systems the
things that you'll come across or learn
throughout the semester are are going to
be applicable to almost every other
aspect of computer science or
information technology and what will
happen is that you'll see is that the
the people that are you know good enough
to write code for database merit systems
in addition to operating systems or
embedded systems you know you can get
pretty much a job in any other
application domain you know if you if
your database doesn't program and you
wanna write JavaScript code people will
hire you but if your JavaScript
programmer and you want a day to write a
database system you know that may be a
harder harder sell right so the kind of
systems background you'll get out of
this course you know goes beyond just
database systems but we're going to
discuss these things in the context of
databases because that's all I really
care about I can just give you sort of
the brief alumni role of the students
I've taken this class and where they've
gone to but this is just a subset of the
students that have taken 7:21 and then
hung out with us and working our system
even further at CMU and they're all
everyone's gone off either to grad
school or are now building database
systems that you know either companies
that build databases or you know
startups that are physically just
building database systems so I'm pretty
happy about that and then the companies
can't hire our students fast enough
all right so the goal of this course is
to you know give you the background and
understand about the bonding practices
and been building database systems and
as part of that you'll become better at
at doing is sort of low-level systems
programming so the goal is that by the
end of the semester you'll learn what it
means to write correct and performance
system code in the context of databases
we we can't we need both right you you
don't want to lose data so you want your
system to be correct and I'll show you
what to process the data as fast as
possible weird fast as possible so you
want to be you know have support high
performance so I'm sort of in my ivory
tower in academia and I like to say like
Oh correctness matters first performance
comes second and that's how I'll teach
things in practice in the real world
that's not always followed you
definitely you look at examples like
MongoDB or bi sequel you know wildly
successful database systems that are
used all over the world and they started
off with going for performance first and
then correct in a second so the other
thing you'll learn about in this course
is that will teach you proper
documentation and testing for your
database system you also learn how to do
code abuse and you work in a larger code
base right so these are things just
beyond the university these are things
that you know that will help you out to
your career no matter where you go and
that the major tech firm is when I ask
them what are they interested in my
students taking this course what kind of
you know do what they want them to learn
B plus trees or locking code they always
tell me they want students that are able
to work independently on a large code
base so that's not something I would
take lightly that's something that I
think doesn't come easy for a lot of
people especially me and this is
something you'll get exposure to during
the semester alright so the sort of core
umbrella topic for this semester will be
single node in memory database systems
and so that means that we're going to
ignore a look for the most part writing
data at the disk as part of like a disk
or dida base system it now fluid that is
later on and we're also going to nor the
problems and challenges when you have a
distributed database system so it's not
to say distributed databases
are not important it's just to say that
for this course we're gonna focus on
getting the single node system working
as fast as possible and it's correct and
correct correctly and what we don't
worry about going to stripping it right
it's in my opinion it's better to have a
database system that works well on a
single node and try to scale that
vertically before you go to a distribute
environment and try to scale
horizontally because that brings in a
whole bunch of other challenges so this
means that we're not going to cover
things like a census protocol or fault
tolerance at a wide scale we care about
the things but not just here and so this
course is also not gonna be on classical
database minute systems so that means
that we're not gonna cover you know that
the basics as we did in the introduction
class about two-phase locking or B plus
trees and things like that I'm gonna
assume you know those things and instead
what we're gonna cover our
state-of-the-art implementations and
other topics that that modern systems
aren't using today I said this is going
beyond what we cover in the Indian Show
class so the kind of things that we'll
talk about during the semester are
concurrency control indexing data
structures storage models database
compression pad actually joins in
parallel or VanFleet vectorized
execution models networking protocols
logging recovery and then we'll spend a
lot of time at the end the semester
talking about query compilation in query
optimization all right these are sort of
the so the more modern things that you
don't we don't really get the chance to
cover in the in the introduction class
so as I said already I'm gonna assume if
you're taking this course that you
already have taken another database
course whether it's 15 for 45 645
Carnegie Mellon or at your undergraduate
institution some kind of intro to
databases so and the reason why I'm
gonna assume this is because we're gonna
discuss modern variations of the
classical algorithms that are designed
for what today is however it looks like
so I'm not going to teach you what how
to do a hash join I'm going to teach you
how to do a vectorized parallel hash
join I think and run multiple cores with
simply instructions I said this is
shorter you need to understand the basic
way of hash joint work so in order to
understand how to do
through the modern implementation of it
so the core background that I'm assuming
you already have would obviously be
sequel because we're gonna focus on
relational databases serializable theory
of concurrent control theory relation
odd and then the basic algorithms and
data structures for sort of classical
databases again P plus trees Ares two
phase locking it and so forth
things like that so the course policies
and the schedule is all available on the
course web page right there's a syllabus
there's a schedule and I'll cover what
the schedule means in a few more slides
but any questions you have about what of
course sort of have a course will be
held and how be graded you always refer
to the course webpage now in terms of
academic honesty I encourage you to go
look at what seems policy is on their on
their webpage about what plagiarism and
what cheating means if you're doing
something like copying a piece of code
that you're not sure whether that's okay
or not I encourage you to please ask me
I'd rather you have asked me and we and
you and I discuss it and see whether
you're doing the right thing and what
you're doing is okay
rather than me catch you cheating and I
have to go you know over pulled you to
point all right so you know let's not
plagiarize let's not be stupid if you
have questions just ask me all right so
I'm holding office hours on Mondays and
Wednesdays at 1:30 2:30 immediately
after this class in my office and gates
that time is not good for you then
please email me and we can make an
arrangement for another time so if you
come to office hours what can we talk
about well a lot of times students want
to come talk about implementing their
projects or if they read the paper and
not sure about what you know if they
fully understand it but there's other
sort of life things you want to talk
about I'm happy to do that as well like
how to get a job as a database to
engineer a database database developer
if you want to introduction to a
database company in a certain state or
region I can definitely do that for you
and then because of my background I
think I'm qualified to talked about how
to handle police you know if you're in a
situation where you know because you do
databases you may end up in a bad place
and you know you need some help getting
that out of it so by all means come talk
to me I'm happy to do so
we have 1ta the semester
he's trillest Matt boo trovich is a
second year peachy or second one and a
half it's not clear what he actually is
PC student with me in the CS department
he's actually a student that took 721
crushed it and I encouraged him to hang
out and be a PG student and now he's
here so he is currently the lead
architect or developer helping build our
database system at CMU and this is what
you'll be using for all the projects
before actually coming to CMU he was
he's from LA so he was like an ex-gang
member of this you know so he's
ridiculous but actually right now since
I've sort of got him on the right path
as being a PG student he is now I'm
training him as a licensed boxing
manager so he's gonna be a cage fighter
he's currently undefeated and you know
through our training we hope that it
will continue to be his way so any
development questions that I can't
answer I encourage you to go ask Matt
because he will know more things about
the internals of our database system
tonight all right so the breakdown for
which expected for you this semester is
the following so there's reading
assignments programming projects final
exam and extra credit so one change we
made this year than previous years is
that I dropped the midterm exam in
brought along a brought back the second
programming project because I think
students got more out of it the last
year than the midterm exam so I'll
explain what that is as we go along and
there's two additional reading
assignments than previous years so the
if you go to the course that schedule on
the web page you will see that for every
single day there's a broad topic what
will be discussed for that lecture and
then there's a list of readings and one
of the readings will have this orange or
yellow star next to it and that's the
mandatory reading for that class I
should sort of be the primary paper that
we will cover in the lecture so before
each class you're required to submit a
review of our synopsis of this paper
that just discusses like the overview or
the min the main take away of what the
per the system actually does and and you
have to spit this to this form on lines
which is just a Google Form and so in
addition in the synopsis it also include
you know what system they use for their
evaluation and whether they modify it
and how they modified him and then what
work Liz they did to evaluate their the
proposed method and this last one is
actually really important because when
you do the final project and you want to
measure how your system or whether the
system actually improved or got faster
or or whatever you're modifying you want
to go see what the workloads are that
people are using in these other papers
and you know apply the same and apply
the same experiments to your own
implementation so the reviews are the
synopsis sort of due at 11:59 a.m. right
before a class stinks that's harsh
that's sticky the reviews are a few
right before class and there's no late
days but you're allowed to skip four
readings throughout the entire semester
and then your final grade will be based
on you know the ones that you do submit
all right so again please don't
plagiarize these writings I think other
people fall along in the course on
YouTube or I looked at the previous
years and sometimes you can find the
synopsis on on github don't plagiarize
don't copy from each other
I've run everything the moss and if we
catch you then we have to report you
again I said again don't be stupid all
right so now the ball kaduk really
prized basically the program projects so
we are building a new database
measurement system here at Carnegie
Mellon it doesn't have a name yet it
doesn't have a public name yet
the repository is currently named that
for my dog which is just Terrier that's
not gonna be the name of the system
because that's not a good name for a
database system so we all announced the
name later in the semester and post the
website published website once once we
get the first version out the things you
care about is that it's gonna be a
modern codebase that's written in C++ 11
per station plus 17 it's multi-threaded
we use LLVM to do query compilation
again I'll explain what that is
and throughout the semester everything's
open source it's designed to be Postgres
compatible so the easier for you to
actually enter and you know interact
with this thing using the terminal so
all the program projects be based on
this and we're going to use github to
manage everything so that we'll be
running a recitation later early next
week to give you an overview of how the
system source code is laid out and gives
sort of pointers on how to get started
on the first project so we'll announce
that where that's going to be on Piazza
later this week so all the development
you gonna do is on your local machine
the data system currently builds on
Linux and OS X I think somebody has
tried to build it on Windows with the
Ubuntu packages I haven't tried this I
don't know whether it works but we're
also provide you with a vagrant PM file
that you just downloaded you want to run
run this in a Linux VM on your phone
your Windows machine so you do all the
development on your local machine but
for the first first and second project
and potentially for the third project
you'll want to do all your benchmarking
consider performance tests using Amazon
because they'll on an ECG machine
because you can get a machine that has
more cores than your local laptop does
so will provide everyone with coupons or
credit codes you can use on Amazon to
get you know a couple bucks to get these
machines so you're not paying out of
pocket and so we'll send that
information out a little later later
this later of the semester so the first
two projects will provide you with the
test cases and the scripts and provide
you clear instructions on what you need
to Mon to modify in the system for you
for your project however also to teach
you how to profile the system like using
perfect call brine but this is
presumably something not something that
most students have experience with so
the first project will be completed
individually the second project we've
done in a group of three so currently
the class has roughly 36 people also be
about twelve or thirteen groups of three
people I like to keep it three people
because that's sort of a it's not too
few and not too many the with some
exceptions or taken a case-by-case basis
if we have actual people we could do a
four or three or four or two-person
group
but again most everyone else would
should be in a three-person crew it's
okay for you start thinking about what
group you want to join to get right now
the third project will be will be the
group project and this will be something
that you get to choose to build in our
system and so it has to be something
that's relevant to the materials of
topics we discuss in the class it has to
be require a significant program effort
from everyone that's on your team and
has to be unique you can't have two
groups work on the same project and
obviously as to be approved by me so
don't freak out about this now you don't
have to pick a project until the we come
after after Spring Break and then I'm
also going to provide some sample
project topics that you can choose from
to build in our system so again for the
first and second project please don't
plagiarize please don't copy from each
other if you're borrowing a library for
project two that's probably not
necessarily a project three again come
talk to me but again don't be stupid
don't copy and nobody will have any
problems all right so the final exam
will be a take home exam and that'll be
long-form questions based on the menus
where any reading through stopped seems
tests in the class
I'll give it out in class on April 22nd
is winter if there's also the same day
that the guest speaker will be come and
give a lecture and then it'll be due
potentially the last day of class a week
later or when we do the final project
presentations I haven't decided yet
all right and the extra credit for this
semester is the same as we did in the
intro class so we are writing an
encyclopedia of database systems at
Carnegie Mellon I currently know about I
think the numbers like six hundred and
eighty-three database systems now that
we know about and so you can get extra
credit if you write a Wikipedia style
article about one particular database
system so there's a ton of them in there
I pick one then you know you find
interesting and you're right about how
it's actually implemented and you've got
provide citations and attributions at
your attributions for where you found
this information it's not just saying
this is what it does because I read I
watched a video you got to actually have
citations because you're trying to for
this trying to have this thing being
scientific so this is entirely optional
you don't have to do this but if you
won't do the option is there
so again for the for the extra credit
articles this happens every year it
drives me crazy do not plagiarize do not
you know even those extra credit you can
still get in trouble
we still report people to Warner Hall
that that that plagiarize for the extra
credit right like the reason why I'm
saying this over and over again in these
videos is because I'm telling you don't
plagiarize so then if you do plagiarize
I go to Warner Hall and sit and show
them this video and say look here's what
I told the class not to plagiarize and
they plagiarize and then so don't do
that either break down for the grades
this year is that the reading views are
worth 15% project one is worth 10% again
that's mostly designed to get you
familiar with working in the codebase
project you is 20% project 3 is 45%
final exam is 10% and then you can order
you can earn extra 10% for your extra
credit so the all the discussion
throughout the course we don't a Piazza
and that's the link there everyone
should already been sign up signed up
before this must have started if that
hasn't happened and please email me and
we can fix this if you have a technical
question about the projects like I tried
running this in a VM and it didn't work
I tried compiling it didn't work or what
is this piece of the code do please
don't email me or Matt directly please
post on Piazza because again it's a
group discussion if you have questions
that other people have similar questions
so Piazza is the right place to do that
anything that's not about projects or
homeworks or assignments or other things
please you email you know directly like
you're sick or your dog died email me
okay
all right so that's it for the you know
forth before the background what the
course will be about logistics so now I
want to do sort of enough sort of fun
mini lecture on the history of databases
so this this lecture is actually come
based on two papers one was written by
Mike Stormbreaker called what goes
around comes around and that was
published in 2006 and that's sort of a
retrospective of you know the history of
databases up to to that point and then
the second paper is one that I wrote
with a industry analyst out of London
what's really new a new sequel and that
sort of picks up where Mike left off in
2006 and talks about the rise of the new
sequel systems and how they sort of fit
into the history of databases so again
there's databases are a super old topic
it's and it's surprisingly still hot
today
I love databases so it's good to
understand where you know how do we get
to the point we're at right now so the
main takeaway from from those two papers
is that a lot of the issues that in the
early database systems were facing back
in email all the way back to 1960s and
1970s are actually still relevant today
you know how do you run transactions
correctly how do you Patti maintain
indexes all these things are still
matter it's just what's different is the
hardware landscape is different so the
one thing in particular that's that's
really fascinating about all this is
that was sort of how history repeats
itself is the you know it's been a
decade now but this idea of sequel
versus no sequel you know which one was
better for you know for different
workloads
that's that debate was basically the
same debate that they had in the 1970s
about the relational model versus
codasyl or the network data model and if
you've never heard of codasyl it's it's
no surprise because it lost right the
relational model one that's why we this
whole courses on relational databases so
you know the the relational data model
has proven to be resilient and robust
and
you know useful for almost every
possible database workload the only
exception I would say is is potentially
machine learning because those are
arrays and although you can model them
in a relational database it's not you
know not that in this awful way so many
of the ideas that were talked about
throughout this entire semester are not
new again we're just discussing the
modern implementations are incarnations
of them and all the times you're hear me
say throughout the entire semester or
that you know when we talk about
particular topic I'll say oh actually
IBM did the same thing in the 1970s with
system or or ingress did the same thing
at Berkeley in the 1970s right these a
lot of these techniques are not new it's
just there now some of them are back in
fashion because the the harbor can
actually support this so that's I think
that's super interesting and it's a part
of the reason why databases are you know
still relevant still hot topic and still
in demand today so let's go back to the
very beginning one of the very first
database systems was developed in the
1960s called IDs the integrated data
store and so this was developed at GE
General Electric internally for some
customer I think it was doing a timber
service or timber company out of like
Seattle so they built this database
system and for this one customer and it
helped them with you know get a hold on
their large organization so you may be
thinking well Andy I've ever heard of GE
selling computers or selling databases
how can GE be responsible for building
the first database system what happened
to them well it turns out that GE at the
time had this this business philosophy
where they said if they can't be in the
number one company in a particular
sector of the marketplace then they
didn't want to be in that market at all
so they said well we're not number one
computing let's just sell it all off we
don't want to be involved in that so
they sold the entire computing division
to Honeywell in 1969 and as part of that
they also sold IDs I actually don't know
whether IDs is still around around today
I mean it could potentially yes but this
is usually demoness that one of the
first date of the systems so the two key
things about IDs that are relevant to us
are they're going to use what is called
a network data modelling which I'll
explain in a few slides and that when
you execute queries you're going to
basically be writing a bunch of for
loops that operate on a single tuple at
a time and we'll contrast with that with
their relational model which can operate
on bags or sets so the guy it actually
ege that helped build IDs was this early
computer scientist named Charlie Barkin
at Charles Bachman who's actually still
alive today and he ended up leaving
Honeywell in the early 1970s and went
off to this this other computer company
called cool lane database systems which
still exists today and he helped build a
new network data model system called ID
8i DMS or an integrated management
system integrated data management system
and that's actually still around today
so Bachman and a bunch of other people
that were involved in COBOL programming
got together in the late 1960s and
proposed a standard called codasyl on
for how programs written in COBOL should
access the database think of us they
were trying to define a standard API
that every database system that written
in COBOL could could could could support
so again based on his experience at
Honeywell this codasyl was based on the
never data model and therefore it
operated on one tuple at a time during
query execution so Bachman is he was an
early database pioneer and he won that
he won the Turing Award for this work in
there in the early nineteen seventies he
said one of the first people actually
win the Turing Award for databases so
here's what the network data model looks
like so for this is sample application
say we're like a large engineering
company and we're trying to model how
the keep track of all the different
parts we have to buy from different
suppliers to build some you know large
rocket which is actually a true example
we'll see in a few more slides but so I
have in my database I want to keep track
of suppliers parts and the
which supplier supplies each part so the
way the network data model set up is
that you have these collections of data
like a supplier a part and supply but
then you're also going to have to define
these membership sets that that say
whether a you know a and a record from
one set is a member of a you know owned
by another set so to show and I can
instance what this would look like so
say these are my use my collections of
data or my records supplier part and
supply so I would have now these
membership set call supplies and
supplied by that would have pointers to
say 4 8 4 you know for a given
membership between a parent and a child
here's all the parent pointers to the
parent records and here's all the child
pointers to the child records so now
let's say I went do a query and say find
me all the parts that are supplied by a
particular supplier I'd have to write
these bunch of nested for-loops that
finds the the supplier that I want
iterates over the supplies set then
iterates her with the supply set then
iterate you know with the supplied by
then I and then I reach my my my part
record our part collection of data and I
can find the thing that I'm looking for
so the first obvious thing to point out
here is that the network data model
requires you to have to write complex
queries you're essentially writing low
level for loops to traverse this the vs.
never have to find the data that you're
looking for the other issue is more of
an implementation aspect but the these
these these databases turn out to be
easily corruptible because AB see back
then in 1916 1970s disks were expensive
they weren't as reliable as they are
today and people weren't you know
maintaining multiple copies of data so
what would happen is if one of these
these membership sets got corrupted you
said you lost the whole database because
now you had no way to know how things
got got linked together
so the the networked data model and the
IDs came first but the another database
is though is sort of built around the
same time in the late 1960s what's this
thing called IMS for information
management system at IBM
so IMS is super super well known it's
widely used still in today if you ever
used at atm chances are you've
interacted with an application that
talks to an IMS database it's still
around so IMS was actually a database
and IBM that IBM built to keep track of
the purchase orders the part supplies
and the supplied information for the
Apollo moon mission for NASA before was
called NASA but unlike codasyl it didn't
use a network data model they used what
is called as a hierarchal data model the
other interesting aspect about IMS was
that they had programmer defined
physical storage formats so when you
declared you know I have a collection of
data like a table you also had to define
what was the underlying data structure
you would use to physically store that
data on disk right whether you want a
hash table or something to order
preserving tree and so it also like the
network data model though you you would
try these four loops to traverse the
hierarchy and do queries that up you
know write queries and operate on a
single tuple at a time so again now
inserted simple supplier information an
example now we just have sort of two
collections we have supplier and a part
but in the instance we actually see a
problem with a lot of redundant
information
so we'd have this supplier collection of
data with our records and then each of
these records would have now a pointer
to some other data structure that would
have all their part information so the
obvious problem we would have here is
that or duplicating data because if
multiple suppliers provide the same part
I have to have different instances of
that you know that record in this case
large batteries over and over again
right for every single supplier that
that sells that part and that means now
if the name of the part ever changes I
have to write extra code to go find all
instances of the batteries the large
batteries and make sure that their names
all get changed together at the same
time and that
they're there in sync the other big
problem in addition to sort of the tuple
at a time for queries is that there was
no independence between the physical
data structure of the databases of the
database and the logical abstraction
that programmers interacted with so for
example if you know if I declared that
my table was gonna be or you use a hash
table as this underlying physical data
structure but then I read earlier later
realize oh I I want to actually execute
range queries well now I gotta dump the
table out and load it back in as a B+
tree and then now the API that I'm
exposed to for that table changes method
rewrite all my application code right so
that's that's wasteful it's very painful
so now in the late 1960s early 1970s
there was this mathematician named Ted
Cod who was working at IBM Research in
New York and he saw all these
programmers at IBM rewriting their IMS
and codasyl programs every single time
the database schema change or the layout
changed and he saw this as being
wasteful right because every single time
the schema change the you know you have
to go rewrite your application code now
back then computers were way more
expensive than humans and so he was sort
of prescient in this in this goal of
removing this burden because now human
two way more expensive than machines
machines are cheap right so back then
this wasn't you know maybe that big of
an issue of it was hard to find
programmers but Italy now may be a big
cost problem and so what he came up with
in the relational model was this this
high level of abstraction of databases
to avoid all this sort of maintenance
burden on humans so the relational model
is has sort of three key ideas that that
are widely used in databases today so
the first is that instead of storing the
databases hierarchy or this network with
with image it'll crash structures we're
instead store the database is just these
simple data structures as relations or
tables right and now we're gonna then
write our program in TOR to access the
data through some high-level language
that can operate on these on these
relations at the time in the first paper
you know he didn't actually propose
language I said this is the first paper
he wrote in 69 but this is the more
common one that everyone cites is the
relational model of for the facial model
of data for large large shared data
banks so M B's in these seminal papers
he actually didn't find what this
high-level language would be of course
now we know this is sequel at the time
sequel didn't exist all right so the
paper strictly you expect
strictly describing the relational model
from a mathematical perspective quele
was actually the first programming
language query language that people came
up with for ingress that followed the
relational model the IBM later came out
with sequel which is the sequel to quell
to play on words
Ted Cod actually proposed his own
language called alpha in a paper I think
in like 1975 but no one no one ever
actually uses that the other key thing
that he came out with that goes beyond
what ims was doing was the physical
storage representation of every relation
was actually left up to the
implementation of the database
management system so what that means is
that I just declare that I want a table
I want a relation that has these
attributes I don't say how I actually
want it stored physically and now the
database system could decide on its own
how it actually wants to store things
right if it wants to use the hash table
wants to use a B+ tree it could do
whatever at once and no matter how the
data changes physically underneath the
covers in theory if I'm doing this
correctly
I shouldn't have to change any of my
query any any queries in in my
application because they're only
operating on the database at a logical
level so these ideas sort of seem
obvious today but back then this is
actually kind of controversial right the
idea of having a database system to be
able to support a high level language
that can generate query plans as
efficiently as what humans can write was
considered a far-fetched idea it sort of
back panels do you gotta understand
people didn't think a high level
language like C and having compiler for
C could ever produce you know machine
code as efficient as some
writing assembly and of course nowadays
nobody you know very few people actually
don't write assembly we write in even
higher level languages right it's again
in our modern world these don't seem
that controversial ideas but back then
back then it was so the just to go back
to our simple example before with
relational model the now we have three
relations supplier part and supply and
these gonna have foreign key
relationships between between each other
so now in my installation or instance of
this database Estonia I can just do
joins now between either supplier number
or the part number to find the to find
the the parent the parent record for my
supplier record so now to do a lookup to
find all the parts applied by giving
supplier I can just do a join between
these three tables and find exactly what
I want and this also means that in a
high-level language I'm operating on the
database as through sets right I just
say this is what I want you to find for
me and I don't specify you know how to
iterate through you know to pose moment
form I want to find what you're looking
for again this is a very powerful
construct that is the basis of what we
talked about for the entire semester
alright so this is now so the relational
model sort of sort of in the 1970s when
it came out as I said it was
controversial so would it mediate right
away that this is the right way to build
database systems so there was a couple
other relational database systems being
built at the time but the three that
most people talked about so today our
system are at IBM ingress at berkeley
and oracle by oracle so system are was
at IBM research in san jose and it
wasn't led by jim gray but he was
probably one of those famous people that
came out of that group ingress was
developed by one of my advisers mike
snow breaker if you've never heard it
ingress before you may have heard of
Postgres right so snow breaker is built
ingress and then he built Postgres after
ingress like Postgres stands for post
ingress right so again we'll talk about
this both of the system's self entire
semester and then oracle is there's a
commercial system that both Larry
Ellison and now he's like
one was richest people in the world so
this this listing is amazing right you
look at Jim Gray you look at Mike
Stonebraker both of those guys won the
touring award for databases Larry
Ellison as I said he's like the seventh
or eighth richest man in the world
this is all because of databases like
this is crazy this is awesome right so
this is why I just why I love databases
because it's you know now only can you
do do research that has been an impact
you can make you know you make some
decent money now you can buy your own
Hawaiian island it's awesome all right
so there's the debate going on between
the relational model and Kota so in
1970s but eventually the relational
model one algorithms clear that this is
the right way to build database systems
so ingress and Oracle were
commercialized but IBM actually never
released system are as as as a
commercial product what they ended up
releasing what in their first relation
Davison they did release was this thing
called db2 which is still around today
and that came out in 1983 so there's
some bits and pieces of system are that
made it into the first implementation of
db2 but I don't know how much of that
code still exists today and so because
for system are they were using sequel
IBM used sequel in db2 and because IBM
was sort of the computer juggernaut at
the time that essentially became the
standard they had to change the name
though so set of spelled out seq you
yell it just got shortened to become
sequel and I think that's because
there's somebody somebody sue them over
a naming issue so sequel became the
dominant dominant programming language
used for databases ingress was
supporting Quell at the time they
eventually had a sports sequel put
Oracle supported sequel from the very
beginning because they copied what IBM
did and you know when I didn't keep me
outside if we have a sequel database
Oracle is like oh look we already have
one too and then they essentially won
the marketplace so the other thing that
happened in 1980 is were in addition to
IBM putting on the first database
there's actually a lot of other startups
that came out at the time it also built
relational databases for enterprise
market or in a commercial market
Informix Sybase tandem non-stop sequel
Teradata was late 70s inter bases
another famous one but all these
database systems are still around today
not in the exact form that they existed
back back in the 1980s but these are
still a billion dollar billion dollar
products that still make a lot of money
for these companies
the other cool thing is that Stonebraker
after running the ingress company for a
while he goes back to Berkeley and he
starts a new database system built on
the you know his lessons that he learned
from from running ingress and he put
that into a new system called Postgres
and this is actually I don't know how
and obviously not much of the same code
is still there but this is the same
person using today is it's a direct line
to this exactly the same Postgres code
or menina derived from the postcard code
that mike developed with his students at
Berkeley in the 1980s so now we get in
the late 1980s and now we start to see
this idea of people repeating sort of
not the same mistakes but trying to you
know fight the same battle that maybe
people that they had in the 1970s so in
the 1980s object or new programming
languages became more prevalent and
people people recognized that well if
I'm writing all my application code in
an object or in a programming language
like small talk or C++ but now I used to
store things my database mode my
database is storing things as relations
so I have to take my objects which may
have nested arrays and other objects
inside of them I've got to break them up
and then put them into relations or
single records or tuples and put them to
my database and so people recognize that
observe that this was a potential
bottleneck this is called the relational
object impedance mismatch so a bunch of
people said that well rather than taking
my objects in my probing language and
then splitting all of them up into two
poles from our relational database what
if I just could have a database system
could store objects directly so then I
don't have to do that translation
and you know did Eli's or DC Eliza break
things up and put it back together
anytime I need to access them so the
couple of database companies that came
out with what are called object or any
databases force on an object store
probably two most famous ones they still
exist today but they're essentially in
maintenance mode this this sort of
category databases never they took off
because there was no sort of standard
way to interact with you know the
program these systems and just you know
because you have to use a proprietary
programming language that made you you
know tightly coupled with the databases
of where sequel is potentially a you
know an open standard that anyone can
implement you know these are the program
these other databases were proprietary
market logic is an XML database that
came out in the late 1990s but it's it
was similar to these things there was
sort of an XML database so although
these systems aren't really around today
and people aren't widely using them a
lot of the technologies that they
developed to store data in these in
these object when a databases actually
exists today and the commercial relation
databases or open source ones right
anytime you store data as a JSON file or
XML field that's essentially doing the
same thing that the object or any
davises guys did back in the 1980s so
again so as Mike said what goes around
comes around so let's all get a quick
example here so I say I have an
application that I want to store Student
Information so every student has an ID a
name and email address and then an array
of phone numbers so if I want store that
in a relational database since a student
could have multiple phone numbers I need
to have a foreign key relationship
between a student phone relation and a
student table and so now when I want to
do a lookup to get all the information I
need for a given student I either have
to do two queries on these two relations
or do a join between them to get the
data that I need I said this again this
is the this would be called the
object-relational impedance mismatch so
what a object warning database would say
is that well instead of storing this as
two simulations
what if I de stored the all the
information for a single student in a as
a JSON field and inside that I could
have my nested array and so now to go
get all the information to instantiate
that object in my application code
as one fetch into the database so this
seems nice
right but now this is gonna cause
problems because for a simple example
like go get one student that's easy to
do but now if I want to start doing
aggregations across multiple students
and start tuning things together not
only to have to have traversed the
hierarchy of the every single record in
my query but now I need make sure I can
join across these multiple records so
the queries to do complex things end up
being more difficult than what you would
have written in using sequel the other
issue is that as I said before there's
no standard API even today for JSON
databases there's no standard
programming language that people use to
interact with these objects on the
databases MongoDB or Redis are sort of
becoming the sort of de facto standard
but there's enough there's enough
document databases or object databases
out there that do something completely
different whereas sequel again the
dialects are slightly different but
they're still similar or not that you
know you can understand it pretty easily
all right so now we get to the 1990s I
typically call this the boring days of
databases and it's not to say that
people weren't putting out new database
systems it's just that there wasn't any
major advancement a major change and how
people are going to design database
systems that help people are going to
kind of applications people are limited
on yes the internet was coming around
but you know in the early days that
weren't that many people on the internet
and the complexity of the applications
that people were building and exposing
through the web or not as sophisticated
as they are now so existing databases
were sort of sufficient the sort of four
major events that I was like to say
during this period were that Microsoft
bought a license to the Sybase source
code they forked it and ported it to
Windows NT and that became sequel server
secret server today still is
state-of-the-art database system and you
know I know how much I don't think of
that much of the site this code is still
there but that was their starting point
and Sybase is sort of in maintenance
mode now that still makes a lot of money
where a single server I consider to be a
state of the art system
the next major trend was that sequel
server or so my sequel was what came
about in the 1990s as a replacement for
M sequel and that's why they use today
Postgres added support for sequel
and that was a based on the academic
code that was developed at Berkeley in
the 1980s most of us actually got was
forked and then there was a commercial
version called a lustrum
that I think supported sequel was
eventually bought by Informix and sort
of died off but two grad students at
Berkeley in the 1990s took their
academic version of Postgres that only
supported quell and add as a porphyrin
sequel and that's why the official name
of post-arrest is PostgreSQL because you
know it was the added sequel after the
original Postgres code was written and
then sequel light was started by one
dude down in North Carolina and it's
most widely used
noxee that's why they use embedded
database and was widely used is data in
general because it's used everywhere all
right so now the big change to happen in
the 2000s was as the internet so the
number of users online grew
significantly and the size of the
databases and the number of concurrent
operations that these systems need to
support was way larger than what you
know what what existed before
so the problem was that all of the
majors of enterprise database systems
the Oracles the SCI basis the the db2
these are all very heavyweight and they
were expensive and the open source
systems like my sequel Postgres at the
time were sort of missing important
features that you would want and
databases that you couldn't use them in
production safely you know so for
example my sequel didn't support
transactions correctly until you know to
enter DB came along in the early 2000s
so any what happening was doing to
support these larger doctor workloads a
bunch of companies like Facebook Google
and eBay and Amazon they end up writing
their own custom middleware that would
sit in front of multiple single node
database instances to loud them to shard
out scale and so that would allow them
to support a larger number of concurrent
users and ingest data more quickly but
now if you have a lot more data anyone
do analytics on it you need a
specialized database system to actually
support these kind of workloads so this
was the rise of data warehouses so these
were the special-purpose data systems
that were built in the mid 2000s that
were designed for these large alergic
data sets it's not to say that the the
existing David's at the time couldn't do
analytics they were you know they were
sort of jack-of-all-trades and not
designed specifically for him whereas
these newer systems were designed just
to do analytics efficiently so the six
most famous ones who at the time were in
a teaser Park Salomone DB Green Pond 8
Allegro Vertica of these mateesah parks
L Vertica and Green Pond were all Forks
and Postgres like they took the
Foursquare source code hacked it up to
make a sport analytics Morton more
efficiently the I don't think about
these systems that was different than
the existing ones is that they were
primarily distributed and shared nothing
because that's you wanna be able to
scale out to do large-scale analytics
and unfortunately they were most of them
were also closed source so the key thing
about them that makes them different
than what was done before is that these
were all columnstore databases all right
so comma stores that has existed since
the 1970s but it wasn't until this time
now these special-purpose data
warehouses that people recognize that
the colony
you know the decomposition model that
come a column store was superior for
doing high performance analytics
so now we get into the late 2000s and
the no sequel movement so how this all
sort of started is this my take on it
was that the companies like Google
recognized that for the kind of
applications that they want to support
on the web they cared more about making
sure that the data system was always
available and the that they could scale
to port a large number of users so they
end up foregoing traditional things like
the Davis provides like transactions and
joints and seco support in exchange for
these sort of other data models or
proprietary languages programming
languages access api's so there's a
bunch of these systems that were sort of
cloned based on what Amazon had done or
what Google had done but other ones keep
sort of came out from just somebody was
putting data system at a company and
recognized that you know it solved a
particular problem that it's useful for
other people so obvious the most famous
ones were probably MongoDB Cassandra and
dynamodb mostly these are open source
except for Dino DB Oracle no sequel and
and BigTable but again the main thing is
that they were called no sequel because
they weren't supporting sequel at the
time although a lot of these Jews do now
today because they were focusing on high
availability more than and correctness
so as a responsive to the no sequel
movement there was a certain other--
database maybe that I was involved in
called new sequel and this is where
we're trying to build databases for
transactional workloads that could have
the same performance of scalability as a
no sequel system but without having to
give up transactions without giving up
the relational model or sequel because
these are useful things to have in the
databases and database so unfortunately
most of these at least when the new
sequel system originally started most of
these were a closed source clinical
thing now is in recent years with like
copper cbt-i DB and you gabite
some of the newer newer new single
systems are actually open source so that
that's pretty exciting spanner is
probably the most famous one at gu
out of all these and they do
transactions using the special proper
clocks which we're not gonna specify
this semester all right so now the 2010
and 2014 so these are where now instead
of this building to a single purpose
daily sitting that could try to do
everything you try to build these you
know one of the new transactions or one
that could do analytics efficiently but
not the other one but then in the later
mm mm mm tens was these H tab systems or
hybrid systems where it was trying to
get the best of both worlds it was like
and it was trying to be a new single
student system where he could do
transactions very quickly but you also
want to support some of the analytics
that you would only be able to run on it
on a data warehouse and the idea here
was that instead of it could have
maintained two server databases one for
transactions on for analytics you could
push some of those analytical operations
directly to the front end system and you
know extrapolate new knowledge new
information all in the data as it
arrives in the database system so of
these HANA splice machine and MC co-op
probably the two most famous ones hyper
is originally started as an academic
system but it got bought by tableau a
few years ago and is now a commercial
system that comes with tableau software
hyper is actually an amazing system we
are actually going to discuss it both
times throughout the entire semester and
next class or later this week I'm
actually going down to the hyper
headquarters to try to get you know go
through like a German seance or get some
German influence in my life to help me
build a better database system so look
forward to that in the next class so
some of these are open source some of
these are closed source again but all
these are going to support the
relational model and sequel is that sort
of the the main thing people want
especially for analytics
the other big thing happened in 2010 was
the the advent of cloud systems so these
are now database systems that are
designed specifically to run in the
cloud environment and so how these first
started were like the major cloud
vendors would sell you a database as a
service that were just taking an
existing database system like Oracle or
my sequel or Postgres and running band
inside a container or VM for you but
since then there's been new database
systems that are designed specifically
for running in a cloud environment or
shared disk combine which I'll show in
the next slide all right so these are
data i/o systems and not necessarily
govern the ground up but they're the
system's assumes that's running in a
cloud environment and therefore it takes
into account the latency of accessing
disk that may not be local to the
machine I would compute is actually
running so of these snowflake redshift
roared and everything Amazon span or
BigTable & Kosmos DVR Poly most famous
ones ziran was a cloud version on my
sequel that went under it's based out of
Israel they failed a few years ago fauna
DB is a it's a serverless OTP system and
slicing dice is a I think a cloud cloud
service from my sequel based out of
South America so there's a bunch of
other ones but these are the one of the
main ones that I'm showing so as part of
it in cloud database you had these new
architecture that was assuming a shared
disk shared disk environment so that
means that instead of having to write a
custom storage manager in your database
system the accesses like a local disk
you would use the existing
you know interfaces or API that the
cloud vendor provided you or a
distributed file system will provide you
and use that as the underlying datastore
I said think of this instead of writing
to you know a proprietary you know a
local file that you know manage on the
disk I would write my data out to HDFS
or Amazon says to reread EBS so in these
environments the storage layer is
usually append-only and so these are
going to favor or you're gonna typically
use a log structured approach because
you just need to keep depending to the
law so this is what most people think
about when they talk about building a
data Lake it's usually something like
this where they have a bunch of files
under you should be a file system or
distributed object store and you just
build it you have this you point the
data system at it and you suck at the
data in and do rent you to run your
queries on it so again although we're
not gonna talk about shared disk systems
or tribute databases you know you have
to bring the data from the shared disk
into a compute node and at that point
it's in memory and so you're gonna do
all the things that were talked about
throughout the entire semester right so
even though we're not talking about
explicitly disagree to databases our
techniques that we'll talk about here
are still used in them the other cool
thing about shared disk systems is that
because now we separated the compute
layer with the storage layer I can scale
them out independently because the
execution layer is essentially stateless
by the final state of the database is
always on the shared disk so if now I
can't process queries fast enough then I
can just keep adding new you know in
your compute nodes and start you know
running more queries in parallel
likewise if I need to start scaling out
more machines I can just add a new disk
of the shared shared disk layer all
right so I briefly want to talk about
graph databases although it's starting
to rain here the every year people so
ask me why don't I cover craft databases
in the class and the answer is I have
not really seen a from the low-level
systems perspective that I care about
I've not seen a compelling argument for
why you want to use a graph database the
only really main image that they have
over existing systems is that they're
gonna abide you a graph tential query
API so that means it's like if I wanna
do a graphical traversal instead of you
know as I walk the graph going back
before doing the application and and
this and the database back and forth to
do that traversal I have a single
command that does two traversal and then
it all runs on the server side so but
there's nothing specific about that that
makes this as you know you couldn't do
that in a relational database that's
storing a graph and in fact there's a
recent research it's a few years ago
2015 insider that shows that it's
actually not clear that using a graph
Center specialized graph central
database system it's going to do
any better over a existing relational
database system with a graph API so for
that reason we're just not going to walk
graph databases this entire semester the
other major trend this this this decade
in 2010s is the the advent of these time
series databases so again these are more
specialized database systems that are
system designed to store time series
event data think of like a modern
service where you're collecting the the
CPU utilization from every machine in a
data center you know once a second so
all these events get sucked into a time
series database and they can do you know
analytics or do analysis on them to find
whether you know there's any issues so
the reason why I bring up the time
series databases is that this is
actually a good example about how if you
make assumptions about what the data
looks like and the worklet pattern
you're trying to execute on then you can
actually apply some additional
opposition's at the storage layer and
the and the execution layer for them so
you could make the same argument about
graph databases I just at the X you'll
there may be or the planning level but
at the low level storage level it's the
relational model could still do this so
a time series databases they're still
relational it's just there are they know
the queries that patterns are going to
look like and so they can optimize for
so of these the ones that's probably the
most interesting to us in the semester
is clique house at a Russia I'll spend a
little time talk about how they do
things because it's actually it's super
stable system that does a lot of the
things that we're going to talk about
this entire semester and it's open
source that's that's very cool all right
so again the the the major trend I would
say the last decade is the rise these
specialized systems no longer it's it's
you know Oracle or sequel server db2
that tries to do everything for everyone
there's enough Daly system out there
that that can better for different
classes of workloads again a lot of
these that still be relational
it's just how they actually put my
things and can be tailored towards a
particular application environment
domain so there's a bunch of embedded
databases that are interesting that
we're not going to
talk about multimodal databases or
mostly model databases are systems that
try to do you know graphs and documents
and key value stores all within a single
database blockchain databases are thing
apparently again I don't find them very
interesting or compelling these may be I
just don't understand it enough to say
that they're good reason for them so
we're not talk about them and there's
also a hardware accelerated basis we'll
talk a little bit at the end of the
semester basic databases that not just
running on the CPU but could you run on
FPGAs GPUs or new non-volatile memory so
the main takeaway once you get from all
of this is that there are a ton of
database systems out there that all do
things differently and sometimes they
make a decision sometimes they don't
they don't make good decisions and so
the goal of this semester so to
understand these trade-offs of all the
different design points of building a
database system so that you know when
you go out in the real world and someone
comes along says hey I have this great
new database that you should give me
money money for you should start using
you you can now make an uneducated
valuation about whether that's actually
a good idea or not all right so here's
what I think is gonna happen in the
future I think that the specialized
databases that start off very
specialized over time as they get more
users and see adoption they will sort of
expand the scope and which the type of
problems that label support so the time
series databases maybe don't do
transactions very well but eventually
what a transaction there may be they
they don't do analytics very well and a
doc need base but eventually they do
analytics water eventually some
databases will just people stop using
and be go in a maintenance mode and then
die off but the ones that that do you
thrive I think will just begin notice
get better over over time it is also my
opinion that the relational model and
declarative programming languages are a
boon for doing high-quality engineering
data engineering in an organization
right so instead of is having a bunch of
Python scripts that are hacking up the
data if you have a way to sort of
programmatically define what the data
looks like and
and operate venom on in sort of
structured manner then that makes it
easier you know for other people to
reuse what you're doing it may not be
the fastest way for you to do it in
terms of engine you know you actually
writing the software but for an
organization that has a lot of people
touching data I think this is actually
the better approach that's a sort of
just my opinion all right so next class
we will do the introduction on in-memory
databases I just sort of to contrast
them with disparate databases and try to
understand why they're different how
they're different and you know that'll
be the underlying assumption we make
throughout the entire semester and for
Wednesday's class you also have to
submit your first reading with you so go
check this course schedule and see what
paper you have to read and then submit
that with a link below okay so like
10:30 at night it's getting smoky here
let me go figure out where or when a 701
is and forgot we're staying and then
hopefully I can record the next class
when I'm down in Germany at the hyper
headquarters all right guys take it easy
Bank it in the side part what is
[Music]
called the okay cuz I'm og ice you down
with the testy hi you look and it was go
grab me a forty just to get my boss song
cuz I needed just a little more kick and
my hunt be to say nice to take a seat