[Music]
Oh guys let's get started again hit it
up for DJ chop tables
[Applause]
how would you weekend who's having
whippets don't do that okay all right so
other announcements other than huffing
whippets is that homework one is due on
Monday at midnight it should be a little
spin oh great script a bunch of you've
already completed it
who has not started Wednesday what did I
say Monday yeah it is Monday
Wednesday whenever the 11th is right who
is not starting start just make sure
okay
and the other thing we will be releasing
project number one on on on Wednesday as
well again the lecture on Wednesday will
be all about what your toes to implement
in project one and then so at the end
we'll talk about those sort of logistics
of how you're gonna go about and do this
in the source code and then again that
will be spending on great scope as well
okay all right so the other things that
might be interesting to you or we have
some upcoming database talks that are
sort of somewhat relevant to what we
talked about in the course this Friday
over in the CIC building we will have a
talk from people from from Salesforce
this is public Salesforce is building a
brand new database manager system to
shoot at database system based on
Postgres a lot of my former students
people have taken this class are now
working on it
in San Francisco in the brand-new
buildings which are amazing and then
next week at the database group meeting
on Monday we'll have our Goa who is
senior alum he was the former VP of
engineering at mem sequel which is an
in-memory database that we can talk
about later and semester she has a new
startup doing
analytic database stuff and he'll be
talking on on Monday next week and then
the following Monday so two weeks from
now we'll have somebody from Vertica
come give a talks to Vertica is a
columnstore database system one of the
more famous ones that was invented by my
my grad school advisors and got sold by
HP and they got sold off to a holding
company a few years ago but believe it
not they actually have an office in
Pittsburgh and so he's gonna come and
give a talk about what what you know the
kind of stuff they're doing here and
when we one of the newer things Vertica
is doing so if i have stated work
columnstore it won't make sense right
now it should make sense by the end of
this this lecture okay because what will
describe what that is and actually try
to give it up and running to give a demo
like too many installation errors I gave
up okay
so again these are all free to the
public there's pizza at this one and
these like fruit so you can plan your
meals accordingly all right so last
class we we started talking about how we
would want to design a disc cornea
database system and again I said a disc
coordinate system is one where the data
system assumes that the primary search
location of the database is on disk and
so we spent time talking on how we're
actually going to organize the the
database at different levels within
files within pages and then within those
pages within tuples and so the reason
why we want to do all this is because we
want to be able to support databases
that are larger than the amount of
memory that's available to us on a
single machine and yes I know you can go
distribute it you can go across multiple
nodes for now we can ignore all that
just saying you have a single box how do
we bring data in when we can't fit it
all in d trance and so we finished up
talking about a lot of pages this just a
quick refresher so a slotted page was
how we're gonna organize tuples inside
of a page so that we we can move things
around and we start packing in as many
tuples as possible so we have the slot
rate at the top the fix and a very lank
to potat at the bottom and we just keep
adding things from from the Gynt from
the end to the beginning and from
beginning to the end until we reach the
middle we don't have any more space and
so I said this is the primary way most
database minute systems out there that
are roasts or systems which again I'll
explain where that is in a second this
is this is primarily the way most
database systems actually do
but it's not the only way and we ran out
of time we didn't discuss the other way
and so I'm gonna briefly talk about that
so just again this is put it in context
most what we'll talk about this semester
will be this organization the database
system you'll be working on for your
projects will use this type of
organization but again it's not the only
way another way is to do is called log
structured file organization so the way
this works is that instead of storing
the full tuple insider and set our pages
we're instead just going to store the
the information about how that tuple was
created or modified right so what I mean
by bad so let's say in our page we're
just going to start appending these log
records and I'll think of it like mall
records like a text file that are read
by humans think whistle is a log record
that's a some binary representation of
what the change was so we record like I
inserted this tuple I updated this tube
I deleted this tuple right and we just
all we have to do is just keep appending
every you know every time you flip the
page we could go create a new one and
start pending more leverage to that
anybody I guess why you want to do
something like this yes it's easy to
what he says it's easy to roll back
potentially yes yeah like if I have a
thousand if I have a thousand columns
and I update one if I need to roll back
I didn't blow away the single update
record yeah that's that's one yes
she says fast right absolutely yes so
memory said that in specially spinning
discs hard drives but even modern SSDs
it's much faster to do sequential right
since we want to read source quench with
access then random access so if I'm back
in this mode and let's say I update you
know ten two pools but they're all in
different pages now I have to go write
and update the the tuple owned across
ten different pages but if I'm doing the
logs structure organization then I put
my ten writes into my single page and I
can write that out in one go so you see
so this idea is not new like it came out
late 1980s early 1990s
log structured file systems or
volkskammer trees but it's really
applying the
ten years that this has taken off and
part this is because there you know
things like HDFS or s3 right there's all
these - distributed file systems where
there are pend only you can't do random
updates you can only keep appending
records so this style of storing your
tuples is it works great for that so
what's one obvious downside with this
she said read it absolutely yes so if I
have to read a tuple now I gotta go back
in time and look at the logs and try to
figure out what is what if the people
look like wait what what was the final
result of the tuple right so if my look
see I'm updating so tuple here and I
have a thousand columns but I don't
update one of them I got to go back and
try to find where it inserted updated
the other thousand columns to put it
back into the form that you want alright
so there's ways to sort of speed that up
all right you can build indexes and say
well if I'm looking for a particular
tuple here's how to jump to the
particular offset in the log that has
the data that I want or another thing
you could do is say just go actually
replay the log and compact it down and
to just it's you know just the one
record per per tuple right so I can take
all these guys and then just convert it
back into just you know is there a tuple
form so as I said this is more common in
more recent systems some of these you
probably heard about HBase Cassandra
there's a bunch of these distributive
systems that are out there that I
written and go
things like cockroach DB where they're
all using rocks DB as the underlying
Storage Manager
alright so the distributed execution
layer is all and go but then underneath
the covers rocks DBS and C++ and so
rather than writing their own storage
manager that is relying on this like as
an embedded system so rocks DB came from
came from Facebook Facebook actually
rusty B is rigidly based on level DB
level DB was written by Google then
Facebook took it first thing they did
was remove M map right and then they
really released it as Roxy be so level
DB still out there but pretty much
everyone uses rocks DB so again like so
we're not really going to cover this the
rest of this semester it'll show up when
we talk about distributed databases
later on at the end but for our purposes
we'll just assume that we're dealing
with tirely slotted page systems
okay all right so for today's class we
want to now go a little bit deeper and
talk about how we're actually gonna
represent the data in tuples so again
again we said the database is
represented by a bunch of pages so then
we discussed up or how to break up the
heap file into pages and then when these
page we talked about how to represent
the slotted array and then we said
roughly inside each slot of the array
you have these slots then then you have
your tuples have a header and now inside
the tuples we want to say what does the
data actually look like for individual
attributes or columns how are we
actually gonna represent that then we'll
go on and talk about how we actually
store the metadata about what our what
our tables look like and then we'll talk
about the storage model the rows store
versus column store stuff okay so at a
high level a tuple is just a sequence of
bytes it's just a byte array right and
it's up to the database management
system to be able to interpret that byte
array and make sense of it and say oh
yeah it's if this is an integer this is
a this is a float this is a string care
you know attribute so that's essentially
all what we're doing here we're just
organizing our tuples as if these byte
arrays and then when it comes time to
execute a query we need to interpret
what's actually in those byte arrays to
produce the answer that we're looking
for and so if this is what the catalog
stuff will talk about in a second this
is how they're gonna figure out oh I
have 10 columns what first one is a
32-bit integer the next one is 64-bit
float it uses that information decide
how to interpret and decipher those
bytes so the way we're gonna use for
most database systems away we're going
to represent data is for fixed length
things like integers and floats is
usually the same way that we would
represent this in like C or C++ this is
usually defined by what's called I
Triple E 754 standard who here is heard
of that before
the 754 standard all right a little bit
less than last year so the I took the 74
standards basically it's a for the
industry it's the specification of how
to represent numbers and CPUs like
integers and floats and things like that
how many bits you know where you know is
it in big-endian little-endian you know
have the two's complement in the front
all that is represented in that in that
standard
so for fixed-length types and integers
big and small and tiny ends and then
floating reels we'll just follow the 754
standard we'll discuss in a second about
the fixed point decimals but basically
these are floating point and then these
are fixed point and this is something we
and the data system will have to
implement for very length things
varchars of our binary techs and blobs
typically there's a header that says you
know you know here's here's the the
length of the blob I'm storing or the
bar at the very lengthy odom storing may
be a checksum if it's a really big big
value and then you have the the sequence
of bytes so this is different than
representing strings and sees where you
have the null Terminator character we're
instead could have a prefix that tells
us how big it is actually going to be
for dates and time stamps this varies
wildly across different database systems
right there's no one way to actually do
this
most of the systems usually just store
the you know the number of seconds or
microseconds or milliseconds since the
UNIX epoch which is like January 1st
1970 for Windows I don't know what they
do and so in a bunch of systems - also
you can say oh I want the date without
the time or I want the time without the
date underneath the covers are still
going to store the full timestamp it's
just the API that you use to access that
data knows that strip out whatever part
you don't need all right so some systems
will actually just pack in just the date
and we store that as a smaller smaller
value a bunch of systems actually don't
do anything so again this is something
we have in our database system this is
something we implement our database
system but the for the fixed point
values this will just rely on you know
whatever c++ gives us which should be
underlying hardware all right so the
thing we're gonna go talk about now
there's more interesting is again how do
we actually compare these to the fixed
point versus floating wooden decimals so
if you want to have floating my decimals
or very precision numbers I these are in
exact numbers that the CPU gives us or
like your c++ gives us because i you
have a c program and i call you know a
declared variable float whatever and
give it a verbal verbal name that's what
we're getting when we claire a real or
double or float in our database system
as like the sequel type again this is
specified how you actually represent
this like the decimal point and the
scope in the precision all that's
defined by the 754 standard so these are
gonna be much faster to executors to
operate on then the fix point decimals
the potato system provides because the
CPU has instructions to operate on these
very efficiently writes one instruction
to take to float floats and add them
together or subtract them but when we
talk about dealing with the fixed point
ones that's a whole bunch of stuff we
have to write and that's mean way more
instructions so this sounds like what
we'd want to use right because it's fast
the palm is though there's gonna be
rounding errors because the 74 standard
like there's no way to exactly store
decimals in in hardware so they have to
approximate this right so here's a
really simple C program I normally don't
like the show code in class other than
sequel but this is simple enough I think
you know you should be able to
comprehend it from your seat so all
we're gonna do is we have two floats x
and y and then we're gonna print out the
value of X plus y and then we're just
gonna print out the constant 0.3 so you
pick your favorite compiler I use GCC
and when you compile it you get this
answer here right that looks you know
that's correct right that's we would
expect but all I'm doing is just doing
your percent time app I'm just asking
that the languages to print out the the
floating-point and let it do whatever
rounding it wants to do when you specify
what precision you actually want so I'm
gonna go into 20 decimal points then you
see that you get a totally different
number same exact code same exact values
it's just when I represent it in a human
readable form now I'm seeing I'm way off
right I can't even get 0.3 correct I can
this is because the harbor can't exactly
represent floating-point numbers too you
know precisely right so again this will
be faster for us to execute but we're
gonna have rounding errors so now you
know this means you may think all right
0.3 my little example here who cares
where there's a rounding error but if
it's your bank account then you start to
care right
or if it's a scientific you know
instrument where you trying to send
something into space these round hairs
cause real problems so to avoid this you
use what are called fixed precision
numbers or picks point decimal numbers
so again these are something that the
ATM system has to implement to represent
these values it's a bunch of extra code
that can take care of all the you know
arithmetic operations or aggregations
you normally wouldn't want to do on any
kind of number right so the way you know
show how Postgres is gonna do this in a
second but the basic idea to think about
this is you're gonna store that value as
like a varchar' the actual like human
readable representation of the value and
then some extra metadata to say here's
what the decimal point is here is what
the scope is here's the rounding
information right and that's all packed
in with the tuple itself just as part of
that that byte array so I always give
this demo every year of Postgres and
sequel server right normally I nobody's
given Postgres
but we'll try for Oracle and single
server as well so let's see what the
performance difference is from these
different for these different types
turns off why is that readable all right
so what I've done is I've created a I
wrote a simple Python script and all it
did was create a giant CSV file that has
ten million rows of to floating-point
numbers right that's all it is
you just put random numbers so I can
load this I'm gonna create two tables in
Postgres I'm gonna create one that uses
reals and one that uses the the fixed
point decimals alright so there's one
for reals there's one for decimals and
then Postgres has a nice command called
copy that will take a file that's on
local disk and then take the output and
write it into the table various database
systems have various commands and secret
servers called bulk in in my sequel it's
called load into whatever Oracle was was
a pain to set up but I got it working
so now we're going to do is we're gonna
run a query that just takes the two
numbers and add them together so let me
turn on timing as well and then because
this is Postgres 10 Postgres 10 added
support for parallel queries so like you
know take a single single query and
split up across multiple CPUs and run
them in parallel so I'm gonna turn that
off as well just so we see like the
performance of a row you know a single
CPU I'm gonna do this for all the other
systems as well so let's see how long
would take if I do it with the reals so
if you've never seen this let me go back
to the syntax sorry so populate says
explain analyze so if you never seen
explain what explain does and put it in
front of any sequel query and instead of
actually running the sequel query it
tells you what query plan it's gonna use
to execute this query all right doesn't
actually run it says here's what I'm
gonna do if I ran it different data
systems have different syntax that's
what Postgres and my sequel do right
we'll explain what a query plan is well
I'm gonna optimize it maze optimizer
optimizer is late in the semester but
basically what happened you know just
saying like you wanna run this query
here's how we're gonna do it so but if I
add the analyse calls in front of it
then this is actually gonna give you the
query plan and also run it for real so
you see that it basically took twelve
twelve twelve hundred milliseconds so
1.2 seconds to run this and then to show
you if it's not a caching effect I can
just keep executing over and over again
and the performance I got little faster
because it got in the cache but it
should stabilize yeah about 800
milliseconds all right so let's do the
same thing now for the decimal one
so 2.4 seconds I run it again we should
get a little faster cuz it's in cash not
much right so again to same values same
data set loaded it as different data
types but though the one query is is
twice as slow because we're doing all
this extra stuff to deal with the
rounding and other things all right and
you see that let me see if I try to run
skin are getting the same values all
right they're getting given values here
right because it's because there's some
rounding issue issues so we can try to
cast this there's a desk mole and then
it'll be human readable right so this is
this is much different than this one
here right this is you know one and this
starts with it with a nine so the the
real one is having rounding issues so
let's try the same thing in in sequel
server the data is already loaded so we
don't we don't need to bother loading it
again so let me run this so this will be
with the reals produced as a result and
told me it took 1.5 seconds just try it
again
just see whether it gets faster not much
and then I'll run the same thing now
with the on decimals and it should be
slower yeah twice as slow we run again
disapprove right and there's this little
max dop it's the degree of parallelism
it's basically telling sequel silver
again run it with one one thread the
last one on my show is Oracle and I had
a breakthrough this weekend I figured
out how to get the up keyed at work so
it was not not by default
alright so it's already loaded I'll do
the same thing where is it Oracle so
we'll turn timing on
run it with the reels and you get 0.53
runabout decimals the same slightly
faster even so the way what's happening
here is that Oracle actually gives you
the fixed point decimal no matter what
you need ask you with the real or the
the decimal it always just gives you the
decimal right and before you say oh look
how much faster Oracle is any other ones
again for this one here like I didn't
turn off multi-threading but also looks
like is rounding off a lot right this
looks way off than what we'd expect from
Postgres and seagull server and that's
because Oracle has this thing where if
the size of the output is not doesn't
fit in whatever characters you specify
but there's none with thing then it
rounds it for you automatically took me
a while to figure that one out but
here's actually what you get when you
have the real number so that looks like
what we expect so again this is
something that just be mindful that you
know this is we have to implement in our
database system this is not something
that you know will magic go faster it's
not something that we can rely on hard
to provide for us yes question is it
doing rounding along the way is it only
at the end as far as a note here but
this stupid numb lip thing it's rounding
on the client side so the server is
giving you this and then it rounds when
it lands on the client why for whatever
reason I don't know right and in
Postgres in my sequel you can are so
Postgres in siegel server like you can
specify the round there's a round
function we could do on the server side
so I think we can do something like this
round and then you say what - what
precision you wants it like - nope
difference isn't that different thing is
that I think that's my sequel syntax I
don't know I don't know what Postgres
alright so you do neut but in your
application you want to do it
client-side or sorry server-side you
want the server to do for you don't want
to assume the clients gonna be
formatting whatever for you yes
so it looks like in the Oracle one that
the decimals is giving the same values
here so his question is it looks like
Oracle is giving us the value of the
real and not the floating box yeah hold
up let's see those three that that's
Oracle and this
let's try sequel server sis that's who
we'll assume that's correct because it's
sequel server but so that was nine
something and let's see what this gives
us nine something it looks the same
right yeah that's that's that's
different than what the reals gave us
I think reals was giving us like seven
point seven and this is seven point five
so going back to Oracle are say that's
press press too many terminals yeah but
it's the same hmm I don't I don't just
type it as live but link to
so maybe that it that is it's always a
decimal sorry it's always a real not the
fix point okay
I'll double-check that I declare it yeah
I definitely declare it as a decimal all
right let me figure what's going on I'll
play some Piazza okay any questions all
right cool
so let's look so what if poster is
actually doing can Postgres sequel
server an Oracle or not and the source
Postgres is if we can't look at it so
this is actually from the post go source
code version 9.6 I think
and so when you declare a fixed point
decimal this is what it stores it stores
this struct so you again you have all
this extra metadata about what the where
the decimal is what the sign is and so
forth and then this part here as I said
this is just a string representation of
what the real value actually is and then
at runtime they know how to take this
and decipher it based on what these
values are set to to ensure that you
have the correct commutation so now why
is it running twice as slow so we're
gonna yak again and look at the source
code to say how is actually doing
addition you see it's not just you know
one instruction you know number plus
number it's just giant switched a bunch
of stuff to try to figure out you know
if it's negative or non-negative it's
zero or if they're equal to each other
right so we're executing this for every
single time we compute those you know
number plus number whereas if it's a
real is if it's a floating point number
it's one instruction than the CPU so you
know we don't have the source code for
sequel server an Oracle but I guarantee
they're doing something something
similar
roughly okay so is this clear okay so if
we don't want to lose data due to
imprecision we use a fixed point decimal
but this is something we have to
implement in our database system for us
okay
so now we will talk about what happens
when the value of the trying to store is
too large and doesn't fit in a single
page there's two ways to do this so in
general as I said last time the size of
a page is going to be fixed throughout
the entire table mostly throughout the
entire database this is something you
set when you turn the system all and you
say I want to have you know 4qi pages or
8 kilobyte pages db2 allows you to play
around with the page saw
per buffer pool but in general for let's
assume that's the case so now what do we
do if the thing we're trying to store
doesn't fit in a single page right well
an obvious thing to do is have what's
called an overflow page so basically in
our tube let's say this value this
attribute C here doesn't fit in the page
so we'll just have a pointer now to some
other overflow page that'll have the
data that we want so this could just be
another record ID like a page number and
an offset to tell us where to find this
particular data that we need so then if
we now have a query and we need this
attribute or value as part of the output
we'd have to follow this pointer and go
bring that page and copy the data out
and produces an output now this data
isn't fit in this page by itself - you
can have another you know overflow page
pointer to some other thing out you know
some other page and we just you know
chain them all together to produce the
output that we're looking for so
different database systems have
different names for this in Postgres is
called toast in sequel server and my
Siegel the card overflow pages and they
have different specifications that when
they would actually use use something
like this so in in Postgres if the value
trying to store is larger than two
kilobytes then it always goes to this
other thing in sequel server it's just
two per doesn't fit in the page it pulls
it out and put them to another page and
my Siegel is half the page so the reason
why you'd want to do something like this
is because you get all the protections
you normally would get when these
overflow pages with your regular data
meaning if I'm writing to this overflow
page and I crash and come back I don't I
don't want to lose anything right
there's all the optimizations you can do
with the overflow pages that aren't easy
to do in the regular a lot of pages as
well like in Postgres for example since
most of the time these overflow pages
are read-only or read mostly like you
know think of like a Wikipedia you
update the you know an article or update
an entry but most the time people just
reading it so therefore I could just
compress this when I put out the disk
for keeping in memory and because the
most the time I'm never gonna have to
decompress it to update it so the month
of optimizations like that and they all
come under the same protections as you
normally would with regular data pages
or regular tuple pages another
alternative instead of storing it
directly inside the database is the use
what's called external storage and the
basic idea here is that we're not
actually gonna store the data for this
particular attribute in the tuple itself
we're just gonna store a pointer or a
file path to somewhere in on the local
disk or a network storage or some
external storage device where this this
data can be found right so in this case
here going from C this could be a file
path on the local disk so say you know
here's where to find this particular
attribute if you ever if you ever need
it right so in the systems that do
support this like Oracle and db2 and
Microsoft you can't actually modify
what's in this file right you can read
it but you can't manipulate it right yes
so his great question is or statement is
for the over lo page disk is brought
into memory just like a regular tuple to
page correct in the case of these
external files where do these things
reside music so if if you if you run a
query like select star run this tuple
here and sees in this external file if I
need to produce it as an output I gotta
go read it in so it could page it in
just like another another tuple or other
tuple pages
it could be ephemeral meaning like I'm
gonna read it and then immediately
discard it rather than polluting my cash
there's a bunch of different ways to do
this but the key thing to think about is
like if someone in now outside the
database modifies this file will see
that change inside of our database any
time we go to read it because there's
outside the control or the protections
of our database system all right so
everything I guess why do you want to do
something like this well what's an
example of a file maybe don't want to
store in the database system say you're
building website right and you have you
have a bunch of video files you want to
you know and you have a tuple that says
you know this person uploaded this video
you don't
store the video in the database itself
because that could be you know gigabytes
I said it's very common to see that and
those kind of things right the the
application frameworks like Django
nodejs and things like that they have
they have you know built-in ways to
store data outside the database system
for images and other things so there's
no there's there's no sort of set in
stone rule to say how big a file should
be but when you know to put it out as an
external file versus keeping it an
overflow page I'll say also to for the
overload pages this is transparent to
you as the application so you don't know
that you've gone to an overflow page
like you can go do what we did before
and look at the actual layout of in
low-level information about where our
data is actually stored like we did with
the CT ID and Postgres and the other
systems but most applications don't know
don't care that's stored in an overflow
page like I wanted to get my data out
for this thing again you depending on
how you actually house actually
implemented you could go through the
Davison or you could just jump to the
file and go get it directly if you
wanted to so the there was a paper
written almost 10 years ago over ten
years ago by some famous davids people
at Microsoft miss the the name of the
article was to blob or not the blob or
blob is a binary large object I just
it's a variable length binary data and
they basically found back in the 2000s
that anything below 256 kilobytes you
want to store as an overflow page
anything larger than that you want to
store in the you know an external file
storage
we had the guy that mented sequel Lite
come to CMU a few years ago came give a
talk here and he said that for a lot of
cell phone applications is actually
better off to store the the thumbnails
from images even up to one megabyte
inside the database system because it
would that that was much faster to read
those records from the database system
because they already had the file open
rather than having to follow this
pointer to the file system and then do
the you do the F open to go get the data
so again there's no hard and fast rule
what to do
this is also more common when when
you're you know the database storage is
super expensive right if you really care
about your data or your database your
views you're gonna run out on high-end
hardware and therefore storing like a
bunch of video files in some really
high-end enterprise this is probably not
a good use of your money so you can take
this you know these files chuck it in
HDFS or cheaper stores I guess three and
then now the days hasn't is not
overburdened with trying to maintain
your files so again it's not just not
just performance reasons the other
economical reasons why'd you want to do
something like this but this paper I
think summarizes a bunch of the issues
that's why I like it
so again so any questions have a good
represent data most of the times you
know for fixed length data it's just
whatever the programming environment
gives us for anything that's variable
length or if we want fixed point
precision that stuff will help implement
ourselves okay so now let's talk about
how what how we actually figure out what
our tuples look like so again this is
what the system catalogs are for it's
the metadata about the data metadata
about the database what comes I have
whether table names or indexes I have
and so forth as well as some other
things like you know user permissions
and security stuff which I don't care
about and then this will come up later
on when we talk about query optimization
but also internal statistics about what
your data looks like how many you know
how many unique values do I have what
does the distribution of those values
look like so pretty much every single
database system is going to store their
catalog inside itself as just just
another table so like eating your own
dog food so I'm gonna store all the
metadata about my tables in just tables
themselves all right and so inside the
source code you obviously don't want to
write sequel query to say you know
what's the name of this table because
it's chicken for the egg problem like
how do I do a sequel query on a table to
find out the table name if I need to
know a table name right so you usually
have like some you know C+ clip sepals
code whatever your theater system is
programmed in to wrap around the
low-level access methods to go access
the catalog
so the most David assistant will expose
the catalog through the standard
information schema API so in the 1980s
all these different database systems all
had their own way of saying here's my
catalog here so here's how to access it
and that became a real pain in the ass
now if you want to take your application
and port it to there from one database
system to another because now all the
catalog stuff is different and you got
to rewrite all your code again so in the
ANSI standard and I think also in the
sequel standard by now they'd specify
this thing called the information schema
that that every data system has to
support to say here's the the metadata
that about my tables but we'll see in a
second bail always exposed the same
information in these tables that all the
Davises was all gonna have their own
what sort of shortcut ways to go get
this information as well so for example
say if you want to get the all the
tables we have so the sequel standard
would say you write it with this
information about tables which is just a
view on top of the real catalog and you
give it the catalog name right or the
database name in Postgres you use /d and
my sequel you shoot tables sequel edits
dot tables and then again all the data
systems all have their own shortcuts and
essentially what they're doing
underneath the covers is converting this
command into something like this same
thing now if I want to get this schema
for a table so again this is how we do
it in the ANSI standard and then the
various systems all have their own own
way of doing this so I want to go a
quick demo of Postgres and my sequel
again just to show you what's actually
going on
[Music]
all right so it's again Postgres if I do
dash D I get the list of all my tables I
can do dash D plus and get more
information and then if I pick a table
it'll tell me what you know what the
metadata looks like so here's all the
columns that I have here's the types I
have something now when I run my query I
look at this information say all right
at the first attribute is an integer I
asking me 32 bits the next attribute is
also an integer that's gonna be 32 bits
and then I have code inside to say all
right if I'm operating ones tuple what
is the schema I know how to again do
that do the conversion of the raw bytes
of the byte array for that tuple and put
it to the form that it expect all right
so let me see if I can do this for my
sequel I think I just destroyed my
sequel let me do this on a another
machine so I can say show tables and
tells me tables I have I can say show
databases same thing here's all the
different different databases they have
and then for a given table I can say
describe knobs right and I'll just say
again same information here's the name
of the field here's the type and then
some extra metadata so this is my sequel
5.7 the newer version actually stores
the tables in the catalog itself or they
start service the catalog and the tables
itself in this version here they didn't
do that all they would do for the cowell
is just read the directory of where the
the database is stored and use that to
figure out what databases are there and
what what tables are there and so we can
actually break it or fake it out by
putting things that shouldn't be there
in that directory alright so if you go
back here let's split it
so do show databases and it thinks I
thinks I have a bunch of these here
right so now if I go back to this
machine login as root go into where my
sequel stores its data live my sequel
right and roughly you see that there's a
bunch of you know there's a bunch of
directories here for the databases that
it knows about but the data is called
tests there's a directory called test so
what happens if I call now make
directory xxx well I want to go back up
here my sequel thinks there's a
directory called xxx so so this is a
good example of where if we rely on
things X terms of the database system we
can't fully control that so my Siegel
can't prevent anybody from going to that
directory and putting better at once in
there but if it's but it's relying on
that to figure out what's in my database
so from an implementation standpoint it
might be easier but from a correctness
standpoint that's problematic
they may say who's gonna be stupid
enough to go create directories to screw
around with my sequel well what about
other things like I'm writing the files
then you know that I don't have the
regular protection I would for my
regular data because I'm not logging
things correctly right we want to put as
much as possible inside the database
system because then we can rely on that
to perform correctly for us okay all
right
so that's it that's all we really need a
cover for catalogs this semester just
kidding just be aware that there's
something that inside the dating system
wherever of what our schema looks like
and that's we're gonna use that when we
ask you queries use that when we build
indexes to determine you know what
should we actually be doing and the way
to think about this the different types
is that in the and there's easiest way
to implement this and you'll see this in
the bus hub code that you guys work on
when you look at the type system it's me
a giant switch statement right if the
type is integer do this if the type is
to float do that and so you're doing
that for every single tuple and that's
actually gonna be really slow because
they're actually interpreting you know
what the layout should be and in the
more advanced systems you can actually
compile or do code generation to compile
on the fly like just-in-time compilation
in the JVM to actually compile those
operations so that you don't have to do
that interpretation every single time my
C code doesn't do that new versions
Postgres does that but Oracle and sequel
server should do that as well all the
major commercial systems do that that's
not something we're to cover in this
class but when we cover a query
execution I'll bring that up to say this
is a way to write to make this run
faster all right so the next thing we'll
talk about is this for storage models is
the first thing if they realize that
we'd covered in the first lecture is
that the the relational model doesn't
say anything about how we actually want
to store data doesn't know about types
doesn't know about you know byte up byte
arrays and so forth and it doesn't
necessarily even say that we have to
store all the attributes of a tuple
together either in memory or on disk
right and so again anytime we you know
so far in the class when we visualize
databases now I'm saying here's the row
here's all the attributes for it right
for a tuple but that's not that may not
be the best way to do that for some
workloads so let's look at a really
simple database example here right this
is actually derived from the MediaWiki
software that runs wikipedia like if you
go look at look at their source code
it's all PHP with my sequel you look at
the DDL file the sequel file it'll look
roughly like this so we have three
tables
we have user account pages and revisions
and so the revisions table is where
we're going to store all the new updates
for every single article so it's a kind
of a foreign key reference to the user
that created that made the change and
then a page ID that corresponds to the
article or the page and this guy then
also has a foreign key preference to say
here's the latest revision for this
particular page so you don't to do a
scan you just can jump in directly to it
again this is a certain approximation a
cleaned up version of what Wikipedia
actually does but for our purposes in
this lecture here it's fine so there's
two sort of general class of workloads
we're gonna care about in database
systems you know they're certainly not
the only ones as machine learning and
streaming stuff but for now is this
focus on just two so the first is called
online transaction processing or OLTP
who here has ever heard that term before
OLTP phew okay good so this is usually
what you're gonna get end up with this
type of application any single time you
you're building your you know building a
new application and if I'm building a
new website I'm building a new iPhone
app or whatever you're typically gonna
building one of these and so for a
transaction OLTP online transaction
processing the idea is that this is
where we're getting new information
we're ingesting new data from the
outside world and putting it to our
database system right so these queries
can be really simple they're only gonna
read a small amount of data or update a
small amount of data every - do be doing
those same operations over and over
again so the example I always like to
give is it's like the Amazon storefront
all right the website you go to when you
buy stuff that's considered an ode to
the application because I'm adding stuff
to my cart I'm making purchases I'm
updating my account information I'm you
know for each of those single operations
they're doing a lot of them because I
have a lot of people buying stuff but
for you as just you as one customer
you're not updating a lot of data you
know you're updating your account
information you're updating things are
your shopping cart so the queries that
are running are only doing a small you
know the only you know accessing the
small portion of the database so then I
said the type of queries you would see
again going back to the BPD example so
here's go get the here's ago get the
current revision forgiven page here
update my user account to say that when
I logged in and here's here's a you know
simple insert query to insert a new
revision write each of those the these
things are accessing a small number
smaller number two goes at a time and
we're but we're doing these things over
and over again so now the other type of
workload is called OLAP or online
analytical processing and this is when
you've already collected a bunch of data
from your OTP application and now you
want to analyze it and extrapolate new
information from it
right this is sometimes called you know
not only say data science but that realm
of like taking a bunch of data you have
and trying to derive new information
from it with that yeah I mean it's in
the name online amical processing a
business intelligence there's another
phrase for this decision support is
another one big data if you want to call
it that right again I've in this
workload in this environment were not
updating data right there's a whole tree
saw it's getting that new information
for us and now we're trying to make
sense of it so a query might be on a
Wikipedia example say you want to count
the number of people that have logged in
per month that where their host name and
what ended with dot-gov there was a
scandal a few years ago where they found
members of Congress were painting or
having their employees go to Wikipedia
and scrub them clean to remove all like
you know whatever scandals the
congressman was involved in right so you
want to figure out all the people that
are logging in from from sitting at the
at the government doing this so these
types of queries are gonna be read-only
they're gonna read a lot of data like
I'm gonna scan the entire table right as
opposed to OLTP where I'm updating one
thing I'm gonna just do a lot of joins
right I know it's me you you you you
usually don't see a lot of joins so one
way to get to grossly characterize these
workloads is that on one end the we know
one acts as you say house how complex
are the queries are they're really
simple like they're you know you're only
accessing a single table or are they
doing complex joins and then what are
their right heavy or read heavy so all
of TP would be down on this
this and the spectrum they're pretty
simple queries and but they're doing a
lot of Rights oh that would be doing a
lot of reads but they're more complex
and then this sort of this new class of
workload called H tab or hyper
transaction analytical processing that's
sort of is trying to do both of them
right you still want to ingest new data
but you want to analyze it as it comes
in now you see this a lot in anybody
wants to do decision-making on the fly
you know as people are browsing websites
you see this a lot in like internet
advertising companies so so now given
that we know about these different
workloads now we can talk about what is
the right storage model to support these
workloads more efficiently so again the
relational model doesn't say anything
about the layout but we can be mindful
of this when we decide how we want to
build our data system yes okay so this
question is what is the relation of OLAP
to no sequel or new sequel systems so I
would say so
then wonder what no sequel is who here
doesn't know what no sequence ok so and
most we haven't heard of no sequel or
new sequel so these are workload types
so so and what you're describing new
sequel versus no sequel those are sort
of system categories so the other
question is we know what is MongoDB for
what you know what is the know see good
for so that the traditional no sequel
systems MongoDB Cassandra Redis they
would be at this end of the spectrum
they're about ingesting new data right
has some support to do some
analytics but when we talk about the the
column store stuff there not a column
store they're gonna get crushed by it by
any you know column store database you
wouldn't want to do hardcore analytics
on a MongoDB you can will support some
queries to do this my sequel post
personal support some queries that that
would would fall under the OLAP category
but they're not going to be as efficient
as as running on a column store system
so no sequel
basically there was this movement in the
in the late 2000s where all these all
these all these companies are basically
saying look Google made it make is
making a ton of money and they put out
this system called HBase or some
knowledge with BigTable and this thing
called Hadoop and they're not doing
sequel they're not doing transactions
they're not doing joins and that's how
the able to scale so all these people
ended up building these no sequel
systems like and Cassandra that
sort of fall dunder you know to try to
follow those EDX or design patterns and
to support you know sort of modern you
know software 2.0 or web 2.0
applications right but they would follow
on fall under this Hadoop is OLAP but
like BigTable saundra MongoDB and those
guys are over here then what happened is
people realize oh well I actually do
want transactions I do want sequel I do
want to do some joins and that's where
the new sequel movement came along and
this is what I was working on when I was
in grad school and actually if you go
read the Wikipedia article for a new
sequel he talked about my system was the
first one of the one of the first new
sequel systems right and this is because
I wrote the new sequel article Wikipedia
so I could say whatever I wanted
but the idea was they were trying to do
you know they're trying to do fast
transaction processing and OLTP without
giving up transactions or giving up
joins the way the no sequel guys did
now there's other no sequel systems you
could say or like you know again the
there's a bunch of systems out there
that don't do relational model that you
wanna do analytic so on but primarily
most people think of it thinking of
these guys down here I would say that
the claim no sequel they you know first
they're like oh we're not gonna do
sequel sequel stupid and then it came
out everybody but now supports
some variant of sequel so then they said
oh no seek overly me is not only sequel
[Music]
but and some of them actually are
starting at transactions like MongoDB
has support for a full fledge distribute
transactions so all the things they
claimed that were a bad idea you know
ten years ago turns out it is a good
idea
Siegel's not gonna die anytime soon
people have tried to replace it right
they've been people are thought with a
bad idea in the 1970s 80s 90s and 2000's
it always comes back right it's what
people want it's not the grim I like it
because you know this is what I would I
grew up with but there's certainly ways
to improvements people try to do this
but it's a core idea of declarative
language on top of your data is I think
this is even one of the major
contributions of Ted Cod's work in the
1970s yeah I did that there's a long
soliloquy does that answer your question
okay we can talk offline about if you
want my opinion of other systems okay
okay
everything we talked about so far when
we took when we show rows and tuples
sorted tuples like this is why I'd want
to use a turn row because when we talk
about a column store it doesn't make any
sense
but every time I showed a tuple I showed
it as a row right and this is called the
n Airy storage model and so basically
idea here is that we ran take all the
attributes for a single tuple and we
restore them continuously in our pages
now again we can have the overflow pages
- you know for large larger objects but
in general it's all going to be aligned
together right so this is going to be an
idea 400 TP because
began the amount of data we're going to
access is gonna be small in these old
speed queries and it's gonna be
accessing for single entities go get my
account information go get my orders and
I want all the data for that you know
you know for my account I don't care
about all the other you know millions of
customers I did want my information so
if a roast or that's actually really
efficient because I just jump to the one
page that has my data I get it and I'm
done all right so let's see what this
looks like so again using the Wikipedia
example so say this is a single page so
we have a header I can assume this is in
the slotted slotted page format we have
our header and then we have the user ID
username user past host name it Lazlo
again and so when we add only after that
we have the last attribute for our tuple
then we have all the other tuple tuple
data right everything is continuous to
each other so again so now if I store
this in my database I can represent this
in a single page so now if I have a
query that says get all the account
information for a given user name and
password I can do a lookup and an index
which we'll cover in in lecture seven
but that's basically they tell me hey
here's the page ID and slot number that
has the tuple that you want I do one
seek I do one reading fetch that page
bring him to memory and I can jump to
exactly to the location that has the
data that I want right so again although
it's we workloads are gonna look a lot
like this go getting the data for single
entities or small number entities so
having all the data for a tuple
contiguously each other is the most
efficient way to do this alright same
thing about one do an insert I my insert
query is gonna have all the data
contiguous anyway so I just find a free
slot and there's right at all all at
once and then flush this this out and
it's one disk right
ignoring a log yes so this question is
from what purpose would be useful to
segregate the data into pages okay so
let's look at why this is the bad idea
for some queries and then we'll see why
it's a good idea to segregate it alright
when we talk about the decomposition
storage model at the columns for stuff
all right so let's look at example where
the row store is a bad idea
so let's
taking that query I showed in the
beginning where we want to get all the
people from the government that are no
modifying Wikipedia pages when they
shouldn't so we break down this query
right we look at it we realize we're
actually gonna need to touch all the
data right because there's a full
sequential scan across the user account
table to find all the people that you
know look at all the user accounts look
at their host names I assume we don't
have an index for OLAP you usually don't
have indexes for for these types of
queries all right so now if I go read
say the first page I read is this one
again we're in a row store here so I
look at my query I want to first do a
where clause is to look up the host name
and try to match up my pattern if it
ends with gov so that means I basically
just want you know these values here so
as I'm scanning along I look at my
catalog and says well I know I have for
this table I have five attributes and
you want the host name so that's that
this all set so I go read them but I
want and then I get to the end and I'll
jump to the next one and so forth the
other part of my query is that I have
this group I where I want to aggregate
them together based on the login because
I want to get it per month and then all
right and then produced that as my final
output it's the count number of
government employees that are logging in
for each month so satisfy this part of
the query I only need this column here
this attribute just the last login field
so what's the problem what's that
exactly so so I had to read this whole
entire page again I can't and in memory
I said in non-volatile storage devices
it's a block based API so I can't just
say just get me exactly these this data
I gotta go bring in the entire page so
now you have all this these columns here
that I'd never even access at all
in order to exit this query but I had to
bring it into memory from disk to in
order to get to get the two columns that
I actually needed so doing analytics on
a row store is is gonna be painful if
you have a lot of data right my example
here I have six pages who cares but if I
have you know petabyte
and in this case here three out of the
five columns that I'm bringing in or
atrs I'm bringing in is useless for the
particular query then that's a bad idea
that's an inefficient use of the
hardware so again the NRI storage model
the rostral row storage model is we
really fast or any inserts or updates or
deletes when we're accessing the entire
tuple all right we want all the at rates
for a single tuple and is usually just a
small number of tuples at a time but if
you have to do analytical queries and
the OLAP workloads we want to scan large
portions at the table then this is gonna
suck because we're gonna bring a bunch
of data in that we don't may not
actually need for for our query so now
it should be a sort of obvious that this
is where the comps or stuff comes in
where instead of storing the all the
attributes for a single tuple together
in a single page we're actually going to
store all the values for a single
attribute across all tuples in a single
page I sort it's in this is where the
column name is we're just storing all
the columns together continuously sorry
all the values within a single column
continuously so this is me fantastic for
our OLAP workloads where we're read-only
and we only want to read up a subset of
the the of the theatrics for a given
table right so again going back to our
example here so this is what it looks
like as a row store but so say now we
just take every single column and we're
going to split that up and now then
within a single page we have just the
data for that column so here's all the
host names together and we had the same
thing where user ID last login and the
other attributes for this table here
alright so forth like that so now I come
back to this query we had before so the
first thing I need to do is do my where
clause on hostname so now I just need to
know all I have to do is go bring in the
hostname page wrong color but ignore
that I just bring the hostname page in I
can then rip through that quickly say
look at every single hostname and do my
my predicates now I have a bunch of
tuples that matched so then I go back
and bring in the bring in the last of
all game page and just jump to the
locations that I need within that and
get the last login information that I
did I
I want to produce my answer so say in a
real simple case here that the last
login page is one last login data is one
page the host name is another page so
before I had to scan all the pages and
this one I didn't only have to scan to I
can't think of in extremes if I'm
talking about billions of pages I then
that that's a big difference
yes so this question is are we storing
the primary key with each columns is
your real question is how do I figure
out I had the host names that match how
do I then go look up in the last login
column and figure out how they match
next slide
perfect and you have questions so the
blows are other stuff we can do with
this that we're not gonna cover in this
class but the most of other advantages
you can get and actually if you come to
the vertical talk in two weeks Vertica
is super famous for this so with the the
row stored model all the values within
or the attributes within the tuple
they're all you know roughly different
domains right this is gonna be a
username this is gonna be host names
it's me last login we're just gonna look
a timestamp right it's all sort of
jumbled together and so if I can then
pack them all this data together that
are the same column now that's one of
compression techniques I can do because
I know they're gonna be all the the same
type right so let's say let's say that
I'm storing temperatures of the room and
you know it's it's 70 degrees now maybe
70 point one seven eight seventy point
two like it's not gonna fluctuate that
much instead of storing that that's the
full temperature every single time what
right is shorter a small Delta of of
what the base temperature was when we
first started taking measurements and
now I don't need to store the entire
value all over again I just store you
know that's smaller representation I
think I mean think of like you know if
you run like gzip or snappy or whatever
your favorite compression algorithm is
you can't compress an mp3 really well
because there's already sort of
compressed but if it's a text file that
you can compress the hell out of that
because there's gonna be a bunch of
characters repeating over and over again
so if you have repeated values in in
your in your attribute then you can
compress the hell out of it and get much
better performance so now when I go want
to go to a read again
with every page fetch instead of maybe
getting a thousand tuples I could get
like ten thousand two books because in
compressed form and some systems
actually can operate directly on
compressed data without you without
getting hung compressor which is the big
win okay we don't cover we're not gonna
cover compression in this class we spent
a whole lecture in it in the advanced
class but I'm happy to talk about more
about it if you want okay so now the his
question is how do I figure out I had a
match in one page how do I find a match
in another page so in general there's
two approaches but everyone pretty much
does the first one so the first choice
is to have fixed length all sets so that
means that for every single value in a
column it's always going to be a fixed
length so again think simple a 32-bit
integer so all these are going to be
each of these values to be 32 bits so
now if I have a match say in this column
at offset 1 and i'm agai need to find
the corresponding tuple in in this
column i know that say this comes also
32 bits and i can just do a simple
arithmetic and say I want offset 1 times
the size of each attribute and then I
know exactly where I need to jump to or
translate that to the row ID or the the
page number and slot number that has the
data that I'm looking for so that this
is probably the most standard approach
of course now the tricky thing is say
well what if I have a bunch of strings
that are varying like the old then you
get into like alright can I compress it
to a fixed length field or kind it's
padded outs as always fits in whatever
the max size is different data systems
do different things but overall this is
this is the most business common
approach the other approach which I
forget there's like one system that does
this which i think is a bad idea
they might have gotten rid of it but I
forget who it is where you actually
store in each for each value in the
column you store a the primary key or an
identifier for it so then you say
alright I'm at it for the column one I'm
looking at tuple 1 and I want to get to
tuple 1 and column B I have another map
or going to do a lookup and say how to
go find the offset location for that for
that particular tuple in this column of
course obviously this has huge storage
overhead because you're storing this for
there's you know this extra 32 bit or 64
that value or our ID for every single
value which is wasteful all right all
right so the advantages of the
columnstore is that we can reduce amount
of waste I owe for these OLAP queries
because we're only reading the the
bearment amount of data we actually need
we're not bringing in things we're never
gonna need it all will get better
compression will give it a bet better
query processing which we will cover and
a few more lectures because we're know
we know we're operating on columnar data
the the downside is obviously that for
anything that needs access a single
tuple it becomes more expensive because
now you essentially need to put together
the the tuple from the different columns
back together whereas in the row store
it's all just in one location for you
and anytime you update or in sort of
delete this becomes more expensive
because again because it you get to
split it all up so I would say that
column stores are not a new idea they go
back to the 1970s there was like the
Swedish military division built this
thing called Cantor which essentially
was they didn't call it a database
system because they used different
language back 1970s but if you go sort
of read between the lines it at his
essence it is a column store database
system it was never released never made
pop made public was this it was the only
this internal project but that's the
first known implementation of a column
store the 1980s there was a paper that
describes the decomposition storage
model and more for more details to say
you know what what are the what's the
short format look like what is the
implications of having this storage
model the some of the probably most
famous commercial implementation among
the first commercial implementations was
this thing called sybase IQ it was an
in-memory columnstore that Sybase
released as an accelerator for their
regular row store database system sort
of have had have you actually worked at
HEPA - and in sync and there never
really got big adoption because again it
was sold as a add-on to the rows store
database rather than a standalone thing
but it was the 2000s when the column
store stuff really took off Vertica
again was founded by mike Stormbreaker
the guy admitted Postgres and ingress
that was his company that got bought by
HP vector wise is a in-memory version of
mo'ne to be monie be
they out of Europe it's academic project
but still around today I see he's
asserted the first sort of columns for
our systems that were ever made in
2000's but then it quickly became
obvious that this is the right way to
build data systems to for analytics so
pretty much everyone now has their own
column store system and actually I
wanted to give a demo of Vertica today I
couldn't get it running I did get the
Maria DB column store working and
stephannie column store doesn't mean
it's actually good so there's a bunch of
stuff we'll cover as we go along for
query optimization in Korea execution
just because I cut your comms or doesn't
mean you're magically gonna go faster I
was actually able to get Postgres to
beat the column store for analytical
queries because you know of how you
actually queries how you actually look
at the data and what the query plan
looks like so the bunch of stuff we have
to do it that we'll cover throughout the
semester that you have to that you want
to do if you know dirt if you're a
column store that not everyone does okay
so any question about column stores so
if you go off and me graduate from CMU
and you want to do analytics and some
was like let's do it on post grass but
it's a roast or don't do that right
there's enough columns for systems that
are out there that will they do you want
to look at they're not cheap though at
least for the commercial ones but
there's some decent open-source ones
okay all right cool so the the main
takeaways from this is that as we show
the the underlying representation of the
of the storage of the database is not
something we can just sort of put in our
storage manager and not expose to any
other part of the system as we go out
the rest of the semester you'll see that
a lot of times I'll say like alright
this is the way to do it if you're a row
store this is the way to do it if you're
a column store and that's because again
we if we know the data system knows more
about what it's actually doing what what
the data looks like it's gonna make
better decisions and better design
choices and in order to get you know
more efficient execution the other thing
to also remember to basically for osep
you want to use a row store for OLAP you
want to use a column store but these
this simple rule will carry carry you
out through the rest your life and make
your life easier alright so now the last
two classes we covered the
this problem here how to actually
represent the data in the database so
now on starting on Wednesday we'll talk
about what do we add we actually bring
the data in and bring them to memory and
manage that yes this question is there
any good reason to do a mix of the two
so we actually built our Davidson that
did did a mix of the two we threw that
away and started over because it's a bad
idea it was too much engineering
overhead there are some database systems
will give you both they'll expose like
some M sequel for example you can say
create this table in it and it's a roast
or create this other table on its a
column store and they have essentially
two separate storage managers two
separate execution engines to operate on
them so those are sort of called hybrid
storage systems hybrid data systems we
were all in I thought that was a good
idea I think it's a bad idea now I for n
memory we actually can do we think we
can do fast enough transactions on a
column store for disk it's a little more
complicated so there are systems that do
both they're not they didn't really take
off as much so usually you see things
like you'll have you could have a single
interface where they have you write one
query and then underneath it covers it
figures out what you want to go the row
store comscore aside there's ways to do
that but having a single single single
cell for architecture that can manage
both I think is is rough he says why
don't we store two copies of the same
data
great think of it extremes my database
is one petabyte so well I'm slides ready
but like I can easily find but I can
cover this next class but basically with
what people do is you have your front
end OTP systems and that's running my
sequel or whatever you want and
then you stream the data out over time
to a back-end data warehouse and then
you basically can prune out the latest
data on the old or old data on the HP
side when you don't you know you don't
need it anymore so you see this in like
eBay eBay only retains the last 90 days
of auctions and after that they print it
out and that's because they want to keep
the OTP side nice and trim and fast
but then they still retain everything
else in the backend data warehouse would
they do all the analytics to figure out
what people are buying what when what
they're doing that's the that's the
standard setup everyone does right and
whether or not that's like montant you
know my Segal plus plus vertical like
two separate database installations or
whether it's a single hybrid database
like splice machine can do this or mem
Siegel could do this depends on what you
want you know how much money you have
what you're willing to do I think that
what we found for our own system is that
building having a super single Storage
Manager try to man both of these things
was a bad idea among other things okay
someone brought up testing last time and
I really want to spend time to talk
about that but I wouldn't have any time
today but again next class we'll start
talking on the buffer pool and hopefully
we talk about testing a little bit at
the end okay and the other questions hit
it
oh cool Michelle in the mix of broken
bottles and crushed up kids let the cows
in the
he's witzy nights in my system racking
up I'm blessed
let's go get the next one then get over
time I'll be dressed down good net will
be son ricochet jelly hit the deli photo
put one naturally bless ya my rap is
like the laser beam the fools in the
bush say nothing like a chicken wrap the
bottle of us a nice Tiffany go you don't
feel like drinking it only to you talk
you can't try using life and if the sake
don't know your phone can tap a