[Music]
all right
hey done grab your wrap you look down
what's wrong city women woman problems
what do you say men problems what are
your problems they were saying your
beats are too fresh and they can't
handle it I'm not qualified to help I'm
sorry okay
all right so let's talk about databases
then all right so a quick reminder
homework one is due tonight and then
project one is going out today I'll sit
at the end of the class there's actually
the website now the source code is
online but I'll discuss what it is what
you're required to do today and then
just like before you're submitted some
great scope and you know everything will
be auto graded all right um I do want to
spend some time talking whatever lab
work loads is where after you've
collected a bunch of data in the OLT
side now you want to start analyzing it
to extrapolate new information like
people in the city of Pittsburgh are
more likely to buy this kind of product
I said you can use that information to
then you know push information to the
OTB side to get people to do things you
want them to do and then the hybrid
transaction analytical processing h-type
workloads this is sort of a new buzzword
that Gartner invented a few years ago
basically describing these database
systems that try to do both of them
so a typical setup you'll see often is
like this you'll have your front end ODB
databases and then you have your giant
back-end data warehouse so these are
sometimes called data silos because you
can do poncho updates into them sort of
one database instance whether it's a
single node or shivudu doesn't matter
because it's a single logical database
and then you apply your changes here but
they don't really communicate with each
other each one is sort of an island by
itself so then you can do what's called
extract transform and load or ETL and
this is sort of a
the term you use is described taking
data out of these front ends cleaning it
up processing it and then putting it to
the back end data warehouse so the
example I like to get for this is like
Zynga the farmville people they buy a
lot of gaming startups and then when
they buy them they all run their own
front end mediator basis but then when
they want to put it in their back-end
giant data warehouse so they can do
analyze things to make you buy crap on
farmville better right and so because
say like in one database the first name
of a customer will be F name another
database we you know F first underscore
name right so it's the same concept or
same entity just with different
different syntax and nomenclature
so this ETL process cleans all that up
you shove it to your data warehouse you
do all your analytics here and then
whatever new information you have you
push it to the front all right and when
you see things like people that bought
this item also bought this item that's
that they're doing that on the OLAP side
and then they shove it to the front end
to expose that through the OTP
application so H tab basically says
let's just also do some of the integral
queries that we can normally only do on
the OLAP side we can do it on the front
end data silos you still want this giant
thing your giant data warehouse because
you want to be able to look at all your
data silos put to put together but now
instead of waiting for things to be
propagated to the backend you can do
some things on the front-end so that's
basically what H type is so again this
could be like your my sequel does your
Postgres MongoDB whatever you want and
then your back-end data warehouse would
be Hadoop stuff spark greenplum Vertica
there's there's large enterprise data
warehouse systems redshift or snowflake
your other cloud ones okay so this is
clear okay so the main topic today we're
talking about is now given that we've
already spent two previous lectures on
deciding how we're actually gonna
represent the database in on disk now we
want to talk about what we actually do
to bring the database from those files
on disk the pages on disk and bring them
into memory so that we can operate on
them right so remember that we the
database system can't operate directly
on disk we can't do reads and writes
without having to bring into memory
first that that's the von Neumann
architecture now there are some new
hardware coming out you can push
execution
logic down to the disks but we can
ignore that for now so we're trying to
figure out how do we want to bring back
those pages in the disk and we want to
do this and be able to support a
database that exceeds the amount of
memory that we have and we want to
minimize the impact the slowdown or the
problems of having queries tap that
touch data on disk we want to make it
appear as if everything's in memory so
another way to think a problem is is
also in terms of spatial versus temporal
control so spatial control is you know
where are we physically gonna write this
data on disk right meaning like we want
we know that these pages are can be used
together often possibly one after
another so when we write those pages out
we want to write them sequentially so
that when we go read them again though
we though we you know write and
physically close to each other and we
don't have to do long seeks to find
different spots on disk we also care
about temporal control and this is where
we make decisions about when do we read
pages into memory what time we do this
and then at some point we have to write
it back out if it's been written if it's
been modified and we don't make a
decision of when we actually go ahead
and do that and yeah this is the
overarching goal of trying to minimize
the number of stalls we have because our
queries try to read data that we didn't
have in memory and we had it right up
you know that was out on disk we had to
go fetch it so this is the overall
architecture of the lower store manager
but I showed in the beginning so we've
sort of covered this part already so now
we know how to have a database file or
files on disk we know how to represent
the page directory to find the data we
need and then we have a bunch of pages a
lot of pages log structure pages it
doesn't matter we have a bunch of pages
on disk and we know how to jump to them
to find them so we now we're talking
about this part up here at the buffer
pool right when something else in the
system like the execution engine the
thing executing queries comes along says
I want to read page two we got to know
how to fetch the page directory into
memory figure out what's in there and
then go find the the page that we want
and fetch that into memory and then the
tricky thing is going to be if we don't
have enough space now free memory to
bring that page we need in we have to
make decision what page to write out so
that's you know this is what we're
trying to solve today right and then the
the other parts of the system don't need
to know or really care about what's you
know what's in memory with not in memory
there's going to wait until you get the
thing you
and give you back a pointer to let you
do whatever it is that you wanted to do
okay so the things were talked about
today is essentially just how to build
what a buffer pool manager actually
gonna do in some comedies the term
buffer pool manager some systems will
call this a buffer cache it's the same
thing right it's memory manage by by the
database system then we'll talk about
how we actually can do different
policies that decide what we know what
pages we want to write out that that's
what pages if you need to free up space
additional optimizations we can do to
minimize this impact and then we'll
finish up talking about two other pieces
of the data system that may need memory
okay so again the buffer pool is
essentially just a large memory region
that we're gonna allocate inside our
database system we're gonna call malloc
I want to get some chunk chunk of memory
and that's we're gonna put all our pages
that we fetch from disk and so this is
again this is all entirely managed by
the memory by the database system other
than having go to the operating system
and ask for the memory right we have to
use malloc there's we handed malloc or
allocate memory on our own so we know s
can provide us this but then we're gonna
break up this memory region into fixed
size or page size chunks called frames
and this is you know frame seems kind of
unusual why don't I just say page or
block or whatever there's so many
different terms in database systems to
roughly describing the same thing so
frames correspond to slots in the or see
I use the term slot when use that frames
correspond to regions or chunks in the
buffer pool memory region that we can
put pages in right and we slot is the
thing we put things into pages within
for tuples
so for buffer pool it's it's frames for
on the page it'll be slots so what
happens is when the database system
calls makes a request and say I want a
page right we're gonna look to see
whether it's already in our in our
buffer pool if not then we go out in the
disk make a copy of it fetch that you
didn't put it into memory so this is a
straight one-to-one copy we're not doing
any D civilization all right we can
ignore compression for now but whatever
however it's represented on disk is
exactly how it'll be represented in
memory we're not doing any marshaling of
the data we just take take it from the
disk and put it directly in the memory
all right we keep doing this roll all
the other pages that that that we may
need
right so the in my earlier example when
I sin I showed how the execution ender
says hey I want a page to write it
manually you know Buffalo manager magic
figured out what page two is so in our
if we're just organizing these things as
frames pages can go in any order in the
frames that they want right in this case
here even though it's page one page one
two three in my buffer pool its page one
three that's not in the same order that
it's out on disk so we need an extra
indirection layer above this to figure
out if I want a particular page what
frame has the one I want because it's
not going to match exactly the same
order that it is on disk so this is what
the page table is page table is just a
hash table that's going to keep track of
what pages we have in memory and if you
ask for a particular page ID it'll tell
you what frame that is located located
in all right and so the database systems
can have to maintain some additional
metadata to keep track of what what's
going on with the pages that it
currently has in its buffer pool so the
first thing we got to keep track of is
called the dirty flag and this is just a
flag single bit that tells us whether
the page has been modified since it's
been read from from disk did some query
some transaction make a change to it the
other thing that I keep track of also is
called a pin count or a reference
counter and this is just keeping track
of the number of threads or queries that
are currently running that want this
page to remain in memory meaning we
don't we don't want it written out to
disk right it could be because I'm gonna
update it so I do my fetch I go fetch
the page I need bring into my buffer
pool then I'm gonna go ahead and go
ahead and modify I don't want that page
to get evicted or swapped out back at
the disk in between the time it's been
brought in and before I can actually do
my update to it there's also gonna
prevent us from evicting pages that have
not been safely written back to disk yet
alright so again so like I get painted
page and say I don't want this thing in
to every ever be removed from the buffer
pool for now and then say I'm reading a
page here sorry I want to read a page
that's not currently memory I want to
put a latch on this this entry in the
hash table
so that I can go fetch the page and then
update the page if I do not point to it
right and I have to do this because
multiple threats were running at the
same time I can't assume that I'm the
only person I'm looking at the page
table so I want to rent somebody else
from taking this this entry in my
patient and while I'm fetching the page
that I need they come and steal it from
me and put something else in alright so
again is theirs well see this as we go
along later in the semester but there's
a bunch of extra stuff we have to do to
keep track of what pages have been
modified so the dirty bit is just sort
of one piece of it we also need keep
track of who actually made the
modification so because we want to write
a log record to say here's the change
that was made we're gonna make sure that
log records written first before our
page is written this is another example
ymf is a bad idea because i can't
guarantee the operating system is not
gonna write my page out the disk before
I want it to okay that's it doesn't
doesn't prevent you from doing that at
least on linux freebsd can let you do
this but windows and linux don't want
you prevent this alright so is this
clear what we're trying to do here right
basically managing our own memory but
we're keeping track of how the
transactions or queries are modifying
the pages and we have to protect
ourselves and the page table to prevent
anybody else and you know addicting
things or writing stuff before we're
done with with what we wanted me to do
any questions okay so I need to make a
very important distinction now about the
difference being locks and latches so
this will come up later on you have to
do this for the first project as well if
you're coming from an operating system
background in in there roll a lock is
what we call a latch so in in in the let
me try both of them in the context of
databases and I'll see us to describe
how they map into the OS world so a lock
in dated in the database world is some
higher-level logical primitive that's
going to protect the contents of the
database the logical contents like a
tuple a table a database all right and
the transaction is gonna hold this lock
for its duration and while it's running
which means could could be multiple
queries this could be you know multiple
milliseconds or multiple seconds even or
even in minutes or hours if it's a
really long running query
so in that world again this is something
that data systems can provide to us and
expose to you as like the application
programmer you even see what locks are
being held for as you run queries
latches are the low level protection
primitives that we use for the critical
sections of the internals of the
database systems like perfecting
protecting data structure perfecting
protecting regions of memory and so for
these these latches we're gonna hold for
just the duration of the operation that
we're making like if I go update my page
table I take a latch on the entry on the
location of that I'm gonna modify make
the change and then I release the latch
all right and we're not we don't need to
worry about rolling back any changes in
the same way we do for locks because
it's it's an internal thing or updating
the physical data structure of the
database system I make the change and if
I can't actually get the latch I want
then I did a board and and don't worry
about rolling back yes okay so he says
rolling back changes this will come
later on we talk about courtesy troll
but basically say like I wanna take
money out of my bank account and put it
in your bank account so we take money
out of my bank account but then the
system crashes before I put the money in
your account I want to roll back the
change I made to my account because I
don't to lose that money that's not to
me like that right this will discuss a
whole lecture on convergent roll it's
awesome trust me but for now the main
thing we're focused on this thing here
right so again in the operating system
world this would allow should be
something like a mutex we're actually
going to use mutexes in in our database
system to protect the critical sections
of things so I will try to be very
careful and always say latch when I mean
latch but occasionally I slip up and
we'll use lock but I said it's an
internal thing we mean latch it's also
very confusing too because the mutex
implementation you would use to protect
you for his latch is called a spin lock
alright but it's really you know this
thing and not this thing ok all right
so the other think we want to make is
the difference between the page
directory and the page table so remember
the page directory is what we're going
to use to figure out where to find pages
in our files so we want page 1 2 3 it'll
tell us what file at what all said or
what's what set of files
have-have what we're looking for so all
the changes we're gonna make to the page
directory have to be durable they have
to be written about the disk because if
we crash come back we want to know where
to find the pages that we have the page
table is an internal in memory map that
just mats page IDs to where the the
frames of a are in the buffer pool so
this thing can be Italian ephemeral and
we don't need to backup by disc because
if we crash and come back our buffer
pool is blown away anyway so who cares
so this page directory has to be durable
the the page table does not does not
have to be and that means we just used
whatever your favorite hash map or hash
table implementation you want right for
project 1 you're just used s to be a
city map that's fine because again we
don't have to worry about this thing
being durable we have to make sure it's
thread safe certainly but not not
durable all right so now when we start
talking about how we want to allocate
memory in our database for the buffer
pool we will we throw to think about
this in two different ways so the first
is that we can choose what I call a sort
of global policies where we're trying to
make decisions that benefit the entire
workload that we're trying to turn
trying to execute we look at all the
queries all the transactions that are
going on in the system we try to say at
this point in time what's the right
thing I should do for choosing what
should be in memory versus not memory an
alternative is to use a local policy
we're on for each single query or each
single transaction we're running we try
to say what the best thing to do to make
my one query one transaction go faster
even though for the for the the global
system that actually might be a bad a
bad choice so the there's no one way
that's better than another obviously
there's optimization you can do if you
have a global view versus a local view
but then for each integer query you
might be be more tailored to what they
want to do to make that run fast
so as we've seen a much of these
examples as we go along for
optimizations the most systems will
probably try to do accommodation of the
two of them what you'll be implementing
for the first project is considered a
global policy because there's just
looking at you know what's the least
recently used page and removing that
even though that make me bad for one
particular query all right so that
basically all you really need to know
about how to build a buffer pool right
it's just you have a page table that
map's page IDs to frames and then you
look in the all set and you're in the
allocated memory and that tells you
here's the page that you were looking
for it seems pretty simple right so now
we want to talk about how to actually
make this thing be super awesome or
super tailored for the application that
we're trying to run or the work over
trying to run inside of our database
system and this is gonna allow us to do
certain things that the operating system
can't do because it doesn't know
anything about what kind of queries
you're running it doesn't know what data
they're touching what are they're gonna
touch next
all right so now we can talk about what
we can do to make this thing do better
than what sort of a naive scheme would
do so talk about how to handle multiple
buffer pools prefetching the scan
sharing and then the last one be buffer
pool bypass okay so in my example that I
showed I referred to the buffer pool as
a single entity and the datum has one
buffer pool in actuality you can have
multiple buffer pools so you have
multiple regions of memory you've
allocated they each have their own page
table they each have their own been
mapping to from page IDs to frame IDs or
frames all right and the reason why you
want to do this is now you can have for
each buffer pool you can actually have
local policy for that buffer pool that's
tailored for whatever is the data that
you're putting into it you know so for
example I could have a a single buffer
pool for each table because maybe some
tables I'm doing a bunch of scruncho
scans and some tables I'm doing point
queries or I'm jumping to single pages
at a time and I can have different
cashman policies or different placement
policies to decide based on the two
workload types but I can't do that
easily if it's a giant just a giant a
buffer pool well let's say I have it I
can have a buffer pool for an index and
buffer pool for tables and then they
have different access patterns and then
I can have different policies for each
of those
the other big advantage you also get is
that it's gonna end up reducing latch
contention for the different threads
that are trying to access it right so
when I do that look up in the page table
I have to take a latch on the entry that
I'm looking at as I go find the frame
that has the data that I want and I'll
make sure that nobody else swaps that
out what but you know from the time I do
the lookup from the time I go get the
page that I want and so that means that
I could have a bunch of threads call
contending on the same latch that could
they're all accessing the same page
table so no matter how many cores I have
on my brand-new machine I'm not getting
good scalability because everything's
contended on these these critical
sections but now if I just have multiple
page tables each thread you know they
could be accessing different pages of
different page tables at the same time
and therefore they're not contending on
those latches and now I get better
scalability now still could be still
bottlenecks on the disk feed which is
always a big problem at least internally
now I'm not worried about them you know
trying to all acquire the same latch so
this is something you see mostly in the
enterprise or expensive database systems
so Oracle db2 Sybase and for max Seigle
server all support this ability to have
multiple purple's db2 you do all sorts
of crazy things you can create multiple
multiple buffer pools you can sign them
different tables you can have different
cashman policies for all for all them if
you set them to be their different page
sizes my Siegel even though it's open
source actually has this as well it's
it's not that as sophisticated you just
say how many buffer pool instances you
want and then they just do round-robin
hashing to decide what what you know if
you'll forgive and pagenty where's the
data that I'm looking for what buffer
pool has it so there's two ways to use
these things right they've to map the
thing that you're looking for to a
buffer pool that has the page that that
you want I said typically what happens
is if you have multiple buffer pools you
can't have a page in one you know in in
buffer pool one this time and then when
you fetch about the disco later on it
comes out another one it always wants to
be in the same location so you know how
you know how to find it quickly so the
first approach is that you can actually
extend the record ID to now include
additional metadata about what database
object this buffer pool is managing
so if you recall when we looked at the
record IDs of Oracle and sequel server
they had extra columns extra information
that Postgres didn't have back postcode
had the page and the slot number will
have like the the object number page
number and and a slot number so we could
use that that additional object number
they didn't have another map that says
all right for object you know XYZ you
can it's a Miss it's in this buffer pool
or that buffer pool and so now the
requests from up at level of the system
you're saying give me you know give me a
record one two three and I know how to
split that up and find out what object
it corresponds to and what buffer pool
will maintain that data for the hashing
approach again I think that's what my
secret does it's pretty simple you just
take the record ID you hash it and mod n
by the number of buffer pools you have
and that just tells you where to go get
the dinner do you want and this you do
is really quickly really fast it's not
an expensive operation actually for
either there's it's not an expensive
operation
all right the next optimization we can
do is to do prefetching so the idea here
is that again we want to minimize the
stalls and the data system due to having
to go to disk or read data so if we
start doing like a scan and our buffer
pool is emptying this query wants to
read page zero page there is not in
memory not in our buffer pool so we have
to stall that thread until we go out the
disk fetch it and then put it into our
buffer pool then once it's in our proper
pool then we hand back the pointer to
the upper-level system say the page you
wanted is now here in our in our memory
go do whatever it is that you want to do
so the way to think about this is like
it's a you can think of this arrow is
like a cursor so internally a database
system is gonna keep track of this thing
kind of cursor like as you iterate over
every single page for that your query
needs you just know where you left off
the last time so when you go back and
said give me the next page it doesn't
start at the beginning it jumps where
you were you left off so in this case
here I get paid zero I'm done right now
I start reading page one same thing I
have to stall because it's not in memory
the disk goes and gets it we've put in
our tour buffer pool and then once I
have that now I can now I can proceed
operating their own
so let's say this query here wants to
scan the entire table alright these are
for our table here here's all the pages
so at this point the data used to
probably recognize oh I know you're
gonna end up scanning the entire table
so rather than just wait with me waiting
for you to ask each page one after
another let me go ahead and jump ahead
and say oh I think you're also going to
need page two and three so let me go
prefetch that for you put into the
buffer pool so by the time you finished
processing page one and now you go ask
me for page 2 or page 3 it's already
there now you don't have a stall and
again based on how I laid out these
pages on disk and that might have been a
sequential read which is super fast so
by preventing things ahead of time I you
know I'm minimizing the amount of random
i/o that I'm doing right let's keep
going this down and and prefetch
everything's that again that minimizes
the impact of these distal x' so this
example is pretty simple right the the
operating system at you could figure
this out too now and and nmap will
actually do this for you right so an M
map you can pat the flag say I'm gonna
do a special read on these pages on disk
and it'll go ahead and prefetch a bunch
of them ahead of time and so again that
will minimize the stalls having because
because you had to read something from
disk so M map can figure this out
without even knowing anything out what
the queries trying to do and the data
system knows what the query wants to do
and can go prefetch ahead of time but
now there's to be some queries where the
operating system is not going to be able
to know what to do but we do in the
nativist system because we know what the
query wants so you so an example of this
would be like an index game so let's say
I want to do a scan on this table and I
want to get all the values I want to
find all the tuples with the value is
between 100 and 250 so now let's say
that I have an index on that value and
I've explained what an index is just
think of this as like a glossary in your
textbook it allows you to jump to a
particular page that has the data that
you want all right so right so instead
of spewing sequential scan I can just
jump through the index and find exactly
what I'm looking for so let's say that
our in our index pages right we know
ahead of time what the ranges are
so when my query starts to do that scan
I always got to read the first page for
the index because that's the route
alright so you know I have to jump to
there but now I'm gonna do a lookup and
say well I'm looking for my query was
between 100 and 250 so I know that all
the pages I need or the values I want
where it's greater than equal to a
hundred or gonna start on this side of
the tree so now I'm gonna jump down into
a page one and read that right that's
still sequential at this point so again
the operative system could Poli figure
this out but now I'm gonna branch and go
down here and I'm gonna scan across the
leaf nodes but this is index page three
index page five they're not contiguous
with each other on on disk and so the
operating system may try to end up
prefetching page two and page three but
I don't need page two that's wasted and
I need page five and it didn't prefetch
that so because we know what the queries
gonna do we can go ahead and prefetch
exactly the pages that we want and bring
them into our buffer pool because we can
we understand what the what's actually
the context what are the context of the
query and what do these pages actually
representing because the operating
system does these pages it doesn't know
what's in them but we know because we
wrote this code we know that these are
index pages and they're connect together
in some way so we know how to do this
traversal so this doesn't come for free
right there's some extra metadata we had
to keep track of in these pages to say
like here's the sibling here's my
starting point or my end point here's
his starting point so I know whether I'm
gonna scan across over here and actually
I can't know whether I need five before
I look at three so you know this I'm not
saying this is like super easy to do but
you can kind of see again how we may not
be jumping exactly through the pages
sequentially in a way that the operative
systems not be able to find again this
this is this to me this is the classic
example of what we can do in our
database system that opera sim cannot do
because it doesn't doesn't know about
what's in the data it just sees a bunch
of region writes all right the next
optimization we can do is called scan
sharing so the idea here is that we can
have queries piggyback off each other
and reuse the data that there that one
query is reading from disk and use that
for its query so this is different than
result caching result caching is say I
run exactly the same query and I compute
some answer and I cache that results of
that same query shows up again I can
just rather rerunning the query I just
give you the answer I had before this is
at a lower level at the puffle manager
in the storage layer where we're now and
just have this cursor accessing pages we
can then reuse the pages we're getting
out from one thread for another thread
so way it's gonna work is that when
allow multiple queries to attach to a
single cursor that's scanning through
our pages and putting them to the buffer
pool it's almost like a pub sub thing
where we say I want to know whether you
get a new page and then you can notify
whatever thread that may be waiting for
it even though they're not the one that
actually did the read so depending on
the implementation the queries do not
need to be exactly the same
typically in result caching they do in
our and our world here they don't have
to be just I need to know whether I'm
reading the same pages and then in some
cases to also if they're computing the
similar result we could share those
immediate results and across different
threads so most like a it's called a
materialized view we'll cover this later
in the semester but for our purposes
here with this game we're just looking
at page accesses so again the way it
works is that if a query starts a stand
and then it recognizes that there's
another query also doing the same scan
it just attaches itself to the first
guy's cursor and then as it gets pages
we get notified that that page came in
and we can we can access it as well so
the important thing to know is that we
have to keep track of where the second
query came along sort of got on the
train for the cursor so that we know if
the cursor ends for the first query
there may be other data we have to go
back and read I said we can if we want
to look at everything we start halfway
we want to know where we started so we
can come back and see the rest so as far
as I know this technique is fully
supported only in db2 and sequel server
it's super hard to get correct it seems
like kind of trivial but it can get
pretty gnarly based on what the the
queries doing Oracle supports has a
basic scare chaning they call cursor
sharing and then but it only works if
you have two exact queries running
exact same time whereas these guys can
extrapolate based on the query that you
know I need I know you're reading this
table I need to read the same thing and
jump on it this thing has to say I have
two queries I'm doing the exact same
thing so let's look an example so say we
have our first query here it's computing
the sum on a so the query the queries
cursors are going to start and it's just
gonna start scanning through the table
looking at each page all right so now
let's say at this point here it wants to
read page three we don't have any a free
frame and our buffer pool so we run our
replacement policy algorithm to decide
which of these pages we want to remove
in this case here we'll do something
simple and say well page zero was the
last page that the the page that was the
oldest since I've accessed it so let me
go ahead and replace that with page
three and then now I continue scanning
but now let's say after this happens
after we swap out page zero at page 3 a
second query shows up that also wants to
do a central scan on this table
so without scan sharing it'll just start
at the beginning like the first guy and
just skin all the way down but this is
actually the worst thing for us because
the first thing is going to read is page
zero but we just threw that out on disk
so now we can end up thrashing because
this guy can't proceed until page zeros
is in so this is gonna you know it has
to stolen to go fetch it back in but I I
just had it in memory but I got rid of
it so that's bad so with scan sharing
this guy just hops along for the ride
and read the same thing that q1 reads
and you know produces you compute
whatever enemy resulting needs for that
part of the part of the data is looking
at so now at this point q1 is done so
it's cursor goes away and then q2 starts
over at the beginning and those nodes
that I started when you were reading
page three so this is how long I need to
scan down until I get my final result
yes
this question is each query is computing
also intermediate results as as it reads
this datum so they also now need a
memory region to to put this data in
that's separate from this buffer pool
yes so we'll see this an exam on
Postgres in a second but the typically
that memory will also be backed by a
buffer pool right and because like if I
end up computing something you know say
I'm computing a join and the output of
that joint operator doesn't fit in
memory
I need B it started victim those pages
out to disk so so any ephemeral memory
like that would still be backed by a
buffer pool but whether it's in the
global buffer pool whether it's a
private one for the query it depends on
the implementation his question same it
is I don't need I don't need to bring
pages from disk in for that query in
Amira's all buffer pool yeah yeah so as
I'm writing data like so this guy and
this is trivial table because the
average is it's a scaler right let's say
this is you know some really complex
computation as I'm generating as I'm
scanning this data I'm updating my enemy
result I may overflow memory and those
gets swapped out the disk so I'm writing
to memory and then they would just get
to get written out the disk as needed
but it's not like I would read for my
query yeah it doesn't make sense because
anything you need free from like the
low-level data is pages you're gonna put
in the buffer pool that everyone can see
all right so again this is another good
point this is a shared data structure
right so it did like q1 is was reading
pages and putting to the buffer pool any
other thread that need these pages is
allowed to go go ahead and read it
alright the pin latch the pin that just
tells you that hey don't swap this out
the disk the doesn't doesn't prevent
anybody else aren't reading at the same
time you are there's higher level things
like the locks that keep track of what
pages you're allowed to read and write
from or what would you know with
database objects this is the painted
spacing says hey I'm operating on this
don't swap it out so that didn't your
question
okay so there's another good example
what's awesome about the relational
model because the relational model is
unordered meaning like it doesn't like I
can actually have Q to start anywhere
for some queries and the answer I'm
gonna produce may be different from
based on when I execute it but it still
considered correct so if I changed this
query to put compute the average and I
limit it to a hundred meaning I only
want me to be the average of 100 tuples
it doesn't specify that I can only I
have to look at the first one hundred
tuples so I could start here at page
three with my with my scan sharing on
this cursor and see the first hundred
tuples in these first three pages and
then that's that's enough for me to
compute the result if I started now at
the beginning I may actually get a
different result but according to the
relational model that's still fine cuz
the database is unordered yes yes so he
perfect so he says would it also still
be valid if we rather than having the
cursor say all right well let's go look
my dispatch is start fetching them what
do I go check out the buffer pool and
figure out what's actually a memory and
compute the aggregation or this
particular query which with what's a
memory absolutely yes and the smartest
systems can do that okay it doesn't
matter
writes in memory as long as I see a
hundred tuples then that this query is
still correct now this is I don't know
like you wouldn't want to write this but
it's yeah it's still valid all right the
last optimization we'll talk about is
the buffer pool bypass so this sort of
related his question before about like
the intermediate result memory but let's
say that I have some queries where we're
doing structural scans and the I don't
want to pay the penalty of having to go
look up in the page table and look at my
buffer pool to go figure out whether the
page I'm looking for is in memory
furthermore I also don't want to pollute
the cache and it may be reading some
data that I'm not going to need in the
near future so the the buffer pool
bypass
cash bypass depending what system it is
the idea is that you allocate a small
amount of memory to the to your your
query a thread running it and then as it
reads pages from disk right if it's not
in the buffer pool it has to go to DISA
to get it rather than putting it in the
buffer pool it just puts it in its local
memory and then when the queries done
all that just gets dropped and thrown
away all right and you do this again
because you want to avoid the overhead
of going to the patient we'll just yeah
it's a hash table it has latches it's
not it's not it's not super expensive
but it's not free it's not cheap so in
for max these are called light scans but
pretty much every single again major
database system supports something like
this I don't know I don't know whether
my sequel eight does I don't think five
point seven does and then again if you
recognize that you know that you only
really want to do this if you know the
intimate result or their thing you're
scanning is not not huge if you're doing
a sort that's gonna be you know
terabytes of memory then you want to be
back by the buffer pool because that
thing can get paid up to disk as needed
all right the last thing to sort of
understand also too is what's actually
going on below the database system
what's happening as we read pages from
the obvious and what is the operation
actually doing so again all our disk
operations are gonna be going through
the OS API at the lowest level the F of
them every to fright you know we're not
going to access the roll all discs
themselves so because we're now going
through the operating system by default
the operating system is gonna maintain
its own separate cache for the file
system all right this is called the OS
page cache so that means again as I read
a page from from disk the OS is gonna
keep a cap copy of it in his file system
cache or OS page cache and then I'll
have another copy of it in my buffer
pool so most database systems do not
want to do want you to do this no no the
operating system to do this so when you
open a file you pass in the POSIX flag
Oh direct or direct IO where you have
the OS not do any of that caching itself
and you manage what's in memory on your
own so pretty much every single day
tourism when you go to read the manual
they would tell you that make sure you
can actually turn this on the only
database system that does
is its Postgres as far as you know the
only major data send that relies on the
others page cache is Postgres and so the
reason they said they do this because
they claim that from engineering
standpoint it's one less additional
catchment thing they have to manage they
still has their own buffer pool but it's
not gonna be as big it's not gonna use
all the memory on the system like my
sequel or Oracle would use but let the
OSD with some additional management
themselves so from an engineering
perspective it's less overhead on their
part from actually maintaining that that
piece of the system and it's a minor
performance penalty to rely on this
which we'll see in a second okay so I
like using Postgres for demos because
it's almost like a textbook imitation of
a database system and you actually
exposes a lot of the important concepts
that we're talking about pretty pretty
easily okay all right so this is running
again a machine back in the lab let me
turn on the lights and I type in those
laptop cuz it's a pain to type on the on
the surface I hate the keyboard alright
so this is running this is just running
H top it's a better version of top and
the thing I want to I want to focus on
is is the memory you should stuff up
here so the green bars are telling you
what's the resident set size of the
processes running on this machine right
it's the memory they've now looked the
the orange bar here
that's the filesystem page cache that's
the operative systems page cache so
again as whatever processes are running
on this machine as they go read if
they're not using direct i/o if they go
read a page from a file the OS is also
going to cache it as well so we can blow
this all away so this is running on
Linux so in Linux we can do a
[Music]
that's not Oh for sorry so we can run
this command that we basically passive
we we stink the OS the FASTA some cache
and we passed this flag three into the
proc file system to allow us to force
the opposite to flush our page cache so
now if we go back and look at H top now
we see that the total amount of memory
beat buying used but the machine went
down to three gigs right so had 32 gigs
before but now it's down to three gigs
so we blew away the file system cache
entirely ok so now let's go let's go
bring up Postgres the first thing i want
to do though is restart it and so by
restarting it we're going to blow away
it's it's its buffer pool all right so
now bring this up and then reconnect
we're ternal and timing and then we'll
turn off the parallel threads so we're
going to use that same table I showed
them last class ten million entries of a
bunch of decimals so we can run this
query and now what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna use explain again but I'm gonna
pass and analyze two flags analyze and
buffers so analyze again is gonna
actually run the query and also show you
the query plan what happened this
buffers flag is going to tell you how
much data it read from disk what
percentage of the pages it was reading
rating the buffer pool verses on on disk
and so because we blew away the file
system cache we blew away the buffer
pool because we restarted the database
system it should the hit should be zero
right and you see that it said that for
the buffer pool it had to read four
hundred four four four four to forty
eight pages it had to read the table
from disk and it took thirteen hundred
milliseconds one point three seconds so
if I run the same query again
now you see it says that the hit was 32
so it was able to read 32 pages that
were already in the puffer pool and then
the rest it had been reaping disk
alright the reason why I wasn't all the
pages is because Postgres maintains a
buffer pool sort of a small buffer pool
ring per query that's 32 pages so for
this one it was allowed to read 30 pages
from the last time it ran I run this
again it should go to thank the 64 yes
so it keeps growing in size as I'm
executing queries over never again
because it recognizes that oh the data
that I need is is it's not my buffer
pool let me increase the size of its
cache alright so now what we can do is
we can force the database system to put
everything in into into memory so they
have this extension of Postgres comes by
default when you when you install it
called PG warm and all this does is that
it's a function that we invoke on the
data system to say hey go take all the
pages for this this table and bring it
to a buffer pool right and tells you
that I ran I did that and I read four
hundred forty four thousand two forty
eight pages
remember when I ran the query the first
time the it said had to read four
thousand four hundred twenty eight pages
from disk because it's getting exactly
you know that's the the number pages of
this table
he says there's six more pages already
there right so this is like forcing just
read everything and I think those 64
pages might have been yeah I think it
doesn't look to see what's in memory it
just says I'm gonna get everything cuz i
if I do it again it should give me the
same number yeah just reads everything
alright so now if I go and run that
query again I'm doing a little bit
better by hit a sixteen sixteen thousand
sixteen thousand pages I needed were in
memory so I hit hit had it hit in the
buffer pool but I started read a bunch
some disk and we take a guess why
yes he's wide still loading everything
into the buffer pool depends on the size
of the buffer pool right so we can do
this in Postgres so Postgres has a flag
called shared buffers and it tells me
that it's currently set to 128 megabytes
right but the size was about 4 for 4 to
8 so select you can use gimme you i'll
updated you can use them as a calculator
so for 4 to 8 times 8 divided by 1024
about giving megabytes so the size of my
table I'm reading is 345 megabytes so
again the shared buffer is 128 but my
size my table is 345 so I can go to the
post rest configuration in theory for
this is post Chris 11 and then go find
that particular parameter and lo behold
it's 128 megabytes so let me set it to
let's be generous let's say 360
megabytes right so now we will restart
Postgres we will blow a our file system
cache from the operating system because
again as we read that page in actually
we go back to H stop it got I mean it's
hard to see we've got a little bit
bigger hmm like if you see there's one
bar there because that's that that's
that's our table we were reading in so
let me go blow away the file system
cache and now go back to post grass I
need to reconnect turn on timing set
that to this to turn up parallel threads
check to see that shared buffers is now
oh I'm an idiot right sorry
server 10 Klein 11 too many co-stars
installation sorry so go back here is
this put about the 1:28 I said about 360
now we start Postgres go back here
reconnect 360 okay good
turn on timing turn on parallel threads
pre-warm we got it four four two eight
four two four eight pages and now I've
run that query again and now my head is
four four to forty so I gave it a system
the right amount of memory I prefetch
and everything and now everything is
hitting the buffer pool I had I didn't
that such a disk at all for this
particular query I do every lookup every
page and I need to access I'm going
looking in that but in that page table
and finding the pate the page reference
in a frame but everything is in memory
here so how can we prove that the that
the database system Postgres is using
relying on the file system cache so
let's turn off just explain everything
here and let's see how long it actually
takes right it's actually so the first
time was twelve fifty and they got a
little faster then it's 7:33 alright so
it takes me roughly seven hundred
milliseconds so what we can do is go
restart Postgres
[Music]
and then that blows away the buffer pool
and now if I come back and reconnect the
Postgres which I think I need to yep so
now I'm now I'm reconnected I slept a
good turn on timing
turn off parallel threads I run that
same query before when everything was
out on disk I think it took one point
three seconds so this one and then with
everything's in the buffer pool it took
seven hundred milliseconds so this one
should be roughly little bits where
timing was all sorry well that ruined
the demo so go back I go back this
restart this go back to this reconnect
timing is on yeah that's one yeah I got
it
parallel threads are off again so I'm
gonna run this query I blew I restarted
the database system that blows with the
buffer pool but the operating system
still has its file system cache so now
that I run this query we're gonna have a
bunch of buffer pool misses because
nothing is in memory but it's still not
going to take the full time right took
800 milliseconds instead instead of 1.3
seconds because the data that it needed
was in the file system cache if I run
this again I should get now 700
milliseconds no
there goes let's go figure what happened
still reading date from disk why is that
well it's still running fast even though
that time I think it's because that time
slower because I think it's running
explain analyze it'll slowly get faster
as it creases the cache size for that
for that query I think I think it's a
query cache thing rather than the global
thing but again the main takeaway we
showed is that we had to give it a
decent enough memory and put everything
into our buffer pool and then we were
able to get the full speed performance
are starting questions yes pre run twice
what I mean oh that's the file system
cache that's about the US cash question
yes yes yes so the very first time I did
this the the buffer pool size was 120
megabytes the table size is 345
megabytes it didn't that's why I had I
had to add lookups in read from disk in
the very beginning huh there's not we
spending all our time boy this is this
is walkthrough right so let's do this go
back we're going to blow away the file
system cache restart Postgres you know
now we go look and and in our I mean
that that bar is not a trivial
potentially for propose grass like
there's other things running on the
system
but I blew away the false ISM cash I've
restarted Postgres now there's nothing
in memory so I go back to the Postgres
you need to reconnect turn off pale
threads and so if I run the query now
the first time great
nothing's in memory I had to read 44,000
pages
okay so that's expected pre-warm tells
the database system to go read
everything that's on disk for that table
brain to my buffer pool all 44 thousand
pages yes I can do this again right it
read 44,000 pages now I run the same
query and now my hit is exactly 44,000
hit means like it was hit I the thing I
was looking for was found in the buffer
pool so I forced the day's doesn't bring
everything back in the memory and the
first example I only had a hundred
twenty megabytes so I couldn't put
everything on yes yes great so our
question is so I said in the beginning
that the Postgres is the only system
that that does you the only major system
that relies on the OS page cache why
doesn't everybody else do this well
because now I'm gonna have two copies or
every single page potentially so I could
have a page in the OS page cache then
I'm gonna have a copy of that page in my
my buffer pool because now if I modify
that page now it's not exact copy
anymore so the OS has the old one and I
have the new one so it's it's redundant
data so you're more efficient in terms
of memory usage if you manage everything
yourself furthermore to you know think
of like in a different database system I
mean most it isn't support Linux now
right
but like the major ones they got to
support Windows BSD all these different
operating systems where the OS page
cache may have different performance
implications or different policies and
so to guarantee consistent performance
or consistent behavior across different
os's you just manage everything yourself
it's a good question yes there's number
pages but again so like I post as 8
kilobyte pages I take this number
multiply 8 divided by 1024 that tells me
them are megabytes of mic my thing I set
my buffer pool size to that size and
that can guarantee everything fits yes
of course question is how does buffer
pool interact with the OS page cache
again be it's like these question is
like are there different options how to
use it
no like so it's transparent to the
program like I call read every go read a
page from from the from disk if the OS
has a page cache that serves me that
page otherwise it goes out and disco
gets it that's all transparent to me if
I pass that flag direct i/o that tells
the option system do not catch anything
and it's always gonna go to disk and get
it it's quite yes save it as the OS page
cache is in between the sort of the disk
and the data in the database
absolutely yes it's gonna matter also to
a lot when we start doing writes if you
call like you write a C program you call
F write does is the operations I'm
actually gonna write that right away
no puts it in the page cache and at some
later point the disk schedule says all
right I'm gonna go write this out it's
only mine I call s Inc when is when
actually it's written but if I want a
complete control of how I'm ready
everything out the disk I want to use
direct i/o and most database systems do
that yes
yes all the t-80
and v60 and be into the book what would
happen the first 1:28 and we would have
been overwritten how many you did sir
clearly you got hit but many times the
query you have started from the starting
so you should have got it because the
memory presence was the later 128m let's
I'm gonna get through the thing for the
project but let's let me talk about it
wherefore it's okay alright so the thing
when to talk about now quickly is the
buffer placement policy so again we
talked about how right we how to find a
page we want based on the page ID and
the page table but now you know am all
my examples we had enough memory mostly
and so now we want to talk about what
happens if I need to bring a page in and
I don't have space for it what do I do
so the things were to care about and a
replacement policy are obviously
correctness right we don't want to write
out data or a big data that that someone
pinned before they're actually done with
it we're gonna care about accuracy
because we're gonna make sure that we we
Vic pages that are very unlikely be used
in the future so we minimize the number
of disk seeks we have we want overplay
some policy to be fast because we don't
you know the as we're doing a lookup in
the page table or holding latches and we
don't want have to run some MD complete
algorithm to figure out what page to
evict right because that may take longer
than actually reading the page anyway
and of course obviously we don't want to
have a lot of metadata overhead of
keeping track and all this additional
data we don't want to have the metadata
for a page keep track of how likely it's
going to be used to be larger than the
page itself so these replacement
policies again as another good example
what distinguishes between the high end
very expensive enterprise databases and
the open-source guys because the high
end ones have very sophisticated
replacement policies they track
statistics of how pages were being used
they try to extrapolate from what the
queries are actually doing and to try to
make the best decision whereas in the
the open source guys and the newer
systems not saying they're bad but they
don't have you know millions of dollars
in decades spent trying to make this
thing run fast as possible and so the
you know they'll do something more
simple which is what we're gonna talk
about here this is like one of the
oldest problems in CS like everyone
their uncle has a paper in the over the
years on how to do caching and things
like that I have one right like this is
this is like one of the oldest problems
in computer science there's a ton a long
history of this all right so the easiest
technique the use and pretty much
everyone does the first time is LRU or
at least recently used so all we do here
just keep track of a timestamp of when a
the last time a page was accessed and
then we have to go figure out what page
you will go evict we just look to see
which page has that old it's timestamp
and that's the one we go ahead and
remove so way to speed this up instead
just keeping a track of a you know a
timestamp her page because then we have
to do a special scan across all our
pages in the buffer pool to figure out
which one has the lowest timestamp we
can just maintain a separate data
structure like a queue that there's
that's sorted by the their timestamps so
anytime somebody reads and writes a page
we just pull it out of the queue and put
it back to the end because it's a
first-in first-out what you guys will
have to implement in the project is an
approximation of LRU called clock
actually quick show of hands who who
here has heard a clock before nobody
awesome okay cool here so I mean LRU
Emily should know right
okay good so clock so LRU is an exact
least recently used clock is an
approximation of this where you don't
have to track the timestamp exactly
every for every single page so instead
we're all the only information we need
to keep track of is a single reference
bit per page that tells you whether that
page was access since the last time you
checked it so you're gonna organize your
pages in a circular buffer like a clock
and then you have a clock hand that goes
around and does sweeps and check to see
whether that reference bit is set to 1
or 0 and if it's set to 0 that you know
has been access since the last time you
checked it and therefore it can be
evicted all right so say I page pages 1
2 3 4 again each one has their own
reference bit in the very beginning the
reference bit is set to 0 so let's say
that some some query accesses page 1 so
I'm gonna go ahead and flip its
reference bit to 1 and no matter how
many times somebody accesses this this
page it's always set to 1 it's not a
counter so now now I need Invicta page
because I don't have any more space so
my clock hands gonna start this first
one I see that it's reference
set the one and therefore it's been
accessed and therefore I should not have
victim but now I reset its reference bit
to zero and then go on to the to the
next one and I'm gonna sweep around if I
come back around and set the zero then I
know I can evict it so this guy here his
bit is set to zero so we can go ahead
and vicked it remove it and replace it
with a new page and then we don't set
its reference to one we just set it zero
and then move on to the next one so
let's say now page three and four have
been access so we check that reset it to
zero check that reset to zero now we've
come back to the page one was the first
one we checked its reference it was zero
since the last time we checked so
therefore it can be evicted
so again reason why this is an
approximation is because azzaman victim
pages I'm not a victim exactly the one
that's the most least least recently
used it's sort of you know it's the same
within some time window these pages have
not been used and therefore it's if
there's I go ahead and victim and the
intuition here is that if the page
hasn't been used in a while then it's
probably not gonna be used again in the
near future so therefore it's something
I can go ahead in a bit right right so
that assumption works a lot works well
for simple things like doing point
queries to go access single things but
clock and LRU are susceptible to what is
called sequential flooding and what this
means is that when we have a special
scan that's gonna read every single page
that's gonna pollute our page cache and
that's gonna end up having we can end up
evicting pages that maybe we do really
want that argument use very right and in
the near future but because that scan
read a bunch of pages all those pages
are gonna have newer timestamps and then
the page I actually do want right in
this case here the most recently page
use page is actually the one I want to
evict not the least recently used so
there's another good example where you
if you could have different buffer pool
different buffer pools or different
tables based on how queries are going to
access them maybe one I want to use most
recently used in another one I want to
use least recently used so let's look at
example let's say I have one query
that's doing a point lookup where where
a equals
we're ID equals one and it reads page
zero so go ahead and fetch that into my
buffer pool and I'm fine so then now
have another query that's gonna do a
central scan so it's gonna rip through
all my all my pages and they want to
once and make space for page three if
again we're using least recently used
then it would figure out that Oh page
zero is the least recently used let me
go ahead and evict that and put in page
three but in my work load I'm executing
queries that look like the first one
over and over again so now if I execute
this query all over again
now I repaid zero I just evicted it and
now I'm screwed because now I got to go
out and disk and get it okay so what I
really wanna should have done is is
evicted one or two because this scans
gonna go through go through a read more
data and it's unlikely anybody else is
going to come and read this thing here
so the way there's three ways to get
around this let me sort of cover some of
these so far so the first is to do
it's called LRU K where K is just you
keep track of a number the the time the
number of times a multiple timestamps
every single time this the page is
accessed so now when you want to say
which which one should I remove you
don't look to see which one has the
lowest time Stan you go look at the
intervals between those timestamps and
you say which one has the Long's amount
of time between one access to the next
access and then can use that to figure
out which one's the least likely to be
used so this because we're using the
history to estimate when it's can be
accessed again to make help us make a
better decision about what pages should
be evicted
so LRU K is what's used in the if the
more sophisticated ad says we'll do
something like this I don't know I think
my sequel might use this I don't I don't
remember all right the next optimization
we can do which we sort of already
talked about with having multiple buffer
pools is to have localization and per
query so rather than have that you know
as I'm skating the table and putting it
into the global buffer pool if I have a
small little set aside some pages in the
buffer pool that are
susceptance till read them but it's it's
I'm keeping track of how I'm using pages
so then then when I want to make a
decision what to evict from my query I
evict the ones that are least recently
used for me not the global view so we
saw this in Postgres Perez had that hit
memory show the hit was like 32 then
with the 64 right that's this little
ring buffer that they're keeping track
of what pages that that queries
accessing they make decisions what what
to evict all right the last one is view
priority hints again this is where we
talked about before when we have we have
indexes we know how they're scanning
data know what pages different access so
we can use that information to make
decisions about what - a bit so let's
say we have our B plus tree or whatever
tree data structure we want and they
have a bunch of queries they're gonna
insert data where there's a global
counter for this table or just
incrementing it by one and inserting
over and over again like a serial key or
auto increment key so if we're now
sorted on this index is sorted on ID
from min to max we know that every
single time we do an insert the ID value
is always going to be one more than the
last one we just inserted so that means
we're always gonna be going down the
right side of the tree and touching
these pages so therefore we should have
hints up into the buffer we'll manage
and say these pages should try to stay
in memory I don't care about these so
much about these other ones here or
likewise if I have a query that does
lookups on on different IDs or actually
any query that does a lookup on this
index I know I'm always gonna be going
through the blue page because that's how
I enter this index I have to go through
that so therefore I want to make sure
that's always pinned in memory that
always stays there right because
otherwise if I if I get by get to the
bottom and I need space and I Vic this
thing it's a bad idea because I look and
that's the least recently used but I
know that the next queries gonna come
through it and go to exactly for that
page so again this is what the
commercial systems can do provide you
some extra information up above alright
the last thing to talk about is how do
we actually handle dirty pages so member
that there's a dirty bit and the page
that says whether a query has modified
the contents of that page since the last
time it it's in since since it was
brought into the buffer pool so when we
announced
what paid to evict to bring a new page
in the fastest thing we could do is just
find a page that was that's not marked
dirty and immediately just drop it and
you know use its frame for a new buffer
pool the slower thing we have to do is
if a page is dirty we have to write it
back out the disk safely before we can
reuse that space for it for our new page
so now there's this trade-off we have to
make and our replacement policy decide
well there's a bunch of pages that are
all that are all clean and I could drop
them super easily but they actually may
be needed in the near future so I don't
want to actually drop them instead I
want to pay the penalty to write out a
dirty page flush it remove it from my
bumper pool and reuse its space so how
you actually balance them is is super
hard right because again I in this case
here to do a disk read if I had to write
out a dirty page it's to disk i/os one
IO to write out the dirty page then
remove it from the buffer pool and then
another IO to read a page that I want in
this case here it's one IO to just just
go read the page that I want cuz I can
drop the the page that's already in the
buffer pool so how you actually figure
that out again it's super hard and this
is what the commercial systems my
opinion do better than the open-source
ones so way to get around this to avoid
that the problem of having to write a
page out as soon as I need it for free
space in my buffer pool I can do
background writing so periodically that
data systems gonna have a thread they're
gonna look through my buffer pool figure
out what pages are marked dirty and just
write them out to disk so that way I can
flip them to be marked it's clean and
now when I do from my replacement policy
just slide what page to remove I have a
bunch of clean pages I can I can drop
right away so you gotta be careful when
you do this because you don't want to
write out dirty pages before the law of
records that correspond to their to
modifying them to make them dirty you
know make sure they're the law were
custom written out to disk first before
you write out the dirty pages we'll have
a whole lecture on why that's the case
later on in the semester but just know
there's like it's not just like I can
blindly write any page I want I have to
do some Etra step protection to make
sure I'm writing things in the right
order this is something that n mapkit
cannot do all right so I'm gonna skip
this for the other memory post just
we've already sort of covered this
it's more than just the pages from
tables or indexes there's when we run
queries we also needed to generate some
some information all right
so the again the the whole point of this
lecture was to talk about how we can
manage memory better than the OS because
we know what kurz are doing we know
what's in the pages we know how things
are being accessed and we can make
better decisions and essentially we're
gonna use information on what in the
query to you know for all these
different things that we talked about
and a bunch of optimization we can apply
to help us make this work better all
right so any questions about buffer pool
all right here's what you really care
about project one right so the for the
first project you're me building your
own buffer pool manager and replacement
policy so this will all be done in our
new database system called bust hub
which is it's an open source system it's
disk based again it's you will see this
will be stub files in the code that you
would download from github then a
clearly show here's the function need to
write and here's here's how to actually
you know implement that what we're
asking you to do so the project is the
write up is available online
the great scope isn't been set up yet
we'll do that later today but if you can
finish this project in a single day come
talk to me because we wouldn't want to
do other things
so we are gonna already provide you to
dis manager and already the page layouts
so you don't worry about that you just
will give you a page blocka blocka pages
and it's up for you to decide how to
store them in memory and then and and
invoke the disk manager to write them
out as needed so for the first one we
have a separate class called clock
replacer and you'll be implementing the
clock policy that I talked about here
today again it's an approximation of of
LRU we just sweep the hand and flip
these reference reference bits so that
means you need keep track of as pages
are being accessed because you'll see
this in the buffer point API you have to
know that when I say read a page or
write a page that you go update the
reference bit inside of your LRU replace
or sorry your clock or placer so the one
thing to be important to know is that if
you do a sweep and all the pages have
been modified then you just pick
whatever one has the lowest frame ID or
of all the pages are pin and you can't
free one then you pick them on the
lowest page ID right cuz otherwise you
just spin forever and this will be in
the write-up the major effort will be on
the on the buffle manager so your
element the clock replace your algorithm
first and then you hook that into your
buffer pool manager and for this one
it's again it's up for you to decide how
you actually want to maintain your
memory how you decide what internal data
structures you want to keep track of
what pages that are available what pages
are are dirty what pages are being
pinned right you can do whatever you
want
it's just you have to implement the API
that we expose to you so it's means
super the thing that always tricks up
students every year is to make sure you
get the ordering of the operations of
how to pin pages correct right so we'll
do multi-threading graded test will try
to read a page and pin at the same time
and you'll make sure that everything
turns out in the right order and this
would be more clear when you look at the
write up and see what we're asking you
to do so how do you get started so again
everything is available on github you
want to go to your if you don't forgive
it a github account sign up one it's
free there's also I think an educational
one that you get extra stuff but
basically you'll go to the github page
for the for the the database system and
could be a little fork button and you
fork it into your private repo a fokin
is your own
market is private so nothing's public
and then just do all your changes in
there if you sign up for the github
account you can get free private forked
repos right because if you put
everything public than other students
can see what you're doing and then
potentially copy from you the very first
thing you should try to do today or
tomorrow as soon as possible be super
helpful try to get the software to build
on your whatever machine you're gonna do
your development on so it works on
Ubuntu it works on OSX it works on
Windows with the Windows server or
server like Linux whatever this package
you can download install the thing
though for OSX is not gonna support the
clang formatting stuff that we'll talk
about in a second so great skip we'll
run this for you you can run it in
docker if you this is a problem we can
also give you a VM image but you'll have
to you don't have to figure this out on
your own we'll have instruction to try
to help us out
it does not compile an Android machine
we tried it it doesn't work the software
they have on there is too slow if this
is a problem you don't have your laptop
please email me and we'll figure
something out ok so things to note
should not change any file that other
than what you must hand in because we're
basically to blow everything away
there's four files you have to turn in
we blow everything else away and plop
your code on top of the latest version
of the the system and run all your tests
the projects are cumulative meaning if
you bomb this one you're gonna have
problems later on because you know the
next project is actually we use the
buffer pool manager that you built today
I build now we're also not gonna be
providing solutions at the beginning and
then we're not gonna happy debug and
your code on Piazza another thing we're
doing new this year is that we're
requiring you to write good-looking code
normally people like fit code and so now
we all want to check to make sure it
actually conforms to a good style guide
so we followed the google sleeveless
style guide and we also followed the
docs in Java doc style guide so we have
checks already in place that will check
all these things for you like if you
call make format it'll make sure your
code looks pretty in the simplest aisle
guide but there's a bunch of other
things like how you allocate memory how
you set up your for loops and so forth
that we use clang tidy and clang format
to to enforce more more detail so you'll
run these commands like
clang tidy collect check censored check
lint it will throw errors they won't
correct it for you or throw errors and
say your code looks crappy here's how to
fix it ok and we're gonna run though
some grade scope so when you turn it in
if you write crappy code you'll get
you'll get a zero score because you'll
fail these tests so this what I'm saying
so Linux and Windows I think this works
for OSX I don't think this works but we
can we can provide you a PM you can do
all your development in there ok last
thing don't plagiarize we will run your
code through moss there's some some
people in China that take the code and
I've already implemented some stuff
there's is all crap we've run it doesn't
work
don't make your stuff again don't put
your stuff on the public repo because if
I run your stuff and someone copies from
you because your account was public
rerun the moss and you both come up as
being duplicates of each other I don't
know who stole from who all right so you
broke they're gonna fail ok so don't put
any of your code public you can do this
thing then this semester because I know
you want to go in the job market me like
oh here's what I did in this class truth
be told no one's actually gonna care
because everyone's implementing the same
thing it's not like an independent study
where you you make some breaks it could
break through so employers they don't
care that much that you have your
project online but if you want to do it
and the semester if we're fine with that
ok any questions next for hash table hit
it home in schools with Michelle in case
any same on Linda mix of broken bottles
and crushed up kids let
he's misty nights in my system cracking
up on blessed let's go get the next one
then get over the net will be son
ricochet jelly hit the deli for a boat
one naturally bless ya what rap is like
a laser beam the pawns in the bush say
not even like a chain wrap the bottle of
us a nice go don't feel like drinking
head boney to you drunk you can't try
cross he's alive and if the sake don't
know you can't a bang