[Music]
[Applause]
so today we're gonna get we're
continuing our discussion on now
actually how to start executing queries
so this is what I showed a few few
lectures ago just the overview of what a
hypothetical database system will look
like a high-performance modern database
system and so we've covered you know
some of the parts down here and the
networking layer and now we're at this
point here and we're going up in this
direction we're start you know talk
about execution
Cori execution today next week we talked
about compilation then we'll come back
and do more query execution and then
after midterm or after the spring break
will then talk about code optimization
query planning okay so the idea what we
talked about today is and going forward
for the semester is how to do a build an
efficient query execution engine and
we're differ this between some of the
techniques we talked about in a
discounted system because if we're
entirely in memory then we don't have to
worry about the main bottleneck that the
disk oriented system had to worry about
right in a disk learning system the goal
was always to produce disk i/o because
that was always the most expensive thing
and so now if we don't have stalls
because we're going to fetch disk to run
our queries now we have on to other
things we got to worry about and those
that there's the the the bottlenecks
we'll discuss throughout the semester
and then the techniques I'll be
describing will show you how to actually
overcome them or mitigate their effects
on on the performance of the system and
so the we obviously still need disk for
logging so that doesn't go away but it's
really like when I actually do a query I
can assume that I'm gonna read a tuple
or read a column we need a block of data
and that's in memory alright so at the
way it essentially think about what
we're talking about here is it's gonna
be there's not any one technique we're
gonna do that's gonna be there's make
everything go better it's going to be
sort of an orchestration or coordination
across multiple optimizations
and the by combining them together then
we'll get the efficient execution
performance that we need so the spoiler
would be just as a heads up compilation
parallelization and vectorization those
are going to be the big three but
there's a penalty about other things we
could talk about as we go along
so what are our optimization goals in
our system so the disk goes away what do
we actually want to care about now to
get a query actuation performance to be
to be good so the the first one is
obvious right we are going to be we want
to just reduce what we do when we
execute queries and we can do this I
predict count that the davison prosecute
in order to to process the query so we
want to execute fewer instructions to do
the same amount of work and that's you
know then we'll get better performance
that way right so the compiler will help
us a little bit like we can pass in Oh
to typically don't ship database systems
with oh three compiled binaries because
that it it's not that none that it's
experimental it just there might be some
anomalies that you may not be prepared
for or can consider Oh two is typically
people ship software with so the
compiler doesn't help a little bit but
what we're gonna end up wanting to do is
specialize our database system for the
cific queries that we're executing again
that'll be query compilation on Monday
next week but we'll see a flavor of what
it looks like today the next one is to
reduce the cycles we have to incur when
we execute these instructions so we've
already done this we've already reduced
our instruction count and so for the
remaining instructions we do have to
execute we want to reduce the number of
cycles it takes to process them then I
know how we actually want to do that yes
she said parallelization not quite
that's the same thing as well that's
vectorization that's paralyzation but
mmm
cindy will give us this it won't
necessarily give us this Yassir branch
misprediction is one but also cat
reducing them our cache misses right we
if we have an instruction that needs to
touch a piece of data and that piece of
data is not in our CPU caches it has to
stall and in spend more cycles to go up
to DRAM to bring it into our CPU caches
so we want to maximize the locality of
the data as we're processing to them as
well as being intelligent about how we
do our how we have branches in the four
loops as you process tuples to reduce
the amount of misprediction and then the
last one is sort of what you guys you
two said here the parallel is 8 and the
rector ization this is just gonna allow
us to now use the additional cores that
we're getting on our own our CPUs to to
process queries in parallel right and
we'll talk about those different schemes
look like today like Moore's law is
essentially ending a Intel really can't
crank up the clock speed anymore thing
there are alternative materials we could
use to build our processors laughing
that don't have that melting point but
we're that's way way in the future
so what Intel and ambi are giving us
it's just Boris
we wanna execute our query is on on as
many scores as possible and that's
really tricky because now when you
potentially coordinator cross done so
paper I have you guys read um with a bit
more I'm gonna say analytical then what
we'll talk about today but it was what I
reason why I picked it is because at
least it's an eruption portion of the
FIR
they went through a lot of the
techniques that we'll talk about today
and just showing you that there's a
bunch of difference you could do to you
know how to design the system to execute
queries that was still an OLAP and
that'll primarily be what we'll focus on
for today's lecture but again they
talked about this difference between
should I do an in X probe which is
random i/o or
special scan and there's no one answer
to say when you want to use one versus
the other the main thing that I want to
get you to get out of it was that
typically in a Discordian system it was
always the it would always make this
decision about whether dude Enix can
respond to scan based on the selectivity
of the predicate if I haven't index and
I have a predicate that could be used on
the index
how many tuples do I think I'm gonna get
back from the index in an in-memory
world we actually do care about what the
performance of the harbor is gonna look
like like what the CPU will actually do
when they we execute our database system
as well as what other queries are
running at the same time and this one
bit tricky because this one needs to be
you know now we need have the optimizer
be aware of what else is running at the
same time and then you make decisions
based on that
so do you only see this applying this
technique in the high-end commercial
database systems
like I don't Postgres doesn't look to
see what other queries are running at
the same time because it's hard to do
this right because it's like here's my
query I run through the optimizer I'm
gonna pick what could be running the
same by the time my query comes out of
the optimizer and starts running those
other queries might be wrong so my
decisions might be incorrect so this one
is hard to do this one you can you can
compute in the beginning although it can
vary if you're running on Amazon because
and you know the even though you get the
same instance type the performance can
change by I think about up to like 20%
because again somebody else might be
running on the same box as you all right
so the type of optimizations we're gonna
apply that they talked about in that
paper as well as some additional ones
we'll talk about today are just how
we're gonna actually go process the
query how we're gonna move data from one
operator to the next or where they're
gonna put you a push or a pull scan
sharing is a technique where you allow
to two or more queries that are running
the same accessing the same data to
piggyback off the iterators and instead
of having each of them read the same day
at the same time you combine it together
materialized views is a way to
pre-compute some portion of a query
ahead of time and can maintain it as the
table gets updated so you can use that
for query execution so for these two
we're not gonna talk about much this
semester I'll try to talk a little bit
later on but it's these other ones here
that we'll spend most of our time
because as I said these three here are
when you get the biggest bang for the
buck
most workloads obviously in some cases
materialized using screen sharing could
be very beneficial if you have queries
that have a high opportunities to take
advantage of these things but typically
these things are general-purpose enough
what we want to do again query
compilation is it's Co specialization
vectorization what he talked about using
Cynthia instructions parallel algorithms
Lucia she mentioned is running the
operator in parallel and then we'll
finish up the animist er talking about
how to embed or how people use yes or
user-defined functions in queries and
there's big opportunities actually
basically merge these into the query
plan itself instead of treating as the
UDF as a black box and you get way
better performance as well so we'll cut
that that'll be at the end of semester
again these are the big 31 that we want
to discuss alright so today's agenda
that we're going to first talk about
what sir modern CPUs look like in the
context of database systems that what
aspects of databases what about a
diffuse do we need to care about when we
build our database system then we'll
talk about different processing models
to how to move data between between
operators and then we'll finish up
talking about different parallel
execution models the idea here is
basically how we're gonna architect the
system to support pale execution of
multiple operators at the same time all
right all right so the over 15 years old
and 2005 proposing a improved version of
Monet TV which is one of the original
open-source academic columnstore systems
are in memory Thomas or systems it was
an improved version of Monet DB where
they showed how existing database system
implementations were insufficient or not
targeting what modern superscalar CPUs
look like and that if you redesign the
architecture of the database system you
can get much better performance if you
write it in such a way that is is ideal
or amenable to how the CPU actually
processes instructions so the way to
think about this is most times when
people tell database systems and
certainly you know that's coming now but
this is very common in this paper they
look like my sequel and post
showed an orbiter this was the case a
lot of times when people build software
they build it in such a way that makes
it easier for humans to reason about
that software of what the actual code is
actually doing but it turns out the way
that's easier for humans is actually bad
for what CPUs actually want and so what
they're proposing here is if you design
the system in such a way that may be
more complicated for mere mortal humans
to reason about but it's actually better
than for the CPU you already get much
much better performance
so Mon ADB X 100 was the name of their
prototype this later got renamed in and
and commercialized as vector wise and
then act in it's a holding company for
old software they bought vector wise
renamed it to a vector
they then like killed it off for a
couple years or they hit it on the
webpage and then every time I taught
this class I would always say vector
wise is great too bad acne and killed it
off and then like some dude emailed me
last year or two years ago and said hey
no no it's still around here's the
webpage where it actually was like they
like the website went out of its way to
hide where you could actually download
the software it was really bizarre but
then they sort of came out and rebranded
it now as Avalanche but they're selling
this as like a that oh that in-memory
OLAP cloud system in the AI runs in you
know AWS or Azure so previous years the
heavy paper the first part is really
good the second part is not so much and
it's a bit dated right it's 15 years ago
so they spend a lot of time talking
about like Itanium CPUs we don't exist
anymore and they talk about how you know
on Pentium 4s pipelines with like 31
stages but obviously in in modern CPUs
the stages are much smaller like on like
as of like 2015 or when husband
Broadwell came out it was like 14 stages
even up the latest one like copper lake
from intel's like I think nineteen
stages or no copper like it's 14 stages
the AMD Rison is 19 stages so building
your system such a way to deal with
these really long pipelines and the way
they describe is not it still matters
but not to the same extent of it they
did back before the other reason why
this paper is also super interesting is
that multi-year bonds and Marcin
Szarkowski Peter bonds went back to CWI
and he's working on duck TB now Marcin
basically went off off and co-founded
snowflake and a lot of snowflakes
designed is based on what what how dr.
Weis laid out the system right so it is
although vector wise is not that
well-known certainly snowflake is super
well-known now and it's it's you know
it's it's the rightful successor of dr.
wise okay so this is gonna be a crash
course on in two slides of like
everything you know about CPUs that
matter for for databases right so as I
said a CPU as wheat is v is going to
execute instructions in terms of these
pipeline stages I and look as I said the
Intel CPUs have 14 pipelines or 14
stages and the AMD has has 19 right so
they're not in the hundreds it's it's
pretty short but the end the idea is of
these pipelines is that it's gonna allow
the CPU to try to be busy at all times
but I type line on different parts of
the CPU so that way if one instruction
is it has a catchment it has to go out
to D Ram to get some data that needs to
process but at that same cycle to see
you can actually get an instruction that
maybe has data already in the registers
that it can execute efficiently so it's
gonna allow us to execute to hide all
the delays from these from these cache
misses and but it's and it's gonna do
this by executing the instructions out
of the order in which they were it into
the pipeline so what that means is like
when you write your code the compiler
turns it into CPU instructions the
machine code it processes that stream of
instructions allows them to the pipeline
the CPU may not actually execute them in
the same order that they were defined in
that stream and that they're gonna track
unreal things like dependencies to know
that the output of one instruction is
used as the input for the next
instruction it has to make sure it
executes in the correct order so the
again these are called super superscalar
CPUs and so because we are aware what
the heart is actually going to do we're
gonna
try to build our database system
execution engine where we actually
process tuples cuz that's the most
expensive part in such a way to to
mitigate problems that can occur when
there's mistakes in visions that the
that the harbors gonna make so the first
problem is going to be dependencies and
this is what I said like if you have a
instruction that that the input of that
instruction depends on the output of
another instruction the CPU can't
execute the second one first it has to
wait to the first one finished it before
it exits the next one so there really
isn't that much we can do in our
database system to avoid this right when
you think about it like you know if I
need to go scan a tuple and the output
of that tuple is then fed and put into a
buffer I can't put that data into the
buffer until I actually do that scan on
the two ball all right so can we there's
not that much we can do to avoid this
problem the one that we are gonna try to
avoid is is when we have branch
mispredictions so in addition to
executing instructions in a part of
executing and you know multiple
structions in the same in a single cycle
when it sees a jump statement rat like
to jump to a branch based on some
conditional rather than waiting to see
what that condition will actually
evaluates to and then determine whether
you go you know inside the if clause or
go go around it it will actually try to
predict what what path you're gonna take
and start executing those instructions
that that are followed in that and that
conditional and then if it gets it wrong
then it has to throw back throw away
everything it's already done and then go
back and refill the pipeline with the
correct path that it should have gone
down if it gets it right and this is
fantastic right we basically did
speculative execution and assume that
you know we were to go down this branch
and we got it right and all the work we
did ahead of time is actually useful for
us all right and again this is law it's
gonna reduce the number of cycles that
take to as we process queries so how the
CPU actually does branch misprediction
from our perspective if people build in
the day to day system we don't know we
don't care and actually unless you're
like working at Intel AMD you're also
not gonna know because this is like one
of those secretive parts of the database
system or the CPU right the simplest
thing you could think of is like if you
recognize you see a branch and you've
been down that branch before you just
take the path at the last
you ever took right that's the easiest
dumbest thing to do but obviously in
these in Intel AMD AMD they're doing way
more complicated things and what we're
actually doing is is is a trade secret
all right but we don't care what
actually is we just we know that there
is something that's doing branch
prediction and we can design our code
around it yes yeah so this question is
like is this part of the problem people
were hitting with like that in the
specter or the meltdown stuff this is
part of it yeah yeah okay as they said
because they have long pipelines the
CPUs can start executing specular
branches for us and again the reason why
we want to do this is gonna hide the
stall okay we think we're gonna execute
this let's go ahead if I get it then
things are fantastic and that'll reduce
my cycle count per instruction so we're
we're gonna hit this the most is for
analytical queries is as we start
scanning tuples we have to evaluate
predicates and our where clause to
decide whether to put something in our
buffer right as the output for this
operator and that's just an if clause
right so now if I have a billion tuples
in my table and I'm doing a complete
sequential scan on that table I'm gonna
have a billion branches I have to
protect potentially predict on in my CPU
and now when you think about it too
unless I'm pre sorting my data like
Vertica the data could be completely
random as I do my predicate you know for
all my attributes when I do my predicate
evaluation so the c2 is happening have
no way to actually predict what branch
are actually going to take because the
the probability that you're gonna take
the same branch as you did the last time
depends on what the data actually looks
like and the selectivity of your
predicate so in a modern c++ you can
actually so we'll see in the next slide
how to design our data system to to
avoid this in super those twenty you can
pass a hint to the compiler called
likely and unlikely when you have like
if calls are a case statement we even
say that I'm not likely to go down this
branch or I am likely to go down this
branch so you could imagine if you're
doing koujun which again we'll talk
about it on Monday
you could start inserting these things
if you know your predicate is not going
to be selective and that's what most two
boys are I'm not gonna get put you know
I get satisfy the predicate and put me
up a buffer you can inject these things
to give hints to the cpu to say this is
not gonna happen
but even then the cpu actually can do a
pretty good job in that case if you're
not very selective log it can still do
really well just do some of this this
came up with project project one
somebody was asking about this about
branch mispredictions I just want to say
there's a way to do this in school those
20 to make this happen I think modern
GCC and there's a intrinsic we make this
happen in modern C not in GCC and clang
they don't have exact keyword but you
can force it to do this as well all
right so let's look an example yes sorry
compiler then I think gives there's an
instruction I think in x86 to tell
before the conditional in the actual
assembly or the instruction stream to
say like I'm not gonna I'm not like any
great down this path it's a hint right
all I said was likely I'm not saying
like what for some probability the CPU
may or may not take that into
consideration and what it actually does
when it sees this hint only in tonot
right all right let's say yes let query
us when we have two predicates where key
greater than equal some low value and
key less than equal to some high value
so normally I tell my PhD students don't
show code and slides but for this for
this example we have to see some code
but it should be pretty simple to to
understand so a really simple way to
implement this that select query is just
a for loop on every single tuple in the
table go grab the key you want to bow it
over we're calls and then apply our
predicate right if he's graduating too
low and key less than equal to high then
we're going to copy that tuple into our
output buffer increment are all set in
the output buffer so that was we come
back around you know we can sort the
next table right so the the bad part of
this about this query is obviously this
if clause
because as I said the unless the key is
you know gonna be almost always the same
value then then like it could be
completely random whether I'm gonna go
down this path or not and and the CPU is
gonna have a hard time actually
predicting whether to do this or not
alright and if I you know I could put
likely or unlikely but again that's just
a hint and it's and it may not be
represented what the actual data is so
this is how to do this scan using
branching we can rewrite it though to do
a branchless scan where we're still
going to iterate over every single tuple
but the very first thing we do is copy
the tuple into the output buffer we
don't evaluate the keys we just say we
just copy it and then we have a little
two ternary operations here where we go
do a comparison of the keys
based on our where clause predicate and
what's happening is if the predicate
matches then we at we have a one if it
doesn't matter zero
and the two things together and that
then tells us whether it's a one or
based on that that's gonna tell us
whether we increment our counter or not
so that if these both therefore zero
then the offset will be zero when I loop
back around when I come I'm just watchin
it and then I need some code down here
to make sure that goodness that last one
didn't match that I don't include that
my offer right but for simplicity I'm
not doing that here so what's gonna
happen is even those look like these
conditionals pause the beam operating on
energy directly the time and write the
arithmetic operation right what is that
I turned this into like keep my you
check but it's
check the actual bits using bit
operators to see whether it's zero or
not like we can rewrite all the more
instructions that do just just do the
math right so this seems like this would
be terrible because for a billion t
blows I'm copying all 1 billion of them
and in this case here I'm only copying
the ones that actually match but again
depending on the selectivity of the
predicate and what our data looks like
this actually might be the better
approach the graph later perfect and a
scan on a table with the branching and
the branchless version of that scan as I
showed before and then the x-axis is
varying the selectivity of that
predicate so over here when the
selectivity is low meaning most tuples
are not gonna match like when no tuples
match the branching one actually
performs the best because again I'm
checked my conditional and it doesn't
match so I'm not wasting instructions
doing the copying furthermore the CPU is
gonna predict like the last you know
this almost every single tuple is never
gonna match that if calls so it's gonna
predict to go around it and not do the
copy as well but opt around 5% then it
actually starts doing worse than the
branch list case so the branchless one
is a flat line because no matter what
what whether the predicate evaluates are
true or not I'm always paying that
penalty to do the copying right so
that's why it's almost a plateau
straight across and as you can see up in
here when it's like 50% selectivity 50%
of the tuples are matching 50% of them
aren't matching that's the worst case
scenario because that's the CPU just
can't predict this at all and only when
you get down here 100 matches that does
the CPU catch up yes
the question is so you're saying this
this graph would look different if you
change the memory bandwidth speed or
that well I mean like leave the memory
of what for the scan yeah so like I have
to do that scan for both cases right
yeah but think about it like coming back
here like I do this copy right
if I come back around if this does I do
a copy the tuple doesn't match I come
back around when I do the next copy I'm
overriding the last place I copied into
memory and that's gonna be sitting my
CPU caches anyway the transfer what do
this copy is this is give me a CPU
caches right
I've read the two but I got to bring in
my cache right I got to do that for both
of them now I do this copy that's
running from one cache location to
another cache location probably gonna be
an l1 right I mean it's it's the next
instruction after this I bring the tuple
my cache then I copy it and that's
running to another cache location then I
loop back around and the the yes by the
time I come I do this and come back
around and I do another copy it may be
the case that the like if I'm
overwriting the last one I copied that
location got flushed my CPU cache maybe
gets flushed from l1 but I think I'm
lucky to get flushed from l2 l3 right
this is a tight loop there's nothing
else we're doing we just evaluate this
one predicate there's no guarantee
because we can't control how the caching
policy of the CPU x86 you can give it
hints but it doesn't not quite follow it
yes this point which I agree with him is
that I I don't know what other
optimizations the CPU could be doing
here sorry the compiler could be doing
like it could unroll the loop so it's
like four copies and then a bunch of
these things and come back around but so
again so this is what sisters research
is right the the exact view
and we see so the hypothesis is that
when branching when most tuples don't
match the penalty of paying that copying
is it's not worth it because you're
you're doing the second instruction
maybe didn't need to write so I so I
agree with you that there's a lot
there's a lot of other things that could
be happening here that the compiler
could be doing but we leave like we can
verify that this is actually working out
correctly we think it is based on these
results yes yeah so his question is this
works fine if if you're doing a table
scan because you've just been a rip
through continuous regions of memory
there's a memory prefetcher that if he
knows were accessing things that are
squinch alyttle bring those things and
reach out cache misses so we get a lot
of benefits from scanning columns if
it's an index scan there's not much I
can do as I probe down other than maybe
prefetch in memory but once I get down
the leaf nodes and now I start scanning
along the leaf nodes am I gonna get the
same kind of benefit if I do something
like this for data in the same node like
if I'm very cheap was in the same node
and I don't have to go maybe look at the
at the the the remaining parts of the
tuple like if so if I have my key my
index is based on this key but then
there's also another part in the where
clause that touches another attribute
where I gotta then go look at the tuple
then this probably is a bad idea or this
probably was not gonna be as a big of a
win but if I'm just looking at what I
need exactly in that node then then I
think that's what still work yes
for what Claus yes your question is if
you use the likely in this case here so
like if our selectivity is 50% so likely
and unlike he doesn't help us here so in
that case could the compiler then
rewrite the code or do what it's
basically like if I had if then else
you're saying like do I get any benefit
from say the else clause is the one
that's most likely to happen should I
should I flip them I do whatever the the
the boolean logic to reverse this so
that the first thing that comes out of
the if Clause is the likely one I
actually don't know what they do yeah
yeah yeah I see your point yeah yeah III
actually don't know yeah actually a good
point actually
wellyes applies to a statement to allow
the compiler to optimize with the case
were passed that execution including a
statement I'm more looking to more
likely an alternate path action that is
not in such a statement so yeah maybe I
mean this is not very documented but
maybe just maybe this is how they this
is what is actually doing correct yeah
yeah so his point is if you know whether
you're gonna go down one branch or not
you can make a decision about whether in
line or not yeah I mean compilers are
hold another beast it's not yeah what
about a magazine article pilot expert
will talk about compilers in the context
of databases in the next class like
things that we that's a good point
okay so the other thing we want to try
to also avoid it which is the first part
we talked about of having a lot of
instructions you you know use more
instructions maybe that mean necessary
the x-rays again if the if we design the
system to be sort of general purpose a
lot of times what you'll see in these
databases are these giant switch clauses
that that as you start evaluating
predicates or evaluating tuples for
every single type of data your your
dailies can support you have these which
call switch calls listen I have an
integer and I'm adding it with integer
do this if I'm adding it to a float and
do that all that at inches all that adds
you know misprediction that's gonna slow
us down and it's just you know it's more
instructions to actually you know
evaluate the conditionals and decide
whether what our type of data is and so
I we need to share this a table before
but this was an intro class if you go
look at the Postgres source code of how
they handle numerics like the fixed
point decimals this is just the function
to do add write to add to numerix
together and you see there's all these
if causes like if it's if it's negative
it's positive
if one you know if we're taking the
absolute value of something break all
this is problematic because this is a
lot of instructions and a lot of chances
for the CPU to get this wrong so we'll
see this again on on Monday next week of
how to specialize our specialized code
Oh for what you need for that one quick
and this is called cogeneration or
just-in-time compilation all right so
now we said we know how to we know what
the CP is going to look like and we want
to know how we want to design our
operator implementations to be mindful
of it now we're going to talk about how
we're going to organize the system to
process the queries which comprise on
multiple operators so last class was
talking about how we actually scheduled
but the tasks that that X P of these
operators but now we're just talk about
a sort of a higher level con so they're
gonna be different trade-offs we're
gonna make depending on what type of
workload we're gonna want to want to
support like OLTP transactions there's a
left analytical queries so there's the
most common one the general-purpose one
the iterator model materialisation model
oh and a vectorized model so again the
spoiler would be that the in a modern
analytical system we're gonna want to
use the vectorized model because it in
pass comment being we can pass you know
chunks of columns between operators and
then use cindy instructions inside the
operators to execute them efficiently
this is some of the volcano model or the
pipeline model bog volcano way-hey
that came out in like the late 1980s
early 1990s in addition to defining the
exchange operator which I'll talk about
in a second there's also the volcano
query optimizer
which we'll cover in a later in the
semester which then was the the
precursor to Cascades which is another
optimizer optimization scheme and I'll
talk about like this the the Gertz graph
II was also the guy that that did the
the wrote the the modern be B plus tree
book that I sent you guys for the first
project that's the guy's does amaze me
stuff it's very influential so in the
iterator model the way we're gonna
implement it is that every single
operator is gonna implement this this
next function and what happened when
someone calls neck on that operator it
has to then return back one tuple and it
could and since we organized tree that
that operator needs data from its
children it
next on children and that sort of
cascades to the bottom or you have the
access methods where you're retrieving
the data from the table or an index and
then we we move the tuples up all right
and essentially just we're gonna keep
calling next next next next at the at
the root and keep getting tuples and we
get output for it for for our cursor
until at some point we get it a good
response and say there's no multiples
available to us so at a high level it
looks like this so say we have a two-way
joint on table R and s and so for every
single operator we're going to have this
little for loop that typically it's
gonna iterate over some some input data
that it's getting either from the table
or from its children and then admit them
up so again think of these is just the
next function so will my child up here
the first the route we call next on our
own a child we come down to this next
block and it wants to do the join so
it's gonna iterate over its left child
come down here and say give me you mean
the next two but you have and this will
send back up a single tuple and we keep
doing this until this is finished till
we get all the tuples and we build our
hash table then we fall down to the next
for loop
call next on this child and then it's
just the same thing it starts moving
tuples up to from the s table then do
our probe in the hash table and then
anything that matches gets shoved up
here alright so this approach yes sir
okay yes
so so we're not that's we're not there
yet so this is like that would be like
how do we one of the CPUs doing when the
processing think of this is like there's
some place that you think a one thread
calls next on the route that calls next
on this child right and there's one
instance that's iterating with this
tuple but I said it's a blocking call so
when I call next this is not processing
this is waiting
okay so fusion almost every single debut
system you've ever heard about the
advantage of this is that we're gonna be
able to do pipelining meaning like in
this case here for as we emit a to best
ride that way all the way because
everything we need to nor the process a
single tuple is available to us at that
point of time when we do it we're
calling next right I can take this to
chuck here or the predicate put the
probe for the hash table and that that
matches then I show up here and do the
projection and then I can produce that
two boys my output so that's considered
a pipeline the fact we take one tuple
and ride it all the way up into in this
case here the output of the query or if
there's a pipeline breaker or we can't
go any farther then it gets buffered up
there so that's the rest area so some
operators are out the block until they
get all the Cho to emit all their tuples
and the other finish you get from the
iterator model is that output control is
really easy because we don't the push
down any logic to do limits necessarily
because if I know I only want to get 10
to poles as for my query then I just
call stop calling next on the route once
I get 10 to poles I've seen everything
and so down here this is just this is
just a sample of the of the of the
databases that use this approach like
these are ones I can confirm by looking
at the documentation or looking at the
source code but
[Laughter]
the iterator model it's the canonical
way yes compilation this is again this
is different than compilation this is
orthogonal this is like you just do do
compilation right I could still take all
these four loops
pop and run it and that would still be
using the iterator model in the case of
hyper they're doing they're still doing
this and that's another thing we need to
talk about as well like this is a this
is a top-down approach meaning I start
at the top and I sort of pull tuples up
the reverse of this would be a push
approach we start at the bottom and you
have this for loop and start here rather
than here and you start emitting tuples
up hyper does that most systems do the
top-down iterator model that's in those
common one yet that's next next awesome
yeah
I realize it's like it's like kind of
lame for me to give this lecture and
like oh yeah here's something cool next
class right it's like people's first and
alright so the other one here is that
rather than having an X where that only
gives back a single tuple I'm gonna have
every operator all the tuples that is
ever going to produce all at once and
then shove that to the next operator and
again I could be either doing this down
like you call you know get nax or next
and then instead of getting one tuple
you get a you get everything all once or
I could push it from the bottom up like
run run the operator get the output and
then put shove it up to the next guy
alright so in the materialization model
you can either do material as an entire
row or a single column like if you're
doing analytics it doesn't make sense to
materialize the entire all the
attributes of a tuple in your output
buffer if you know that you know most of
the most of the table most of the query
is not gonna need those at columns at
all or all the rest of the queries that
means the comments at all
and so this big same thing you need to
be a comm store or a row store and do
this so going
instead of having the next function we
just have this in every single operator
now we're gonna allocate an output
buffer and then we just keep filling it
up with tuples that match and then when
we're done we shove it up
so again super Mike from the top down I
call output function on this guy he
calls the epitope function this guy he
puts all the two plus if he has in a
buffer puts it on this thing now he can
iterate over this this output buffer and
build out his hash table and then we do
the same thing for this other one here
and we shove data up alright so in this
example here this is this is this is
like the this is a naive implementation
this is obviously really stupid because
for some of these things I actually can
combine together what the operator is
actually doing right so in this case
here what am i doing up I'm scanning the
table s putting all the tuples in table
s into my output buffer then passing
that output buffer now to this operator
which is just going to iterate over that
and if I with my predicate so a better
idea was obviously just combine these
two operators together so I do that one
scan as you just do scan the table
evaluate the predicate and if I see the
match then I put in my output buffer I
and you could do the branch this one or
you could do the the branching one and
it depends on the implementation so
although this seems like in the naive
example this seems really stupid you
don't want to do this like there are
optimizations you can do to make this go
faster and you do other things like if I
know I've have a limit clause of above
and I only want two n-tuples I could
push that down and eat it as well all
right so is my opinion that the
materialization model is the best for
for quality workloads because these
operators are these queries only want to
touch a small number of tuples at a time
so the size of the output buffer that
I'm shoving up to the next operator is
it not going to be that big go get an
ease account record on as Amazon you
know Amazon's website that's one tuple
that I mean need to move from one hopper
to the next right and we're gonna
benefits because we call the operator
once we call that output function once
we get all the tuples we're ever going
to need for the operator we never go
back to it again
and we shove the data long and that
reduces the number of function calls
which are going to be expensive because
those are jumps in our instruction
stream that the see us execute so for
only I think this is this is the right
way to go and then when we built H door
which was then commercialized volte B
this is how we how we did it Monay DB
did it as well although they're trying
to do this for analytics and so there
was a bunch of papers that they had to
come up with to actually overcome this
issue of like trying to materialize all
the data at once in memory high-rise
originally does as well there's a German
academic system the old version of this
approach the new version does not they
rewrote it to do the vectorize model and
then surprisingly I think this is true
Teradata does the same thing but they're
like a massive scale you know parallel
data warehouse so they're running OLAP
queries so they have a bunch of crap
they have to do to do bunch of push
downs as much as possible and basically
inlining operators within each other to
avoid having to you know move data in
wholesale from one you know one no to
the next I need to double check this but
I'm pretty sure this is how it works as
well
surprising because you know well tear
data was designed in 1979 so it's before
sort of the vectorized model came along
alright so the last one is this
vectorize model so this seems sort of
obvious to us now but like before the
x100 paper from from peter bouncing and
marcin marcin people just didn't build
database systems this way they either
did the materialization model or the or
the the iterator model so with the
vector prize model is basically like
iterator where you have this next
function and put obviously instead of
sitting sending a single tuple which
would be expense to do if we have to
scan a lot of tuples all at once we can
send a batch of tuples and the size of
the batch is going to depend on what the
harbor is gonna look like depending on
like whether we can be operator we're
gonna feed it into is gonna be able to
do vectorize execution right on sim DS
so if you know the size of our senior
editors we can then make decisions of
how big our batches shouldn't be so
going back to our example here now
slightly more complicated we still have
our next function but now when we call
next instead of getting back
a single tuple we're gonna get back a
batch of tuples and then inside the
kernel here when we do our for loop we
could do you know vectorize instructions
to execute those things and in parallel
efficiently take that batch apply all
the predicates with a single sim you
look at the same thing now for the other
side so this is ideal for OLAP queries
again because we reducing the number
invocations per operator for moving
tuples around from one Operator to the
next in such a way that we can execute
vectorize instructions very efficiently
most date and a little database systems
built in the last 10 years are gonna
follow follow this approach so see both
server and db2 and Oracle if you just
get the regular general-purpose row
store version of these database systems
it's all gonna be using the iterator
model but then they have the specialized
execution engine is like the fractured
mirror stuff we talked about for Oracle
db2 has this accelerator called blue
right these are all sort of these
standalone copies of data that have
vectorize execution models and they get
better performance cockroach DB is
actually not and surprisingly they have
a blog article that shows that they have
a vector engine and then in our new
system that we're working on here
everything's effect threads as well ok
yes question is is the size of the
vector aligned to the same knee size in
our system it's a line to the seamy size
but it's not going exactly the same knee
register size so like if you're if
you're simi registers are 512 512 bits
it's not like you want to pass around
only five and twelve bits you would pass
around maybe like like ten chunks that
are each five and twelve bits so they
like you can take a chunk within that
vector and then do the vectors execution
on it and typically the way that works
is and that's what we do in our system
when it when you turn on the database
system they go read information from
from the CPU like would your assembly
register sizes where your cache size and
then you can make a decision how
had a had a size things up that way it's
usually just heuristics okay so I
already said this before right there's
yeah I'm sure all my examples I was
showing top to bottom but you can
actually go bottom the top all right
this one is the most common because this
to people you know this is like the
textbook implementation of how people
vote database systems the paper you'll
read for next week from hyper shows that
you actually want to use a bottom-to-top
approach because now you can be very
careful about how you organize the code
for the extra queries so that within
your pipeline you're not just riding up
values from tuples within your CPU
caches they can go even more lower-level
and try to control things like so they
remain the CPU registers because that's
gonna be even faster than then the cache
l1 cache in our old system which was
that we have this technique called relax
operator fusion which I'll cover in
later lectures but this is actually now
in our new system as well the idea here
is that we're trying to combine the the
bottom-to-top approach with vector is
execution and we're trying to get the
best of both worlds as hyper in vector
wise so we're trying to pass vectors and
do bottom bottom to top and need to be
careful about where you sort of put your
your buffer boundaries so that you can
stage things in a certain size so that
you can pass things along and that can
fit in steeply registers sort of what he
was saying and it may not always be the
pipeline breaker point it may be points
within within a pipeline I think I will
cover that more later on this buster
all right so now let's talk about
regardless of whether we're doing a
materialization you know what processing
model were using we can talk about how
we actually run parallel queries so
we've already talked about how to do
inner query pedals in before but that
was the scheduling stuff we talked about
last class or we talked about well the
idea here is this we're gonna allow
multiple queries to run at the same time
and so you basically have a you know a
scheduling mechanism to decide you know
what tasks for what query runs hyper
original just had it we can only run one
query at a time
when that query is done then you switch
to the next one in the new system they
don't do that and most
you don't do that right because you you
want to have the system be responsible
as possible so sometimes you have like a
fast Q fast query Q and a slow query Q
so the different techniques and then we
use concurrent role to protect the the
data if queries are updating things so
this is a conjecture of mine I can't
prove it but it's after I thought about
for a little bit I don't think that
there is any difference in in the
complexity of implementing a different
query processing model the complexity
doesn't change if you're using different
control schemes meaning like if I'm
doing two-phase locking or OCC it
doesn't matter whether I'm using the
materialization model or the the
vectorize model I I think they're
they're they're isolated from me from
each other enough that it doesn't
actually really matter because a my
access method want to go that's tuple
that's when it goes and check to see
whether I can actually read something or
not whether it's being held you know
something else lock on it and all that
doesn't matter if it for this alright
well we care about though though is
intro query parallelism and that's how
we take a single query and now X key to
all its operators in parallel again the
scheduling stuff was last week this is
how we assign these tasks to cores now
it's basically how do we then organize
the flow of data within our query plan
so that we we can determine whether one
task is allowed to run yeah run yet or
not so the two approaches mean we're at
horizontally crossing the crepe and
vertical pair
I can have different parts of the query
plan execute at the same time again I
need to be mindful about what data
dependencies I have between these
different tasks to determine whether I'm
okay and again although I'm laying out
as he approaches it's not like either or
you can actually combine these these two
things together you can do parallelism
and vertical piles and together as
within the same query there also be
within every single operator there also
be a parallel version that we can use
execute the query
all right do that operator and that's
what books aren't covering next week or
they're my parallel joins in sorting but
Twitter's our operators then are
instantiated into or as separate
instances and they're all good they're
gonna perform all the instances of the
operate are gonna form the same function
just on different pieces of data this is
the more some of it last time break my
table up into horizontal motions and
then the different instances are gonna
run through different different
partitions at the same time so to
coordinate now these different instances
running the same time is they basically
another way a breakpoint in our query
plan so that we can recognize that we
can't proceed up into the query plan
until all the operator instances below
us produce all the tuples that they're
supposed to produce there's a wait again
for us to organize the query plan and
keep track of internally whether you
know whether one set of tasks of
operations are allowed to run or not so
say we have simple query on beam so we
can take this scan on a and we can break
that up into different operator
instances and each of these guys are
gonna run on us and in a separate worker
and then now because I want to do I want
to find other operators within my
pipeline I can also do the the filter as
well so take the output of each of these
scans and feed that immediately into
this filter operator to then remove
anything that shouldn't be there but now
also I can do other organizations like
if I have this projection up here that
shows me that i only need
I only need eight hid for my query and
say this a stable a has a thousand two
pools so rather than me copying a
thousand tuples up from one operative
annex I can actually push down now make
a copy of the projection here to filter
out everything just the except for a I
do I need here so then now they're gonna
do the for the join they need to build
the hash table and I'm not declaring
whether this hash table is a single hash
table or whether this partition it
doesn't matter but I know I can't now do
anything on this side I can't start
scanning B and doing the program in the
hash table until the hash table is
actually built otherwise I could get
false negatives right ID look up and say
it is my hash table contain this key it
should but I just haven't gotten yet I
wait these brought before proceeding
with the next one so this is what the
exchange operator is doing for us it's
basically now a way to coalesce the
results from running from these
different tasks running on different
workers and keep track of I can't
proceed until this is done then now for
for this on this side right I'm doing
the scan on B same thing also do the
filter do my push down my projection now
I probe my hash table in parallel right
and each of these guys are gonna produce
an output but to make sure that I don't
produce the final result of the query
until they've all finished I add another
exchange operator up here just knows
that I'm waiting for three threads to
give me all the results and then once I
have everything then I can show up the
output to the two up above right so now
my example here I put the exchange
operator up after we build the hash
table this is on a bottle we definitely
we definitely need this but I could have
set the query up such that I have a I
have an exchange operator here where I
do the scan do the filter do the
projection and then all my my my
operator instance tasks start filling in
an output buffer in this exchange
operator and then once they're all done
and that's all done then now I can flat
have the theory the queries blast the or
do the join and produce results so
there's different alternatives to doing
exiting this query and again it depends
on
what the dista tends on the selectivity
of the predicate attends the selectivity
of the join clause the datum could try
to figure out what the right way to do
this is or there's not one plan that
works for everyone all right so now for
inter operator parallelism the vertical
parallelism the idea here is that we can
overlap now different operators running
at the same time we can still have to
use an exchange operator to keep track
of whether you know a operator instance
a set of operator instances have
produced all the results or so to
produce but instead of you know doing
one and then you know a bunch of work
and then switching over to the next one
I could have a thread start processing
data as it arrives from the query plan
below it and do it in parallel right so
this is sometimes cut line parallel
meaning I'm running the pipeline's in
parallel so say I'm doing a Cartesian
product across four tables I join a B
and C and D with no no--don't calls
right but you wouldn't actually do this
but here it is right and so the query
would look like this where I can now run
the a and then B and do that in parallel
but it says I know I can't do the the
remaining join on on the scene D output
until that until this is all done then I
put my exchange operator so what will
happen is I could have one thread do the
join on a and B fill up some output
buffer here right and then which mean
building out the hash table as well then
another thing I can do that join and C
and D but then once and then as these
guys are and for the person the join
result got this thing nap time
right
because in this case here there's no
where clause
there's no join clause to determine
whether something to match or not so I'm
doing Cartesian product so I want to
take any tuple that comes out of C and D
and mashed-up fit any tuple that matches
with a and B so I don't need to wait for
these guys technically the fairness they
can search shoving all the data out in
parallel and have it you know certain
start computing the rest of the joint as
well right okay so to finish it real
quickly the theme we can really talk
about too is also like how to determine
the number of workers we're going to use
we talked a little bit of a little bit
about the last time of how we want to
organize the sort of the sketching
mechanism but we never really decided
okay well I had this number of cores
haven't and this number tasks how many
workers should actually use and as I
already sort of alluded to in that one
example with the with the horizontal
parallelism it depends on what the the
data looks like what the selectivity of
the predicate is and how much output
data I'm gonna generate so one simple
way to do this you can in the case of
hyper you just have one worker per core
and you just pin them to the core that
they're actually running and then
another approach is you have multiple
workers per core which is the Hana
approach and the idea here is that if
one one worker ever blocks then we just
you know we let other cores run run
threads run in the cores at the same
time right the last thing to talk about
again is this that is is I think we
already cover this last class actually
the push versus pull yeah actually we
ignore this this is just the sketching
stuff I don't know why this is here
sorry this is just saying that like in
the case of hyper I was pulling from a
from a global queue whereas in the case
of Hana I was pushing things into the
queue and then the threads had to take
down right all right so to finish up so
the as I said today it was seen as more
on Monday the easiest way for us as
humans to implement parts of our
database system may turn out be the
worst way for the CPU to actually
execute this and so if we're aware and
what the harbor looks like how it's
going to behave we may not know exactly
how that's gonna be but we at least be
mindful of it'll look
we can design the execution code for our
data system to be optimal for with the
Harvard with the CPU actually once and
then as we see in today throughout the
rest of the semester the it's my opinion
that vectorize the bottom of execution
approach will be the best way to always
exit olaf lab queries for OLTP it'll be
bottom-up materialization but most
systems that a lot of times like you
think like Postgres my siegel db2 oracle
all of these are sort of designed to be
general-purpose systems and that's what
the iterator tries to be like instead of
good for everyone yes
why is it matter of Bodmin for the
top-down fewer of function calls right
so like for bottom up in the
channelization model i I called the
operator the execution function for that
operator it runs produces some output
take that output now call the next
function on on and so forth right if
you're going top down it's like call
this call this call this I guess this
stuff is still the same for
materialization it doesn't matter for
vectorization yes yes he's right it's
its inner execution is that of a crisp
execution and then when you have like
the the as far as my understanding is
the best code you can have for compiler
if it's just a bunch of no conditionals
everything's sort of one instruction
after another because that the hot the
compiler can look event holistically and
make better decisions okay you have a
smaller cross leg as well yes that
typically is not gonna be an issue
query plans but it's like put like like
the call stack you know it's not I mean
yeah but I can't imagine is gonna be
like a million function calls okay like
even operators in query plan that that's
the onion door I can't even example like
that that's a the query can't be big but
like the theme no one's doing 1 million
table joints I think the the highest
number solve was from I saw a talk from
Hana people recently where they had one
query that was doing a join of 1,500
tables it's a lot but it's not a million
so it's it's a it's not gonna be the
call stack I don't think it's me bad bit
alright so again I I realized again I
keep saying oh well cover this on Monday
we'll cover this in one day so the
compilation stuff which is stuff on
Monday I that is is the paper meeting is
from the hyper guy and I'm saying god I
finger ler like Thomas Newman he that
system and wrote the paper by himself
which is crazy and it's it's a bit dense
because it shows little of all L of M
bar which you don't need it for yeah
there's any idea what they're doing
organize the query plan is such a way
that it's ideal for the compiler to then
generate CPU efficient code is what the
main takeaway should be okay question
yes yes yes
this question is should those data
points for Cindy instructions again will
cover Cindy in way more detail we'll
have to do two lectures on it question
is for Cindy instructions do the data
points you want to put into the same
instruction do they need to be
contiguous so the way it works is
there's there's a there's a vectorized
register and you have to do loads into
that the the data you're loading in
doesn't have to be all you have to put
it in application it actually continues
memories he PU cache and then write that
in I don't think you can do like load
multiple times from like different
locations so if now the data is in
different locations in memory you have
been copying into a single location then
copied it but I think about if I'm
trying to do a scan on a column and
apply a predicate into the vectra's
instruction it will all be contiguous
for me yes yes so he said there's a
scatter and gather CP instruction for
this I don't know one of them is
implement where I forget which one I
think it's the gather a might like as
I'd like to 2019 2020 maybe it is there
was a period where like gather had to be
implemented through multiple
instructions and it did that for you
yeah we'll cover all that as well yes
yes yes so I don't know what share
screens so a shared scan is if I have
two queries show up at the exact same
time and the boat accessing the same
table it's it's a bit more tricky and in
memory system this is why they want to
cover it like for disk based system but
most expensive thing is going fetching
the page so even if you and I are
running the same time but we have
completely different predicates if we
can share that disk i/o to go fetch that
in and then we take a copy of the table
or the block and do our predicates
separately then that's a huge win for an
in-memory system
oh I'll still get some benefit of maybe
having locality bring it into my CPU
cache like that'll still matter
put the overhead of coordinating the the
different predicate at the same time I
think is tricky like sometimes you can
do things like I think the Hana guys do
something look like this like if my my
query is like we're we're a equals
equals one and your queries where a
equals two they would then convert that
to where a in 1 comma 2 and apply that
predicate at once and then the output of
that we both get and then we have both
have to then apply our additional
predicate to get what we really want so
there's tricks like that you can do I I
don't think it's that common for enemy
systems because it really requires that
was like pinpoint precision of a query
showing up at exact same time that can
do this
right yeah yeah so his question is so in
a disk based system for scan sharing or
one technique to do is if if I need to
do scan on the table but I have a limit
clause so I only need you know maybe 10
to poles rather than just opening up a
cursor or scanning the the table
can I go peek in my buffer pool figure
out what I already have from that table
and if I have enough tuples then I just
process based on that I don't think
anybody actually does that I think
everyone always just does the scan
because if it's already in your buffer
pool when you go do the lookup on that
page you'll get a hit in the buffer pool
I don't think anybody actually does what
you're proposing we should do that for
me for a project an intro class um the
the other more common thing that would
be the covering queries for for indexes
where if
I have all the answers I need to process
the query in the index itself it's a
minimally scan sharing that's it's just
avoiding having to go look at look at
look at the actual scan on the table so
that that's probably more common I don't
know of anybody peeking into the buff
ball see what's around there and see if
there's enough for me right because you
would need to maintain some heuristics
to say like I think what you're doing
right it's it's a needle in the haystack
search so my query shows up it's on
table a but most of the queries are on
table be so but every single time I go
look at my brother pool and I'm all you
see pages from B then I'm just wasting
time
mm I'll just go scan a so you'd have the
maintain some heuristics and maintain
some kind of quick lookup to say like oh
if you're looking for table a like go
you know find some stuff you know you'll
find some stuff in the buffer pool
there's probability
I don't think anybody does that would
and I don't know if there'll be enough
queries acted to want to do that right
for ol OTP go get Andy's record I'm
gonna follow the index it's gonna take
me to the page I want to get and I fetch
that in for OLAP it's usually like scan
the entire table things with limit calls
would be like think of like loading a
web page look like of like like hacker
news you see the top ten posts wherever
they're for the most recent ten toes
there's a limit call as to make that
work right but it's sorting based on the
on the on the timestamp and those tuples
may or may not be all in the same page
so I I don't think it's actually I don't
know if queries actually make that
affected worthwhile and the other head
are doing it it would be too high yeah
there's a good thought experiment though
anything else any other random queries
about databases cool awesome guys all
right my new class will be will be a
compilation and then get started on the
on the ii project as soon as possible
and then we will we will announce what
what machine you should test your
concurrency stuff on okay
so his question early to be in the class
was the first check point we will not
check for concurrency we're only check
for correctness so if you wanted to you
could put a giant latch on the top of
the thing
and this proved that you can do inserts
and lookups correct correctly okay
because in grey scoop only gives us a
single thread so we really can't Hammer
it too much all right what is this
[Music]