[Music]
alright let's get started alright you
need to drop tables as back thank you
did you solve all your problems
[Applause]
yeah okay you know you don't want to be
in that boat it's awful yeah everything
else okay I mean you still gonna have
three girlfriends or you try to come
back one and a half what's the half okay
alright alright alright
so we have a lot I think a lot of things
to talk about today so real quickly
before we get into the course the the
topic for the lecture today so this is
the final docket for everyone this
semester this is everything that that
you have to finish up project 3
obviously was due last night homework 5
should go out today ish and that'll be
due in two weeks on December 3rd perfect
for will go out went out this weekend
and that'll be due on December 10th the
extra credit is due on December 10th as
well and then we'll have the checkpoint
which I'll talk about next slide and
then the final exam is on Monday
December 9th at 5:30 p.m. not in this
room I don't know what room they'll put
us in
but it's sort of a suti time so maybe
we'll do is that new candy maybe a new
pizza or something like that something
better okay so any question about any of
these things all right and then some
other things that are floating around we
have three more sort of I'm Convio
lectures but like course topic lectures
on material that's this week and then
one one class next week and then when we
come back from effort the Thanksgiving
break on Monday December 2nd our friends
at Oracle will be coming giving a talk
about the the stuff that they're working
on and again this is not like a it's not
like a lecture where there
you know instead of me talking about the
material they're gonna talk about the
same material they're actually gonna
talk about what they're been building in
in their group and you'll see how it
ties in together all the things various
things we talked about through the
entire semester the other thing that for
the second class in the last week I do
two things one we'll do a final system
review and the second one will be what
I'll call systems potpourri where if
there's any system you want me to talk
about for like 10 or 15 minutes to teach
you about what it is how it works and
why it's interesting you know and using
the vernacular that we talked about
through the entire semester we'll have a
vote online at this URL it's just a
Google form and you go select whatever
system that you want me to cover for 10
or 15 minutes okay so we usually have
time to do three or four of them so the
list that I'm showing here is the when
you go to the Google Form it's the it's
the systems on the DVD DVD video website
that have had the most views for the
last two months so that they're in that
order but you don't necessarily have to
you know follow that but and also
there's another one that's on DVD that I
oh that we want to cover that that's not
on that list just you know that you can
even type it in okay and you can go back
last year and see what I cover but I
encourage you not to do that before you
vote you don't want to sort of take your
your your bias to you just do whatever
people did last year because I'm always
curious see what you guys are just about
like yeah we've covered post miss a
little bit we covered my single Oracle
and sequel light a little bit easier to
see what you guys are seeing on the
internet or what you want to do it in
your job or on a hobby project we know
what system you've been thing about
maybe using and I can come teach you
about what it is and how it works okay
all right and then the extra credit
feedback again you can submit your extra
credit article next this Sunday on
November 24th and then the myself and
the TAS will give you feedback and say
what you're doing correctly what you're
not doing correctly and that way you can
fix it up in time for the this mission
so they did get full credit okay and the
questions about any of these things so
I'll put a deadline for when you should
go vote right if like you obviously
can't vote the day before the lecture
because then I don't have time that you
prepare it certainly or maybe the the
week of Thanksgiving
we did in London for this okay and the
last thing is that in addition to giving
an in-class lecture on on the ii that
should be December third on the Tuesday
December third book will also be giving
a graduate level research talk over in
the PTO in the CIC building I think
they're also giving an undergrad talk
Monday and Monday afternoon as well so
there's me three Oracle talks in two
days and you know one of them you'll
require to come to or not required but
you'll get extra credit for for the
final if you come to that and then these
tuition ones are optional okay any
questions we're almost done all right so
today's class is now the beginning for
our discussion on distributed databases
and as I said last class we can't
actually you know before we just you
know jump in neatly into distributing
databases we had to spend however weeks
we've gone and so far in this semester
to understand how a single node database
system works because when now we start
going distributed you know just because
we have more machines or more hardware
doesn't magically make our system easier
to build or better are you all the
things that we had to talk about for a
single node system we have to still
solve them in a tribute ax system and
actually they're even harder because now
you have to account for the network so
we've already talked about this before
when we talked about query executes this
this contrast between a parallel
database and a distributed database
system and when I talk about parallel
database system we were just assuming
that the the database system was running
on a single box that could have multiple
cores and multiple CPUs and then we
assumed that the the workers that were
executing the queries could communicate
very quickly with each other and that
communication was reliable because if
you're running on the same physical
machine you're sending things over the
interconnect between CPU sockets that's
super fast but now under strip in a
database system we still have to you
know there's still the things we care
about how to do parallel execution but
now we're doing this potentially across
multiple machines and so now we actually
need to be mindful on what it what the
cost is and the reliability of
one worker communicating with another
worker because it's going over the
network that you know that other worker
might not be in the same data center
right mining meet you on the same
continent and so now we can't assume
that you know we send a message there
guillotine to get that and that's gonna
come from problematic when we start
talking about transactions and other
things so as I said the for the Shiva
DNA stuff we could talk about starting
today it's it's building on all the
things we've already talked about so we
still have to do logging we stuff to do
a concur to toe hoodoo query
optimization we have to do query
execution to do joins potentially all
those things we still have to do in
attribute database and now they're just
everything is more expensive everything
is harder so for today's lecture as I
said today's sort of introduction to
distribute databases just to understand
you know what what they actually look
like the different designs of them one
of the implications of those designs and
then we'll talk about how to do
partitioning which is the the key way
we're gonna divide up our database
across multiple resources to get the
parallelism we want in a distribute
environment and then we'll finish up
briefly touching on how how hard
distribute concurrency control is and
then that'll segue into Wednesday's
class where we'll spend the entire day
talking about how we actually do this
and again like we're still going to do
face blocking potentially we're still
gonna do timestamp ordering all those
things we did on a single row system
still apply here just now it's
distribute it so it's even harder okay
and again stop and ask questions as we
go along so the first thing we need to
discuss is what is the system
architecture of the database system so
as I said before when we talk to
parallel systems we talked about there
being there being these workers that are
typically tied to either a process or a
thread that are running on the CPU and
they're gonna access shared resources
like disk and memory and so the design
of our database system in an urban
environment depending what our
architecture is right the variations of
these architectures are going to differ
in how you actually can coordinate the
CPUs and communicate with each
as you're running queries or
transactions in parallel and where are
where is the memory and where is the
dislocated in contacts to to the CPUs so
what we talked about so far the entire
semester is what is known as a shared
everything system assume this is a
single box a single rack unit that has
CPU and CPU has local memory and memory
and you know there's a local disk that
you can read and write to right now any
time I want to access something in the
binomial architecture that we're based
on anyhow I'm gonna get something from
disk I got to bring it to my buffer pool
into memory and then my worker up above
running on my CPU can can read and write
two things read write two pages and then
I let you write them out the disk again
most database minute systems that
everyday the system that's not
distributed is using this approach as I
shared everything system so an
alternative in a distribute environment
is one alternatives called shared memory
and the idea here is that you'll have
multiple CPU resources that are
potentially running on different
machines but there's there's a
communication layer that allows them to
have a unified memory view across all
those machines all right assume this is
some kind of high speed interconnect
like InfiniBand or tcp/ip it doesn't
matter the high level architecture is
still the same and then there's still
going to be some some local or started
some shared disk that everybody's
reading running to I said typically the
spoiler be this is actually not actually
I don't know of any database of them
actually that's commercially or open
source that actually uses this this kind
of architecture is mostly seen in the
HPC or high-performance computing world
like the people running on
supercomputers at like the big National
Labs they build software and assuming
this model for databases is there isn't
that much another approach is do you
share disk and the idea here is that the
CPU workers are the workers running on
the CPU they have local memory but the
the disk where we have maintained a
persistent state of the database that's
some scrum shared architecture shared
device that all these CPUs can can read
and write in to nice to think of this if
you're running on Amazon this is
something like s3 or BBS or HDFS and
kind of distributed file system so all
the the CPUs are still seeing the same
same disk but in order for them to
communicate with each other they have to
maybe send messages back and forth
between them right because they you know
this CPU can't read the memory of this
CPU the last architecture is what most
people think of when they think of it
attributed database just what is going
to shared-nothing meaning every single
worker is running on on a sort of island
by itself it has its own local memory
has its own local disk and the only wave
to coordinate between different workers
it to go up above and communicate at the
user you know using some kind of
messages fabric on the top so again this
CPU worker here can't read the memory or
disk from and any bits animate its
neighbors or friends in the cluster so
again we'll go through each of these one
by one so again under shared memory as I
said this is not that common in
databases I'm not aware of any system
that's actually people are using that's
based on this and the basic idea is that
the database system service is running
on these different CPUs it's running in
the same operating system instance and
assumes it has a single global address
space that maybe just aggregated across
different machines and then there's some
networking layer that allows them to
pass messages back and forth to make
make this work right so again this could
be InfiniBand this could be tcp/ip this
could be intel's omni path alright some
fast interconnect between them so in
this in in this world the database
instance running on one CPU it like the
worker is aware of other workers and so
if they want to communicate between each
other they can just do what you would
normally do in a shared everything
system you can write something into a
global data structure or send a message
over over an IPC and you know the other
process of the other worker running on
on the other another machine would see
that right again clean in the context of
a shared everything system when we were
doing to base locking with if we wanted
to tell another worker that hey I hold
the lock for this tuple I add an entry
to my lock table that's sitting in
memory
so same thing here if I one worker one
sit-up acquire lock on a tuple just
updates the global lock table and then
the the messaging fabric is guarantee to
make sure everything's coherent across
all those all those workers okay as I
said this is not that common I don't
know if anybody actually does this the
more common one is share disk and again
the idea here is that we have these
compute nodes that have their own local
memory they can have a disk up there as
well but that's not the the the final
storage location of any kind of data in
the database you can just use it for
caching in case you need to spill the
disk on your local machine but the
database the final resting lok resting
location is down here so if I say I
bring a page into my buffer pool in my
local memory say I modify it and then
I'm gonna write it out because it's
dirty I would write it down here to the
shared disk and now potentially any
other worker can can see my change how
you coordinate that will make sure that
they're told about that change will get
will get to later so as I said this is
the this is the present architecture in
today's cloud environment because the
disk is going to be you know something
Amazon provides like s3 EBS so pretty
much every sort of cloud native database
system that you've heard about is is
gonna be running this environment
because one big advantage you can get is
that you're able to scale up the compute
resources and the disk resources
separately because the compute resources
are stateless the state of the database
is down here so if these all these
compute resources crash and go away my
you know assuming I you know of log
things out correctly everything is still
here and then I can bring up another
instance and and pick up where the other
guys left off we'll see in a second
that's not so easy to do in a in a
shared nothing environment because every
node every node hold state so let's look
at a high-level example like this again
so we have our application server it's
gonna send requests to these front-end
compute nodes right this is where we
have the workers running on CP us and
the local memory and then we have some
back-end storage storage device
that everyone can can read right - so
let's say that the application says I
want to get record 101 it goes to this
node however it knows the good how it
how it the application knows to go to
this node will cover in a second but
assume it does so then this says some
kind of book up that says well record
101 if I look at my index I see that
it's in page ABC so I go to my shared
disk storage and I say get me page ABC
and I bring that to my bar full same
thing this guy wants 200 he doesn't have
it in its buffer pool so it goes out the
disk and fetches it in so now if I want
to scale up compute resources because
again the state of the database is
always here on own shared disk I can
just bring him a new guy here I don't
have to copy anything immediately
because if I now request say 101 same
thing I just go to disk and bring it
back to my buffer pool and I could serve
the request tricky sorry yes it's
question is how does the lock manner
work in the setting like this and then
we'll cover this yes not yet
to reduce simplicity we're talking about
how do we ever get things in now yeah
[Applause]
yes so this question is in a shared
memory architecture how is that
different than a Multi multi socket
multiprocessor shared everything system
they're the same but think of like so
there are there are there are there are
distributed systems that have a unified
memory cross multiple physical machines
so each machine has its own motherboard
has its own like physical physical
memory that it can be right to but
there's a there's a layer that it says
all the processors think they have this
one giant block of memory
nobody does that for databases you see
that in HPC world like all those people
are doing like nuclear bomb or particle
physics simulations they're writing
those Fortran programs assuming they had
this like no terabytes of memory across
smoke machines they can do computation
on yes
you come mean that companies like this
question is if you zoom in a shared disk
architecture like this if a database
vendor davison vendor is using a shared
disk architecture does that mean that
they either have to have all the the
data for a database in one location no
well we'll get to that again I mean
think about this there's an abstraction
between the physical and the physical
location and the logical location of the
disk these guys don't know anything
about where these things are right so
like it just says hey here's this file I
can I can read and write to just as you
would as if it was a local disk when in
case Amazon or Azure you get like a like
a block base or object based API give me
this bucket give me that bucket that
Nats sending a restful class to go to
some back-end service you don't know
where that data's actually is yeah yeah
so we'll get to that as well so his
question is in my example here when I'm
sending this request in this in this
example here I this the application says
I'm going to this node to get this
record you could have something in front
of this that could hide that or this
thing can maintain to say where to go
get the thing I need we'll come to that
just the third thing I'm gonna focus on
here is like it's like this guy has no
state of the database other than within
its buffer pool but that's not
considered to be that's good not
consider be you know durable or
persistent its ephemeral so this guy
crashes anything we had in here it goes
away
all right so now the tricky things gonna
be if I do an update right so update
page 101 hour sir an ID record of 101 I
have to update page ABC these guys all
read that same record they have page ABC
and the buffer pool but they're not
going to know about the the chains
because these shared disk architectures
they don't provide a notification say
hey by the way somebody updated this so
I have to have additional messages in my
knees notes to say hey I think you have
page EBC by the way I just modified it
and here's the latest version or if
you're gonna find out what the latest
version is come asking me about it
so that's all the stuff that we have to
build in our database system right this
is just reading writing to some desk and
so related his question that it's all
transparent so right now I'm showing the
database and this in this in this
diagram is on two discs but I can easily
add a bunch more to now split up the
data cross more - I'm getting better
parallelism better better replication
better reliability but none of these
guys in the in the compute layer they
don't know anything about that
because that's all hidden from me so you
had this nice separation where you can
scale things out independently but
you're gonna pay a penalty in terms of
locality of access because I can't for
the most part I can't run queries over
here
s3 allows you do some basic filtering
but about anything like a join I have to
do over here so that means I open pool
the data to my computes yes so yes
question is this is different in
charting or partitioning we have
explicit divisions of who has what data
we'll get to there I'm just showing you
what share disk is and a high/low
you can still partition at this level
there's nothing about share disk
precludes you from doing partitioning at
the compute level correct if if you're
not doing partitioning
any question is in this example here I
said when I update page ABC in this node
it sent a message to the other guys
updated and say hey I haven't make a
change is it always like this or what
all over the alternative yeah yeah so
what I said it in this case here I
update a page ABC it has to the compute
node at the top is update these compute
nodes to the bottom an alternative would
be a way to do a push notification and
say hey I just got an update ABC by the
way everybody needs to update and
refresh themselves I'm not aware of any
shared disk architecture like EBS s3
whatever the address up they don't do
that because that would be super
expensive because if you think about it
it's like a pop sub system I need to
know who needs to know about my change
because otherwise I'm sending messages
that are wasteful so as far as they know
nobody actually does this you have to
coordinate at this layer here and this
is the database system does this the
distributed file system or the object
store doesn't do that
yes his question is are we assuming here
that the notification is reliable or
fast enough no I didn't say what this is
I'm saying how we're doing the same
thing you have to do this his question
is can't you run an issue still raise
absolutely yes that's that's concurrency
tool we'll get there yes okay so the the
again the the pilot most people think
about when they think about distributed
databases is the shared nothing
architecture where you have each node
has its own local disk and old local
memory and the only way for me to
coordinate as I run run queries is to
communicate directly between my nodes so
if I want to get data if I query shows
up and he's accessed data on another
machine I can't go to disk and get the
shared disk and get it cuz that doesn't
exist I can't read the memory from up
from the other guy because I can't do
that I
a message to say hey I think you have
this data either run this query for me
and give me back the result or send me
that datum and then now you get the
issue of like who should have what copy
of what data right we'll get that so
this is gonna be the most hardest
architecture to increased capacity and
ensure consistency that's the stale read
issue that he talked about because I
need to be able to run the system and
move data around in a way to ride I'm
not losing things I'm not having false
negatives or false positive as I execute
queries right otherwise I shut the whole
system down then move data around and
add new capacity but I don't want to do
that because I want my system to always
be online so now you say well that this
sounds hard why would I want to do this
well the advantage you're gonna get over
a shared disk system is that you're
gonna get better performance and better
efficiency if the system is is is
written correctly because I can now be
mindful of the locality of data and try
to move the least amount of data over
the network as much as possible yes
correct so yeah so his statement is if
you assume that your your your Chiba
database is partitioned which we'll get
to in a second if now I need to add a
new partition and I need to reach
potential Erie shuffle data depending on
how I'm doing partitioning I may have to
move the whole database I'm in a segment
of it but again I don't want to have to
stop the world while I move that and so
depending how much data I have a single
node and I'm going with a network to
some other machine where's that machine
how long does that take right it's if
I'm doing this if I don't care about
consistency which we haven't talked
about yet then who cares just move data
around and if you if you if you miss a
read whatever because I do care and I am
running turns
then I'm gonna be very careful how I do
this and people get burned by this a lot
so as I said this is just a brief
smattering of or a very limited subset
of the some of the shared-nothing
distributed database this was a better
out there look most of the time for the
no single systems that came in around
maybe ten years ago they're all they're
all considered shared nothing so let's
look how this works again so no longer
we have a shared disk on every single
node we have a we have the CPU workers
we have our local memory we have our
local disk and then now what I'm showing
is we've partitioned the database or
shard in the database into subsets such
that each node has some portion of of
the database and so now I have explicit
information about what data I'm having a
habit each node so now the application
says well if I want to get ID equal to
hundred it has to know that this node
has has the data that it needs so go
ahead and get that and again now this is
operating as the same single node shared
everything data so we had before like
it's it's not my buffer pool I go to
just bring it in and then do whatever it
is that I want to do to answer the query
and return results so if all your
queries are accessing a single node this
this is super fast because again this is
just a single node database system the
tricky thing is then when you start
touching data that's uncross multiple
machines so let's say I have a
transaction that says one get ID you ten
and get ID two equal to hundred like a
single query wants to do this so now I
need to somehow get that data that this
other guy has up here but what am i
sending am i sending the request to run
the query or am i just asking this guy
hey I know you have this piece of data
send it up to me and I'll run the query
up here alright back back in very
now in terms of the the scale out issue
right on the shared disc architecture I
just bring up a new compute node every
compute node it's stateless so therefore
it comes along and start executing
queries and brings things from the back
end shared disk into a buffer pool as
needed but now and I shared nothing
architecture if I have to say bring up a
new node it now needs to get some
portion of the database from these other
nodes here so that I balance things out
right so let's say that this guy is
gonna send it you know a some some
number tuples from this guy from this
bottom partition the other guy here is
it sent up sometime close with another
partition and then once I've new I've
copied the data now I update some global
state to say all right well this node is
now responsible for the range 101 to 200
this guy's 201 to 300 a guy up about 1
to 100 and I was saying to his point
like this is this would be hard to do if
I care about transactions and I don't
want to lose any data because I don't
want to have a query show up but maybe
that wants to access ID equal 150 and
I'll and here and the the data hasn't
been transferred yet so maybe I can
answer but maybe it has been transferred
yet and I go here and it says I don't
have that data anymore so it returns
back nothing even though it existed this
node down here so how did it how to
actually do this in a transactional e
safe manner is is tricky and not not
easy to do yes in the back
his question is his question is how
often you have to scale capacity can I
shut the database down once a month and
add new nodes but what if I won't go to
the other way but so what so let's say
it's singles day or black or Black
Friday or Cyber Monday it's the one day
of the year where like I have a huge
spike that one I can plan I know it's
coming so I can prepare ahead of time
but let's say I have like a flash mob
right everybody wants deejay drop tables
new album all of a sudden so also we
have a huge spike in traffic that's
unexpected I want to be able to scale up
without having to shut everything down
and scale up gradually the the the older
systems will do exactly you're saying
any time you see any kind of financial
website says we're down you know Sunday
at 3:00 a.m. there probably may probably
not running a trivet a system but they
they're moving data around and doing
maintenance things but if you're an
online website you can't do that yes
your question is what's the advantage of
doing this versus having a single node
with like like you know instead of
having two nodes run these to hold these
two partitions what have a single node
and you say well this CPU socket has
this disk in this memory to run this
partition and then another socket has
this memory in this desk that you're
asking all right so your question yeah
instead of having two separate machines
that have you know disk memory and the
CPU what if I had one machine that just
had the same amount of resources that it
has put across two machines but now in
you know a single unit so questions what
were the advantages of doing the shiva
Davis so one is if the you get
diminishing returns as you scale up
Hardware vertically so there's
horizontal represent scalability as is
adding new machines vertical scale
voting to take my one machine
and adding more resources to make it
more powerful going vertically is way
more expensive usually and you get
diminishing returns and there's
obviously an upper upper bound how how
big you can make a machine right leave
one example in the early days when I was
in grad school we visited PayPal because
PayPal was running Oracle and they were
freaking out that because every
Christmas they were they would hit the
they were running Oracle on a single
machine they bought the most expensive
machine you could buy from IBM right and
you had to buy two of them because you
need a hot standby right so the every
every every holiday season they were
freaking out because that Oracle machine
was was was hitting the in the limit
what the harbor can do and they couldn't
buy a more expensive machine right so
they couldn't scale anyone any more
vertically so they were mainly moving
portions of the database off that the
humans are moving the portions Davies
off in like November to these separate
machines on the side just to get to the
holidays and then they moved it all back
so in that environment if they had a
distributed database system with cheaper
machines then they'd say oh the holidays
coming up I'm going to buy or turn on a
bunch of new machines and had the
systems scale out that way handle my
high demand then when the demand goes
down I can start turning them off and
coalesce into smaller machines
your question is a so these is the
advantage of attributed versus scaling
horizontal versus scaling vertically is
the advantage that you can scale out
much more cheaply horizontally for quick
but it is there's trade-offs right like
as we'll see as we talk about how we
actually manage attributed a data system
communication is now more expensive I
can definitely run faster if I'm on a
single node because I don't need to
coordinate between other different nodes
and send messages over the network but
as I said like you you can start to hit
scale go to bottlenecks right the the
trend in data systems up into the 90s
was always scale vertically the trend
now is to scale horizontally because it
just it's it's considered you get better
performance and for getting the better
performance you pay less you pay less
is that always true yeah I think that's
that's the convention wasn't that's
always true yes a statement is like a
isn't it better for disaster because
well again if you're running like a five
million dollar machine from IBM you're
not plugging into the wall outlet right
you have you have generators you have
backup power right but I would say that
the issues really would be the never get
severed right if you're if the the
network to the Machine even then even
then you'll still have redundant Knicks
going into it but even then if you can't
communicate the database but potentially
on how you design your Chuba database
system you could have the database
spread across different data centers and
then you can still be available well it
discuss more of this on
on Wednesday but this is this is this is
one of the trade-offs you get between
the no single guys versus the
traditional or new sequel or relational
database systems the no sequel guys were
caring about availability so they no
matter what they wanted a website to be
online and available and so in exchange
they would give up transactions to make
that happen because
if you have to have new transactions
then that the communication is more
expensive you make sure that everybody
is up in order to make changes and and
and they argue that was that was less
than ideal for some applications I think
that makes sense for for anything
financial that doesn't make sense I will
cover the next class okay so distributed
aliases are old some of the first ones
were built in the late 1970s muffin was
created by one of my advisers Mike snow
breaker the guy who built post grass and
ingress and vertical and volt EB he had
a system called
muffin that was a trivet version of of
ingress sdd one was a I actually thought
it was actually a real system turns out
it was just a prototype they actually
never actually had anything running but
there's a lot of seminal papers in the
late 70s written by felt the the great
Phil Bernstein on on how to build a
tributed database and do transactions
across them a lot of a transactional
theory that we talked about in this
class all right all that early work was
done by Phil system R star was a
research project at of IBM that was the
tribute version of of system or that
never became a product although there is
a distributor version of db2 today gamma
was an influential system out of
Wisconsin by Dave DeWitt that was one of
the first like high-performance Toshiba
Devi systems and then non-stop sequel of
all these is the only was the only
commercial distributor database system
and that was that was helped built or
Jim Gray helped build this Jim Gray was
the guy who was at IBM invented like
two-phase locking and a lot of the early
stuff that we talked about under system
are so nonstop was an interesting
company they originally were selling
these like super fault-tolerant machines
like think of like redundant hardware
like space shuttle level redundancy like
you have for CPU is running and if one
goes down the other three you can keep
on running so they would sell a database
system that would sort of build on this
architecture um it's still round today a
lot of financial systems actually still
still still use this and it's amazing
how long it still runs
I guess it's nonstop right
all right so uh all right so now we now
that we understand the the what the
architecture looks like a lot of you
have these questions that like hey how
is this thing actually gonna work how to
actually find data how do we actually
make sure that everything is consistent
so all these things we need to be
mindful of now when we build and shape a
data system and there's trade-offs
because we do not be able to do
everything so we're not gonna have a
system to be guaranteed online all the
time
and make sure that we always support
transactions and and not lose any data
or have inconsistent results so as we go
along
we'll see what these trade-offs are and
why you're not gonna achieve everything
the other big question we're gonna have
is how we actually execute the queries
on this distributed data and so I showed
two examples so far I showed the example
on shared disk where the compute nodes
pull the data from the shared disk
system into their local memory and
compute the compute the result and then
in the case of the share nothing system
we would send the query to where the
data was located run that locally and
then get back the result
so there's trade-off between how you
actually want to better doing a pusher
or a pool so the last thing to talk
about too is what does the architecture
look like in terms of what are the nodes
doing in the cluster for the Shiva
database and there's basis you know
there's just two approaches you either
have a homogeneous cluster or a
heterogeneous cluster so in a
homogeneous cluster every single node in
the database cluster is can perform
every single kind of task you'd ever
have so I mean like you could send a
query to any single node and that node
will figure out how to get the result
that you're looking for and they're all
gonna give me a potentially background
tasks and and other things so the
advantage of this approach is that it
makes provisioning and failover
potentially easier to handle and support
because now I just add new nodes and
long as I'm you know like I can move
data around safely I can add new nodes
and there's you know the system gets
gets stronger it gets better in a up
into a point which we'll see you next
class another approach to do header
heterogeneous cluster where you can have
specific nodes or members of the the
database system be responsible for
separate tasks and so now I can't to
make a decision say if I'm running my
systems running slower I want to add new
nodes I have to know what I should add a
node for this type of node or this other
class of node right I have to make a
decision at that at that level so give
me example what a one of these
architectures I always like to use
MongoDB because that's the most basic
one to understand
so MongoDB uses what is known as a
heterogeneous cluster architecture
so you have you have special-purpose
nodes that are responsible or doing
specific tasks in the system so in the
application wants to send a request or
execute a query it always goes to this
router and and so the router looks at
the request and says you know I want to
look at I want to get record with PID
equal 101 these guys are stateless they
don't know about what any of the data is
on the actual shards so goes to this
config server node that it's responsible
for spending sending is sending out back
the information about where to find data
on these different partitions or these
shards here so that's all this thing
does this thing is responsible it is
like a global State for what the
configuration of the system is so now
the router used gets this routing table
from the config server and then it can
send the request to the manga D or the
shard server and then that sort actually
excuse the query and get gets back the
result
so under this architecture again if I
notice that oh my my router
infrastructure is my bottleneck that I
can scale this thing out and add more
new nodes without touching the config
server or the or the the Charlotte
servers
yes
this question is what sin is able to
test so like garbage question we talk
about MVCC or building indexes or moving
data around because I'm I'm I'm I'm
scaling up or scaling down again like
you can't send a query to this guy here
he can only tell you what the
configuration of the system looks like
and this guy can't hold any data you can
only tell you how to send your you know
where to send your query so the other
thing we sort of briefly touched upon is
about this notion of data transparency
in a distributed system and that's where
we don't want ideally the application to
know anything about how the data is is
split up and divided or replicated
across the different nodes in our
cluster so the same sequel query or
whatever query language I'm using and my
application for my database system I if
I'm running on one node that same query
should still work and still produce the
correct sync same result if now I'm
scared out on a thousand nodes because
otherwise if I have a query says like
you know a select star statement and
then you have like some special thing
that says you know we're node equals one
two three if one two three gets now
split up across multiple Sheen's or not
one two three goes away I don't want to
go back and rewrite all my out I'm all
all my application code so we're gonna
hide all the details from the
application where the data is actually
being stored although we can push some
information to the client level at a
driver it allowed to figure out what
node he wants to go talk to you but our
application code
you know the Joe Schmoe programmer
should not know anything about how the
data is split up ideally it's not always
the case but this is what we want so now
to talk about how we're gonna split the
data up we've already sort of touched on
this a little bit we're gonna use we're
going to use partitioning why can't we
talk about this as well when we did I
think was the this time one of the types
of boarding protocols talked about this
and we talked about us with with
parallel execution the idea here is that
we're going to take our database and
split it up into disjoint subsets that
were then gonna assign to different
different resources if you're coming
from the no sequel world they're going
called a sharding but partitions and
shards are essentially the same thing so
now what's gonna happen as the Davis
system is going to get a query and it's
gonna look at what data the different
parts of that query plan need to access
and then it may potentially need to send
fragments of the plan to different nodes
to go have them exit that part of the
query and then send back the result that
they generated and we can use that same
exchange operator we talked about before
under the iterator model when we did a
parallel queries that same exchange
operator is how we can paralyze things
in attribute environment so let's talk
about how we actually split our tables
up so the most simplest way to do table
partitioning is you just take a single
table and you have every single node you
have each node store one one of those
tables so I have three tables a B and C
node one gets a no two gets be no 3 gets
C that's the easiest way to do
partitioning alright for this one
obviously have to assume that the table
can fit on a single node but for valve
it's fine
so I have two tables one and two I just
take all again all the tuples in table
one goes to one partition all the tuples
in table to go to another partition so
the ideal query in this environment is
any query that obviously touches one
table because now I don't need to
communicate through between these
different nodes I just send my query to
this one node it runs and I send back
the result again I'll get parallelism
assuming that I my workload is easily
divided across these two two tables but
we obviously know that's not always the
case that's not realistic so the only
very few systems will let you do this I
know DB can DB you can say
in their world they called a collection
instead of a table you can tell Bangi to
be store a table on this one you know on
a single node by itself but this this is
it this isn't that common in other
systems yes this question is what are
these partitions doesn't matter
for simplicity assume is shared nothing
actually yep in assume is shared nothing
in a shared disk architecture you don't
have you don't necessarily have fine
grain control like this you could could
you basically you could to say in like
in like s3 you just have different
buckets for different tables but you you
don't know any information you don't
have any information where it's actually
being stored so assume this is shared
nothing what is more common we get most
people think about in a distributed a
this is to do horizontal partitioning
Frost again we're assuming we're doing a
roast door system so for this one we're
gonna split the table up row by row by
looking at one or more columns as as the
partitioning key and examining the value
of those partitioning keys and then
deciding what partition to assign it to
so again in in a shared disk system so I
shared nothing system you do physical
partitioning because every nodes gonna
have actually store locally on at the
local disk its partition and then in a
shared disk system you would do a
logical partitioning where you fit you
assign a compute node to be allowed to
access a particular partition so that
you know you don't have a copy of the
same page across multiple multiple nodes
to reduce the amount of coordination you
have to do so let's look symposium it
like this let's say that we select this
column as the partitioning key and we're
gonna do hash partitioning which is just
we're gonna scan through and look at the
value for every single to boil for this
particular column and there's gonna hash
it mod by the number of partitions we
have and then that will tell us where
we're to actually want we want to go
send the data so now if a query shows up
and it's like you know select star from
table where partition key equals some
value we just take that value running
through our same hash function and now
we know exactly where our partition is
so this is hash partitioning you also
you can do range partitioning where
which I've shown before you basically
say you know this contiguous segments of
the value space
column goes to this partition then the
next we know 100 keys go to this next
partition and then same thing the query
shows up you look at the value they're
trying to do a lookup one and I you know
I know where to route the data that I
want or go route the query to find the
data where I want yes yes her question
is the just rephrase your question
selecting what partitioning key to use
is an actually an np-complete problem
because there's so many different
combinations I could do how do I know
what to do so this is something I
actually have done research on there's a
there's like a forty fifty year history
of people developing different methods
and algorithms to pick the partitioning
key again my advisers adviser wrote one
in the 70s and he's dead I wrote one
right it's basically it's like a search
optimization problem I look at my
workload
I see how I'm accessing like my queries
my queries are accessing the table and
I'm seeing this thing you know partition
key you know something equals something
over and over again then that's
obviously the one I want to choose for
all TV applications oftentimes you can
we'll talk about snacks class you can
almost develop like a tree schema and
identify like brain or passed down to
the tree that you then split everything
up so for example like say Amazon
divides up its its database based on
like state where the customer is located
so here's all the customers in
Pennsylvania and then here's all the
orders for the customers in Pennsylvania
here's all the items that they bought in
Pennsylvania so I can take all of the
Pennsylvania customers and put them in
one partition all the the Maryland ones
going on another partition so it's a lot
of times it's sort of obvious what that
key should be for OTP for all apps of it
more tricky you definitely have to look
at the queries what the queries are
because again you want to minimize mount
of coordination or data you're sending
between diff
partitions yes question is if we have an
index on the partitioning key will this
have an impact on the design I mean the
selection of the partitioning key what
do you my design alright so this
question is will get that this question
is this is my query my application sends
us how do I know that where to go what
partition has the data I'm looking for
like how does it know that it uses hash
function and send the query so if it's a
heterogeneous system you could have a
front-end query router like a did
it say oh I know the sharding key is
this thing here so let me go pick that
out of the query hash this value and
then I say that's where I want to go if
it's a shared nothing system with the
homogeneous architecture you could say I
land on p1 p1 says oh you won't actually
this query but I don't have this data p3
has it so there's rot your query for you
or it sends your query down here runs it
and then sends back the result through
p1 there's different ways to do this all
right so I'm showing showing hash
partitioning here right we just take the
hash value mod by the number of
partitions I have and that tells me
where I need to go what's the problem of
this is this collision ignoring
collision assume we have a good hash
value
so he says well yeah so if you do hash
partitioning if you do its crunch will
scan like if this is a range predicate
set of a quality predicate hash
partition is a bad idea because I can't
hash a range just the same time of the
hash table but not something else so his
question is if I update the partition
key right if I said a partitioning on
this column I partition this column I
got to move everything around yes but
that doesn't happen that often right
like like think about like your your
your Amazon account ID that they're not
they're not gonna say all right we're
not partitioning on that and what were
purchasing on his other than your email
address that rarely ever happens bingo
so he says if I if I had a 5th partition
here I have that same problem I had when
I we were talking on hash tables and I
see why we have to talk about the single
node stuff first if I had a 5th
partition here now if I rehash all the
values and modify five they're not
guaranteed to be the same partitions I
may end up moving the entire database
everyone might might be swapping and
moving to another location so that's bad
so we need a way to handle that who here
has ever heard of consistent hashing
very few good ok perfect so consistent
hashing was a technique developed in the
early 2000s and the way it basically has
to do it allowed to do incremental
updates and removals of partitions in
your cluster without having to move
everything around so the way to think
about this is that the hashing space is
just a ring 0 to 1 and so I'm gonna have
say three partitions a B and C so the
way to think about this is like if I
hash now key and I don't modify the
number of partitions I just hash it and
say you put it between 0 1 Sally and at
this point in the ring so then I travel
forward going clockwise motion until I
find the node that has the first node
that shows up and that's where I know my
data it's gonna be located so I hash it
I get a value put it between 0 & 1 and I
know that in between this you know
from doing this and this is a so the
data I want is on that right same thing
over here I hash to I land here so we're
in the ring space and I jump here to go
to sea so again the way to the the key
space for all these guys is is from from
the bueno punchin starts back into the
next partition right that's fine that's
not so great
what matters now is that when I add new
nodes against AI my disturb a database
can't keep up with the traffic I'm
trying to support so I want to add new
machine it's and scale out so let's say
I had a new partition here deep so if I
was doing the static hashing technique
that I showed in the last slide then I
add now a fourth fourth partition and I
got a Reno rehash and mod bye for now
everybody and we had to move potentially
move all of data around but the way
because system hashing works is that I
add my guy into the ring here and now
the only thing I need to transfer is
whatever C used to have weird emails
located so it's just this part here of
all that all the batteries that are that
are in this partition that would be
covered by this part of the Ring I send
them down and everybody else in my
cluster stays where they are at so I can
add new part you know getting new
partitions and they just update the ring
and add a new space in and likewise if I
take take a partition away then anything
here just goes up to where C was so it's
really interesting about this technique
as well is the way to do replication
okay and we'll cover more this next
class but let's say I want to do a
replication factor of 3 so for every
single in tape tuple I insert to my
database I wanted it to be I wanted to
be replicated on three different nodes
or three different partitions so that
way if one of them goes down I have two
others available for me that can serve
as a backup and my database doesn't go
down so now say I'm replicating a and
I'm gonna replicate it on three nodes so
I have on an a councils one then two and
three so any right to a any key that was
an a is also going to be on F and B so
now when my query shows up
same thing I hash to this point in the
rain
and I can get it from either a F or B
and I'm there it's guaranteed to be
there assume you're doing transactions
we'll talk about next class so this now
actually gets into the consistency issue
that we that we sort of glossed over and
we talked about transactions before and
talked about acid right if I do a write
on a how do I know that it's been
propagated to F and F F F and B well I
you have to wait until they all
acknowledge that they got the right
which could be bad cuz one of these guys
could go down one I'm waiting for the
acknowledgement and I'm stalling or I
say I don't wait but now I have this
issue where I I may do a write on a and
then merely try to read that thing on B
and I might not see what I expect to see
again so this will we'll cover this more
in next class but this is the
consistency this is the C and acid that
I said we were gonna gloss over for
single node databases but matters in
distributed databases so consistent
hashing is a really cool technique and
it's actually used in some distribute
databases so the three most famous ones
are memcache D which is that caching
service
Cassandra and dynamodb like Dino DD I
think was that had the first paper
discussed an architecture using this and
then at Facebook the one of the
cofounders of cloud era he saw the
DynamoDB Bieber hope that was a good
idea started but in Cassandra at
Facebook
facebook says I don't we actually don't
need this anymore and they decided not
to use Cassandra so then they just open
sourced it and put it out there and then
that people picked it up and started
started making Cassandra actually be you
know a quality system so these probably
three most most famous systems that use
this consistent hashing technique
alright so the new ones have briefly
about what the distinction is between
logical partitioning and physical
partitioning so again this the idea is
the same that you have this hash
function or range range function that
allows you to divide up the data base
and two disjoint subsets
but under the shared gist system you
have to do logical partitioning because
you don't have control over how the data
is actually being written to the shared
disk thing right Amazon controls this
you don't
so the basic ways where it works is that
you
have a son you sign some portion of the
database to these different compute
nodes so that again the application
server knows that if I want X you to
query here's here's the machine to go
get the you know go to run it right
likewise from down here he's responsible
for forth for three shared-nothing
systems are running when you do physical
partitioning again this is where you
have the the each each node is assigned
the the the partition a portion of the
data that's managed by partition so
again same thing I know how to get the
data that I'm looking for from these
different nodes alright so we have like
ten minutes left so let's finish up and
then that'll set us up for from
Wednesday's class so when we want to
start actually transactions this is when
things get hard and this one things get
expensive this is why I see her question
is her question before was Oh doesn't
always make sense maybe try to scale
vertically why would you ever want to
scale horizontally there are gonna be
just as if there's diminishing returns
if you scale vertically the harbor can't
actually get any better cuz you just you
you can't buy a machine that gets in you
know there's immediately faster it's
also assumed your software can actually
scale and it's not gonna be plagued
plagued by cersei concurrency
bottlenecks and other things if you're
not scared hosana lee then you're also
gonna have diminishing returns and
performance gains because now you're
gonna end up with what are called
distributions actions so if I have
something that has to update data on a
single node we know how to do that we've
card an entire semester about this and
that's gonna be the fast
the best-case scenario where my
transaction that I needed mean to touch
data it's all in a single node I can run
that with ever without having to
correlate with anybody else if I need to
have state across altima nodes then now
I need a way to make sure that if I make
a right here and I make a right here
when my transaction says commit that it
actually does commit because I only make
sure that all might change their atomic
and durable just as just as I wasn't a
single node system and that's gonna get
expensive because how do I make sure
that if I say I commit then everyone
actually truly commits
so the way we can do this is through a
sewer transaction coordinator so you
sort of think of this is like a traffic
cop for the entire system it allows a
way to determine who's allowed to do
what and when when it goes time to
commit that everyone agrees that we're
actually going to go ahead and commit so
the two different approaches are do
centralized decentralized a centralized
one is where everyone goes to some
centralized location that has a complete
view of everything going on inside us
inside the system and then it makes
decisions about whether you're allowed
to commit and it is decentralized
approach where the nodes try to organize
themselves and make a decision about yes
we this this transaction made these
changes and we're allowed to commit and
we can notify whoever else is involved
in the transaction that they've
committed successfully so the very first
version of one of these transact our
transaction coordinators was this thing
called a TP monitor from the 1970s in
1980s
nowadays I think if you look at the
Wikipedia article TP stands for a
transaction processing monitor back in
the 70s they call these things telecom
processing monitors because these things
are built for like the early you know
the phone companies that come back in
the day because they were the ones that
had most of the traffic I mean you know
most of the data so the way to think
about this this TP monitor is that it's
the standalone piece of software that
everybody has to talk to in order to
figure out whether they're a lotta doo
doo do certain operations on a
distributed database so the database
system itself could be stored across
different nodes and they don't really
know that they're actually involved in
the distributed transaction or
distributed database if you just take my
sequel whatever single node system you
want run that separately and then up
above you have this to be monitored
allow you to figure out whether you're
allowed to do certain things so it looks
like this right so we have application
server we have four partitions so save
your transaction with such these these
three partitions so we're gonna begin
our transaction by going to coordinator
and say hey we want we want to modify
some data at these partitions we need to
acquire the locks for them are we
allowed to do that and then the
coordinator says well I know it's where
else is running the system because
everyone has to go through me yes well I
see these locks are available so I'm
gonna sign them to you
then tell you that you you know you've
acquired them and then now the
application server can go to the
different partitions do whatever it is
that wants to do to make the changes and
wants to make and then when it wants to
go to ahead and commit it goes to the
coordinator and says hey I want to
commit I made these changes these
partitions am I allowed to do this and
the coordinator is responsible for going
and communicating with these guys down
here and say hey I think you know about
this transaction because it told me it
was gonna touch you did it actually do
anything and then they come back and say
yes you know these changes were what
happened and they're okay or safe to
commit and then then once once we
everybody agrees once the cornea
recognized that everyone agrees that we
can go and commit we can stand back our
knowledge meant question questions I
know what scenario would it be not safe
to commit so let's say I violate a you
know integrity constraint here my
transaction aborts right I try to insert
a duplicate key the coiner doesn't know
what you did it says hey I want to pry
the locks on these things and I want to
I want to commit in a distributed
fashion you have to go ask them whether
that's a lot like they were allowed to
do that for simplicity his question are
we lucky the whole partition simplicity
yes right there's a I think it's like
the XA if there's a protocol that allows
you do more fine-grained locking just
stupid partitions makes it simple okay
so again there's a bunch of a lot of the
enterprise software vendors sell you
something that that is a TV monitor
Oracle has this thing called tuxedo IBM
sells this thing called tranzec
which actually was a senior startup like
the guy that did the af-s stuff in the
80s they did a startup called tranzec I
got bought by IBM and IBM still sells us
there's a project you can't really read
the logo it's called Apache Omid it was
built by Yahoo it's a it's basically a
teepee monitor for HBase anos ecosystem
that's actually used by a couple other
systems today so you can build a tribute
database without worrying about
transactions could you just rely on
these guys to figure things out for you
and you just do all the single node
stuff that you'd bet you're normally
but pi more common is to use a
centralized coordinator as a middleware
where you had this piece of software
that sits between the application server
and the database partitions all queries
go through this middleware and the
middleware is responsible figuring out
oh this data wants this query want to
touch this data this partition so it
looks at its it's it's you know it's its
global lock table or information about
partitions are there and it routes the
queries as needed for you so you look
like you're talking to a single single
node database system through the
middleware but in the backend its
distributed and broken across these
different partitions so when the commit
request shows up by the application
server de moda where does the same thing
as the TP monitor does it communicate to
these guys and say hey are we allowed to
commit and only when everyone agrees do
you then send back the acknowledgment so
this one this this approach is actually
very very common like Facebook is
probably most famous one Facebook runs
the world's largest my sequel cluster
and they have a middleware assistant to
do all this routing for you Google used
to do this for for my sequel in the ads
there's a planet-scale that came out of
YouTube but this approach is actually
very very common you take us you know
Postgres my sequel whatever you know
your favorite single node database
system is and you build this little
wrapper layer in front of it
eBay did this with Oracle it's very
common the other approach is the last
versions to do centralized coordination
where you don't have a coordinator you
don't have a centralized view of what's
going on in the system the application
never communicates with some home
partition or base partition some some
master node that's been responsible for
this given transaction all their notes
will be master nodes if you're assume
you're a homogeneous architecture so you
send all the query requests either to
directly to the master node or to
individual partitions it doesn't matter
but it's when you want to go commit you
go to the master node and say hey I made
these changes I want to go ahead of
commitment transaction and then it's
responsible for communicating with the
other partitions and deciding whether
you're allowed to commit and if yes then
you send back the acknowledgment
all right so the thing that I call
Stover is that part of a how do we
figure out whether it's safe to commit
question this question is how do you
take the locks so it would be say again
assume I'm doing a lot project locking
the whole partition so when the query
shows up right you you you try to
acquire the lock at that point so the
masternode would only know information
and potentially about what partitions
you touched doesn't know what you did at
them right and it's respond to the
application responsible are saying hey I
couldn't get the lock of this partition
I have to abort my transaction so you go
back to this guy hey say I aborted
alternatively you just send all the
requests that this guy and he's
responsible for farming out to the
different machines at the masternode if
you touch the data at the masternode
sure yes okay
so we'll cover this in more detail next
class it's an impress upon you and then
you'll think about it and see on
Wednesday why you know how hard it
actually is say we're doing two-phase
locking my last example and say that my
nose or over the white or never one note
is in Pittsburgh one node is in San
Francisco
so at the same time I have two
applications trying to update the
database right and the very beginning I
get a lock on my node here for a this
guy gets the lock on B but now I want to
update this guy wants to update B the
other guy wants to update a so now I got
to go over the network and send a lock
request to get the other lock on the
other thing the other guys doing the
same thing
I'm obviously ending up with the
deadlock here so how do I actually
figure out who's actually should should
be allowed to commit this again if I'm
doing a decentralized architecture if I
don't have that TP monitor but even if I
do I men have not the fine-grained
information about what exactly it's
doing on each node because you can't
always know what the queries gonna do
before you actually run it
someone needs to figure out I have this
weight to a graph of a cycle I need to
kill somebody
and then so let's say this guy says oh
I'm gonna back off I have a deadlock if
I'm doing dog prevention I kill myself
this guy could be doing the same thing
so this is what we're gonna talk about
on on Wednesday how do you actually do
to ship it control how do you how do you
figure out you take two phase locking
timestamp ordering and run it in
attribute environment where you don't
have a complete global view of
everything's going on side the submit a
and a given time we're also gonna spend
time on when my transaction says go
ahead and commit how do I guarantee that
I that I commit everywhere because what
happens if a node goes down while I'm
trying to commit what should I do
that's actually super hard to get right
so if you're injured in these kind of
things there's this great is this great
website called the Jepsen project by
this guy called Kyle Kingsbury so he was
he's basically he he built this torture
chamber for distributing databases
Britain enclosure which is a bit gnarly
but he basically has this test suite
where he can take your distributing
database run through these weird edge
cases and identify that it's not always
correct and has and has has problems on
a guaranteeing reliability availability
or correctness of transactions so right
now he he has a consult company people
pay him money to go actually run this t
v-- build his website he has these
write-ups which are super super detailed
and take a long time to read to
understand what he's actually talking
about but he talks about how these
different data systems he's tried this
against they claim that there may be
transactions correctly they claim that
they can always support high
availability or good performance and his
thing shows that that they don't so they
paying him money to go run his thing on
their database system and then if they
pass they can announce that they're
certified there's one day to his company
was aerospike which is a distributed
key-value store they used to claim on
their website they had you know they had
strong consistency guarantees he ran his
thing against theirs crushed it showed
how it wasn't and they had to go back
and change all the marketing crap to
remove it because t humiliated it says
websites awesome his Twitter feed not so
much you'll see why to go look at it uh
it's not my thing but he's a he's a
really sharp dude I think there's a
really good website alright next class
just Roberto to me systems replication
cat theorem and then real-world examples
again we'll go through
start worrying about how we're actually
gonna run transactions in a t-shirt
environment will tell them about no
sequel systems and see why they don't
want to do transactions because it's
gonna affect performance and
availability okay all right guys awesome
see you on Wednesday ricochet jelly hit
the deli for the one yeah don't drink it
the sake don't know your phone can't pay