[Music]
alright let's get started okay let's uh
again give it up for DJ top tables
thanks boys how was your weekend good
you know I was recruiting what TLC new
jobs that's hard right
actually I found out Salesforce has in
the lobby in the main building San
Francisco they have a DJ every morning
and it rotates oh do you want to figure
out how to get you that job or what
okay yeah I guess you gonna do okay so I
think most people are at the TOC today
so that's why it's a low turnout which
is unfortunate because this is one of my
favorite lectures hash tables right so
we have a lot to discuss let's get right
through it so real quickly and then
reminders for what's on the docket for
you guys what's due project one is due
next week on Friday at 27th at midnight
and then homework 2 which will be
releasing later today
that'll be due the 30th the Monday after
the project so any quick high-level
questions about project one setting in
to what the question is when with the
autograder be released I mean so it's
live on great scope now you can submit
things today but we're not giving you
the source code for the test obviously
because that's means that the great yes
sir it should be live if you if you
submit it doesn't work please post on
Piazza okay and the other high level
questions okay so we're at now for the
course is that we've spent the first
couple weeks again starting at the
bottom of the stack of a data system
architecture and working our way up so
we've discussed how to store data on
disk the pages on disk then we talked
about how to bring those pages into
memory and our buffer pool or buffer
cache and having having a policy decide
when it's time to evict something and
how to pin things when I do writes so
now we're going above the buffer pool
manager and we start talking about
methods so these an access method is a
way we're going to you know get
essentially read or write the data that
in our database that's stored in the
pages that are stored out on disk so
today we're talk about today we begin of
a of a set of lectures we're going to do
on data structures that we're gonna
maintain internally inside the database
system and we're gonna split it up
between two discussions between hash
tables and and order preserving trees so
each of them have different trade-offs
if you because you've taken an
algorithms course by now so you
understand the implications for both of
these but we're gonna describe what
matters to us in the context of database
systems because just because you have a
tree versus a hash table maybe
understand how to do proofs on it or
write algorithms to it to interact with
it now let's talk about what what
happens when we actually put it inside a
database system and actually try to use
it so data structures are used all
throughout the database measurement
system right for a variety of purposes
so one thing we've talked about so far
we turn how to use data structures for
maintaining the internal metadata about
what's in our database when we talk
about there being a page table or a page
directory and that was a hash table to
do lookups between a hash IDE or so a
page to a page ID to a frame or a page
ID to some location on on disk the next
thing we can use them for is actually
just the core data storage of the
database itself so what I mean by bad is
instead of as having on order to heap a
bunch of pages we can actually organize
them at a higher level to be a hash
table or a B+ tree or tree data
structure and have the the values in in
the data structure actually be tuples
so this is very common in a lot of
systems like like memcache for example
essentially a john is a giant hash table
or my Seco in a DDS engine is just a B+
tree where they store the tuples
themselves inside of the side of the
leaf nodes of the tree we can also use
data structures to maintain temporary
data so this would be like if we're
running a query and we need to compute
something very efficiently we could
build a data structure on the fly
populated with whatever data we need
finished executing the query and then
this throw away that data structure and
be done with it and the last one that's
why you
you're most familiar with is using these
data structures for table indexes right
essentially building a glossary over
keys inside of our tuples and allows how
to do you know quick lookups to find
individual elements that we want rather
than having to do a sequential scan
throughout the entire database so for
all these purpose again you need good
data structures to do all these things
so the things we want to care about how
we design our data structures is is the
two following things so the first is
were to carry out what the data
organization is we need how are we gonna
represent the key value pairs are the
elements of the data that we're storing
in either in memory or on pages that
were storing on disk and we do this in
an efficient way that can support fast
reads and writes without having to your
major overhaul or maybe maybe
restructuring of the entire data
structure every single time the second
issue is that how we're going to allow
multiple threads to access our data
structure or multiple queries access to
the our data structure at the same time
without causing any physical violations
to the eternal representation of the
data so what I mean by that is we don't
want to have maybe one thread update a
memory address while another thread it's
reading that address and then they see
some torn white or some corrupt version
of that address and now that points to
some invalid page or installed invalid
memory location where we end up
producing incorrect results so we'll see
how we actually handle this we'll talk a
little bit long as we go along today but
we'll spend a whole lecture while
discussing how to do concurrency control
inside of indexes inside of these data
structures but for our purposes today
but you sort of simplify the discussion
just assume we only have a single thread
and because this is going to matter
later on also to when we talk about
transactions because the type of things
we'll talk about here we'll use latches
to protect the physical data structure
that prevents from again reading invalid
memory addresses or invalid page
locations there's also a higher level
concept of what's the logical
correctness of our data structure that
we need to care about as well and
that'll come later on in the semester so
it says what I mean by bad is to say I
have an index I delete a key if I come
back Mike my thread comes back and tries
to retrieve that key again I shouldn't
get it because I know it's been deleted
even though the physical bit still may
be there because I I'll do some
background garbage
to clean up later on but logically Mikey
should be gone even though physically
it's not so that this topic is very
complicated and so we'll touch on a
little bit today but mostly care about
the physical the physical integrity of
the data structure rather than the
logical one okay today again we're going
to focus on hash tables so a hash table
is a abstract data type that we're going
to use to provide a unordered
associative array implementation or API
and all that means that we're able to
map arbitrary keys to arbitrary values
all right there's no ordering to this
thing like we're gonna see in trees and
so the way we're gonna be able to do
this these fast look ups to find
elements that we want is that we're
gonna use a hash function that's gonna
take in our key and then compute some
offset in some way to some location in
my array and that's gonna tell me either
exactly the element looking for or I can
roughly look around close to by where
I'll and after I use my hash function to
find the thing that I'm looking for so
the hash function isn't always gonna get
us exactly where we want but at least
get us in the right location and we know
how to then look around to find the
thing that we are looking for so again
so this none of this should be new you
should all take an algorithms class so
the space complexity in the worst case
of a hash table is is Big O n that means
that we for every single key we want to
store we least have one one entry for it
in our hash table so to allocate that
amount of memory amount of space the
operational complexity is interesting
because on average we're gonna get o one
lookups meaning we in one step in
constant time you can find exactly the
thing that we're looking for worst case
scenario and we'll see why this happens
when we in a few seconds the worst case
scenario will get Big O n meaning we'll
have to do a squinter scan or a linear
search to find to look every single
possible key to find that the key that
we're looking for so you may be thinking
alright this this is great any hash
function or any hash table will do
because I'm always gonna get o 1 for the
most part in practice even though this
is super fast in the real world where
money's involved constant factors
actually matter a lot and so we'll see
this when we just look at
functions right hash functions what we
you know sometimes it'll be it would
still be super fast but there'll be some
hash function that'll be twice as fast
or three times as fast as other hash
functions so you may say all right for
one hashing who cares but if now I'm
hashing a billion things and my crappy
hash function takes a second slower than
the fastest one
now that's I'm spending a billion
seconds to do this lookup so when
there's real money involved when we're
looking at large-scale the constant
factors actually matter when you take
your algorithms class there's like oh
one we don't care about anything else
the constants don't matter in our world
it does all right so let's look at the
most simplest hash table you could ever
build right and all it is is just a a
giant array which is now like a big
chunk of memory and then we're gonna say
that every single offset in our array
corresponds to a given element and so
for this to work we're gonna assume that
we know exactly the number of keys are
gonna have ahead of time and we know
exactly what what there with the reduced
we shouldn't their values are with what
their actual values are right so now to
find any key in my hash table I just
take the take a hash on the key mod it
by the number of elements that I have
and then that's going to get me to some
offset and this is exactly the thing
that I'm looking for so let's look at
and see how this works so let's say that
and we have three keys ABCD de F X Y Z
so again I can just take this thing ABCD
ABC hash it and then that'll tell me I
know I'm at offset zero is exactly the
thing I'm looking for so this is not
exactly what our hash table is actually
could look like if this is just storing
the original keys and practice what
we're gonna need to have is actually
store pointers to where the original you
know some other location where that
original keys is located again think of
this like a table index I don't want to
store the keys maybe in might my hash
table I want to store it a pointer to
where the key is found all right
so what are some problems to be
sometimes we made with this kind of hash
table yes in the back
correctly you say that we know the
number elements ahead of time in the
first place that's one
what's the second assumption because all
the batteries are near each other in the
cache that does for this purpose that
doesn't matter here but he says there's
no collision between keys so what is a
collision
he says the hash in the same slot
exactly right so this really simple hash
table this is actually the fastest hash
table you could ever possibly build but
you have to make these assumptions in
order to make to work right so the first
is that as he said we need to know
exactly the number of elements that we
had ahead of time so we know exactly how
many slots we want to allocate in our
array and in practice that's not always
going to be the case all right if I'm
building a I'm using my hash table as a
hash index am I on a table when I create
the table I don't have any I don't have
any data in there in the first place and
as I started inserting things then the
number of slots I need actually grows
the other assumption that we mixed was
that we said every hash or every key is
unique and that's what he that's what
he's saying that there's no collision so
we're assuming that every time we hash
it it's always gonna land into a unique
slot for that one key and only that key
ever to be able to exactly find the
thing that we're looking for and so
because we know all the keys ahead of
time and because we know that they're
unique when we hash them this is using
what is called a perfect hash function
so a perfect hash function is like this
if theoretical thing it exists in the
research literature but in practice
nobody actually does this because it's
impractical you can't actually do this
and a perfect hash function just means
that if I have two keys that are not
they're not equivalent then whatever
hash I generate for them is also not
gonna be equivalent so for every unique
key I generate an exactly unique hash
value and again you can't actually do
that there's no magic hash function that
exists today that can guarantee this the
way you would actually implement a
perfect hash function is actually use
another hash table to map a key to
another you know
the hash value which is kind of you know
stupid cuz now you have a hash table for
your hash table it's so nobody actually
does this in practice so the thing that
we're gonna talk about today is how do
we actually build a hash table in the
real world to not have to make these
assumptions and be able to use them in a
database system so when people say I
have a hash table they essentially mean
it's it's a data structure comprised of
two parts
the first is the hash function which is
a way to take any arbitrary key and Matt
you know a map it to a integer value in
a smaller domain right so I can take any
string and the integer and you float
doesn't matter I throw it to my hash
function and it's gonna produce either a
32-bit or 64-bit hash unique hash value
integer or not unique so I hash hash
integer so there's gonna be this big
trade off and and what kind of hash
function we're gonna use between how
fast it is and the collision rate
because again if we have different keys
mapped to the same slot that's a
collision and now we have to deal with
that in our hashing scheme so what's the
fastest hash function I could ever build
with that is mod prime number even
faster with that he said that value
itself you're close but what does that
mean if I have a string how do I return
back that value and then put it into my
slot even faster there's bits of memory
to give it if it's a large string he
said mod if there's a mod nur yes
constant one right no matter what key
you give me I return back the number one
that's gonna be super fast because
that's gonna be on the stack that's
gonna be impossibly fast but your
collision rate is because it always goes
to the same slot so in the other end of
spectrum is that perfect hash function
but I said I need I need another hash
table to make that work max like the
worst case scenario so my collision rate
is is zero but that's the slowest so we
want something in the middle okay all
right so the next piece is the hashing
scheme the hashing scheme is essentially
the the mechanism or procedure we're
going to use when we encounter our
collision in our hash table
right so again there's this trade-off
between memory and and compute which is
the classic trade-off in computer
science so if I allocate an impossibly
large
you know slot array like you know two to
the 64 slots because that's all the
memory you have them on my machine then
my collision rate is gonna be
practically zero of course now I can't
do anything else in my database because
I've used all my memory for my hash
table that's barely even full but my
collision rate is gonna be amazing if I
have a slot array of size 1 my clear
rates can be terrible
and if I have to do a bunch of extra
instructions to deal with those
collisions but my storage overhead is is
the minimum so again there's this we
want to be sort of in the middle here we
want to balance the amount of memory
we're using or amount of storage we're
using for a hash table with the extra
instructions or grant code you have to
do when we have a collision all right so
today we're gonna focus on again the the
the with send beginnings are still about
hash functions just get to show you what
what hash fronts are out there the
modern ones that people are using and
then we're talk about two type of
hashing schemes the first is static
hashing is where you you you have an
approximation of what the size of the
keys are trying to store the key set and
then we'll talk about dynamic hashing
where you can have a hash table that can
incrementally grow without having to
reshuffle everything again the
combination of a hash function and
hashing scheme is what people mean when
they say I have a hash table alright so
again a hash function is just this
really fast function that we want to
take any arbitrary byte array or any
arbitrary key and then spit back a
32-bit or a 64-bit integer so can
anybody name a hash function maybe one
they've used before
he says sha what sha-256 that's one can
name another one yes md5 perfect all
right this is actually a great example
so he said sha-256 he said md5 sha-256
is a cryptographic hash function that's
actually reversible right it's a public
public/private key thing so given a key
I can hash it and then I know how to
take that key and reverse and get back
the original value
he said md5 which takes any arbitrary
key and fist back a 32 character unique
hash that in
it's not supposed to be reversible it is
now cuz people cracked it but that's
something where it's of one way hash
hisses hisses of reversible hash so in
our database system we do not care about
cryptography for when we do we're doing
hash tables now that's you know you you
can encrypt the data when you store it
on on disk or on your public cloud
infrastructure but when we're doing our
hash join or and building our hash table
we're not gonna care about cryptography
we're not gonna care about
leaking information about our keys
because we're just trying to build this
hash you know build our hash tip hashing
data structure so we're not gonna use
something like like sha-256 because one
we don't care about the cryptographic
guarantees it provides it's also super
slow so we're not gonna use it at all MP
5 is 1 is 60 a one-way hash and that's
something we could use for a hash
function we don't because it's super
slow we'll see other ones that are that
are faster and it's also sweet one way
but people have rainbow tables to
reverse it so that has doesn't we have
good cryptographic guarantees all right
so again we care about something that's
fast we care something that has a low
collision rate so B this is just sort of
a list of some of the hash functions
that are people are using today so CRC
is used in the networking world it was
originally you know a Menten in 1975 I
don't remember whether it was 32 bits or
16 bits back then
but now if you want to use CRC there's a
64 bit version and you would use
something like that
so again this will produce something
with a reasonable collision rate and but
it's gonna be super super slow so we
nobody actually does this in practice so
this is sort of murmur hash sort of
again from a database perspective this
enters the era of modern hashing
functions and these are the ones that
we're gonna care about so murmur hash
came out in 2008 it was just some dude
on the internet posted up his his
general-purpose hashing code on github
and then people picked it up and then
started using it Google then took murmur
hash in in the early 2010's modified it
to be a faster on shorter keys and then
they released something called City hash
and then later on in 2014 they've
modified this again to have farm hash
that has a better collision rate than
City hash so farm hashes City House are
pretty common in some systems
what is now considered to be the state
of your art and the fastest and has the
best collision rate in four hash punches
today is actually Facebook's xx hash and
not the the original one 2012 there's a
xx - 3 that is actively under active
under active development now I think it
came out in 2019 so right now this is
the fastest and has the best collision
rate of all these hash functions so if
you're building a database system today
you want to be using xx hash so again we
don't care so much how this is actually
implemented right I don't this is not an
algorithms class I don't care about the
internals are again all I care about is
how fast it is and what the collision
rate is and there's benchmarks to
measure and the quality of the
collisions cousin rates all these
algorithms so this is a benchmark
micromanager like I've run you every
year so this is like an open-source
framework that I took I modified that
just scales up the number of keys you
throw into the hash function and see how
fast it can actually compute hashes on
things so this here we're looking at
from one to eight bytes for the key
sizes which is pretty small right when
you think about essentially a 64-bit
integer but you want this is beyond what
like email keys or URLs it will be so at
the really smallest level right the the
CRC actually does the fastest here but
then of course as you scale up the the
farm hash City hash and the Facebook
access hash do you know are getting much
better what really matters is one wheel
actually looking larger key sizes which
is something like this so now you see
the CRC hash sucks ass and no matter how
much bigger the key is the throughput
rate is is essentially the same but you
see these really nice spikes here for at
32 bytes and 64 bytes for font hash city
hash and xxxx hash three alright and
this is because the the the key that
they're processing that they're
computing on fits within a single cache
line so as I see you a single fetch into
memory I'm bringing in 64 bytes into my
cache and I can operate on you know for
that single fetch I'm operating on all
the data within that that cash cash cash
lookup so that's why there's sort of the
solitude pattern here and then beyond
this I think after 64 byte City hash on
farm hash switch to a different
algorithm and then it's
be different you see different
properties whereas xx hash still does
quite well so again I'm not showing the
collision right here but there's
benchmarks online they can show you that
even though XS hash is actually the
fastest here it actually still gets a as
good as a collision rate as City hash
and farm hash so in our own system today
we're using excess hash as much as
possible so any questions about that
kind of hash function just takes a
arbitrary key spits back a value yes his
statement which is when I'm not heard
before is that it's possible that
someone could give a someone could give
a data in such a way that it they know
the values would always hash to the same
thing and therefore you would have a
potential denial service attack because
you're causing the the collision rate to
be super large and now for it's taking
longer to run your queries all right
let's talk about this so one is in the
database world at least the data stuff
we're talk about here the users are
trusted meaning I'm running Postgres in
own shop or whatever system in my own
hardware whoever is supposed to give me
access to that has already betted me in
trusted me so I'm not gonna be that
malicious to you also provided a seed
when you do these hashing so that one
unless that's hard coded you may not
know exactly what that is and then three
you may say all right what if I'm in a
cloud system and I you know someone is
malicious that way well Google doesn't
care or Amazon don't care because you're
the one paying for the hardware so if
you give me keys then then hash to the
same thing and your collision rate is
super long now your query takes a long
time and they're just clocking your
money so it's not it's not I'm sure you
could think of a tack that does this but
for what we're talking I'm hearing in
terms of the system nobody cares again
there's databases that will encrypt the
data at rest on on s3 or EBS buckets
that's a whole separate thing from this
there's another question or now okay
again I there are equipped erratic
databases I'm people are spending a lot
of money to worry about these things
because data breaches are a big deal I
don't care at this point my life
I'll get point and then they don't care
but now I don't care alright so again
we're not reading hash functions we're
just gonna take one of these three or
what you know in general we wanna take
xx hash and that'll be good enough okay
don't write your own hash function it's
not worth your time all right so let's
talk about now how do we use our hash
function in our and our hashing scheme
to deal with collisions so again what
we're talking about here it doesn't
matter what hashing function we're using
right could be the slowest wanted to be
the fastball fastest one
all these hashing schemes will still
work the same because this is this is
what we're doing after we'd hash it
after we jump to some location and now
we got to figure out how do we deal with
collisions or how to find that thing
that we're looking for so we're gonna
search talk about be the most basic hash
table you can have it called linear
probe hashing and then we'll talk about
some variants to improve on this
potentially called Robinhood hashing and
cuckoo hashing but they're all roughly
based on on linear hashing and again
these are all static hashing schemes
meaning we have to be told at the
beginning when we when we allocate
memory here's the number keys that I
expect a store and so that in some cases
you actually can can guess what this is
so when we do query processing and we're
doing we're using the hash table to do
joins i roughly know i hope to know that
how many keys i'm gonna have to hash a
my hash table and then i can allocate
accordingly if our hash table gets too
full and we'll see what that means
essentially means we have an infinite
loop or all our slots are filled then
that means that we have to double we
have to increase the size and
essentially double the size of the hash
table and then basically take all the
keys in the first hash table and copy
them over to the second hash table which
is obviously super expensive to do so
ideally we can have a good approximation
of you know what the upper bound is for
our keep for a hash table size so that
we don't have to do this to do this
regrowth or rebuilding all right
so again linear probe hashing sometimes
called a
addressing this is sort of the most
basic hash table you can have and all it
is it's just a giant table of slots and
we reuse our hash function to jump to
some offset or add some slot in that
table so if you get a if you use Python
and you allocate a dictionary this is
essentially the same data structure
you're gonna get underneath the
dictionary it's gonna be a linear probe
hashing table so the way we're gonna
resolve collisions is that if we hash
into a slot and we find something that's
already there I'm trying to insert
something there we just keep scanning
down to the next position and keep going
until we find the first open slot and
then that's where we insert our the
entry we're trying to add so now when I
want to do a lookup I would then land at
the slot where I should have been and I
keep scanning down till I either find an
empty slot meaning the thing I'm looking
for is not there or I find the thing
that I was looking for right it's it's
it's pretty basic it's pretty
straightforward all right so again so
let's say that these are the keys we
want to add all right we have some
hashing function that's gonna take these
keys and map them to our slot to a slot
in our hash table all right so this
first one we hash a that it lands here
and again inside of this thing it's a
key value pair we have the original key
that that we inserted plus whatever the
value that we wanted to be so it's a
pointer to another tuple will turn
another page or you know some other
arbitrary value it doesn't matter the
reason why we have to store the key the
original keys because when we start
doing lookups and we have to scan down
you know start looking at multiple
entries we need to know whether the
thing we're actually looking for were in
a slot is the key that we actually want
because it's not always guaranteed to be
exactly where we hash into the table so
if we hash BB lands here now we hash c
c/e lands here but again a is occupied
the slot where it c wants to go so all
we do is just jump down to the next
position and then insert our entry into
that same thing for DD once we go over c
is so we put it here he wants to go
where a is it can't because a is there
can't go over C is can't go over D is so
it ends in here and the last one for F
down here right pretty straight board
and this is actually really fast to do
I'm not showing the division between
pages here but you just think of this is
like I have allocated a bunch of pages
and I know how to go from one position
to the next I know that if I'm in the
last slot in my page I know what the
next page is to jump to to continue the
search yes yes yeah so because this is a
circularbuffer
so if I see his question is say I want
to search G & G one Segovia's can't so
it goes here it can't go there it loops
back around and continues here all right
yes yes the question is what if I delete
a value boom next slide excellent okay
so let's say that we want to delete see
what do we do again we hash it we with
land where a is that's not what we won
cuz again now we this is why we have the
exact key in there so you can say a is
not equal to see this is not what I want
scan down ah C equals C that's the one I
want this is what I wanted to delete so
let's say I just do something really
simple and just remove it what's the
problem with this exactly I do a lookup
on D I look in here I see empty slot and
it's it's I think all right my search is
done it's not what I want even though
it's the next slot down so there's two
ways to handle deletes so the first is
that you just add a tombstone marker you
basically take wherever C used to be
just a little tombstone that says
there's not an entry there's not a
logical entry here but physically
consider this off this slot occupied so
that one I do a lookup and I land here I
say well there's no data here but it's
not really an empty slot let me jump
down to the next one and that's the
thing that I wanted of course what's the
problem with this now we are you know
we're wasting space you know we have to
go clean this up later on eventually so
this is going to contribute to our fill
factor the other option is do data
movement essentially recognize that I
have an empty slot here and just move
everybody up
one and then that way I and exactly
where I want to go now in this example
this is this works fine because II maps
exactly to where where it would be found
F maps exactly where it would be found
but again remember I said it's a
circularbuffer so technically B might
actually want to go here because it is
it is technically comes after F even
though physically it doesn't so in this
case here if I end up moving B around
this was gonna be bad this is gonna be
incorrect because B hashes in that
location so had I moved it here I would
then do a lookup and B and find nothing
because as I scan down I'm going down
this direction I would not know to loop
back around and look at the previous
entry so in practice mostly we'll just
do tombstones because it's this data
movement thing is actually complicated
there's another good example of why you
want to have the original key in here
because in order to figure out whether
it's okay for me to move this up by one
I need to go to a hash and decide
whether the thing the location where it
should be is less than or up above where
I want to move it too because if i if I
now go above it then I'll get false
negatives the hat will hash the thing
and not buy X you find it so for some
some operations or some some instances
of a hash table in our database system
we don't worry about deletes at all
again if I'm building a temporary data
structure to do a query a query I'm not
gonna delete so I'm just gonna scan my
input data populate my hash table and
then start using it if you're using as a
hash index though then we could have
deletes and we have to account for this
and tombstones is probably the most
easiest way to do this yes
yeah so his statement is he said
movement is probably the worst way to
handle this because I can't say it again
I can't move things I'm above it up why
not but that's okay so if you go back
here when we first start of it right
correct so right no not necessarily
right so so F wanted to go here but he's
there so it's okay to move that up by
one he wanted to go here but I can't so
I it's okay for moving up by one and
then D wanted to go here in a can't
scream move like one
so my toy example here it's it is
perfectly safe for me to move up
everybody up by one but the point I'm
trying to make is we can't actually move
B because b actually wants to hatch to
there basically it's not contiguous
logically it is so I should have have to
moved it here but exactly as you said I
had to hash it in check to see oh is it
safe for me to move it down here in this
case no because the hash actually wants
to go there so as I go down one by one I
have to say is it okay for me to move it
up yes yes yes question is in mice
against super similar example here it's
sort of you know I only have six keys I
can kind of estimate what the keys that
slots I need in practice how do you
actually estimate how many slots you
need in practice its 2n you have to n
the slots of the number of keys you
where ends and the mark easier that you
are not put into it all right and we'll
see in in cuckoo hashing it's slightly
different because they have two hash
tables but it practices to N and then
what happens is when you if this gets to
four this is now that filled when you
resize you double the number of slots
you goes up by two yeah
could you also like just track like the
number of ships all right so here's
Haman which you guys are amazing
segments he's saying couldn't I also
just record the position aware how many
steps I am away from my original
position and use that to determine
whether say for me to move it yes this
is called Robin Hood hashing but we'll
get to that in a second all right the
nice thing I want to talk about now
unique keys as well and then we'll get
to his point about Robin Hood hashing so
again in your albums class you probably
when you discuss hash tables you just
assumed all the keys were unique for
primary indexes this is fine but in
practice in real real real real data
sets we can't assume that the keys are
unique so now we need it'll handle them
in our hash table so there's two ways to
do this and I'll say that the two ways
I'm describing can be used for any of
the hashing schemes that we're talking
about today they're not specific to
linear hashing you can use them for
anything so the first approach is just
you maintain a separate linked list with
all the values so that you have say your
key in whatever your hash table is in
your slot and then set up pointing to
the the underlying tuple whatever the
thing that should be pointing to it
instead points to the separate linked
lists that have the values that of
course put the head off I will have the
same key so if I want to say give me all
the give me all the key value pairs for
the key XYZ I just jump along this that
follow this pointer and then I know that
everything inside there has that key the
other approach which is probably the
most common approach is just to store
redundant keys so all you do now is just
in your in your your slot array you're
just duplicating the keys over and over
again right so the key X Y Z ABC appears
multiple times and each one has a unique
value I'm just recording that multiple
times and then que filling of probing
everything still works that you know if
I'm looking for something I do my lookup
and I just keep scanning down until I
find either empty slot or the thing that
or yet I find em slot but I know my
search is done so if I'm saying find me
one key incident with Elif key value key
equals XYZ I just could jump here and
find exactly what I want but if I went
all in that I got to keep scanning down
until I hit an empty slot again in
practice everyone does the the second
one even though it's it's you know
slightly wasted storage because you're
repeating the key multiple times where
is it that top one you only store the
key once all right so let's talk about
the what he was sort of proposing to do
but we want to see this in a slightly
different way rather than deciding when
to shift around it's it's rather than
deciding how to move bulk movement they
had a bulk moving of keys through our
hash table let's look at how to use
these positions to move individual keys
so Robin Hood hashing was proposed in in
1985 it's one of those papers that came
out that no one really paid attention to
and then in the last decade or so it's
showed up on Hacker News a couple times
and now people are trying out in the
different systems so again Robin Hood is
this folklore tale from England about
this this rogue who would steal from
rich people and give it to the poor
people in immediate medieval England so
that's essentially what we're doing here
in our hash table we're gonna have
Porky's steals Lots from rich keys and
I'm defining poor versus rich meaning
the number of positions you are from a
way from where you should have been when
you first hash into the hash table right
so to do this the basic idea is that
we're trying to balance out throughout
the entire hash table to minimize the
likelihood that we have one key that's
really far away from where it should
have been so that we overall were sort
of balanced and everybody's equal so
let's say this so again we want to sort
these same six keys a goes here
but now as he as he was suggesting we're
also Cannell store the the number of
jumps we are from our original position
when he first hashed into this so our
table was empty in the beginning so when
we hashed a it landed this position here
it was exactly where it should have been
so we said it's it's it's number jumps
to be zero
same thing with BB hashes here it lands
at the top so it's its position is zero
so now we insert C and a occupies the
slot where it wants to go but in the
very beginning
the number jumps a is from its from his
optimal position is zero and at the
beginning C landed here so at this point
C's number number of slots where C is
from from where it wants to go is 0
since 0 equals 0 we're gonna leave a
alone and make C go down to the next
slot and take that and now we see we
updated its position counter to be one
step so it's one step away from where it
should have been when it first hatched
into the table so now we do this with D
D lands here he wants to go in this slot
but C occupies that but C's counter is 1
and 1 is greater than 0 so a higher
counter means you're more poor I mean
you're farther away from where you want
to be so C would be farther away from
where from its where it wants to go
where D would go if D took this position
so we don't let D take this slot and we
make it go down here so now I look at 1
or e we started up once ago or a is
again 0 equals 0 so we leave a alone 1
equals 1 so we leave C alone but now
ease counter is 2 because this it's you
know 0 1 2 jumps away from where it
wants to go so 2 is less than Suze
greater than then 1 so 2 is considered
more poor than D so it's it shoots D in
the head steals its wallet steals its
slot inserts itself here and then now
the insertion continues as deed goes
down to here and now we update its
counter to be 2 so again before we had
it we had a c d e but now on a Robin
Hood hashing ease now closer where it
wants to be and D is is as far the way
than when it should have been because
overall now and now we're more balanced
same thing where f f/a go here 2 is 2 is
greater than 0 so D stays where it wants
to go and F goes down here in fact yes
yeah statement is on a Robin Hood
hatching the the the algorithm says that
it's better to have two keys be one
position away from where they should
have been rather than having one key be
two positions and one key be zero
positions yes I'm not saying this is the
right thing to do
I'm saying this is this is one approach
to handle collisions a different way the
the I mean you're essentially trading
off resore rights so now when I want to
do a look-up on any of these guys
alright any of these keys it's there's
nothing one key that's gonna be all the
way you know wrap around all the way
right everyone's gonna be on average the
same distance but in order to do that
that's making rights more expensive or
inserts more expensive cuz now I have to
write more things so when I did this
stealing here let's say that I have to
update this page right there's a page
split right here so I update this slot
here on the first page to install e so
that's one right and then now I got to
come down here and do another right to
insert D into this page had I left him
alone like on a regular linear probe
hashing I would only don't want one
right to the page so again this seems
like a really nice iya idea the the
research at least the modern research
shows that especially for in-memory data
structures that you you pay a big
penalty for a branch misprediction
because you have more conditionals to do
these checks to see whether one should
take it from another one and you're
doing more rights and that's more cache
invalidation so in practice linear
probing crushes everything still it's
still the fastest way to do this I think
we're disk it's the same thing ok
another approach to deal with collisions
is instead of doing linear probing and
just keep scanning down and possibly
swapping things as an Arab Robin Hood
hashing where we just have multiple hash
tables and then we decide where we know
which hash table to insert our our key
you know is whatever which one has a
free slot for us so that we don't have
to do these potentially long scans so
that's what cuckoo hashing is so I've
always mistakenly said cuckoo hashing
was named after like a cuckoo clock
where the the the hand goes back and
forth and
actually do with a cuckoo bird the
cuckoo bird is is known to to move
itself from one nest to another so it
steals another nest from another bird
and that bird has to then move something
else so we'll see how that works in a
hash-table so that's that's what it
means
so lookups and deletions and under
cuckoo hashing is always gonna be oh one
meaning we're always gonna jump and when
we do a look up we're over to jump to -
no - there are hash tables and find
exactly whether the thing we want is
there or not we don't have to do any
additional scans but the inserts could
be more expensive because now we may
have again ping-pong or move keys all
around so this look an extremely simple
example with two two hash tables again
in practice most people use this just
use - there are some people that use
three beyond that it's sort of
impractical and it's unnecessary so - is
always sort of the right number so let's
say I want to insert a so for every hash
table I have in my cuckoo hashing setup
I have to have a separate hash seed for
my hash function so I'm gonna take this
key and hash it twice it's gonna be the
same hash function like murmur or xx
hash but I'm just gonna give it a
different seed so that the for a given
key it produces a different hash value
so I'm gonna hash a twice my to my to CD
hash functions and the first one's gonna
land this position and the second one's
gonna land of this position so at this
point here my hash tables are empty so I
can insert in either one so for our
purposes we'll just flip a coin we'll
slide let's insert it in the first hash
table here in practice you can do more
complicated things you can say like
alright well what's the fill factor for
my from my hash table maybe always
choose the one that's less full or if
you have metadata about the collision
rate for your hash tables you can make a
better decision as far as you know
everyone just flips a coin and that's
good enough right random is actually
very very good for a lot of things
alright so I'll say I wanted cert B same
thing I'm gonna hash it twice first one
goes to this slot where a is already
stored but the second one goes to an
empty slot so in this case here my
choice is obvious right I always want to
go to the one that's empty because I
don't have to move anybody I just insert
it there and I'm done so that's our
insert C same thing I had it twice well
now the first hash function
that's to this slot where a is and
second hash function maps to where B s
so now I need to make decision which one
I want to kill again let's just flip a
coin that's gonna be good enough and to
make the demo work I'll pick this one
right so we'll go now steal that slot
from B and insert C so now I think B out
now I gotta go put it back in the other
hash table so I'm gonna hash it with the
first hash function and that's gonna
tell me where I go to insert it but we
as we saw when we try to insert it
before it one of the go where air a was
and so we have to now steal it slot put
B there and now put a in the other one
so we hate we hashed that it comes over
here and now we've landed to an empty
slot and so now our insert is to see is
done because everybody has landed in a
free slot yes his question is which is
absolutely the answer is yes can this
have cyclic behavior can you be stuck in
an infinite loop absolutely yes so in
that case you have to recognize where
what your starting point was so if you
come back around see wait a min I've
seen this spot before and there's
something there is I can't put anything
in there I'm stuck in an infinite loop
so that's when you resize okay so again
the in practice everyone always does
just two hash tables and you want to
allocate this in such a way that you
know the likelihood that you have a
cycle is minimized okay so now all of
the hash tables that we talked about so
far are again where static hash tables
meaning I need to know approximately the
size of the number keys I want to store
ahead of time so I know how to allocate
it you know allocate it luck to be large
enough today that I minimize collisions
and I don't have infinite loops or get
completely full alright so again as he's
pointed out before if you now have to
resize it need to grow larger which is
more common but also shrinking if you
want to reduce the size you essentially
have to rebuild the hash table entirely
right we'll talk about consistent
hashing there's there's hashing schemes
we are hashing functions or methods we
can talk about later in the semester
when we talk about distributed databases
that don't have to resize the whole
thing but for for a hash tables inside
our database system we are got to rehash
everything I reset rebuild our hash
table because now we change the number
of elements when we mod and the hash
hash value and that means things aren't
that you know we're in one bucket or one
location before one slot now could be in
another slot and I you know everything's
gonna go out of whack so in practice you
have to rebuild from scratch so this is
what dynamic hash tables are trying to
solve that they're gonna be able to
resize themselves on demand without
having to rebuild the entire thing most
basic one is a chain hash table and this
is what Hollywood people most think of
when they think of a hash table but when
I talk about to more complicated scenes
from the 1980s that are still used today
extendable hashing and linear hashing
all right so chain hashing or chain hash
table or bucket and hash table is it an
emic a hash table we're gonna maintain
link list of buckets for values that map
to the same or keys that map to the same
dies that are part of the same key so
when you allocate a hash map and Java
and the JVM you get one of these this is
the the default data structure that they
use so the way they're gonna deal with
collisions is that they're gonna just
keep appending to the end of this bucket
list so each bucket chain can grow
forever because you just keep adding
more and more buckets the linked list
gets even larger and of course this can
obviously degenerate to a essentially a
scrunch else can give all my keys map to
the same bucket a bucket chain then my
bucket grows forever and then I'm just
doing a linear search and I'm no better
than just you know reading from a table
so insertions and deletions are pretty
straightforward because you're just
modifying the buckets you're not
actually modifying the slot all right so
again it just looks like this we have
our slot array these map to buckets and
then any single time I want to do an
insert saying to this this bucket chain
here if my last bucket is full I just
allocate a new one and I keep appending
things until here until I to know till I
run out of space and allocate the next
one so you can think of these buckets
are just pages right in the table heap
or on the heap file and I was a liqu
eight new pages and chain them together
using page IDs to figure out how to you
know Trevor
yeah this is pretty straightforward this
is pretty easy to implement this is
actually pretty easy also to make Fred
Dave because all I do is just take a
latch on either the slot which is the
the easiest thing to do or just the
individual page anytime I'm modifying it
so let's look at more complicated
schemes so with extendable hashing we're
gonna take the chain hashing approach
with the buckets but instead of letting
the link list just grow forever we're
going to want to split them
incrementally and the key difference
here between rebuilding splitting and
rebuilding is that we're only gonna
split the the chain that overflowed
rather than the entire entire data
structure and it's our hash table so in
order to make this work we're not
allowed multiple slot locations in our
slot array to point to the same bucket
chain and that it'll make more sense
when I show that in the next slot and
the advantages again is that the women
have to move data around we're only
moving the the bucket that overflowed
and not all the other buckets all right
so it's gonna look like a chain hash
table instead I'm gonna add some
additional information so the first I'm
gonna have is this global counter that
corresponds to the number of bits we
have to consider when we want to figure
out what bucket to look at what slot to
look at in our hash function so in this
example here we'll start with a global
counter two and then three for each
bucket chain or each bucket we're gonna
have a local counter that corresponds to
the number of bits that we use to get to
that location so in this case here this
first bucket has a local local counter
of one so that means that we only need
to look at one bit to address into it
and this is why if you look at 0 0 and 0
1 both of these guys map to the same
bucket because the first bit 0 is the
same because this bucket has a number
float we haven't had a split it yep
whereas the the other two buckets have 1
0 1 1 and that because they're local
counters to that says we have to look at
two bits so the global counter you need
to figure out what how many bits you
need to look at
logo counter it's just for your own
sanity internally to understand what the
you know how did you get to the location
where you're at right but you don't
actually need this to figure out you
know how did you look up in the
slaughter right because obviously you
can't you can't know what this is until
you do the look up through the slaughter
right all right so let's say I want to
find egg so then again I'm gonna hash it
I'm gonna produce some a bit sequence
for my from a hash value and then I look
at my global counter and it says how
many bits do I want to examine in my
hash function from a hash value decide
where do I want to jump to so my global
counter is two so I only need to look at
the first two bits 0 1 I do my look up
in my slaughter a look at 0 1 I follow
the pointer and then I land to the
bucket that I want and now I just do a
central scan to find the entry that I'm
looking for
so now let's say I want to start B so
again global counter is 2 I only need to
look in the first 2 bits I land here
follow slaughter a this guy had a freed
for you location so it's safe for me to
go ahead and sort that is never flow but
now I want to start see first you bits
are 1 0 I follow this I land here but
now I see that I don't have any more
free entries in my in my bucket I'm
gonna overflow so now I have to split
this so then the splitting process is I
look at my global counter and it's now
set to 2 so I'm going to increase that
to 3 so that means I don't need to
examine three bits so now I'm gonna
double the size of my slot array to now
count for 3 bits again this operation is
cheap because this is just an array of
pointers so I take a latch on that
protect it resize it and then put it
back in so it's not like I need to move
around any of the data here which is the
more expensive part so now like a Lobel
counter is 3 and I'm gonna split this by
then now examining the 3 bits instead of
2 and to figure out which hash table or
Succot they belong to so this guy just
slides down I restructure this thing I
just split the data that that was stored
between that single page I remap
everybody based on the the local counter
so this guy up here and we still only
care about one bit so there's
two slots that map to it up there and
two slots down here that also map to
where again where the first bit is zero
and then now it's now I want to go back
and try to insert C so now I look at
three bits that tells me I want to look
at this position here I follow the
pointer and then I'm be able to insert
into it so again this this movement here
look like it was kind of expensive like
sliding around but all I'm doing is just
splitting that one page I had before to
make another page so it's to pay page
rights plus the pages you have to update
for the for the slot array in the back
yes her question is is it not considered
to be expensive to remap the slot array
to all the new pages no because all I'm
really doing like these are still at the
same page ID in the files on disk so now
I'm just updating this again it's a
single array updating the values now
point to you know where the data is
actually stored so this operation is
cheap moving pages is expensive yes yes
so her question is what if say the first
one fills up won't say what would happen
well now I would split it and again the
lote the local counter is one so we
would increment that to two now yeah so
now it's split on two so now it would be
0 0 0 1 0 0 0 1 so anybody with zeros
over here these two entries would point
to the same thing and 0 ones are one
point of the same thing ok humors like
ok we'll get to that deletes yes pleats
are basic reverses the back yes
his question is are you storing the
entire page ID page in the in the solana
right here or is it just a page ID it's
just a page ID in the bucket this is
this each bucket would be a page yes
this question is what is it relation to
be in a hash tape on a buffer pool so at
a high level I'm ignoring that in
practice depending on whether you want
it to be durable to disk you would
allocate a page just as you would for
for a a table right a slot a page in
your buffer pool and you can store a
bucket page in that same thing the
buffer pool doesn't know doesn't care
you just say give me a page here's the
page ID and hand you back something some
memory address and you write some data
in there it doesn't know whether it's
part of a table or a part of a hash
table like this like a data table or a
hash table so again all the same
addiction algorithms you would use now
you want to see like how we're jumping
around this and accessing our hash table
it certainly look a lot different than
how we jump through and do the
sequential scans in a data table so
maybe you want different caching
policies for them or addiction policies
yes the statement is and I'm using three
bits at this point here to map hash
values to
slots and then it tells me what offset
to jump into right and then within that
slot in this array I would have a page
ID that I can then follow to get to the
bucket how's the mapping from page IDs
two buckets work yeah
it is like there's I'm using the term
bucket again instead of a page because
it this could be in memory it could be
back by disk it doesn't matter but you
can think of if it was backed by disk
then this these are the page IDs and the
bucket is a page and they're synonymous
so the only thing I need to store here
is page IDs absolutely statement is
again going back up here at this year my
global bit counter is two but I know
that I haven't split this first page
here it's local counters one so even
though if I wanted to look up I can look
at two bits but in practice I only care
about the first bit for this page here
so that's why these guys have the same
eight page ID bucket id whatever you
want they make a mat to the same
location because they have not split yet
it's quite the statement is which is
correct is after we do a reach a page we
just do a linear scan to find the thing
we want absolutely yes saving this isn't
that expensive again if I have a billion
tuples then doing that lookup to scan a
kilobyte page is nothing and they say
all right I want to be a bit more crafty
you've got smarter well maybe I store a
filter or some little pre computed
information at the top it says the key
look you know here's the list of keys
that I have it doesn't tell you where
they are it says that you have them so
you do that quick lookup to see whether
it's there but like that linear scan is
going to be super cheap compared to
reading it from disk or having new 20 an
entire data set okay so the other
dynamic hashing table is called linear
hashing so one problem with the with the
extent while hashing well it's not a
huge problem is that we're have to
double the size of the slaughtering
again computationally it's not that
expensive but while I'm doing that
resizing I have to take a latch on it
prevent anybody from reading and writing
it until I reallocate
everything so that will become a
bottleneck of everybody's trying to go
into that too my hash to about the exact
same time so with linear hashing the
ideas that we're gonna localize the
resizing to just be whatever the the the
bucket are that overflowed so we don't
have to take a global latch that locks
out everybody from accessing our hash
table so the way this is gonna work is
that we're gonna maintain multiple
hashes hash functions the same way we
did in cuckoo hashing again it's the
same hash function algorithm just
different seeds that are gonna tell us
where to jump to the right bucket for a
given key and we're gonna maintain this
new thing called a split pointer that's
gonna keep track of what's the next page
we want to overflow or do what we want
to split and then we incrementally
increase the size of our slot array so
how we decide when do it my flow can
depend on what we want to do it could
just be when we run out of entries in
our in our and our in a bucket and then
we that trigger the resize it could be
if the size of our bucket is larger than
the average size of all the buckets
again it's left up to the implementation
they all have different trade-offs
alright so it looks like this okay we
have a slot array that's gonna help
point to buckets just like I chain
hashing so again we're gonna add is now
this this new split pointer that's gonna
keep track of what's the next bucket we
want to split whenever we have an
overflow anywhere in our hash table so
we're gonna split the the bucket point
to by position zero whenever any other
bucket not just when bucket zero gets
overflowed so if any of these other guys
overflow we won't we will split 0 even
even if it's not the one that overflowed
so at this point here our split pointer
is at the bit is at the beginning of our
slot array so we only have one hash
function all right I'm a member just
gonna modify the the number of entries
that we have so let's say I do I look
upon on six I just hash it mod by four I
jump to location do a linear scan so I
find the key that I want right that just
works just just like before under chain
hashing but now let's say I want to
insert seven
all right I hash it 17 mod for I'll and
to this position here but now I don't
have any more free slots or free entries
in my in my bucket so I'm gonna have to
create an overflow bucket right and
since you just create again the chain
link list and then that's where I insert
17 but because I now overflowed that's
gonna trigger a split
wherever the split pointer is pointing
at so even though 0 still is I can take
entries in it i over float once
somewhere that can cause me to overflow
so the way this is going to work is that
we're gonna add a 1 new entry to our
slot array now position 4 and then we're
gonna have a new hash function that now
mods by 2 n right the idea is that as we
keep splitting down and down we'll keep
adding new entries until we're 2 N or
toward twice as big as where we were
before we add it here before we started
doing splitting so the way this is gonna
work is that we need to keep the split
poner is going to keep track for us
whether we want to use the first hash
function or the second hash function
they tell us how far along we split in
our slaughtering all right so in this
case here we we add the new entry for
recreate a new bucket and then this is
where we insert 20 into and we move this
foot pointer down by one so the split
pointer is essentially this demarcation
line here so the basically says that
whenever I want to do a lookup I first
hash it the first hash function so I say
I wanna do a lookup on 20 I put the
first hash function and that's gonna
take me from 0 to 3 and then if the
thing I'm pointing to is above where
that demarcation line is for the split
pointer then I know that the the bucket
that I'm looking at has already been
split so therefore now I need to look at
the second hash function and decide
where I really want to go for the data
so now when I do a look about 20 I hash
should use the second hash function I
mod that number by 8 because that's to
end where I started wet and then that
tells me that I want to jump down here
same thing I do a final nine nine would
land here that's below or above the
split pointer basically you know
perceive it but it's you know it has
been split yet so therefore I only need
to look at the first hash function to
find the thing that I'm looking for so
is this sort of clear yes so question is
back up here when I insert a seventeen
isn't this is what overflowed why did I
split the first one and not this one
because that's the way leaner hashing
works the algorithm works that you own
if you split whatever the split pointer
works at looks at no matter whether this
thing whether it was one that overflowed
or not because eventually like if this
thing keeps on overflowing that'll keep
moving the split pointer down by one
eventually I will get to this I will get
to every one split split it and then
loop back around start over again so the
statement is if I end up splitting this
one here right say the slope one is down
now I split it I will then you know use
the second hash function to decide how
to redistribute them correct you
reassure all the all the values or all
the key instances that map to that's
that bucket and then delete the overflow
yes now may be the case that like say
this guy was you know this overflow
thing was at the bottom here so I kept
inserting to it I can't we're floating
and I kept triggering splits and then by
the time I get down to split it again it
may also overflow as well that's just
how the algorithm works and you loop
back around do it again so worst case
scenario the everybody's inserting to
the same bucket and it takes a long time
for it to split in practice though with
a good hash function in the local ocean
rate this shouldn't happen okay so the
rights against splitting the bucket just
basically means that although we're not
splitting the one that overflowed
eventually we will get to it eventually
everyone get split and then everything
will balance
so in this example I only showed inserts
the pointer can also move backwards if
you start doing deletes and same weekend
you can reverse the extendable hash
engine if you wanna start deleting
things to start coalescing coalescing
buckets but in practice though this is
quite tricky so let's go back to where
we were before right
split pointer was pointing here and
we've almost put it we only split the
the the first entry position 0 in a slot
array so now if I want to delete 20 so I
hash the first one that takes me to 0
but this position here is is you know
above our demarcation line for the split
pointer so I need a hash it again and I
land here now I could find the entry
that I want so now I'm going to delete
this guy and now the page is entry empty
so I could just leave it alone and does
assume that's later on I'll go ahead and
fill it up again but if I wanted to
start doing compacting I want to start
reclaiming memory then I just do all the
same steps that I did before and reverse
it all right so I blow away the bucket
blow away this pointer moved the slip
pointer back up by 1 and now this thing
goes away my hash function goes away and
I've reclaimed the memory right just
getting just doing all the steps in
reverse order yes his question is do I
eventually remove hash functions after
you remove all the tables yes I think
after you get down to the bottom I think
at most you have two hash functions
statement is instead of having 20 if I
also delete 11 what the same thing
happen missing what you're saying sorry
yeah you can't read you should because
it because then the hash function is it
has to be terminus ik same key should
always produce the same hash value so we
know exactly where to find it in the
back
yeah so her say that is if I go back
here if I was here and I did leave his
six six I would have to leave there
correct there's only one hash function
so if I try to remove this I can't
resize this one down here so I just
leave that empty yes so anything I surf
flash it already but what's the what's
that obvious prom why this would be
problematic if I if I do actually
you know deleted the page and removed it
and then put the slim pointer back up by
one exactly where the very next thing I
do is insert 21 now I overflow now I
gotta split what everything's pointing
at and I just do all the same crap over
again right so again the this is what I
was saying that leggy when you decide to
do an overflow maybe don't do exactly at
the moment you know you insert something
into an overload chain so maybe wait
till this thing overflows again and then
then you split or two pages become
buckets kind of empty man you shut
reversing so people that have spent a
lot of time making the inserts go fast
deletes are harder to do because in
practice and maybe defeat some cases
might be better to rebuild the entire
index but you can do incremental deletes
with these data structures okay all
right so the we spent today talking
about hash tables again these are fast
data structures that that on average
will do oh one book ups for for you know
fine keys and we're gonna use this all
throughout the internals of the database
system for as we execute queries for
page tables and immediate data
structures in practice though and for at
the application level a hash table is
usually not what you're gonna want to
use for a table index database desin
will let you do this some systems will
say when I call create index I want to
use a hash table but when I call create
index in most systems without any
specification what data structure to use
I'm not gonna get a hash table I'm still
going to be getting an order preserving
index and this is because the hash table
can only do exact key equality
predicates quality look
meaning if I want to see whether key
exists I have to have the entire key to
do a lookup but I can't do a partial key
look up and I can't say find me all the
key is less than my given key because
again the hash function can't do that
for you so in practice this is not what
you want to use and we'll do demos next
time with my sequin Postgres and we'll
show that performance implications of
this
so instead but you mostly get when you
call create index is the beloved B+ tree
it was called the ubiquitous B+ tree of
ubiquitous data structure in 1979 and
4050 years later it's still the best
data structure out there my opinion and
pretty much every single database system
it's going to have some kind of B+ tree
implementation except for those systems
that are like you know memcache that are
just a hash table entirely every single
major data system is gonna be used
something that looks like a P plus tree
or straight-up B plus tree now they're
gonna differ on how they actually store
things and do searches in some ways but
at a high level we'll talk about on
Wednesday will be the sort of the
canonical B+ tree again it's everywhere
okay so any questions
it's wixi nights in my system racking up
let's go get the next one get over there
with me son
ricochet jelly hit the deli for the boat
one naturally bless ya what rappers like
the laser beam the pawns in the bush say
not even like a chain wrap the bottle of
us if we go don't bail out drinking that
boney - you talking can't cross the line
and if the sake don't know you
can't a pain pain