[Music]
[Applause]
alright let's get started so real
quickly about project 2 if you haven't
signed up yet for a group please go do
that the other thing we're gonna change
is that we felt that the number of
submissions of people submitting their
project one at the very end was higher
than I wanted and it sort of partly my
fault for not warning you guys ahead of
time hey don't wait till last minute and
so to avoid this same issue for project
two what we're gonna have is we'll have
a check point half way where you just
have to do inserts and reads so if they
do splits and then so that'll be like 25
or 30 percent of the grade and then
we'll have the regular submission
deadline that'll still be the same and I
thought that the support the fool the
full test suite okay
again it's just a 14 function for you
guys start looking at this sooner rather
than later through not like trying to
write a thread safe in memory index one
day before it's due that's gonna be a
bad idea okay all right so today we're
going to talk about scheduling so last
class was about how to take a query
request from the client put into our
system run it somehow we didn't say how
all getting there and then we would take
a response from the result from the
query and shove it back over the wire to
the client so now today's class we start
the next chapter of how we're actually
going to execute those queries and so
we're gonna focus on scheduling so we're
still not actually executing the the the
scans yet and reading our indexes but
we're getting we're getting closer
closer to that so we need on just need
to define some terms we're gonna use
going forward
describe what query execution looks like
so a query plan is going to be comprised
of operators and you can think of these
as sort of like a relational algebra
operators and so we'll talk about how we
do query planning and if you more
lectures the basic ideas we get the
sequel query like this and we have
represented as a as a directed tree
structure of operators and
the lowest level we have these access
methods were they're going to scan
tuples or scan to index and feed them up
into the next operator and then the
results percolate to the top so we're
gonna define now a an invocation of an
operator in our query plan a specific
invocation of it will be defined as an
operator instance so for a given
operator in our query plan like scan
table a we can have multiple instances
of this operator that allow us to
execute this scan in in parallel and now
the idea is the way we're going to group
up group group together the the
operators instances that we're going to
execute in our system alright were to
call these groups as tasks right and the
idea is that sort of like in the
pipeline model we wanted to have string
it together as many tests as we can
within a single task or pipeline so
though we don't have a context switch
going from you know from one task to the
other so for a scan on a I can do the
filter and then depending on join
algorithm I'm doing like if I'm doing a
hash join then I can have the pipeline
also build the hash table for me so I'm
just passing her up intermediate results
from one operator instance to the next
so again at a high level our job today
is to figure out how we're going to
schedule these tasks right and where
they're going to execute and what
they're actually going to do so for
every single query plan that shows up we
got a side now where when and how to
execute it and so this case one of these
decisions will have any task so we
actually use for our query plan like if
we say we have this number of cores when
we have we could assign one task for our
query plan for each core remain when it
over subscribe have more tests and we
have cores and that way we can have more
flexible scheduling then this question
of how many cores we actually want to
use right so we can have a X number of
tasks and Y number of threads and or
cores and we can decide how many cores
we want to use then we had to spec
decide on what course should tasks
actually execute on and then when that
task completes and it produces some
output we need to decide where that
output is going to go all right even Bay
about this so far are we saying are we
actually this query we get back result
but now as we are starting executing the
tasks that are comprised in that query
we had to make decision of where we
should tickets output and and as we see
as we talk about different sort of
memory architectures we need to be aware
of where that memory is actually located
what we're reading writing to so that we
get the best performance right so the
reason why we're gonna do all of this is
that the database system is knows
exactly what the query is knows exactly
what the tasks are it knows what what
threats has available to it and knows
where the memory or the data is actually
located so we're in the position to make
the best decision about how to execute
this query planning efficiently the OS
doesn't know this question this question
is how do we find what a pipeline is
will come to that next class but the
basic way to think about this is how far
can I take a single tuple or batch of
tuples and write it up the query plan
before I have to before I get to a point
where I can't go farther so in this case
here scan a filter and do say you're
doing a hash join I can build the hash
table on this side of the join but I
can't actually produce any result to do
the projection because I need to do the
probe side so this is called a pipeline
breaker yes so state question is is it
is this truly a pipeline breaker because
if I had if the pipeline breaker was
here and I might II realized the output
from both of these guys then shove it to
my hash table right like the basic
things I can't go higher and to treat
until I have all the data from one side
right so there's a pipeline here for
this side but the pipeline for B can go
all the way up what doesn't make more
sense next class but the main idea what
I care about is like you understand it's
like oh well a task is what we're gonna
schedule on the task and B cries of
multiple operators and we're roughly
gonna base it on pipelines and the the
the main takeaway again from all this is
that we're not gonna rely on the OS to
do any of this for us we're Network the
Davis it's always going to know better
so it
can make the best decision so to begin I
want to first talk about different
process models we can have in our
databases in architecture it basically
tells us you know what is it it's gonna
find what a worker actually is is it a
thread is it a process then we'll talk
about the problem of data placement in
for in memory databases we need to be
aware of the layout of memory or the
physical location of addresses in memory
so that we can have our threads try to
or workers try to act to operate on
local data and then we'll talk about the
different techniques for doing AI Namek
scheduling in a database system okay so
the the paper had you guys read on hyper
you know that's an example of doing
their dynamic scheduling and we'll
contrast this with something like Hana
which is gonna be doing you know having
different types of worker pools a
different kind of stealing versus no
stealing policies right so that's sort
of what our focus is on today but for
this part here but to make this decision
about how we're gonna design our
databases and your scheduling here we
need be aware of what we're how we built
the system up here okay all right so
let's first talk about how we're going
to assign workers to computation on
units in our database system so the the
the process model is gonna find whether
the system is how the sip is going to
support concurrent requests from a
multi-user application meaning our
application could send multiple queries
at the same time or multiple transaction
invocations at the same time and we
needed a way to decide how we're going
to interleave them at the sort of
low-level hardware level all right so
we're not talking about how do we decide
a logical level like what what
transactions lottery what pieces of data
this is like how do we take a task and
actually assign it to some worker and
what is that worker so I'm using the
term worker
I'm cajon gonna slip up and say thread
but and and for the systems we're
talking about it is going to be a thread
but the way to think about this is like
it doesn't the data says doesn't know
technically doesn't need to know whether
it's a and it doesn't need to know take
that it's it's a sort of high-level term
to describe again a a component in the
system that can execute tasks and this
could be either a process or
read the reason why I'm saying I take
back what I said would the adenosine
doesn't need to know but certainly if
it's a process I need to know how to
communicate with with other processes
because they're not going to technically
be in my same address space so it's just
basically a way for us to execute tasks
and then return results to the
application so there's a great book
written over a decade ago from Mike
Stonebraker Joe Hellerstein at Berkeley
and the guy that runs most AWS James
Hamilton I called architecture of a
database system so this is in the
context of a of a dis coordinate system
but this book really lays out at a nice
sort of clean abstraction you know how
you actually design the system at that's
sort of this low level education level
here all right so the three approaches
we're talking about a process per
database worker process pool and a
thread per Davis worker and again we've
covered this in the introduction class
but I just want to go over this again
and the spoiler would be that for all
the systems we're gonna talk about today
and going forward breath of the semester
it's gonna be the last one here because
this one is the most common one in in
modern systems so process per worker is
where every single worker in our system
is going to be a separate OS process so
that means that when a request shows up
say goes through some kind of dispatcher
it can then handoff the connection to
another worker that that will then read
the socket and allow and take any
requests that it gets from the from the
from the client and executed on the
database system and so the all the
scheduling that's being done here is is
managed by the operating system because
we're just calling fork to start off a
new process and we have no direct
control to say whether you know it
should when it when it shouldn't it
should run so the tricky thing is
sometimes often is that what this is
like I may not know my dispatcher
exactly you know how much work these
workers are doing and I have to rely on
the OS that do sort of throttling and
and and flow control because these guys
can just do whatever they want or need
to write extra extra code and they have
them communicate some way back to the
dispatcher to have a centralized view
about what's happening but in systems
like Postgres as far as I know they
don't do this all those systems that do
the approach is db2 and Oracle db2 is a
weird one because
there is a you know there's when people
say oh I'm running db2 there's actually
four versions of db2 that are completely
separate code bases like one for z/os
ones for some other mainframe system and
then there's like the Linux UNIX windows
one and there's a fourth one I forget
right and they're all completely
separate so we'll see in the next two
slides db2 is gonna support all these
approaches because they have to run in
all these different environments but it
may not be the exact same codebase every
single time okay one advantage you get
from this is that if the worker if
there's mistake in the software and the
worker crashes you don't take down the
whole system because workers dies and
then you can fork a new one and bring it
back up so this makes the system
slightly more resilient than you would
have in a and a threading based model
because if one thread has a seg fault
then the whole process dies the next
post is just an extension of the worker
a single process per worker
we have a process pool and rather than
forking off the dispatcher of forking
off a new process for every single
request that shows up it knows it has a
bunch of workers that are available to
it that can hand off the request and
have that you know run the query for us
and in some cases to say if I want to
support intro query parallelism I can
take a single query and run across
multiple processes of metalworkers this
one worker could identify that there's
other workers available to it in the
same pool that are idle and start
handing off work to that right the bad
bad thing about this approach is that
it's gonna ruin our locality unless we
have extra logic in the dispatcher to be
mindful of what worker executed our
query the last time right because say
these guys are all running on separate
sockets and if for this one request the
first query shows up I run on this
worker the next query shows up for the
same connection but it runs a noun or
another worker running on another socket
all the cache locality I had for
bringing in data into memory or that the
local cache for this worker is now gone
because now I'm not running on a
complete different socket so this often
times me bad for in memory systems is
because the overhead of keeping track of
what work I ran on last
and either pause until that workers
freed up if it's in running another
query before connects you my next query
or you know basically holding it until
the next query shows up which is just
the same thing as the previous slide all
that sort of orchestration can slow
things down and Postgres added this in
2015 all right they can have intro query
parallelism and as I said db2 tries to
support everything what's the most
common one is the thread per worker
right a multi-threaded application
question assume you're running on a
thing for this assume for this semester
it's all single machine sockets few more
slides would make more sense if they're
on the same socket you have local cache
and l1 l2 is not shared but l3 shared so
if you run on the same socket the
penalty of a cache miss depend of the
cache misses it was the same for like
the likelihood that the data I need that
like if I have a query they execute some
recent data the next pretty shows up
wants to read that same data right
you see used all the time I read after
write or read modify write then if I'm
running on the same socket then the data
is read could be hanging on l3 cache and
that'll go fast if I'm known another
socket which doesn't have to share that
l3 cache I pay another cache miss so the
previous one is like for this connection
right this worker is now dedicated to
the connection to this client so any
query that shows up is always going to
go to this worker right because it
basically takes over listening like
basically what happens is the bluee
Postgres works if this is called the
postmaster the the connection shows up
the postmaster says great I can hand you
off to a worker go now right to this
socket or this port number here and so
this comes back now and this thing's
listening on this port and now has
direct access to write 10 queries here
yes you're bypassing the dispatcher this
one is like I'm always going to this new
dispatcher I think of this as a
sectionalized scheduler and it's now
making this kitchen how to hand handle
things off in different processes
threat poor workers is is it's a single
process and we have inside that process
we have multiple threads you may or may
not have a dispatcher a thread you still
can do the same approach where you have
one thread listens on a socket that all
incremental quests have to go to and
then you hand it off to an another
socket on another thread so it can
process things or you can just have a
dedicated thread per your connection or
you just have a sort of a
general-purpose networking layer that
his hands off work to anybody that has
has idle cycles as I said every single
database systems written in the last 10
years is follows this approach so you
may be thinking well this is clearly
better you know you know pay a penny for
context switches everything's in the
same address base so any thread can read
any any you know memory location of
another thread yes you have to do the
the current suite of stuff to make sure
you don't have any issues or or the
latching to make sure that you don't
clobber each other when you access
critical sections so but this is clearly
gonna have the lower overhead than the
process process approach and we take a
guess why nobody built databases this
way in the 1980s 1990s correctly says
POSIX threads or P threads were not
standardized so all the different
operating systems you know son or
Solaris H parks for Linux even came
around but the limits came out in the
early 90s there wasn't a POSIX standard
to say here's a threading API everyone
had their own API and they had semantics
of how they you know could spawn threads
and and you know do join from them was
slightly different wasn't dramatically
different but like the API was certainly
different so if I want to support a
bunch of operating systems for my
database ism then I would have to have a
sort of wrapper layer to make sure that
that that I had it sort of the lowest
common denominator of what the thread
API was so it made it more portable now
a P threads this is this is not an issue
so one thing also say to well one of
things we did when we serve first
started building peloton was we took the
Postgres source code forked it like
everyone else does we then converted it
to be multi-threaded if you go google
Postgres multi-threaded you'll see a
mailing list post from i'm former PhD
student saying hey look we did
afraid why we did it was a bad whatever
ah but it turns out the way we actually
got it to convert convert it was wasn't
like we took the in the Postgres source
code it's a single code base but they
have all these pound of fines that says
if you know if Linux do this if when 32
do that if you go take the windows code
you can actually convert that to
pthreads much more easily then you could
convert the the Linux code anyway and we
also converted this tipo plus 11 which
again for for historical reasons I don't
remember but in our new system we threw
all that away we don't have any we don't
inherit any Postgres code anymore so
again the multi-threaded approach is
better you have lower overhead context
switch and then you don't the manage
shared memory in the multi process case
you're either sending I pcs to each
other or you have shared memory to so
that everyone can read and write into
the same location the important thing
else to point out too is just because we
may be using a multi-threaded process
model doesn't necessarily mean we're
gonna get intro query parallelism in our
database system so Maltin my sequel is a
multi-threaded database system but it's
one thread per query request right they
can't divide it up the tasks across
multiple workers and in their
environment doing OTP that's that's
that's fine and as I said I'm not aware
of anybody any other system in the last
built in the last ten years and the last
their forked from from post graphs which
is a process pool model approach and
let's they're based on post grass every
new system is gonna be using both multi
threads okay and that's we're gonna
that's what we use in our system alright
so now let's get to his question was
about this this issue of of whether this
core running same corn same socket or a
different socket so regardless of how
we're gonna do our worker allocation or
task assignment policy in our system we
want to make sure that all the workers
are going to operate on local data so in
a distributed system this is like a
no-brainer if I have two machines and my
data is you know my machines on the west
coast one machine was the East Coast my
query shows up and wants to touch data
on the west coast I send the query to
the west coast and process it there that
way its operating on local data well a
multi socket multi-core data or
but socket multi-core system even though
it's running on on in a one box still is
sort of like a distributor database
system so the same rules the same same
concepts apply here so we want to make
sure that we always have our tasks
operate on local data for where the
thread the worker is actually running so
this means now that our scheduler needs
me aware of what the memory layout is
for our underlying hardware and at a
high level there's two approaches this
is a uniform and and then the
non-uniform memory access so this is
also the acronym is Numa so you're here
meet a multiple times numeral region
Numa this noon with that that's that's
this one this is the most common one we
have in a most eSATA system today back
in the day we had what was called
uniform memory access this is sometimes
called symmetric multiprocessors SMP and
it's basically the same thing and the
idea is that the the tasks of the
workers are running down here in the
cores they do have some local CPU caches
l1 l2 l3 but all memory is managed
through this system bus so for any task
running on any socket the cost of
accessing a chunk of memory is the same
no matter where I'm running on right so
if I'm down here and I want to access
memory that's in in this this damn here
the cost of retrieving that is the same
if I was running here or the other ones
because there's overhead of going over
there this system bus so we still need
to do cache invalidation in this world
right the the the the hardware is aware
of I read this region of memory and now
it's in my CPU cache somebody else reads
the same thing and rights to it the
system boss has to take can handle of
invalidating our cache every you know
our cache entry up here all that sort of
handle for you so they said this is how
they built up until maybe like 2005 ish
2006 this is how Intel and AMD we're
designing their multi socket CPU systems
but now we have have the Numa stuff and
in this world there's not really any
from a database system perspective
there's no intelligence intelligence we
need to embed in our scheduler because I
said it does we don't know we don't care
this looks like one John address base
and the access cost is the same
what modern systems look like is in the
new model is that you still you now have
memory that's local to each socket so
you again you always have your your
local CPU cache and then you're gonna
have dims that are there gonna be
physically closer to your socket and
have a direct path to go read and write
to it so on on Intel chips the CPU cache
for every core the l1 l2 will be
specific to that core but then they're
also share share l3 and then obviously
they share the dim here and then now if
I need to have my my tasks running here
if it needs to access memory that's not
in my local dim and I got to go over to
this other CPU here I'm going to go over
this interconnect to send my message in
the hardware to say hey go read this
thing for me then the CPU knows how to
go out to the dim and then bring it back
down into me
so the the performance difference here
for just pure like read/write speed is
about 50 percent slower so if I have to
read data around here roughly it's could
be 50 percent slower than if I was
reading data locally yes like for the
here to here no look at the bus is
basically like this bus is basically
saying like alright I want access memory
address and you basically translate that
into some dim slot right yeah look
locally is yeah so if I have to read
here as 50% slower than reading local
here like think of this as like as the
fast path yeah so again like that means
now in our database system when we start
loading in our data we want to be aware
we're actually gonna put it then when
queries show up and they want to start
executing we need to be aware of what
data they want to touch right in our
task and make sure our tasks are on here
then OS doesn't know anything right the
OS sees a bunch of threads that want to
do some kind of work but it doesn't know
you know doesn't know your Bitcoin
mining thread from your database to some
thread so we have to tell it hey we want
to make sure that we run things locally
here right so the this interconnect if
it's you know it's a high speed high
speed
not really I don't think though I
wouldn't call it a bus but they say it's
a high speed connect
between these different sockets that's
multiplex you can go both directions and
talk to anybody in television we call
this the quickpath interconnect of the
qpi then that wasn't good enough so now
they call it the ultra path interconnect
in 2017
AMD has their own version it's now
called the infinity fabric power has
their own thing an arm
I think has their own thing as well but
it's at a high level they're all it's
all doing the same thing right
okay so now if I called Malick question
is where's my memory going to show up
all right so the way to think about this
is that we're going to take the the
tables that we have in memory and we're
going to partition them or break them up
into two chunks of data blocks and then
now we want to assign them each of these
blocks to a specific CPU core right and
in a more high CPU socket or Numa region
so if we're aware of where we're putting
our data where that data is being
located when a query shows up and we
make decisions about how to break it up
into tasks and what those tasks what
pieces of data those tasks of an operate
on we can make sure that we schedule our
operators to execute on data its local
to this so this is an old problem in
distribute data this is called data
placement so think of partitioning is
deciding like how do I break it up and
what boundaries and then data placement
is saying where do I put those actual
partitions that I've generated so in
Linux you can control this through the
the move pages syscall or the noumic
control command-line option or command
line tool so basically what happens with
new it would move pages that if you just
invoke it with a memory address it'll
come back and tell you what numeration
and it's on but if you invoke it with a
memory address a size and a numeration
it'll it'll move that data to to that
location and I think that's a blocking
syscall so if you think about this if I
have a one terabyte database and I can
load it into memory and then sort of get
randomly scattered across different
different sockets then I can go back and
call move pages and start putting things
in and what you know where I want them
all right so let's talk about now what
happens when you call malloc so let's
say our data system calls malloc cuz
we're gonna load into one terabyte
database
the question I have for you guys is what
happens what happens in that Cisco
assume that my allocator as already
handed out all the the the pages that I
have that's already pre allocated what
does it actually do yes
he says calls s break yes sort of well
yeah that's this right so as break will
extend the process data segment but
that's just getting moving it to be
larger but after that it's actually not
doing anything it's like all a day was
update the internal bookkeeping data
structures it has for for this boundary
but all the virtual memory just
allocated with the S break is not
actually physically allocated in memory
because no one's access to debt it's
only when we touch the data does is
they're paid fault and then the OS says
oh it looks like you're actually gonna
use this memory let me go may have and
be backed by physical memory right so
now though let's say after the page
fault so after call s break and then
someone tries to access this memory
where are we actually gonna put this
this memory week that we just allocated
let me take a guess is it to thread that
allocate of it or is the thread that
touched it touch it
why that's what the paper said yes okay
good
fantastic okay yes so there is a policy
that to tell the OS that whatever thread
touches that memory that's where I
wanted to be allocated so when there's
so I can allocate it it adult calls s
break extends virtual memory from light
for my process but only one no threat
touches it then there's the page fault
and then we put it in that physical
location yes this question is the OS
cannot promise virtual memory unless it
has physical memory what do you I
promise
think big I I want I want one terabyte
of memory what happens oh you can't you
can't yes yes it's bad but is it wrong
yes phosphates yes so that's the way so
actually you can see this now if you run
some of the tests with a SAN from our
database system it'll say the virtual
memory size of the database process is
12 terabytes we obviously don't have 12
terabytes on any machine right so the
the OS is making the decision here that
like most people are gonna allocate more
memory than they actually need so I'll
to let you have it and if you actually
end up needing it then you yes you you
have to start swapping out pages to to
the swap space on disk and that makes it
look that's virtual memory it makes it
look like you have more memory than you
actually have
all right but in our in a database world
for the things we talk about here we
actually talk about that the the data
the inside tables the tools themselves
we're gonna use that space so seeing of
this is like alright well I I'm not
gonna allocate I'm not gonna turn to
anybody says mourn and have pre-allocate
you know one gigabyte of memory it's
only as I start inserting data that I've
recognized oh well I'm running out of
space for my pre allocated memory that I
have now let me go grab another you know
100 megabytes break it up to block start
filling data in so the question is we're
trying to get here is like when I do
that where's that M memory actually be
stored by default you get this where the
OS does round-robin to start just
writing out pages to lean in one socket
at a time and goes around over and over
again what he said as he pointed out the
paper that you can tell the OS I want to
use the first touch policy so that I'll
allocate the memory and then when the
task actually starts inserting into that
into that block there'll be the page
fault and then that's when it updates
the the virtual memory table to now be
back by physical memory and then I can
that data into the to the table and that
physical memory will be wherever my
threat is actually running right again
you can do this you can modify the
location after the fact you can call
that move pages sis call to say alright
well I've loaded my table and let me go
start moving things around accordingly
but that's actually obviously stupid
because like if I'm loading a one
terabyte data is I don't want to load it
all in first and just have it be
scattered around randomly then go back
and do sequential scan and then actually
start you know moving things to the
right location I want to use this policy
ahead of time be aware where I'm
scheduling my schedule might might my my
tasks so that I have an even
distribution of the data across all all
threads or close all sockets right so
let's see the impact of this when we
have fine grained control of where we're
putting data so I'm gonna show to slides
here the first will be LTP and the first
of the OLAP so this is from a paper a
few years ago from a natasa Telemachus
group at EPFL and so this is running an
in-memory database on a four socket
machine eight cores per six cores per
socket and they're just gonna run the
TPCC payment transaction and what
they're gonna do is they're going to put
the different warehouses or the blocks
of data for the for the for the database
on different configurations across the
the sockets so spread will be every
every socket has has you know an equal
portion of one quarter of the total
table group was where you're gonna shove
everything when to a single socket mix
is where you split it 50/50 and the OS
is just letting the OS do whatever at
once and I'm putting question marks in
here because like we don't know so
whatever the policy that the OS decides
to do is what it gets and so what you
can see here obviously that if our
threads can access data that are all
running on the same socket you'll get
about a 30% improvement over what the OS
will do because the OS is gonna do
something looks like it's doing
something a little bit smarter than
spread but not that you know much
smarter than mix or group so we this is
just showing you if you let the let the
OS be in charge of deciding where
they're gonna place data and also where
it's gonna schedule our threads is you
have a bad time and you get 30% better
by doing it yourself
right and when I think of the students
like all the feds are running on some
Woonsocket so you may be thinking all
right well wouldn't be better for me to
spread across multiple sockets so that
our threads have you know a larger
portion of the CPU caches to themselves
well no because going over that
interconnect to transfer data from one
thread to the next is gonna be
problematic because this payment
transaction will update data at
different partitions so you may have to
go crawl socket the next slide I want
show you is a micro benchmark experiment
that some former students of mine ran a
few years ago so this is running a sort
of a simple execution engine that they
wrote for I think for taking 618 and all
it's going to do is just a sequential
scan over 10 million tuples and they're
gonna run this on a beast machine we had
in the PTL or PDL there was eight
sockets at the time ago 2008 machine
it's a bit old but like there's the only
a socket machine we had access to and
every every socket has 10 cores plus
hyper threading and so the what along
the x-axis you can see is they're gonna
add more threads to do the sequential
scan in parallel so the the size of the
table has always been the same and now
we're just adding more threads so that
we can you know do do do execute the
scan in parallel so what you see is that
at the lower core counts or thread
counts the performance difference
between the the so the raina partition
is like you just let the OS decide where
wants to put it
the local partition is where you you
assign threads to execute the scan on
data that's local to its its numeration
so at the lower thread counts because
the the table is spread across multiple
sockets the probability that a thread is
going to have to access data at a remote
socket and go over the interconnect is
higher so therefore it doesn't really
matter if you're dividing up
intelligently or not but as we now
increase the number of threads then the
amount of cross socket traffic we have
for our scan threads goes down
significantly for for when we do the
local partition local partitioning and
that's why you get better performance
and then this division point here is
when hyper threading kicks in so up into
80 cores
it's all you know
Harbor chorus but then in the
hyper-threading you get the virtual
course and at that point here we're
bound by memory bandwidth so throwing
more cores and more threads at us that
doesn't help us anything because it's
not like you know one thread stolen
waiting for like disk i/o another thread
it can run everybody just waiting for
get stuff at it out of the memory
controller so that's why the performance
plateaus so this case here I forget the
exact numbers but it's almost about a 2x
performance difference between or over
2x performance difference between being
intelligent at how we do or you know
place our data on run time on our
operators versus letting the OS and the
hardware manager for us okay so as I
said briefly the is this notion of
partitioning and data placement we're
not gonna talk about partitioning here
but think about partitioning scheme is
again it's some policy we're to use to
decide how we divide our data up into
chunks and the placement decides the
placement policy decides where we're
gonna put those partitions so the
placement policy is sort of agnostic to
what's actually in our partitions and
you saw this in the morsel paper right
in the morsel paper that said all the
threats care about is that they're
operating on data that's local to it and
they just pull it out of queue and this
process it in a partitioning scheme you
can have some higher-level logical
meaning or semantics to how you're
dividing up the data that you can then
exploit in your query execution and this
is what we'll cover this in future
lectures like if I know that my my quick
might workload is always going to be
doing hash joins on a given partition or
starting I want to give an attribute
then I could decide the hash partition
my data all in that joint attribute so
that now when I run the joint algorithm
all the data that that every operator
needs to operate to do the join is is
local to it and the query optimizer is
aware of this partitioning scheme all
that is sort of above us when we do data
placement scheduling here okay all right
so at this point what we have we have a
process model we have a task assignment
pilot model basically how we're gonna
decide you know where should where
should tests actually run its where the
memory is local to it and we decided how
we're gonna saw it you know
determine what mechanism we're going to
use to pin chunks of memory or chunks of
data to memory locations so now we need
to talk about how we're actually to
create a bunch of tasks that we want to
then execute for our for our logical
query plan and then once we have those
we can get aside how we're actually
going to going to to schedule them so
402 B queries this is super simple
because most of the time there's not
really any opportunities for parallelism
in a single old to be query I could have
multiple OTP queries running at the same
time across different transactions and
certainly I want to have them run on
separate threads and they want to run on
on you know on the the sockets that have
the memory that's local to it but for
the data they want to access but within
a single or to be query I can't really
divide that up into sub chunks right
like go get andis account record that's
like a single and next probe to go get
my one record
I can't paralyze that so this is gonna
be this what we care about this for is
for the OLAP queries and then we can
still apply now the same techniques
we're gonna do to schedule OLAP queries
to schedule multiple ultimately queries
at the same time right okay that are
running on behalf of different
transactions so the easiest way to do
scheduling is called static segment and
that's where the data doesn't decide
before it even starts exceeding the
query I know the number threads that I
have a number of course that I have it
can decide like I'll just say I have one
task for every core and then shove them
off to the hardware and let them execute
right so this is the easiest thing to do
because I don't worry about monitoring
the behavior of the task while they're
running I just say this is my plan I'm
sticking with it and I don't care about
alternatives so this is the if you're
building a data system for the first
time this is probably what you end up
building because it's the easiest thing
to do so again this is not the same
thing as is the placement policy stuff
right we we have a place in policy into
us to have that we use to assign the
tasks to threads basically the data
location this just sort of saying how do
we divide up our tasks and and and at
runtime how do we actually schedule them
so the approach that I had you guys the
reason why this is me Paulo Matic for
OLAP queries especially is that
it doesn't take into account the the you
know the the runtime of these individual
tasks only different courts so if I have
that one terabyte database and I have a
sim I'm doing a scan on it with a
predicate and for whatever reason on one
socket the data at that socket that
predicate evaluates to true for more
tuples where every other socket that the
predicate is very selective so I should
end up throwing most of the data away
and so that means now for my task runs
on my one socket it's gonna spend much
longer than the other sock has to finish
that one task because more tuples are
getting put into its output buffer as
it's doing more memory copying and if I
static scheduling approach I can't
dynamically adjust the system and say
alright well I see this guy's going slow
and there's much more data than that it
could possibly execute the heck bet
we're waiting on let me go bring in
other threads to help it out to speed
things up so statics - you can't do that
but this is what dynamic scheduling can
can handle and this is the problem that
the hyper guys are trying to solve what
their approach so the more so driven
scheduling is the idea is that we're
going to process our tasks in parallel
over these horizontal partitions that
they call morsels so morsel is a hyper
term it's not like a standard term in
database systems I think they picked it
because they didn't want to use word
term block because that's uses a bunch
of places they didn't use a term
partition because that's already bunch
of you can use as much places like a
morsel is larger than a block but
smaller than a partition it's a way to
think about it as far as you know no
other system actually uses in this term
this is specific to hyper so they're
gonna have one worker per core and so
you have a multi-core socket you can
have multiple cores per support for that
socket there can be a pool based tasks
einman meaning the the workers are gonna
run they're gonna check some centralized
data structure and say what work is
available available to me and then when
they load the data in they'll just do
round-robin data placement so they'll
have you know say I'm doing a bulk
insert and I'll say well some portion of
that ball concerned goes to this socket
some portion goes this office I got the
morsels so it's gonna be interesting
about their approach is that the
implementation of the actual database
system is going to be entirely Numa
aware meaning they'll have
implementations of operators that
recognize whether they're accessing data
on a local numeral region or a remote
Numa region and they'll do they'll have
different strategies of where they put
they put the output data or what what
album they actually may want to use
right and they'll use this when they
make decisions about how to pull things
out of the task task queue so as I said
they're using a pull model so that means
that there's no separate dispatcher
thread there's no single thread in
charge of having a global view of what's
going on in the entire system and the
threads are doing the workers arguing
cooperative scheduling because
everyone's looking at the same queue so
what's gonna happen is that when they
pull tasks out of this queue each worker
thread is going to going to prefer
threat of tasks that aren't gonna
operate data local to it but it also can
recognize that there are there no tests
available to it that's that's operating
on with local data and go try to steal
work or steal tasks from another worker
thread that may be operating data that
that's that's remote to my worker thread
but because this other worker thread is
is going slow for some reason we'll pick
up the slack and take some of their work
and then their approach also - I'm not
actually I'm a slide for this but in
their model they only execute one query
at a time so a query shows up they're
gonna break it up to a bunch of tasks
and you don't move on to the next query
until all the tasks for that for that
one query are finished
alright so it's either the query is
completely done and there's no more
tasks available to it I move on to the
next one or a worker thread can go steal
tasks that the straggler worker can't
keep up question yes question is like
yeah so his question is what is actually
dividing up of query into tasks and
putting them into the queue I would call
that a dispatcher that's like a that's
sort of like the the front-end layer the
query shows up you parse it you know
parts the sequel front of the query
optimizer and then at that point you
have a you divide them into tasks and
then a certain to the queue and whether
that's a dedicated thread that's that's
separate from the networking thread or
the networking thread itself it doesn't
it doesn't matter at this point I
actually don't know what they do in our
current system we the same thread that
takes the the sequel query off the
network socket parses it binds it not
buys it well then it divides it up but
you could hand it off to another queue
yes this question is how that works you
only work
give me two slides we'll get there all
right so first thing we need to do is
divide our data up into into morsels so
say this is our data table we have four
columns so morsels are just horizontal
partitioning where we're gonna say
within some strive all right this is
this is the boundary of a morsel in the
in the paper they talk about they use a
hundred thousand two pools per most
morsel and they say they pick this
number because it provides the right
amount of parallelism versus the
overhead of putting stuff in a queue so
for every task I get and pull out of the
queue I'm gonna least operate on at most
100,000 tuples in peloton our block
sizes were a thousand tuples in aged
order the system I helped build before I
came to see him you we did ten megabytes
as far as I remember from the
discussions of those systems we just
picked those numbers out of her ass like
it's not like there was any magic to it
I think in the case of hyper they said
they actually did some you know some
internal micro benchmark to determine
that a hundred thousand one actually was
actually reasonable in our new system as
I said a few more few lectures ago our
block sizes are 1 megabytes because this
allows to have the 20 bit offsets that
we use the line as command in c + 11 i
didn't look to align our blocks of 1
megabyte chunks in memory right and
again so for each of these muscles we'll
just order to assign them to different
CPU sockets so now getting to his
question how how we're actually going to
do work-stealing so say now we take our
query plan
and then we're gonna chop it up into
different tasks then we're gonna put in
this global queue and then now down here
for every single socket it's gonna have
its local memory and then it'll have a
buffer that the control results but it
also have all the morsels that it's
aware of that are local to it and so the
buffers will be as you process a task we
want to write data to our local buffer
it's sort of the same way we talked
about doing the Delta store in the hyper
approach where as I was generating new
versions
I put the old versions in thread local
memory and that means that I didn't have
to have a coronation of a global shared
memory space that that multiple threads
be ready and ready to at the same time I
know that no the threat writing to my
buffer at this time so I don't take a
latch on it so now all the threads are
gonna go look in the queue and pull down
the first bunch of tests that it must
execute so in this task you you maintain
information about the dependency between
these between the between the tasks so
it would know that I can't actually
execute the probe until I do the build
the hash table and do partitioning for
on the other side here so it knows that
these are the tasks I can execute first
so again so as the each each thread runs
a worker runs the task it's pulling data
out of its local memory which is gonna
be fast and then as a you know actually
X use the operators and produces some
output result it writes it now to its
local buffer yes question is is the
global task queue in some sort of socket
or is it distributed I think they let
the OS manage this one because there's
not really anything everybody if
everyone has to read and write to it
there's not any magic you can do and
think about it - like the
yeah so his point is like well well
we'll see this in Hana wait his damn it
is this global task queue is a shared
shared memory space right so I need so
they're going to use a lot free your lat
tree hash table to avoid having to
synchronize on on this or have a heavy
synchronization synchronization
primitive but you could partition the
memory of this global task queue such
that these guys look in their local
memory first find tasks that are
specific to him and if not gonna look at
other ones Hana would do this as far as
I know hyper Hana does this was seen a
few more times yes there's this quote I
think yes for what everything they
didn't do this so but the point the plan
is gonna make is like the morsel size is
100 100 thousand tuples that's where the
big the bottleneck is gonna be if I'm
going over the inter connect to a remote
socket like the bottleneck is reading
this going fetching one task that's
gonna be maybe a kilobyte of a size it's
not me that big so going getting
fetching one thing from a memory region
it's not a big deal that's not what the
bottleneck is so again you want to add
is I'm knows law we want to optimize
where the big overhead is or spending
all our time it's with this and that's
what the Optima is all right so say now
these first two threads make sure the
sister won't good the first two threads
are finish up the first three workers
finished up their tasks but the third
guy is running slower as I said so maybe
this filter is is unselective so we're
generating a lot of output and running
into our buffers and that means we're
doing copying and wrong slower so now
the other two workers can go grab the
next two tasks or to execute
same thing but say now this first one
though finishes up this task more
quickly it can then recognize that oh
well the b3 is waiting
also needs the executed before we can
exit the the next task in our in our
pipeline or in a query plan so let me go
ahead and steal this guy bring it down
and and and operate on it so that means
now I'm at the copy data or move data
we're not moving data you're copying
data from the memory of the morsels for
this socket here you're putting into
your CPU cache over here so that's going
over an interconnect but as I produce
output then I'm gonna write this in my
local buffer and there's some metadata
that maintaining to say for this task
the location of the enemy result that
the next operator would need in our task
queue is located here so there's some
internal bookkeeping the third Natur
they're keeping track up to know this
task output got written to this location
yes the same I think they mean by that
is like they're not the because
everything is in memory the amount of
time like say here for this one when
they were all A's because everything's
in memory they're gonna be close enough
it's not like this thing's gonna be
waiting on disk and therefore be minutes
slower right it's just like the idea is
again because they only excute one query
at a time rather than have this guy be
idle waiting for b2 to finish then a3
has to finish and then has to actually
be three before you connect to the next
task in go ahead and just go ahead and
steal it yes this question is for this
one here when I had to copy the more
soul into my CPU cache running the sake
here do I then do I then physically you
know permanently move it to be over here
no right because again the net score you
might show up and now maybe this this
socket is it's the slow one right and
then this guy might be stealing back
from me
right typically you don't move the
memory
once it's all ready once it's already
placed in locations you may want to
report it repartition it may be split up
on a different attribute but that seemed
rare and many said that in those systems
as well okay
so again because they only have one work
uh procore hyper has used that work
stealing because otherwise they're gonna
be they have threads waiting for for
stragglers and as we already said they
use a lot free hash able to maintain
global work use so that means that the
overhead of going grabbing things from
the work queue is not that significant
relevant relative to the actual cost of
processing the morsel so now let's talk
about another approach from Hannam and
it sort of gets into what he was saying
about how you want to organize the queue
so Hana is gonna be using a I should be
very clear this is from a research paper
that a PhD student wrote while employed
at sa P so in in in in Germany they have
a model for PhDs where a a student can
go work full-time at the company they
still do research they still write
papers they get paid by that company you
like a regular salary like I'm not like
a PhD stipend but then they get they get
the degree from an institution so as far
as you know what I'm describing here
never actually made it into the real
Hana system although the student was
actually physically working on the real
Hana source code when they implemented
this but this is sort of a a different
approach of how to do scheduling that
than when Hana actually really does so
his statement is does that mean whatever
they describe here did not work out and
therefore they did not want to put it in
the real Hana system there's like yes
this is a good idea we should do that
and then there's like the engineering
overhead of taking this research code
and putting to the real system that's
oftentimes why this stuff doesn't
materialize right but it's not not like
it's wasted work right certainly like if
now ACP decides to build a new system
which they actually end up rewriting a
lot of Hana you know they now know
something about you know some of the way
different alternatives way to organize
that's the schedule mechanisms so they
could have done this
so as you don't know since the 2019
rewrite of Hana that came out last year
I don't know whether they do this I
suspect not but I just don't know
all right so what they're gonna do is
they're gonna it's a pool based cue but
they're going to have multiple workers
per socket so it's not gonna be the same
thing in Hana where you have one worker
for a core every core could have
multiple workers and there being
different different they're gonna have
different statuses and so each group now
also is gonna have a soft and a hard
priority queue so that's what he was
saying so couldn't I have a cue where I
know that's local to me and I go check
that first and if nothing's there then I
go check another cue that's the global
one that's this so the soft key would be
local to my group it's gonna be some
number of workers running on the same
socket I sorry take it back that's the
hard cue the hard cue is local to my
group and hard means that nobody can
steal for me and the soft one means that
someone is allowed to go ahead and steal
this so I still want to execute both
tasks this just says that this thing has
to run in my socket or my group no one
can take it and these are things that
are eligible to be stolen from other
other things so now they're gonna have
have a separate watchdog thread that's
going to have a global view of what's
going on at every single group on every
single socket and then they can decide
that whether some group is being
oversubscribed and has more tasks that
they can actually process and then it
can take threads away from one group and
then allocate additional threads or
allow additional threads to run in
another group so so it's really you're
getting births cut the balancing you're
having the work-stealing that you have
under hyper but you also have the
ability to crank up the number of thread
you want to be executing tasks as well
so you sort of get that you're using
both approaches so as I said we have a
soft queue and a hard queue so fred's
are allowed to steal tasks from other
soft cues and the Hark you how to do
that and then for the different pools
for within a group would have four
different pools that'll keep track of
what types of threads we have running so
working thread is when we have one
that's actually running a task that it
pulled from some queue it doesn't matter
what queue came from because we know
that it's processing something we have
an inactive thread where we know we're
blocked in the kernel give you some
latch and
it's some later point it'll get woken up
a free thread is one where it's gonna
sleep a little wake up check its queue
to see whether anything for to execute
in the software the other or the hard
queue local to it if if so then it go
ahead and execute it and now becomes a
working thread if not then it goes back
to sleep and then we have part threads
where the thread the sleeps and it
doesn't get woken up until the wash dog
thread comes comes along says hey we
need you you know wake up and actually
start doing stuff and so again what this
isn't allow us to do is we can now scale
up the number of threads we have like in
the park thread queue case cuz like or
the pool case cuz if I recognize that my
group cannot all my threads are working
or they're inactive there's no free
threads because they're all they're all
working on things if I don't have enough
resources to process the work I need to
have for my group I can now release
these Park threads or unpark them and
have them start processing things as
well and then maybe on another group
I'll park their threads so there's a lot
of work right this is this sounds like
an operating system because it sort of
is and we'll see this from from from
sequel server and a few more slides but
they actually did build an operating
system that runs inside the database
system do they even call it that
so with this they're gonna again they're
gonna they're gonna adjust the threads
from the pinning of the threads where
they're actually running based on
whether the task is CPU bound or memory
bound so like if my task is if for my
for my group if my task says that I know
I I have a bunch of tasks and I can't
process in the fast enough
I can allow threads to well I couldn't
part them if I have to not enough work
if I could unpark bam if I have two of
more than actually need and I have to do
that for other socket because I don't
want to saturate the memory bandwidth
over the all system because the maybe
those tasks are pulling data over the
interconnect right what was interesting
about this is that they found that when
they looked at the really large socket
machines that khana can run on they
found that the hyper approach of long
the work stealing was actually a bad
idea so in the hyper paper they were
looking I think at two to four socket
machines the Hana guys are looking at
like sixty-four socket r128 socket
machines
so in that environment what you want to
do is you don't have any soft cues you
put everything in the hard queue and you
can then scale up the number of threads
you're running on every single on every
single group on every single socket but
you don't allow threads to to take work
from another socket and go over the
interconnect everybody always process
things things locally right yes the task
of the Softee in the heart here like
what would be an example so the question
is what what how do I know what to put
in a hard humour soft ass could be like
well we'll see in the next slide so in
Hana for this example they have the
entire system architecture is running on
these these whirlpools so that means
like never requests will be running on
the whirlpool so if I have a if I have a
task that says you know read the next
message next packet from this socket
I want to run that you know at the at
the thread or at the socket were at the
CPU socket on the network swear that
never sock is located and I don't want
somebody else to go go take that from me
yeah I mean this is the next slide so
again like there thread groups are
running everything so in the hyper case
the the the pools were only doing
processing queries they're putting
everything in the system so now you can
do things like if my if I have I'm over
subscribed on the number of queries I'm
executing rather than accepting new
never requests I'll take some networking
threads from their pool and spin up new
threads or unpark threads in my
execution pool and so that sort of gets
the natural flow control of not you know
taking more queries than you actually
can execute so here's that same query we
had before right and so save these tasks
here we can put into the soft queue and
then for whatever reason we put these
other tasks in the hard queue right for
my purpose here it just doesn't actually
matter and shown this registration
purposes so now again all the worker
queues the worker the worker threads are
pulling from the soft queue by inactive
threads
are just waiting on something in the OS
the free threads are just spinning on
the soft Q or the heart of Q looking for
work to do and the park threads are just
blocked by the watchdog thread so I
can't say here that I recognize that I
can't keep up with my demands so say now
my free thread pulls out something from
the heart Q then it gets migrated now
and now it is considered to be a working
thread and the watchdog thread above
that all this knows how many threads
were actually running on every single
group and can make scheduling decisions
about about our resource allocation
decisions up above yes
parts that are like threads in reserve
so like instead of calling spawn I just
hadn't there right so they are I
actually don't know what the true
difference I think in actual thread
would be like I'm blocked waiting to get
to the latch or a mutex
and the OS but if I come back then I
become become working this is like I
think you're parked in the OS you're
blocking me West on some mutex and it's
like it's the conditional variable where
like some other threat has to come and
say now you're allowed to wake up and
the idea is that I can dynamically have
these guys get released and execute
without having to call call spawn
because that's a contact switch or a sis
call and the context switch okay so the
last scheduling thing I'm gonna talk
about is which i think is the most
fascinating one out of all of these it's
not for an in memory system but again
it's it's so it's so different than
everything else we've talked about so
far but I think I think it's amazing
so in sequel server in 2005 they
released in the new version of sequel
server they now released that in bundle
inside the dated system this basically a
user mode operating system called sequel
OS and the idea is that this is a layer
that sits above the real operating
system with the Windows kernel and the
actual the database system engine itself
that manages and provisions hardware
resources and the original motivation of
this was that rather than the the you
know as new moon was coming more
prevalent as there was hardware changes
rather than having all the different
implementations or of the different
operators inside the database system
execution engine rather than have to all
be aware of of Numa and
and memory look memory layouts and
things like that they would have
abstract all that away through the
sequel West layer and have it makes
decisions about you know where to
actually run tasks and how to actually
run things in parallel so it's things
amazing because it's more than just like
scheduling threads they do a bunch of
other stuff like IO scheduling they
actually manage up the buffer pool
inside that cos they they do lock
scheduling and unlock management inside
this as well again the idea here is that
rather than us having to to have these
ad hoc invitations of specialized Lodge
to deal with like oh this threads ready
for this lock and therefore might my
join Alvin can run this way or whatever
like all that is taken care of in the
sequel West layer and you just implement
your basic operators up above and this
thing handles all that for you right
again when you think of like if you took
the intro class we talked about
disscourn and database systems right we
talked about the buffer pool manager the
role manager is basically replicating
the same logic for the OS does for
virtual memory allocate some pages or
III can allocate more memory than
actually available to me and I know how
to swap things out on disk so so
Microsoft basically went all-in so let's
do everything the OS is doing and put it
inside our database system right it's
it's pretty amazing so but for this
lecture what we talk about is they are
doing for thread scheduling they're
gonna do non-preemptive thread
scheduling by modifying the the database
system code itself to be able to yield
back to some to the scheduler so before
we get to that I also say to is like
this sequel OS layer is part of the
reason why Microsoft was able to port
sequel server over to to Linux so
there's announcement was in 2017 and the
this TechCrunch article they talked
about how when they had to take C Co OS
and instead of talking to win32 they now
talk to the Linux kernel that wasn't a
major change for them I mean was not it
was not insignificant but it's not like
we need to change all other aspects of
the database system because all of this
low-level
management of OS resources and hardware
resources is all done by these OS layer
so you just change the sequel last part
to make its talk to Linux and not touch
anything else
so the same codebase for doing other
joint algorithms doing all the X
shishun flow control or control or the
indexes all that sits above C go s and
then have to modify any of that going
back to my example of db2 before db2 did
not have that abstraction layer so
that's why they have four different
distinct code bases right they've
attempted I think to try to have a
unified code base but it never you know
it's never happened it's never gonna
happen
Microsoft was able to do it through the
sequel OS so I think it's really
fascinating okay so what is pre-emptive
thread scratching look like in their
world
so in CIOs the quantum is gonna be for
every thread it's gonna be for
milliseconds and I know what the quantum
size is in default Linux these questions
what's the quantum quantum is like so
you haven't so you have a thread it gets
scheduled on the OS schedules it for
execution it's gonna run for a certain
mount of time called the quantum and
then it's some point when the quantum is
up there's interrupt
they take your thread away and handle it
and I have a context or another thread
right time slice would be another term
right so Freight for those you've taken
OS or OS class what what is that what is
the quantum size and Linux nobody knows
go to the vague answer because it's
actually dynamic right it can it can
vary I you know depending on the clock
speed depending on what else is running
right if it knows that there's no other
threads running that are you know taking
demand from this from the CPU it can
then make your quantum slightly larger
all right to avoid a context switch to
some other task that that's not needed
right if you switch into real time mode
for Linux then the quantum is fixed to
be I think a hundred milliseconds now
the idea there is like again the context
switches are not cheap because you're
taking all the registers putting out you
know into GPU caches changing the the
program counter like all that's not
cheap and so in the real time at last
they let your quantum long for a longer
time so in in cos the quantum time is
gonna be four milliseconds but they have
no way to enforce this because this is
all done in user level in user mode
meaning we hand a task off to a thread
it runs there's no way for us in our
inner because we're
the same process and we're not the OS
there's no way for us to say thread
you're done give us give us back control
of the core and you can't do that
because that's what the OS does because
they can do it through hardware so what
they're gonna do now is modify they went
modified the the source code of sequel
server itself to introduce yield calls
to cause the thread to go back and you
know return the control back to the
schedule so let's say this is a simple
query here a select star from a where a
value equals some parameter so a really
simple implementation of this would be a
for loop where we get a bunch of tuples
evaluate a predicate and then if they
match our predicate we admit it
so what basically what Microsoft had to
do was go back and modify the source
code to keep track of the amount of time
that they spent at each different part
and recognize that if the if the times
it's the last the last time I called
yield to the scheduler was boys you know
more than four milliseconds ago then I
go ahead and yield back puts control
back now to the scheduler guys you can
decide whether to run your tasks again
or whether they hand it off to another
task and so this is amazing this is like
pseudocode they're obviously not calling
you know get current timestamp over
never again for every single tuple that
would be stupid
I I think the way they did it was they
sort of knew like in the code itself
like if I'm doing a for loop you know
they know the cost of going and maybe
retrieving the tuple and whether it's in
disk or it's in memory the worth the
time that is and they can then use some
in built-in calculations to decide very
cheaply has my form four milliseconds
gone up yes so his question is how do I
control with the next thread the OS is
going to schedule right you can't arrest
yield or sequel or yield so dizzy this
is this is not a versus mode this is the
Seco OS you
they can control what secret summer task
is running yes right and since a bunch
of banners does this so one is your
right eye like I can't prevent the OS
from swapping out the scheduler right so
what your best practices we're setting
up any database system is run the data
system on a machine by itself and so you
know you're not doing Bitcoin mining or
you know encoding a video or watching
YouTube at the same time you're trying
to run transactions right so the the
contention for the CPU will be lower and
with cooperative scheduling or the the
fair scheduling approach in Linux if I
know know the thread is trying to access
you know trying to do stuff I'll come
back to Mike the thread right away so
yes I could be in the middle of this the
OS might swap me out
correct so this to this this quantum
times is a user mode concept what's that
yeah yes
another interesting advantage you get
from this as well as like now I can do
sort of fair scheduling and provisioning
for between maybe different tenants of
the same money on the same database so I
have two customers running my same
sequel server instance one is I could
just divide them up to run on different
sockets but I could also now just use
these Quantum's to enforce that they
both could equal time or like if I now
have a budget for how many Quantum's are
going to get from one tenant versus
another the quantum times still gonna be
4 milliseconds but maybe I give more
Quantum's to this other guy because
they're giving me more money than the
first tenant so this is allows you to
search all sorts of amazing things you
can't easily do with the hyper approach
or the or the Haan approach because they
they don't know what what the actual
tasks are actually trying to do right so
I don't know whether as far as you know
nobody else does this with this sequel
West layer this is something I want to
do in our system because I think it'll
benefit the self-driving stuff
the only other system that I know that
does something similar is fauna DB and
so they're not doing the same kind of
like fixed quantum size or not again
it's not fixed
to make it be always for milliseconds
but but the way Hana does this is that
they only yield back to the in database
scheduler whenever you do i oh so in in
cos i could do all this in memory and
I'm still gonna yield back after my
quantum is is it's roughly up in fauna
DB they basically say oh I'm gonna read
something from disk or over the network
let me go back to my schedule and say
hey I'm gonna pause for a bit
schedule somebody else if you can and if
this guy says oh you're fine go and then
you get back control otherwise to
schedule something else yes is it a good
project read yes we can talk about this
yes and right now we don't really have
anything I don't have slides with us we
use for query execution we use intel's
thread building blocks which i don't
like because it's basically it's almost
like a black box you basically basically
for the query plan you divide it up into
a dag you hand it off to the to thread
to TV TVB library and it's scheduler it
does its thing and a better you get back
response but you can't send in or
something else at the same time at least
I don't think okay alright so the last
thing I'm gonna talk about is how to do
flow control I sort of briefly talked
about this about with the hard and soft
queues approach like if I recognize that
I can't process queries fast enough then
I can take away networking threads and
assign unpark query processing threads
but basically like if query share
showing off faster than we can handle
them then we're going to become
overloaded so once again the OS is not
gonna help us because if for cpu-bound
then it just does nothing right if for
memory bound and actually what his
question is like if I allocate one
terabyte of memory and I don't have one
terabyte of swap space what's gonna
happen
well the OS called has this special
thing called the out of out of memory
killer om and basically says oh I'm
running out of memory I'm running out of
swap days let me pick a random process
and just kill it right and you get a sig
term it you you know it just kills you
right yes
what sir what is cowlick sorry Oh
cowlick sorry yes um what would say what
would that do I feel like if I try to
malloc and initialize one terabyte of
memory it's gonna start running up the
swap space and again like if I don't saw
spaces I think the policy is for om I
think it picks whatever the one has the
most memory because again from the
operating system world like Linux job is
not to die right and if and if so nor it
survived it's got to kill your database
system it's gonna do it right um so you
know in it so from the obvious
perspective this is the right thing to
do instead of me crack grinding to a
halt and never doing anything right I'll
I'll kill the data system and then that
way you can still know what YouTube yeah
so from a again from the Davis isn't
that's the same thing in this crash but
we knew something that's smarter and
they're basically two concepts here
emission control and throttling and
basically the idea is where do we
recognize where our bottleneck is that
we can't process things fasten off and
then how do we then expose that out to
the to the outside world so that new
queries don't show up and we get
overwhelmed so Mission Control is
basically we recognize that a query
shows up and then we don't have enough
resources to actually - right now
because we're CPU bound or we're running
out of memory we go ahead and say we we
reject the request and I think in the
post ghost protocol I I don't think you
can send back it's the rejection request
but you can send back a like query fail
or it's close connection throttling
would be you just introduced some
artificial delay for queries as they
show up so that the idea is that I sleep
a little bit for us maybe start
processing the query or as I'm running
the query maybe sleep a little as well
and that way the for the system overall
because now queries are not trying to
all do you know do work at the same time
this is sort of smooth things out and I
can I can you know I can actually
process things that make forward
progress so I'm not saying one is better
than other different systems do
different things this one is probably
the most common one but again this needs
you need to now be aware of what's going
on in the in the in the in the actual
worker pools we're to actually exceeded
queries in order to make this decision
for this one you don't need any
centralized control you just say you
know well other than like I need to
recognize that I'm going slower or my
queue is getting a lot of certainty I
can't it's getting larger than it is
smaller as I process things then I just
introduced these things but I don't
really make a global decision every
threat could make its own decision about
about introducing to sleep okay so the
high-end systems can do this this is
sort of like a approach one approach to
sorry it's a backwards but like this is
the easiest one to do the high-end
systems can do this because you can do
other things like I can have I can have
priority queues to say like if a someone
connects with this username let their
queries always run even though I'm
oversaturated whereas like if someone
else is like a low low paying customer
they can run slower and certainly if I'm
the admin like a lot of these systems
always maintain one open port for it for
the admin view it'll connect to the
system and actually queries start
killing things and in you know free up
resources so in that case here that's
you know this is very common alright so
we covered a lot today
the main takeaway again throughout the
entire semester and especially today is
that what is a database system well it's
a beautiful piece of software that we
don't want the OS to ruin for us so
we're trying to do as much as we can as
possible sequel West is sort of one
extreme but at the very least we need to
be aware of the layout of memory where
threads are be running so that we we
minimize that that traffic over to
interconnect right and the amount of
metadata mean you maintain about where a
morsel is locator where a block of date
is located is pretty low right it's not
like we need you know anything inside
this is need to know if you want this
address here's where it's located or we
could also do the cisco on the fly and
say well I know there's black located
here what neumann region is it located
in and then assign a task to it after
that but typically that's that you don't
want to do that because that's a syscall
and so we wouldn't track everything
ourselves and the OS again it's a
frenemy we need it to live but we don't
want to actually have to talk to as much
as possible we don't want it to do
anything ok any questions all right so
next class now we're going into more
detail about what are these tasks
actually could look like and how we're
actually gonna execute them okay and
then we'll post on Piazza for the update
of the the checkpoint for for project
two and if you don't have a group I will
email you today and force you to make
friends and pick a group okay
guys what is this
[Music]
and my hood won't be the same I've diced
you take a say I said a prayer