[Music]
[Applause]
all right so today we're talking for
covering protocols and so there'll be
some you know in the interruption class
we talk about areas we talk about how to
we want to restore the days after a
crash and in a memory database we're
gonna do the exact same thing right
obviously that if we the database you
know pretend it's down and crashes we
won't want to be able to restart the
system and put the database back to the
correct state such that we guarantee the
asset ethnicity and durability
durability guarantees they would have an
asset system right so animosity means
that we can't have any partial
transactions consistency means that we
don't put the database and like a funky
state where like the data could be
actually incorrect and then durability
just means that you know if we write
changes to the database we tell to
commit a transaction the outside world
hears that that transaction is committed
when we come back then all our changes
are still there so every recovery
algorithms gonna have two parts there's
the part we're gonna do at runtime where
as we process transactions and they
update the database we're going to take
some extra steps to record some extra
information so that if we crash and come
back we can look at extra extra
information to figure out what was going
on in the system to put us back in the
correct State and then there's the
recovery protocol you actually do after
the crash or after a failure when you
look at all the information you've
collected that you generated in the
normal processing and then you figure
out all right what I need to do to go
back so we'll talk a little bit about we
spent time took my Mme database or
logging part of all the protocols the
paper I had you guys read was not in a
memory database and I'll explain why I
assigned it the there's actually not a
lot but not many papers about in-memory
database login recovery when you look
back at the early ones from the 1980s
they all make this big assumption that
the log or the database itself will be
backed by what is called non-volatile
memory or persistent memory back in the
1980s there's just mint battery-backed
of DRAM
so you have a little battery on the
motherboard that could be triggered any
time you recognize that the powers can
go down and they used the battery to
actually gracefully shut down the memory
read it out the disk and so when you
came back all your contents or D Ram was
still there so battery backed FD ran has
been around for a long time it's not
widely used because it takes up space on
the motherboard right they they're great
until you try to use them and they don't
work right because you have to make sure
the battery is always functioning
correctly so you don't see that too
often the wall if you certainly can't go
to Amazon and get a AWS instance that
has has this so the other kind of
persistent memory though instead of
betting battery back to DRAM is to do is
what it's called true non-volatile
memory or true persistent memory and so
for years and years and years every time
I taught this class I would say Oh novel
you know real novelty memories coming
out one year from now one year from now
and finally last year Intel stepped up
and released true non-volatile memory
called the op team and again the idea is
that it goes into a dim slot like you
normally would and with DRAM but this
has magic inside of it that says you
know if I if I lose power I still
maintain everything it's me slightly
slower than DRAM
but it's coming way faster than then
SSDs so we're not going to talk about
nvm stuff or pass it to memory right now
we'll cover this at the end of the
semester yes the question is it really
expensive with that what do you say oh
yes and no it's not like it's not like
outlandish it's like maybe a couple
thousand for like a hundred twenty eight
gigs or something like that I don't know
the exact prices I don't think until
polishes them you may be able to get
from OEM but yeah it's more so than DRAM
more up spensive than than SSDs but like
it has certain properties that you can't
get out of an SSD
you can also get it in a form factor
that goes down on the PCI Express so it
is that looks like a flash drive even
though it's a special basically it's not
NAND flash it's not DRAM it's a special
storage medium called phase change
memory you can get it in other form
factors and that one though the prices
are close to what SSDs are but for the
dim stuff it's more pricey
okay we'll cover this later in the
semester
the point of just to make is like if you
go read the early papers on logging
protocols for in memory databases they
all assume this but back then they
didn't really have it so we still have
to design our protocols using relying on
SSDs or spending just hard drives so the
good thing though for us in an
innovative base is that our recovery
protocol is gonna be slightly easier
than what we have to do in a dis
coordinate system and this is just due
to the fact that since the primaries are
the storage location of the database is
in memory when we crash or there's a
failure that memory is wiped so when we
come back all we need to do is just load
in the last checkpoint and replay the
law from disk and we don't have to worry
about any dirty pages from transactions
that may be linking around on disk that
we have to reverse as we would in a disk
coordinate system so we don't have to
track dirty pages right as we run like
if it turns actually make some changes
and then it doesn't commit and we crash
well all those memory pages get wiped so
that's fine all right so this means now
we don't have to store the undo records
to reverse these things because there's
nothing to reverse the only thing we
need to write out the disk is just redo
information the other big difference is
going to be that we're not gonna log any
changes that we make to indexes so in a
disk based system as I update my table
and that causes updates the indexes I'm
also going to create log records that
that record the changes to the index but
in memory database I don't do any of
that and so when I crash I have to load
the database back in from the checkpoint
file anyway so the disk is way more
expensive than doing the computation so
I'm just gonna rebuild the indexes on
the fly as I love the checkpoint in and
in a disk based system you don't do that
so we still have to deal with the fact
that disk is gonna be slow and so we
still wanna take advantage of all the
optimizations we would do in a
Discordian system like group commit
batching things doing specular lock
releases things like that all those
optimizations are still gonna apply for
us here even though we're in memory so
today I'm gonna talk about first about
different types of logging schemes and
again the paper you had you guys read
was for a disk or name system but it's
relying on multi versioning so I think
that's kind and we'll see how that works
and then we'll talk about checkpoint
protocols and these two here are what
you need for to guarantee your database
will actually this is all you really
need to guarantee your database is
durable this is a way to speed things up
after a crash and this is a way to speed
things up if you're gonna do a restart
and you know that it's gonna be
scheduled at a certain time
so there's one you have to absolutely
have to have this one is an optimization
to make this go faster and this is an
optimization to avoid having to do all
this okay
all right so at a high level there's two
types of logging schemes this physical
logging and logical logging physical
logging is like it taking a DIF as you
wouldn't in get the idea is that we're
gonna record the changes that we're
making to a record at the bite level if
you think of also an NBC C when we're
using a deathless tour I'm just
recording I here's the column that I
modified here's the new value right so
then after a crash we're essentially
good it's gonna replay these log records
and reapply the changes to the columns
the other approach is do logical logging
and this is where instead of storing and
the low-level bytes were modifying
within a tuple we're just going to store
the high-level operation that the cap
application invoked or are requested on
the davison to make that change so it
would be like recording the actual
sequel statements that they would send
us the answer update delete queries so
the idea here is if I have a database
but the table has a thousand tuples like
make it big maybe a billion tuples if
I'm doing physical logging with one
query that needs to update all 1 billion
tuples that I need 1 billion log records
the correspond to every single tuple
that I bought that I've modified but if
I'm doing logical logging then I only
need to record that single update
statement and that's enough for my
system after restart to really play that
update and put me back in the correct
State so logical logging is gonna say be
much smaller log files and potentially
much faster to commit at runtime but the
recovery processes could potentially be
more expensive because there's no magic
I can do to make this update go faster
during recovery so but if I have to
update a billion tuples and it takes an
hour the first time I run it
after I crash and restart and replayed
this update query it might take a you
know an hour again so my taking a
delayed amount of time it takes
for me for my database to come back
online so for this reason most systems
are going to choose physical blogging
and this is only used in certain
specialized systems okay now the
question is when do we actually Lush the
log records that our transaction
generates so the first approach is do
all at once meaning as it transaction
runs and they're making changes they're
executing queries that update the
database doesn't matter what it's
physical logging or logical logging I'm
just going to record in memory in this
log buffer for my transaction here's
here's all the log records and only when
the transaction says go ahead and commit
we pass our validation then we hand off
those log records to some our logger
thread who then flushes it out the disk
course we have to wait until all those
lawbreakers are written to disk before
we can tell the outside world that our
transaction committed so it could be a
you know updated billion tuples and
repairing wall records either right wait
for those 1 billion lower your blog
records to get written to disk the other
approach to do incremental flushing and
this is a sh transactions run and there
cumulating these these law of records
when they're when they're their local
log buffer gets full they could hand
that off to some some writer thread who
can then start writing about the disk
and then they get a new log buffer to
start filling up with new log records so
that means that if there's a crash now
in the log there may be log records from
transactions that did not commit yet
right because we're allowing things
getting written out before before
everything is finished so in this
approach here for the all at once
this makes recovery easier because I
know if I crash and come back I'm almost
never gonna see log records from
transactions that did not commit I may
see a transaction did commit and they
start writing out all their log records
but they but we crashed before we write
the rest of it and the commit message in
that case I certainly have to undo it
but most of the times I'll have all the
log records in the case of incremental
flushing I have to do some extra work to
go figure out here's a bunch of
transactions that that haven't finished
let me go ahead and make sure I don't we
apply their changes so this is not that
big of a deal because again we don't
write out any dirty pages
we're reloading from the check one
anyway it's just we have to do some
extra process
singing the Lord make sure we skip
things that should have committed yes
yes yes and those 5 billion things God
stood yes and cracked yes again there's
nothing to undo but updated what and
updated in memory pages we crash that
memories gone so when we when we come
back online we're loading the checkpoint
there's no dirty pages right it's just
in this case here like we'll talk about
replication next next class but like
it's sorta like when do I send the
outside world like a toy to a replica
hey here's here's all my money updates
for my transaction in this case also -
if I update 10 billion tuples I had to
have a log buffer that can handle 10
billion tuples and I may run out of
memory so for this reason most systems
are gonna do this approach but there are
some advantages to doing this all right
these are the standard techniques we
talked about before in the introduction
class it would still apply for us in a
in Murray system so we'll do group
commit it just means that we had this
this log buffer that we can fill in with
the blog records from different
transactions and that we can then flush
them out whenever that log buffer is
full and then have a log buffer another
log buffer start getting filled out by
other transactions and the idea here is
we when amortize the essent costs across
multiple transactions so if you're the
first guy getting out of this queue then
yes you wait the longest because it's
wait for the log buffer to get full but
if they're the last guy then you're
basically running with a dedicated F
sync all right so this is a really old
technique as I said it is used in pretty
much every system today it was
originally developed for this thing
called fast path which was a specialized
in memory engine for ibm's IMS from the
early 1980s but like I said everyone
pretty much does does this today the
other thing we can do now which is
related to the speculative lock release
or specular reads we saw under Hecate on
Andrew MVCC is that when in transaction
goes it goes ahead and commits we don't
have to wait
for the the updates to become durable on
disk before we release all our locks we
can let other transactions start
modifying the tuples that we've modified
assuming those log records will get will
get written out longer getting written
on some desk well they read things that
we modify to me before the lower has a
flush to disk and we have to keep track
of that we did these spec into reads
even though the transactions it's
logical is committed physically it
hasn't gotten made the disk gap so we
know that if any terms that can read
something that we wrote we do have they
have to get stalled until we actually
flush the disk so that means that my
read-only transaction then it reads an
update from from your transaction but
your transaction has been written the
diskette I have to wait for you to get
flushed before I can get committed again
this is a standard technique and NBCC
you know we would know this information
because we maintains and maintain the
state map that says there's transactions
log records have not been flushed yet so
therefore you can't commit right away if
you read something from them ok so I
sort of alluded this a little bit now in
this last couple slides where if we have
a multi version system then the the
Delta records we're going to generate
for MVCC are more or less the same thing
we're gonna generate for in our log it's
not exactly the same because depending
however doing orders the newest or
newest oldest right we could be
generating redo records or undo records
alright for our tuples are modifying
whereas the the database log file wants
to have redo records at least four in
memory database so the idea is that what
if we can combine all the metadata we're
generating for MVCC with all the
metadata or Jenny generating with the
log file and that way we're not
duplicating this effort so that was the
paper I had you guys read for today it
came out and just this year and or last
year and got to be 2019 so as I said
it's not a memory system but it's a
multi version system and I think it's a
good description of how you can
piggyback off of the MVCC metadata
you're generating to make logging may
work better so it's so this protocol is
gonna be a physical logging protocol
that's we rely on the database systems
I'm travel table which they call the
virgin store or the temp TBT so we're
gonna rely on that their time to have a
table to act almost as a recovery log so
what will happen is we'll start writing
out the changes we make to this version
store to a log file but they're only
going to contain essentially the redo
records of the versions we've generated
and then we'll meet when we crash to
come back all we need to do now is just
suck in this version store into disk are
starting alpha disk into memory and we
don't need to undo anything right away I
we just bring those pages back in then
the database is now at the state it was
at the moment of the crash and then we
just need to do some background extra
work to do this logical reverb to make
sure that we don't read things we don't
persist versions from transactions that
have knocked that did not commit at the
crash so the problem they were trying to
solve if they mention in the paper is
that they had certain customers running
on Azure in the cloud or sequel server
in the cloud where they would have these
really long transactions that when there
was a crash now I need to undo all the
changes so this 10 billion table update
we just mentioned like if I crashed
before I finished all updating all those
those tuples when I come back now I got
a under spent a long time undoing
everything so what they wanted to do is
have what they call constant time
recovery which was saying that the the
time it's gonna take for me to restore
the database back to the correct state
is only contingent on the size of the
log file because I just need to be able
to read that in the redo phase and I
don't don't worry about how much time
I'm gonna spend going reverse direction
to undo things that make sense so let's
go to my tables and then we'll see how
it works so again this is with sequel
server as your sequel was the name of
the cloud version of it but as I said
they for this feature they're putting
out in the the on-premise version which
includes the Linux one so they're doing
time travel version storage but they
just call it a version store and so the
idea here is that you have the main
table and this has the the latest
version and they're doing news to oldest
so this this version has a pointer now
to another tuple that's the the
the the you know the next oldest tuple
and then there's a virgin chain allowed
to go back in time to find previous
versions so now if what roads actually
comes along almost update this tuple
here we first make a copy of the current
version into our version store update
the pointer to connect the chain and
then we can overwrite the old version
with with our new one here right so the
idea here is that they want to leverage
this thing which is basically redo
information all right to to then allow
them to restore the state of the
database just by loading this thing back
in so there can be two variants of how
they're gonna do this persistent version
storm so the first one is that they're
gonna do in row versioning where this is
actually you're not going to use the
version store this is gonna look like
that cicada inlining where instead of
making a whole copy of the tuple and
putting to the version store they're
gonna pack it in the in this special
field inside the tuple of just the Delta
record of what got what was modified and
then that gets written out to the right
ahead log just as it would any other
tuple update and that's enough
information to recreate the database
State and I'll show this the next line
and then the for the off road versioning
which is actually using the time travel
table instead of having a time travel
table for every single logical table in
your database they're gonna have one
giant time travel table for every single
table this is way different I've never
seen this used before and so the way it
works is that the in here like instead
of having discrete columns or attributes
that represent the columns in the table
there's gonna have one column that and
then to store a blob or byte string of
the seer lies data for that tuple and
that way you can store any tables tuples
inside there because there's no we're
all we're sort of we're not doing any
processing on looking at the actual
columns in this right we're just almost
using it as a in-memory log then that
then gets flushed so they're also going
to modify the the data table data
structure itself so that you can do fast
and current inserts so that means that
they're going to partition the database
in memory so that our start of the table
in memory so that different threads
write to different regions
of the table and then this allows you to
you should write them out very very
quickly to the right ahead long and you
never came allowed to go back and update
any other tuple right it's only a pend
only and I can now you do central writes
out to the law which is efficient so
this is the in bro versioning this is
the same thing we talked about with
cicada basically they when I do it
updated this tuple instead of making
this copy of this old version and
putting it in time travel table those
embed Delta record inside of here and
then that just gets written out to write
a head loggers as you normally would
so an important distinction here about
why they can do this and why we can't do
this very easily an emery database
system is that in a disk oriented
database the tuples can be variable
length in a memory database we said we
had the primary location of a tuple has
to be fixed length so we either had to
allocate this Delta space for every
single to boy it can only be a certain
size if we're in memory but in a
displaced database I can leave this
thing empty and then if I decide to use
it when I started the new tuple then I
just grab a new slot in my page and can
write everything out right that that's
one important distinction between what
they're doing and what how do you do
this in in-memory database okay so let's
see how they're gonna do recovery so
this is almost looks like standard Aires
except that under Aires the the database
is not available until you complete the
undo phase in their world
it's a neatly available after the redo
phase because all they're doing is
they're loading back in that version
store and then all the versions the old
versions that are around are now are you
know are now available and then we just
piggyback of all that same version
detection or identification that we do
on our MVCC to identify which tuples are
actually visible to our transaction so
analysis phase again we just came
through the log up to the last
checkpoint to figure out what
transaction we're running and then in
the redo redo phase we're gonna replay
the right ahead log to put us back in
the correct State for the most main
table in the Virgen store but as I said
the verges store is only going to it's
going to go and contain versions from
from transactions that did not commit so
I was in the main table but because
we're MVCC we know what the timestamps
were for
versions and then when we come back
online start running rivers transactions
we would notice skip over things that
were uncommitted right cuz we're gonna
maintain this global state map that says
here's all the transactions that are
around and here's what their statuses
then in the undo phase we select
transactions to start execute and when
they find things that that are aborted
they can go ahead either clean them up
or there be a separate background
process to - to clean them up and yeah
asynchronously and they refer to this
thing as a logical work but from from my
purpose it just sounds like garbage
collection although it's the fact that
transactions can do slightly something
slightly different when they find a
board of versions is not exactly about
risk leptin say this is already what it
says so you had separate threads gonna
scan through the blocks find all the
criminal versions and then if you
recognize that the the latest version of
a tuple is in the version store then you
just move it back at you know bet into
the main table right again that's the
same thing we would see and regular GC
that we've already talked about the only
one optimization they do do that do do
that's slightly different is if a
transaction recognizes that oh in the
main table I see the current version the
master version of the tuple is from one
aboard of transaction then instead of
copying that out and make a new version
and then the time travel that is
completely overwrite it alright so again
like I said I think this is interesting
because this is although it's a disk
based system it's showing you how you
how you can use the MVCC metadata to do
a Tiferet have a logging scheme and
potentially get better performance any
questions about this there's this other
bit about the syslog where they would
store changes for non-virgin data
structures like page tables and people's
tree layouts that again we all we can
ignore all of that in an in-memory
system because we're not going to
maintain that information yes
yeah so he's screaming it and he's
correct like does this mean at runtime
if I need to go read an old version I
have to go to the the Virgin Storm and
everything just serialize is a blob do I
pay a penalty for having to read that
yes but I think they measure it it's
kind of small
it's anything with a delta record if the
inroad Delta record I have to replay it
and may pay computational cost for that
but it's not as it's not as free as like
going reading and having everything
there I agree with you yes yeah that's
why we use Delta story in our own system
my most transactions
I remember that if they say the paper
motions actually don't update all
columns its write the Delta story is the
end reversion is usually gonna be enough
so this idea what they're doing is not
new this is actually very similar to how
Postgres was originally designed back in
like nineteen eighty six again Postgres
if there's a paper called the design of
Postgres and star maker talks about how
oh well the the log is not really a log
file it's a log table and everything's
it's getting a pendant of that and that
gets flushed out so at a high level this
this is very similar and they claim the
difference here is that this paper is
about taking a system that was not
designed to be multi version in this way
and adding this after the fact whereas
Postgres was designed from the very
beginning to be like this again Postgres
is an MVC system okay alright so so
again this is a this is this is a
protocol that takes advantage of the
fact that we're multi versioned so now
let's look at another blogging protocol
that is for Mme databases that's more
about how you could architect the system
to be aware of what the happens to the
CPU is actually work and how they
operate
so silo is a a memory OTP embedded
database engine that was developed out
of Harvard by Eddie Kohler
so it's not gonna be multi version it's
gonna be a single version system that
uses
and they're gonna use an epoch based
garbage collection protocol to keep
track of when you actually commit
transactions and flush things out the
disk so this is silo it's the same
people that developed the Mastry they
wrote mash to you first and they built
silo around it so the paper this paper
here is a proposes they made physical
doggy technique called silo R that is
gone if try to paralyze as much as
possible all the logging checkpoint and
recovery processes so that we get the
best best performance and the way
they're going to do this is that they're
going to disaggregate the log across
multiple files of court in which could
be stored on multiple discs and allow
them to be read in in parallel at the
same time so the way the way this works
is that for every single CPU socket in
my system I'm gonna have a dedicated
longer thread and dedicated log file
right and the idea here is that we want
to localize all the memory rights we
have to do to that our local socket so
we're never going over shared memory to
another another socket or the
interconnect and then that way that log
thread can be just you know pumping data
out as fast as possible to the log file
so now as transactions run they're gonna
get a log buffer from their local logger
thread and then write out just redo
information because we're in memory we
don't them do any undo and in this case
here there they are to make it simple
assume that all the log records for a
transaction will be written out actually
in this case you can do incremental but
in most cases it could be done all at
once alright so again I've already saved
some of this so every logger thoughts
gonna pull log buffers we hand them out
to our local worker threads that are on
the same socket as us when my buffer
gets full I hand it back to my logo
thread the logger thread can then start
writing it out the disk which means you
can do incremental flushes and then the
worker thread tries to get a new log
buffer if there's no more log buffers
available then the worker thread has to
stall until the logger thread comes back
and says you know he flashed out enough
here's a new log thread or log buffer so
now what is gonna happen though is that
because now our our log file is broken
up across multiple files on different
disks it may be the case our transaction
might modify data
it's managed by different CPU sockets
and therefore the log records for that
transaction might be broken up across
different disks so I need a way to
coordinate all of them so that I don't
have you know if I touch 2 log files
Mitra's action commits the first log
file gets flushed but the second one
doesn't and then I tell the outside
world that I crashed and I come back and
now the you know half the updates from
the other log file never made it to disk
so you need a way to coordinate all of
them so that you know that all the
updates per transaction have been safely
flushed so this is what the epochs gonna
do for us so what's gonna happen is
every so often I all the log the this
epoch will get incremented and that
forces every log thread right out there
the current contents of the log buffer
and then we record what was the epoch
everyone wrote at and now we know that
any transaction that has been committed
and and and flush to disk prior to that
epoch is now durable and we can tell the
outside world that we've committed
they're gonna use this epoch in other
ways in the system to minimize again
coordination across different CPU
sockets but for our purposes here we can
just focus on how we do it for logging
so our log records contain the idea of
the transaction that modified a given
tuple and silos gonna be do serializable
a serializable isolation or so
sterilizable scheduling so that means
that the the transaction ID will be
enough to guarantee the ordering the
correct ordering of the updates to the
database so if we just replay the log in
the order of the transaction IDs then
that will put us back into the correct
State at lower isolation levels you
can't do this because I I may update
something and you may read something and
update something else and the unless we
have a log secrets number to order those
things we may come back and replay
things in a different order so if by
being sterilized what we can guarantee
that this is this will Porter back to
the correct state yes
it isn't the snapshot isolation to
guarantee that the yeah if your first
writer wins and that also solves that
too but the main takeaway is that the
transaction T is enough to guarantee the
ordering to put you back in the correct
state and you don't need a separate log
seamless number because with a log
seamless number if a 90 corny that
across multiple sockets then that's a
that's a bottleneck so the log file is
gonna be a triplet just the table the
key and the value that gets modified and
the value can just be the Delta record
by of what the change actually was so
again in fact if I'm doing simple query
to update all the people that are lame
than that myself then the law of record
would be will have a separate log record
for every single tuple that this thing
modified alright alright so here's the
high-level architecture of the system
and again the idea here is that I'm
going to expose to you or show you that
hey you know this is just physical
logging so there's nothing really novel
being done here it's how they organize
the system that I think is actually
quite interesting and is I don't see
that I haven't seen any other system so
again the transactions can update or to
their worker threads or can execute
transactions so they're only going to
execute these things that store
procedures they call them once not
transactions but the basic idea is that
we do a request like an RPC say execute
this transaction and all the program
logical when that transactions going to
do is embed inside the system so we
never go back to the clients
everything's done in in one invocation
so when a transaction starts running the
worker thread has to go to the logger
and get a log buffer and once it has
that I can start filling up the changes
that's that it starts making to the
database and at some point this log
buffer will get full so we hand it back
to the log of thread and say this
thing's full please flush it for us and
we'll go ahead and get another log
buffer so then now at this point here
say that transactions still running
this other epoch thread waits up and
says all right now the new epoch is 200
so that's gonna force all the longer
threads in the system to now flush
whatever buffers that they have
including any ones that that were handed
off before so now the worker thread has
to hand back the log buffer
you to the logging friend and then it
could keep on running it could say now
give me another log buffer start filling
up but in this case here there aren't
any more so it's gonna have to stall and
wait so now the log our thread can start
flushing things out the disk right and
as it flushes them it frees up log space
and then we can hand back the log
buffers and let this guy keep on running
so in the most simplest world assume
every transaction will be finished
within epoch if it's if it spans multi
pox then you basically have to keep
track of like this transaction was
around it spans multi pox so you can go
back further in the logs when I figure
out what actually happened to it but the
main idea here is that by having the
this backpack Schurman pressure
mechanism where if we run out of log
buffers we don't allocate more memory we
make this guy stall that prevents us
from generating log records faster than
we can actually write them out the disk
because otherwise the log buffer just
grow infinitely and we'll run run out of
space so let's talk about this
persistent EVOC thing actually does so
every worker every logger threads can
have the CERN file or records all the
the Delta records that transactions are
generating when they run but then there
could be a special log file where we
keep track of the highs epoch that all
the log for all log or threads have
flushed out successfully to disk now
everyone is flushing at the same time
when the position when the epoch
increments you tell everyone to flush
but then they may not all happen exactly
at the same speed and only when everyone
says alright I flushed it then you go
update and update the persistent epoch
now you don't need this for correctness
this is actually just an optimization so
that when you crash you come back you
can just look at this one file and say
all right what's the epoch I need to
start with otherwise you'd have to go
look at every every single file to
figure out what's the you know in the
intersection of the epoch across all of
them this is just an optimization it's a
nice to have and the overhead out of it
is it's somewhat small other than an F
sync okay so we know that if this thing
gets written out the disk then we know
that any transaction that executed in an
epoch that's less than less than or
equal to our position epoch we know is
durable
so it looks like that say we have now
three logo threads right and each each
you have their own log file that running
up to disk and each you have a bunch of
worker threads and again these guys are
just going and getting the log buffers
from the logger threads and then you
have this now the special precision
epoch thread that's going to update the
file on disk every so often now the
epoch changes so everyone has has then
flush out all the changes they have up
to that epoch once they all then confirm
with this epoch thread the precision T
black thread that they've written out to
disk then we're allowed to go ahead and
write out the person T Bach file so for
this one I like I said you don't need
this for correctness this is just not
position so I don't think you actually
need this to be another F sink like
these do what you want to ask them to
know that you have to make the disk I
think for this one if you crash in s
sink now you have to execute if you're
gonna you rely on this to figure out
what the intersection is of the epoch
across all them you have to F sink right
that just you could beat another five
milliseconds yes what what ages they're
not checkpoints these are just log
records three more sites okay the
checkpoints yes but yes that's what
checkpoint sauce yes
this is just again the architecture here
is how to do test arrogated log files
across multiple disks and do you just
have some centralized location that you
only update whenever this thing gets
changed in the size of paper they do
this for every 40 milliseconds so in a
real system this is problematic because
if you need like sub-millisecond latency
of your transactions you're not gonna be
able get there with this you have to
crank this thing down when I asked why
they pick 40 milliseconds they said this
seems like a decent number right so you
could Ratchet it down so this thing is
updated every 10 milliseconds or five
milliseconds but now that you're
flushing a lot and this thing is getting
written out a lot and you now could
potentially have transactions that span
multiple epochs and you have to do more
stuff and recover to handle this
all right so now next slide we get to
your question so well talk about
checkpoints in a few more slides in more
detail but as he said if you don't have
checkpoints then these log files grow
forever and when I crash them and
restart I got to go back and potentially
look at the entire log file so every so
often they're gonna take a checkpoint
and then when you when you have to
recovery you load the last checkpoint in
and that sort of bounds how much the log
file you have to look at and they're
gonna rebuild the indexes based on the
checkpoint as I already said because
we're not gonna make any log records for
the indexes now what is gonna be
different though than a disk based
system which is super interesting is
that when they do recovery
instead of doing in the redo phase you
saw with acetyl server where they start
at some point in the past and they
process log records going forward in
time silo's guy actually can start at
the end of the log file and go in
reverse order and start playing blog
records from from newest to oldest and
again we can do this because we're in
memory because we know that there's no
dirty pages sitting around they got
loaded in from the last checkpoint
so as we replay the log we just need to
know that what should be the final state
of the of the database of a tuple in
order for me to say the data this has
but has been restored so if I have a
tuple of been updated 20 times if I'm
going to reverse order I don't need to
replay that log record for all those 20
updates I need to find the last update
and apply that all right that's totally
different then as you would do this in a
discarding system because again dirty
pages may have written a disk so at some
point I need I need I have to replay
everything and then undo everything that
shouldn't be around right so what
they're gonna keep track of the
transaction IDs and every two board to
keep track of what was the timestamp of
when this tuple got updated so ever as
I'm replaying the log immerse order if I
find a log record that has a timestamp
that's that's smaller than the current
to post time Stan meaning was updated by
transaction in the future that I
replayed earlier in the log then I can
just ignore that log record and I don't
want to apply it so maybe the case if
I'm only updating a small
of tuples over and over again my log I
may be able to realize that you know
within you know maybe the first megabyte
of a log record data I can ignore
everything else after that I still want
to look at it but I still don't the
replay it yes question this won't work
if it's not similar version if you don't
need the old versions that I think this
is okay and so you could say all right
well if I don't need the old versions
because well one is no transaction it's
not like after a restart any transaction
that was running prior to restart it's
not magically reappear when you come
back so there's no accurate run time
transactions with timestamps that could
possibly you read those things so I
could just ignore them now if I'm trying
to do audit logs or retain things new
time-travel queries then yes I got to
replay everything then yes this won't
work I still need to redo it but if I
don't care about its careful ways the
latest version then this works the
reason why most systems don't do this is
that when you do replication which I'll
talk about next class the replicas are
essentially like in recovery mode never
just replaying the log so if you do it
from oldest to newest then the same
mechanism you would do to do a blog
replay is the same thing you can do for
on the replicas if now I have a
specialized recovery mode where I can go
reverse order but only on the single
node then I have to have basically
re-implement this twice so the style is
the only system I know that does this
it's just it's interesting way to think
about it though which I like okay this
one way I think we've already talked
about right so we go we go look in the
persistent epoch file figure out what
the most the most recent persistent
epoch that was flushed to disk then as
our transit our log of threads start
replaying the log they just ignore
anything that's greater than this new
epoch and actually I already said this
all before that because we're going
newest to oldest if I recognize that the
tuple has already been modify
by transaction that came later in the
log that I've already processed then I
don't need to replay that log record
okay okay so now we also get to check
once in more detail as we already said
the log file can grow forever so that
means that I potentially at the replay
the entire log every single time at the
restart right if I have a one year's
worth of log without a check point then
I potentially take me one year to
restore the database which is nonsense
like nobody could do this so for an Mme
checkpoint the different approaches
we're going to choose are going to be
tightly coupled with our control scheme
and in some ways if we're focusing on a
mostly version systems MVCC then
checkpoints essentially can become easy
if we depending on how you know what we
want the consistency level to be in our
checkpoint right because it could just
be we just have a start a transaction
that takes a snapshot scans through a
table and we just write out all the
versions of the tuple that were visible
to our snapshot and anything that's not
visible to us meaning it came in the
future will let us we'll have the log
records and we just replay those all
right so there's a paper written by Dan
Abadi who did some early work on calm
source a few years ago in sigmod we
basically lays out what are the ideal
properties you'd want for a checkpoint a
schema in memory database system and
these sort of seem obvious but it's
important to keep these back of our mind
so obviously we don't want to slow down
the regular transaction processing
because it's not good if you know we can
run really fast and also me take a
checkpoint and now the speed of our
system is cut in by half so the
conventional wisdom for checkpoint
schemes is that about a ten to fifteen
percent overhead is considered
acceptable so every city every so often
if I'm taking a checkpoint if I get ten
percent slower then people are okay with
that likewise you don't want any sort of
huge latency spikes meaning I don't want
a blocking checking scheme I don't want
to block the system or lock a table
while I take the checkpoint I have all
these transactions field behind this and
then finally I release the lock and then
they're allowed to run because that's
gonna be a huge spike in our latency
and people people would pay attention to
this the last one also too is that we
don't want to acquire any excessive
memory overhead meaning ideally we don't
have to take you know a complete copy
the database in memory as we write down
a checkpoint right we want to be able to
minimize that overhead because that puts
pressure on on our games and many
bandwidth and our caches so we reduce
this as much as possible so let's talk
about the different properties you can
have for a checkpoint for any memory
database so this looks like this one
here is this idea here is very similar
to what we talked about for displaced
systems last semester so you have this
notion of fuzzy versus consistent
checkpoints so consistent checkpoint is
when the snapshot of the database that's
written a disk only contains updates
from transactions that committed again
think it's just like under MVCC with
snapshot isolation the the file I write
to disk only contains the the updates
from transactions that committed before
the transaction started so now when I
crash and restart when I load the
checkpoint in I don't like to worry
about as much as my checkpoint contain
changes from uncommitted transactions it
only contains changes for committed
transactions so again this is easy to do
with MVCC I've run run my query that
scans the entire table and write it out
the other approach to do fuzzy
checkpoints well this is where the
snapshot could contain updates from
transactions that committed after my
checkpoint started so my checkpoint
starts running and I have a transaction
that updates two to two tuples and say I
scan through half the table then the
transaction updates a tuple we've I've
already passed through but a tuple I
haven't passed through yet
my checkpoint now contain half the
updates of that transaction so now I
have to do some extra stuff when I come
back and recognize that oh there's an
update that I may have missed because
this guy was running one eyebrow when I
was running and I make sure I find the
log records to reapply things correctly
so this is the easiest to do right with
MVCC this one is potentially be faster
and have less memory overhead because
now I don't have to worry about
maintaining old versions and pausing the
garbage collector most I most systems
choose this this one has advantages for
storage overhead the next is how we're
actually going to do that the the the
checkpoint
so as I already said a do-it-yourself
implementation of this would be just a
scrunchy scan on the table and write out
every single tuple that I find that's
visible to me all right another approach
is to do an OS Fork so this idea is
interesting because when Mme database
when we call Fork in the operating
system what happens right we have a
child process what's in that child
process memory it's exact same things
the parent process all right
yes question yes the way it works is
there's copy-on-write so I call fork the
child process now has mapped in it's in
it's virtual memory table all the same
pages is the parent process but if the
parent process updates any of those
pages or if I my child process updates
into these pages then the OS will make a
copy of it and and remap it for your
process so as the parent process starts
modifying the in memory that the
database the child process won't see
this so the only sort of well known data
system that actually does this approach
is Redis so this is the rent out Redis
takes checkpoints and they can do this
because they're single threaded single
threaded engine so it is Paul's
transactions do the fork and then now
the child process can has a consistent
snapshot that it can start writing out
the disk right if you don't if you're
gonna allow it if you're not gonna pause
all transactions or updates while you do
this then in the child process you now
need to reconcile the database to remove
any uncommitted changes from
transactions that were running at the
time you before you forked so hyper
actually did this back in the day so
this is the paper from 2011 this is the
first version of hyper it was actually
influenced by a system that I was
working on or helped build a store which
then became Polti be so they basically
sort of built their own version of volte
be but they also wanted to do analytical
queries so they would do OS Fork and
then on the child process they could run
analytical queries without slowing down
the the parent process who was running
transactions and then they also could
then take the child process and write
out that check point to disk with the
game and without slowing down the
slow down the parent process execution
but because now when they took the
checkpoint but did the fork there might
even some in-flight transactions that
were running at the same time they men
in the child process you need to look at
the undo logs for those transactions
which are in memory and make sure you
reverse the database the reverse there's
changes so that again you have a
consistent snapshot and then after some
period of time either when the
checkpoint was written the disk or when
you finished processing you analytical
queries they would kill the child
process all the memory gets cleaned up
and then the parent would fork it again
so again Redis is the only one that does
this the it's easy to do because your
single threaded I don't know of any
other system other than hyper that has
attempted this when we try to do this in
each tool but we were based on the JVM
if you read the manual for the JVM and
says don't fork it we said screw that we
forked it anyway but it has also the
problems because like the carpet like
you have a bunch of zombie threads
because like the garbha collector
doesn't get doesn't start keep running
again other background things don't run
so it would work but it was a bad idea
okay the next issue is that what are we
actually gonna store in our checkpoint
ok the two approaches are do complete
checkpoints the Delta checkpoints
complete checkpoints just taking
whatever it's in my snapshot on my a my
on my table or my tables in my database
and there's write that up in the
mountain tirely out the disk the Delta
checkpoint is where you try to recognize
what what has changed since the last
time I took a checkpoint and only write
out those you know those updates
so most systems do this right the only
system that I know that does Delta
checkpoints is hecatomb right because
the issue is that with a complete
checkpoint from a sort of a sort of
administrative management standpoint I
had this file now on disk I can say oh
this is my checkpoint this is the exact
snapshot of the database at this given
time with the Delta checkpoint I need to
retain a bunch of deltas because there
may be some updates that were in this
snapshot but not the next snapshot and
in order for me to have make sure I put
the database back into the correct state
I need to have all of them
so when hackaton does this they have a
background thread that will start
coalescing combining these dr
checkpoints to make it basically one
giant complete checkpoint but you need
be mindful of this you know what the
following is that you're what the file
contains that you're looking at
so this is easier to implement a waste
more space but from it from from
engineering and a mansion point this
one's better one way to also to make
this not have a huge storage overhead
like if at my data base is one terabyte
and then in the LAT since the last
checkpoint update one megabyte this
thing stores one megabyte this stores
one terabyte over and over again if I
store the data uncompressed on a file
system that supports deduplication then
the pages of memory that I write out are
going to be duplicated over and over
again and the file system could cut
could could you know compress them down
for me so you can rely on things outside
that database to make this this thing
actually tenable alright the last one is
gonna be the frequency of how often
we're going to take a checkpoint again
we couldn't take a checkpoint all the
time but that could slow down the
regular transaction workload and so
typically what you do is either say I'm
gonna fire off the checkpoint at every
at a fixed interval like every five
minutes or I fire off a checkpoint after
I've written a certain amount of data to
my log file alright so in this case here
like this one you can bound how much
time he's gonna take for you to recover
like say if I crash all my database we
would come back in within five minutes
so I can take a checkpoint every every
four minutes so I know that when I crash
I only have at most four minutes of log
I need to replay to put me back in the
correct State this one you can sort of
do the math and figure out oh if I come
you know if I can replay the log at one
megabyte per second then if I set it so
that you know I take a checkpoint after
one hundred megabytes then I know I can
recover in a hundred seconds so they're
essentially the same thing it's just a
different way to think about the problem
and again some applications where you
know some applications where you maybe
don't care about things being super
highly available within a single node
they can use replicas to hide all this
so maybe you take a checkpoint at you
know at longer intervals or the longer
fall fall fall buffer sizes and so that
way if like if you have a replica if the
master crashes you can the replicas can
come up without having to recover the
log will cover that on on Wednesday the
other thing though we need to do which
every system has to do is that if the
data sent is told hey we're going to
shutdown then we want to take a
checkpoint at that moment of time we
acquiesce or to stop all the worker
threads let them finish whatever
transactions
running and then take a you know
complete snapshot a CLE check one of the
database right this is why you want to
tell the name is hey I want to shut down
don't just don't pass it you know you
kill - 9 and do a hard cig term you want
the database to be able to write things
out gracefully
right cuz otherwise it would if you do
this then you don't have to replay the
law because you know the database is in
the correct state so this is just a
quick summary of what other what some
Mme DV systems actually do right as I
said the systems in terms of what
direction you in a store are going to do
complete complete checkpoints only
hackaton is doing the is doing the the
Delta one and then what sort of
interesting to is like some of the MVC
systems like packet on and and mem
sequel are doing consistent check long
game which is just like snapshot
isolation juice camber anything out both
DB is not any system but they still have
some checkpoints because what happens is
when you say I want to take a checkpoint
they switch into this sort of
specialized two version or multi version
system right where you just have the
version of a tuple that existed at the
checkpoint and then you just have
another version that's always the the
latest version you can't you don't have
any have version change other than you
only have two versions so that's how
they would do consistent checkpoints
alta base can actually do fuzzy and
consistent checkpoints I think they do
the same thing under x ten we're like if
I'm shutting down I'll do a consistent
blocking checkpoint but otherwise I'd
know me take a fuzzy checkpoint all
right Ahana does fuzzy with time-based
again different database systems do
different things
if you're doing nbcc than my opinion
doing the consistent checkpoint and
taking a pleat snapshot is the way to go
there's less engineering overhead of
figuring out what they actually write
out you just scan through and write
everything so any questions about check
once again after restart I load the
checkpoint in and as I scan the
checkpoint I'm copying data into my
tables and as I do that it's essentially
like an insert I update any indexes that
are on that table so that that way they
get they get pop populated correctly and
then once that all that's done now that
is back online yes question is with the
four thing the index are to get copied
depends on implementation you don't have
to right yeah yeah so for yes all the
indexes get copied we know how to you
don't have to write all right it spy it
again it's a waste of space my indexes
are huge it's not worth the disk IO to
write that out if I'm gonna repopulate
it anyway on recovery right that trade
up teen computation and and and and
storage all right so the last thing I
want to talk about very quickly is how
to do fast restarts so everything I
talked about so far that the the crash
recovery for silo and sequel server and
all the checkpoint stuff this is assumed
that oh well our system was operating
all right systems running something
happened somebody tripped over the power
cord lightning struck the data center
and we did a hard crash it was
unexpected right but there's other times
we actually may need to restart the
database system it's not gonna be from a
crash right very commonly maybe we have
to update our les libraries there's a
technique in Linux called K splice
allows you to update kernels without
hundred restart the system but let's say
you can't always do that sometimes you
have to restart the whole whole OS
certainly you're gonna upgrade the
hardware some discs are swappable but
dims I don't think are like you have to
turn the system off put the new games in
or certainly if you're moving to another
AWS instance that's a whole another
piece of hardware and then sometimes you
just want to update the data system
software again Oracle has techniques
that allow you to do patching without
taking everything offline but most
systems don't have that so let's say we
want to do this one here all right for
the zoom these ones here we have to
restart there's no way to get around
this but in start restart the entire box
for this one here though we don't have
to restart the us we don't have to
restart the hardware so the interesting
to see away if we can restart the system
and it for an in-memory database and not
have to flush a checkpoint out the disk
and then load it all back in over and
over again so this is what Facebook can
do in their scuba system so I'll briefly
talk about what scuba is in a second but
like you
from the introduction class we spent a
whole you know this is what this is what
the students voted for the most
interesting system they want me to talk
about so scuba is a it's a distributed
in memory OLAP system developed at
Facebook to do event log processing so
whenever you load a page in Facebook
they're going to keep track of about
every single stage every single service
it touches for that request record all
the information and then dump it off the
scuba so you can do analytics and say
find me the you know explain to me why
my page requests 120 percent slower than
then yesterday right because they're
pushing out updates all the time for
further through the web apps they want
to know whether things are regressing so
what they're going to do though is that
when they want to update the the
database system software that instead of
shutting it down and taking checkpoint
and loading it all back in they're gonna
write out the contents of the database
essentially the checkpoint to shared
memory restart that the process come
back up see that my database state is
now in shared memory and suck it all
back in they're essentially using shared
memory as like as like a ram disk which
is kind of interesting so you know I've
already said this it's a distributed
Emery's in my system it has a
heterogenous architecture with leaf
nodes and aggregator nodes this is not
too interesting for us but just the
thing to be mindful is the state of the
database is only at these leaf nodes
here right the aggregator nodes and the
root node up above these are stateless
and there's combining results of queries
that these guys are they generate so all
the updates inserting new data goes to
these leaf nodes so this is the primary
search location so if we want to restart
these guys we need a way to can shred
this out the shared memories so we don't
the load the check on foo disk as a high
level the way it works is that if I have
a query like this they're gonna play
come to plan fragments and say this guy
goes down these guys are all gonna send
their updates off and then we just
combine it together to reach the final
answer this is actually basically how
men sequel work said well thangkas the
story goes the guy that founded mem
sequel he was at Microsoft all the
Hecate on project bard some of their I
was inspired by their ideas went to
Facebook
Deana I don't think he's old-school but
he saw this this patterns used in other
systems at Facebook saw this idea and
then combined together to make them
sequel alright so there's two approaches
to do this
so the we've already said this we could
just do the shared memory heaps so that
we could just in our system we modify
the memory allocator such that whenever
we call malloc for that for the data
we're storing in the in the table
instead of being local to my process now
it's sitting in shared memory as far as
you know there's no overhead in the OSF
saying something is in shared memory
because it's just getting back a memory
address the u.s. knows that it's just
the that memory should last beyond the
process lifetime so to do this though
again you have to modify J email or TC
malloc we're never to malloc
implementation you're using to be able
to write things out to shared memory and
be able to divide things up efficiently
so that multiple threads meet writing to
the same location so in the paper they
talk about how they can't do lazy
allocation of backing pages and shared
memory meaning if I call malloc and
something the shared memory the OS is
actually need to have that backed by
physical memory so they claim this in
the paper they Facebook bought the guy
or a B hired the guy that that that that
created je malloc so in the paper you'll
have what how they talk to the GE
Malachi he says you can't do this I
posted this on Twitter or at least the
slides for this on Twitter and then some
dude reached out to me and said you
actually could do this like he actually
tried it and in at least in the newer
versions of Linux that you could do you
could allocate memory shared memory and
not have it backed by a physical memory
right away so this part is actually not
true anymore
so you actually could still do it this
way so you could have your memory
allocator allocate pages on the heap and
shared memory and not worry about any
thread safety issues or backing it right
away but instead what they're gonna do
in this version of scuba is that when
I'm told my process is going to shut
down I stop all updates from any
transactions any queries write
everything out to shared memory and then
I go ahead and restart and so they do
some extra
that where they keep track of what's the
layout of that memory that they're
running out to shared memory like what's
the version that the atavism they wrote
about so that if you restart and come
back
and you recognize oh I have some shared
memory contents of the database from
what it was before I've restarted did he
make sure that the layout is still
correct so they basically maintain some
extra metadata and when they run out to
shared memory to say oh by the way my
layout looks like this and this version
so if I come back and it's incompatible
then I just load it back up from desk so
scuba is interesting system because in
their world this this is not high-value
data right it's not like your timeline
or all your whatever your friend
messaging crap like they it's data that
they could potentially lose they don't
want to but it's not like they lose
money if this goes away so ideally if
they you know say a node comes back and
there's nothing on disk but the shared
memory sorry the the database system
comes back there's nothing on disk
everything's in shared memory but the
shared memory data is not compatible
with our new version of our software
then they'll just backfill it from from
another disk for some results in their
world that that's okay so I like this
idea I don't know if anybody else does
this with shared memory the most famous
shared memory system is Postgres but
they're obviously not in memory and
they're doing this to coordinate across
different processes this is like this is
now this is interesting idea to think
about because it's it's passing data
from one instance of the process to the
next even though they don't actually
overlap in time they're allowing the
memory of the database go beyond the
lifetime of the data system process
itself cuz I find super fascinating any
questions about this again if my
database is one terabyte if I don't have
this technique and I restart the
database then I gotta suck in one
terabyte off a disk which could be slow
but in this case here I could come back
and instantaneously have everything that
I that I need okay all right so just to
finish up the main takeaways from this
is that physical logging is probably the
best approach you would want to use for
an in-memory data is that and it's gonna
support all possible contextual schemes
there are some advantages we can we can
take up take things we take advantage of
if we're using MVCC like doing the copy
on updates to get consistent checkpoints
by just you know relying on the idea of
snaps
isolation to only see changes from
transactions that have already committed
and as I'll talk about at the end of the
semester non-volatile memory is here it
is going to change how we want to do
some of these login upfront protocols
but the the high-level idea will still
roughly be the same that we don't need
to maybe restore or don't even log any
undo information if we're careful where
we store our data then we only need to
keep track of renew information and that
makes the law of replay much faster okay
all right so next class we'll talk about
networking protocols and I don't have a
list of here but we'll also introduce
project to I'll post this on Piazza you
guys should start thinking about how to
form groups of 3 because that's projects
project you will be a group project ok
if you can't find a group to be in send
me an email and we'll figure out
something for you ok I forget how many
students are in the class I don't think
many lore drops through we should have
enough to do exactly 3 I think 13 groups
are 3 or something like that ok
yes that's B 3 ok so make friends and
again and whoever you servers in your
group for project three well I'm sorry
project 2 will also be in the same group
for project three so if someone is like
a hygiene problems you know if you you
know if you can't stand run project 2
then you have to give one the project 3
and that's not gonna be good ok and I
five to break up fights I don't know 4
and I can do it again which ideally
don't want to do this ok any questions
Bank it in the side park what is this
some old fools hey yo real
[Music]
ain't with that here called the
whole it cuz I mochi ice cube down with
the testy hi you look and it was go grab
me a forty just to get my buzz song cuz
I need it just a little more kick
[Music]
there's a nice and my hood won't be to
say I'm nice to take a say I celebrate