[Music]
okay guys let's get started again Thank
You DJ drop tables always always always
keep it down
how's your mixtape going oh it's going
we'll release it at the end of okay and
it's all it's all like DJ drop table
beats
oh nothing but you and like your own
stuff okay alright so let's get started
it's a beautiful day out and I think
that's why the turnout here so low which
sucks cuz my every lecture is all so
much here but this one I like a lot to
be before we get into the course
material just to discuss real quickly
what's on the schedule for you guys
project one is due this Friday at
midnight and again you should submit
that on great scope homework 2 is due on
Monday at midnight also spindle grade
scope so we'll send an announcement out
on Piazza but we've updated the PDF so
that you could drop the pictures in
right into the the PDF so you spitting
that know so we give you a template for
draw IO so it's an online tool to go
quickly edit and modify the templates
for your answers
so should we know handwritten drawings
and no photographs of like drawings that
everything should be done digitally and
then we'll be releasing project two on
on this Monday as well and that'll II do
think two or three weeks in October okay
so any high-level questions about the
project or homework - okay so let's get
into so the thing we need to talk about
now is that we spent the last three
classes talking about data structures
we'd spend down hash tables and spent
two days on B plus trees radix trees and
other tree data structures so for the
most part during this entire
conversation when we talk about these
data structures we've assumed that the
that they were only being accessed by a
single thread but there was only one
thread that could be reading and writing
data to the data structure at a time and
that simplified this part of the
discussion and so that you just underst
what's the core essence of how these
data structures work but in a real
system we obviously don't want to just
have a single thread be you know only
accessing the data structure at a time
we would allow multiple threads because
a modern CPUs there's a lot of CPU cores
so therefore we can have multiple
threads running queries and all updating
our data structures but also don't allow
this the high disk stalls due to you
know or stalls due to having to go read
read things from disk because now if one
thread is doing something and it reads a
page that's not in memory it has to get
stalled while the buffer pool manager
brings that in and then we can let other
threads keep running at the same time so
we're have a lot of threads running in
our system and we do this because that
maximizes parallelism or maximizes the
reduces the latency for the queries you
want to execute so for today we're now
talked about up now we bring back
multiple threads and want to update and
access our data structure what do we
need to do to protect ourselves so let's
say is it a quick aside so everything
that we'll talk about today is what how
most database systems actually work most
database systems that support multiple
threads will do the things that we're
talking about today doing this latching
stuff there are some particular systems
that actually don't do any of this and
only the owl single threads has to
access the data structures and they
still get really good performance so
volte B and Redis applied two miscreants
one set dips so in case the Redis Redis
only runs in one thread it's a one
threaded engine in both DB it's a
multi-threaded engine but they partition
the database in such a way that every B+
tree can only be accessed by a single
thread so you avoid all this latching
stuff that we talked about today and you
get really great performance but
obviously this means that it complicates
scaling up to multiple cores or multiple
machines but again we'll talk I'll just
talk about these things later on in the
semester but the main idea now is that
everybody pretty much does this thing
things that we're talking about so the
way we're going to protect our data
structures is through a control protocol
a control scheme and this is just the
the method in which the database system
guarantees the correctness of the of the
data structure by enforcing all the
threads to access the data structures
and using a certain protocol or sort of
certain way and so I'm putting the the
word correct in quotes because that can
mean about mean different things
and the kind of things were talking
about they're accessing although we've
been focused on data structures but it
really could be for any sugared shared
object in the system right it could be
for two-pole could be for an index could
be for the page table and in the buffer
pool it doesn't matter so the two types
of correctness we care about in converge
hole are logical correctness and
physical correctness so logical
correctness would be like a high level
thing that says if I'm accessing the
data structure am i seeing the values or
am I seeing the things that I expect to
see so if I have a B+ tree index I
insert the key five my thread that
thread comes back and reads key five
right away it should see it where I
should not get a should not get a false
negative but that's a logical
correctness thing that I'm seeing the
things I that I expect to see the thing
that we're gonna care about this class
is physical correctness but how do we
protect the internal representation of
the data structure of how it maintains
pointers and references to other pages
and keys and values how do we make sure
that as threads are reading writing this
data that the integrity of the data
structure is sound so it's able to be we
don't want the case where we're falling
down traversing into the B+ tree and
when we jump to the next node we have a
pointer to that and then by the time we
read the pointer figure out where we
need to go and then then try to jump
there somebody else modifies the data
structure well now that pointer is
pointing to a an invalid memory location
and we would get a seg fault so this is
what we're trying to do today we're
trying to protect the internal data
structure to allow multiple threads read
and write to it and that they still that
the data structure is is behaving
correctly for the logical correctness
we'll worry about this more when we talk
about transactions and current reach all
right this is a whole another engine
super interesting topic but for today we
say you know happy make sure that the
data structures are thread safe so we'll
begin by talking about what is actually
a latch they're a bit more detailed than
we then we talked about so far and how
it's actually implemented and then we'll
start off with an easy case of actually
doing thread safe hash tables using
latches for those because that they're
actually really simple to do but then
we'll spend most time talking about how
to handle sin B plus trees and what's
talking how do leaf node scans and other
optimizations again when we have
multiple threads accessing things
same time yeah all right so I showed
this slide last time and I don't think
everyone you know we only talked about
very briefly and I don't think everyone
absorbed its on it I want to send more
time talking about the difference
between locks and latches so in the
database world where I live a lock is a
higher level concept that protects the
logical contents of the database so a
logical content would be like a tuple or
a set of tuples or a table a database
and we're having using these locks to
protect these logical objects from other
transactions that are running at the
same time like if I'm modifying
something in a transaction and so I
don't want anybody else to modify that
that tuple at the same time that I am
right you may for other reasons but for
our purposes assume that we don't want
that to happen so for these locks we're
gonna hold them for the entire duration
of the transaction again that's not
entirely true but again for our purposes
just assume that's the case and then we
need to be able to roll back any changes
we make to our to the objects we modify
if we hold the locks for them so if I'm
trying to transfer money from my account
to her account if I take the money out
of my account and then I crash before I
put the money in her account when I come
back I want to reverse that change I
made to my tuple so these so in that
means the daily system is responsible
for knowing how to roll back these
changes so notice up here I didn't say
anything about threads or I'm talking my
transactions so a single transaction
could be could be broken across multiple
threads and they could all be updating
the same tuple that's okay that's
allowed because the transaction holds
the lock it doesn't matter what thread
that that's actually doing the
modification where we get down to the
low level constructs that we care about
protecting the physical the physical
integrity of our data structures or the
objects is latches so in the operating
system world they this is what they call
locks of mutexes in our world there's
latches because we need to distinguish
them from locks so latches are going to
protect the critical sections of the
database systems internal data
structures from other threads that are
reading right into that data structure
or that object at the same time so we're
only hole
latch for a short period just for the
duration that were in the critical
section to do whatever operation that we
need to do I want to update a page I
hold the latch on that page make the
change then release the latch we don't
need to be able to roll back any changes
here because the opposite of the
operations we're trying to do are
essentially meant to be atomic so I hope
I grabbed a latch from something I make
whatever change I want and then when I
when I release the latch then the
operations considered done so all the
changes are there if I can't acquire the
latch then I'm not gonna do the
operation anyway so there's nothing to
rollback so another way to think about
this is this great table from the that
that B+ tree book I recommended a few
lectures ago from Gert scrappy we has
this nice table that lays out again the
distinction between locks and latches so
four locks we're gonna separate user
transactions from each other and they're
gonna be protecting the bidets contents
tuples tables things like that and we're
gonna hold them for the entire duration
of the transaction there's gonna be a
bunch of different lock types that we
can help
hold on these objects again we'll cover
this in a few more lectures and then
when it comes time to actually dealing
with dead locks
we're gonna rely on some external
coordinator a lock manager or
transaction manager to resolve any dud
locks that that could occur and the
methods we can use are waits for timeout
sub or some other things and what we'll
focus on these later what we care about
is over here we have these latches
they're gonna protect threads from each
other for our in-memory data structures
we're gonna protect the critical
sections inside these data structures
there's only going to be two lock modes
read and write and the way we're going
to avoid deadlocks is to us being good
good programmers which is nice for
databases good equals expensive right so
it's up for us to make sure that we
write high-quality code in our data
structures to avoid deadlocks because
there is no external thing like a
transaction manager or lock manager
that's going to rescue us if we have a
deadlock it's all for us to design and
implement our data structure in such a
way that deadlocks cannot occur and
we'll see what that looks like later on
so again our focus is on here we'll
discuss all this lock stuff in lecture 7
after the midterm again I find all the
super pass men but this this is this is
like this is like one but the the black
arts of database systems if you can you
know actually make this stuff work all
right so let's talk about the latch
modes work for that we can have again
there's only two modes read and write so
a latch the latch is being held in read
mode then multiple threads are allowed
to share that read latch right because
again it's a read-only operation so I
can have multiple threads read the data
structure at the same time there's no
conflict there's no integrity issues
that could occur so they can all share
share that if I take out the latch and
write mode then I can only that's an
exclusive latch only one thread can hold
that latch in that mode at a time so if
I hold it right latch I'm making changes
nobody else can read that object that
I'm protecting until I finish all right
the only two modes we care about think
of this is like again multiple threats
we share this one this is this is an
exclusive latch all right so let's talk
actually how you implement a latch in a
Braille system so the first approach is
PI the one you're most familiar with you
know when you take any kind of systems
course or operating system course is a
blocking operating system mutex and
blocking OS mutex so this is the
simplest thing to use because it's sort
of built into the language like it like
in C++ the standard template library has
this thing STD mutex and it's really
simple to use you just declare it then
you call lock do something what you know
on your the object you're protecting
with it and then you call unlock and
you're done right so does anybody know
how this actually works in the operating
system in least some Linux how did the
mutex like this work yes
he says few texts what is a few texts
what's that he said well so he said few
texts he's correct in Linux few tech
stands for fast user space mutex the way
it works is that there is the in user
space meaning in the address space of
your process there'll be a memory
location that has you know a like a bit
usually a byte or so but I'll have a
memory location that you can then try to
do a compare and swap on to to acquire
that that
latch but then what happens is if you
don't acquire it then you fall back to
the the slower default mutex where that
goes down into the operating system so
the idea is you do a quick compare and
swap and in userspace
if you acquire it you're done if you
don't acquire it then you fall down to
vos
which is gonna be slower because what
happens is if you go down vos and sit on
a mutex inside side the kernel then the
OSS aha well I know you're blocked on
this mutex and you can't get it so let
me tell the scheduler to D schedule so
you don't actually run and the reason
why this is expensive because now the OS
has its own internal data structures
that is protecting with latches so
you've got to go update now the
discussion table to say this this
process of this thread can't run yet so
he's correct fast user-space mutex is
will be fast cuz that's just a spin-spin
latch we'll talk about the next slide
but he fall down to us then then then
you're screwed so this is another great
example were like we were trying to
avoid the OS much as possible for the
first project you guys use this because
it's fine but if you have a high
contention system then everybody is
going down to the OS and that's that's
gonna be a problematic so the
alternative is to implement ourselves
using a spin latch or test and set spin
latch so this is extremely an extremely
efficient it's super fast because on
modern CPUs there's a single instruction
there's an instruction to do a single
compare and swap on a memory dress I
think it just like I check to see
whether the value of this memory address
is what I think it is and if it is then
I'm allowed to change it to my new value
so think of like the latch is set to 0 I
check to see whether it's 0 and if it is
then I said at the 1 and that means I've
acquired a latch and you can do that a
modern CPUs and interesting single
instruction right you don't have to have
you don't the write C code like if this
then that it does it all for you so the
way even implement this is in C++ is
that you had this atomic keyword which
is templated you can put whatever you
want there but they have a shortcut for
you called atomic flag which is just an
alias for atomic pool and so inside this
now it will when we want to acquire this
latch we have to have this while loop
that says test and set the latch if I
acquire it then I jump out of the the
wild they're gonna because I hold the
latch if I don't fall into the wild loop
and now
it has some logic to figure out what
should we do the simplest thing is just
say all right let me just retry again
loop back around and keep trying it
right the problem with that is though
that's just me burning out your seat
you're not burning out literally but you
just burning cycles and your CPU because
you just keep trying to test that set
test and set test the set and it's
always gonna fail and you keep spinning
around and in this infinite loop so this
to the OS thinks you're actually doing
useful work because it doesn't know what
instructions you're executing so it says
you keep executing instructions let me
keep scheduling you and you're to spike
the CPU so this this test and set thing
is the same thing he said before about
the fast user mutex this is the same
thing the OS provides you in the Linux
standard or the STD mutex on Linux but
maybe I don't want to burn my cycles but
he's keep me trying maybe I want to
yield back to the OS get D schedule and
let it schedule some other thread or
maybe I try a thousand times and I'm
saying I'm not gonna get this and I just
up work so this is a good example of
where we as the database systems
developers we can be smart or we can we
come to the our implementation however
using latches and our data structures to
be mindful or try to accommodate what we
think the workloads gonna look like if I
think that this latch has to be like
whatever the operation I'm doing the
latches to be super fast then it's PI
faster for me to just keep retrying
because whoever holds the latch will
give it up real quickly but if I think
the operation is going to be super long
then maybe I want to yield or for some
amount of time or eventually abort we
can't do this in the blocking us mutex
soon as we try to get it we can't get it
the OS takes over and we're blocked yes
the questions what is this this oh this
yeah like the primers would be like it's
compare-and-swap it says at this memory
address check to see whether the value
is this like passing a zero if it if it
equals zero then set it to one right and
then there's different there's different
API sometimes you'll get back the old
value you'll get back a true whether
it's exceeded there's a bunch different
things and then they have they have
tested sets for you know for all the
different types you could you could be
based on
so again the main takeaway here is that
again we we in the data system can do a
better job than the OS because we would
know in what context we be using this
latch so for these two examples though
the latch has just been you know do I
hold it or not as I said before we have
we have different modes so we need a
reader writer latch that can support we
have these different notes the way we
basically do this and we build on top of
whatever our basic latching primitive we
have either the spin latch or the POS
mutex and then we manage different
queues to keep track of how many threads
are waiting acquired to different types
of latches right so it may be just
mentioned some counters to say here's
the number of threads that help hold the
latch in this mode here's the number of
threads that are waiting for it so if a
rethread shows up and says I want to get
the read latch well I look over here and
say nobody nobody holds the right latch
and nobody is waiting for it so I go
ahead and and hand it out and I update
my counter to say I have one one thread
that that's uh that holds this latch
another threat comes along and once also
quite a real a CH again Reed latches are
compatible or making me shared so we
just recognize that this guy already
holds the reed latch so this guy can
also acquire it and we just update our
counter so now the writer writer thread
comes along what's the right latch it
has to stall because the because the
read latch is being held by other
threads and so we just add our counter
here to say that we're waiting for this
so now if a read thread comes along and
wants the read latch what should happen
right so you guys depends on what policy
were using we could just immediately let
the say uh read latches already is
already being held go ahead and also
acquire it but that could lead to
starvation because the right on the
right thread will never get to it so in
this example here we could just stall it
add it to the counter say we're waiting
for this and then eventually when the
first two guys at least the latches the
writer thread will get the latch again
this depends what policy we want to use
depends on in what context we the the
latch is is being used
right if it's a if it's a if it's a data
structure where there's not many rights
but the rights are really important then
we want to give higher priority to the
right of threads okay and again we just
build on top of our the data structures
that are that the latching primitives
that I showed before to implement
something like this and you can still do
this you still depending on how you
organize the memory you can still do
this
most of the operations on this
atomically okay all right so let's now
see how we take these latches and
actually do something with them so the
first thing is as I said well first talk
about do hash tables because this is
actually super easy to do and the reason
why it's super easy to do is because the
ways in which threads can interact with
our hash table is is limited meaning we
probe into a for this one assuming we're
doing like the static hashing table the
extendable linear stuff that dynamic
ones they're a bit more complicated but
the the same principles apply here but
today in a linear probing hashing table
Mikey shows up I just hash it I jump to
some slot and then I just scan down in
sequential order on the hash table try
find a thing I'm looking what I'm
looking for and everybody every other
thread is doing the same thing they're
always scanning top to bottom eventually
reach the bottom and loop back around
but you think of that is just a circular
buffer where you're essentially always
scanning down so in this case here
deadlocks aren't possible because
everybody is going in the same direction
nobody's coming up in the other way and
they hold a latch it up that I want and
it holds a latch that I want like you
can't you can't have a deadlock so this
makes it super super simple so for an
out it's a resize that pay the table
this one we just take a global latch on
the usually in the header page that just
prevents anybody else from from reading
and writing the table until I complete
the the resizing but again that's if we
size our table a large enough to in the
very beginning like this is a rare
occurrence most of the time we're doing
you know probes or insertions and
that'll be fast deletions also
complicate this too if you want to do
compaction or move data around but for
that we can just ignore
so the two approaches to do this will
differ on the granularity of the latches
so the first approach you just have at a
on each page you just have a single
reader/writer latch and so when a thread
wants to do something you know do a
lookup before it can read the page or
access it it has to acquire the right
latch for that page the other approach
is be more fine-grain latching where you
have a latch for every single slot so
that means as you're scanning down you
can you acquire the next slots latch and
then you go into it and then do it look
for whatever whatever you're looking for
so there's this trade-off between the
computation the storage overhead between
these two approaches because the the
page latch we have to store less latches
there's only one per page but now this
can potentially reduce our parallelism
because I can't have two you know even
though two threads might be operating on
different slots because it's in the same
page they can't run at the same time in
the case of having a latch per slot it's
gonna lob for more parallelism because
the latches are more fine-grain but now
I'm storing more latches in every single
slot and now it's also more expensive to
you know - keep quiet ease latches as
I'm scanning through because I'm doing
it for every single slot that I'm
looking at so let's let's look at some
high-level example so first one would be
page latches so again say we have a
simple three to three page table that
has two slots per page and so the first
thread wants to find D and say D hashes
to this this position here this slot so
before I can go look inside of it to see
whether the thing I want is there I
first have to get the read latch on it
and then once I have that now my cursor
can start looking at it now let's say
another thread comes along and they want
to insert E and E wants to hash to where
C is can it do that can actually start
looking at it no right because because
it wants to take a write latch on this
page because it doesn't know that C is
is full it doesn't know it's gonna have
to scan but so before they can even look
at it
it needs the right latch the right latch
is not compatible to read latch so it
has to stall and wait so the first guy
scans down he looks at C and now he
needs to go look at this next page here
and again the way we figure out what
page you look at
is we just look you know we look in our
the header for the hash table and the
headers gonna say here's all the pages
that you're looking for but logically
they're order sequentially right so like
page zero page 1 page 2 so you look in
the header and say where do I find page
2 for my hash table and so in order to
do this traversal when I want to go from
from page 1 to page 2 I actually don't
need to hold the latch on one in order
for me to jump down to 2 because my hash
tables static I'm not resizing so this
location is always gonna be the same so
I can immediately release the latch
before I jump to this and allow anybody
else to keep running and then I can go
ahead and quire the latch for this this
is gonna be different when we talk about
B plus trees B plus trees you have to
hold a latch on whatever node you're
coming from before you jump to the next
node and it's only when you get to the
next row do you then release the one
behind you yes yeah so he's so he
proposed an optimization where in this
case here for thread thread 2 instead of
trying to acquire require a write latch
could I just require a read latch figure
out whether the thing I actually want
would be there or not and then if it is
then I go back and try to acquire the
write latch or I just jump down here and
say you know do the same thing because I
know it's the thing I'm look for is not
here if there's no delete to know
movement yes we'll talk the same
technique when we apply for B plus trees
I'm doing it that sort of the the naive
way but yes you can actually do that in
general you don't do you you don't
really do latch upgrades you can't say
I'm in read mode now put me in write
mode you release the latch and then in
one mode and put and get acquired again
another another another mode all right
so this guy Gavriel at she can start
reading this now this guy gets the right
latch it sees that sees not what a once
so wants to scan down here and this time
t1 has gone away so can go ahead and be
the right latch see that the thing
there's this slots occupied come down
here and do the insert again it's more
coarse-grained because only one thread
can be inside if they're doing if the
the latch mode conflict was only one
thread at a time to be
side the the table but it makes it more
simple to actually choir these latches I
don't not acquiring latches every single
one so let's let's see how to do it in
which slot latches so again t1 starts it
wants to do find D it hashes to where a
is so it acquires the read latch on a
and then t t2 starts it wants to do a
right so acquires the right latch on C
and at this point when t1 starts up
again and tries to look at this it can't
run because you can't get that latch
whereas so he has to stall whereas this
other thread can keep going down here
and then now this guy can then pick up
me and keep going behind it alright so
then eventually it has to stall too
because they can't go here this guy
moves on does his insert and then this
guy can then proceed right so we can do
the exact same optimization that he said
and we'll see this in content sippy +
tree I could escape T key real a chance
try find the spot that I want and then I
try to acquire the real s what I want
but I do have to handle the case or I do
take the read latch see this is the spot
I want to go then I release the real a
CH then come back and try to take the
right latch and in between that time
somebody might have inserted something
in my slot and then I need then I need
to be able to handle that and keep
scanning down below so just that
technique works with blue sector stuff
you have to do so again the main
takeaway I want to get from all this
there can't be a deadlock because
everyone's scanning from the top to the
bottom that makes our life easier
there's nobody else coming in the other
direction so that's why also - we can
just release the latches before we jump
to the next one because we're not
worried about the location of the page
we're W changing okay alright so let's
talk about more complicated things let's
talk we had to do this in a B+ tree so
again we want to have multiple threads
running at the same time and then we
allow them to redo reads and writes
without having to lock the or latch the
entire tree or during that duration of
the operation so the two things we need
to handle in our B+ tree to make them
thread safe is that we need to handle
the case where two threads are trying to
modify the same node at the same time
and then we need to handle the case
where one thread might be traversing the
tree and then down below it before it
gets to the leaf node
another thread does a modification that
causes a split and emerge and now the
location of a page may end up a node may
end up getting moved around and the data
I'm looking for is not there or in worst
case scenario I have a pointer to now
and in memory an invalid memory location
so let's look at high-level example here
so we're gonna focus on this side of the
tree I'm just labeled in ABCDE and then
so forth on the leaf nodes so say we
want to do a delete on on 44 down to the
bottom so the first threads going to
start at the top again we just do the
traversal we talked about so far we look
at the separator keys we figure out
whether or you want to go left and right
and we move down to the child node based
on that so then we may get down to this
leaf node here and we can go ahead and
delete our entry but now we see that our
node is less than half-full in this case
it's entirely empty so therefore we have
to rebalance and so we're gonna want to
in this case here instead of doing a
merge we'll just copy over a key from
one of our siblings but let's say before
we can do that rebalancing the OS swaps
out our thread I and we get stall it and
now another thread start running and
that other thread wants to do a lookup
to try to find key 41 right down here at
the bottom so that does the same thing
it starts traversing the tree and then
it gets down to this point here and it
looks at the separator keys and figures
out oh I want to go to this node but
then it get it Bo stalls this switches
back to our first thread and the first
rad moves 41 over and then now when my
other thread starts up running again I
get down here and the thing that I
thought was there is no longer there
right so that so best-case scenario this
is just you know we got a false negative
here we thought key 41 does exist but
the index told us it didn't exist that
all the anomalies or issues were talked
about today at the best-case scenario
worst-case scenario was this node got
moved around and then now this pointer
pointed to nothing and we went and we
would get a seg fault in a program a
crash so the way we're gonna handle this
is the classic technique called latch
crabbing or latch coupling when I you
know when I was a young lad when I was
taught databases
I would be game I was told the term was
called lat crabbing
I don't know what the textbook actually
uses but the Wikipedia I think calls a
lot latch coupling it's all the same
concept same thing so lats crabbing is a
technique that allows multiple threads
to access the the B plus tree at the
same time and we're to protect things
using latches so the basic idea the way
this works is that anytime we're at a
node we have to have a latch on that
node being in right mode or read mode
and then before we can jump to our child
we got to get the latch on our child the
next the next node we're gonna we're
gonna go to and then when we land on
that on that child we can then examine
its contents and if we determine that
the child node we just moved to is safe
then it's okay for us to release the
latch on our parent and so the term let
crabbing sort of has to do with the way
like crabs walk like moving one leg past
another that's how we're going to
acquire latches as we go down so our
definition of safe is one where if we're
doing a modification the the node we're
sitting at will not have to do a split
or merge no matter what happens below it
in the tree so that means that it's
either not completely full if we're
trying to insert we have room to
accommodate any key that may come up to
us or any key that we're inserting and
then if we were doing a delete we know
that it's more it's more than half-full
meaning we have to delete a key we're
not gonna have to do a merge all right
so again the basic protocol worked like
this at the very root you acquire the
right latch you need so in the case
we're doing a fine it's all read latches
all the way down again every single time
we we get to the next node we release
the latch on that parent hood where we
came from okay again we're not making
any modifications so every every node is
deemed safe for inserts and deletes we
start off with getting right latches all
the way down and then please we
recognize that the node we're at is
considered safe we can release any right
latch we have up above in the tree
because again no matter what has below
us they would not be affected they would
not have to get changed so let's look at
some signals so again find is super
simple I want to find key 38 at the
bottom so my thread starts off the
beginning I get the real a on a I come
down to now B and now this
point here again because it's read-only
operation it's a fine it's safe for me
to release the latch on a so as soon as
I get down to B I can release the latch
na and I'm good to go and now I keep
scanning down and do the same thing get
to D release on B get to H release on D
and now I do my read and and I'm done
right pretty straightforward so let's
see now if we want to do a delete so I
start off with the right latch on the
root I come down to B after i acquire
the right latch now this point here is
it is it safe for me to release the
latch on a No
why because I only have one key and B
and so I don't know what's below me yet
I'm going down and going I'm doing 38 so
I'm going down here I don't know what
these other notes look like yet so if I
do a delete and I have to merge and I
have to remove this key now I do like
them you know make a change up to egg so
in this case here we have to hold the
latch on B I'm sorry I hold the latch on
egg so then we get the latch on D get
down here and now we recognize that no
matter what happens below D we know that
we have room to accommodate or we can
lease to meet one key and I'll have to
merge so we can at this point here we
can release the latches on on a and B so
essentially the threads are sort of
keeping a stack of like here's all the
latches on I'm holding as I go down so
it knows at some point when I when I am
at a safe node I just release everything
up a bumping alright so now I get down
to H I can release the latch on D
because H is is one Humberts at full
then I go ahead and do my delete and
then when I'm done then I release the
latch and go home let's see now an
insert same thing
start with the right latch on a and the
roof go down to be at this point here I
recognize that B can accommodate any new
insertion so it's safe for me to release
the latch on a so I'll go ahead and do
that and then I go down to D D is
considered full so I don't know what's
gonna happen below me and so I had to
hold the latch on B so then I get down
to I and now I recognize that I can
never split because as enough room so
before I do the update I release the
latch on B and B and D and the night
then I can do my insert
so for this the the order in which you
release the latches doesn't matter from
a correctness standpoint right so back
going back here I have to release the
latch on D and B if I release latch on D
before bead that doesn't matter because
no one's gonna get to D anyway because
they can't get to B so from a
correctness standpoint it doesn't matter
but from a before my standpoint we
obviously want to release this one first
because this this covers no more more
leaf nodes so you want to release the
higher up latches as soon as possible
okay let's look at one more example
where there could be a split so I wanted
to cert 25 same thing right latched on
on a right latching be be won't won't
get over a full I can release the latch
on a I come down to see see he's not
gonna go get over a fool so I can at
least latch on B and then now I come
down to F and now I see I need I need to
do a split so in this case here I need
need to hold the latch on my parent node
on C while I make the change so I first
start 25 here take the spillover page
over here put 31 there and then update
my my parent node do I need to have a
latch on this new guy down here what
that says no why he says no we can
access it because you could have you
have a latch on the parent that assumes
that there's no sibling pointers which
we'll talk about in a second so in this
example here for simplicity reasons I'm
not going to acquire the latch because
everyone's going top of the bottom if
I'm scanning along the leaf nodes then
yeah someone can get to this and I have
to protect it but we'll get to that okay
yes
[Music]
yes Damon is I said that the threads
have a stack of the of the latches
they're acquiring us to go down
shouldn't be a queue yes first-in
first-out
okay yes yes say - I said come back to
this table here I said that you want to
release the latches in the from the top
to the bottom and you're saying it in
the OS world you-you-you release them in
reverse order so again think about what
we're doing in the data structure here
at this point here like no one can get
to D unless they go through B so me
releasing the latch on D doesn't do
anything because nobody's waiting to get
that latch up somebody up above could be
waiting to get required B so I want to
release that latch as soon as possible
so it's because we know what the data
structure how it's being used we
understand the context of how of your
latches are being used you want to
release this one first okay okay
so now I want to ask you guys what was
the very first step I did for all those
modifications and examples for the
inserts and deletes what's the very
first step you do exactly you latch the
root in exclusive mode or right-right
mode that's problematic right because
again the right law right latch is
exclusive no other thread can can
acquire any other lasha
during that on that node so this becomes
a single point of contention a single
bottleneck in order to get into the data
structure
everyone has acquired this right latch
and only one thread can hold that right
latch at a time so this is a big problem
this is gonna prevent us from getting
too high parallelism to high concurrency
so we need something better than just
everyone decline the right latch and
soon as they go in and so what we're
gonna actually give them to do is
exactly what he proposed before from the
hash table is make an optimistic
assumption that most threads are not
gonna need to do splits or merges at the
leaf nodes so rather than taking right
latches all the way down
I take read latches all the way down and
then I take a right latch on the leaf
node if I determine that I don't have to
split then great I got down with just
read latches and I can make whatever
change I want if I if I get it wrong and
I do what this do a split or merge then
I just abort restart the operation in
the beginning and take right latches
down so this is this is a standard
technique we do in systems where you
optimistic versus pessimistic I'm
optimistically gonna assume that I'm not
gonna have to do a split so therefore I
take the fast path and do do read
latches well see this in context of
other things like for transactions later
on and for most data structures remote B
plus trees in the real world this is
actually a pretty safe assumption right
in my example some shown nodes would
have two keys in them in a real database
system your node is gonna be you know
eight kilobytes or 16 kilobytes that's
gonna have a lot of keys so most of the
operations you're doing are not gonna
have to do a split in the merge in the
rare case that you do have to do a split
merge and then again you just fall back
to the standard latch crabbing technique
that I showed before so this is from a
paper from 1977 from these German guys
Baron schlock Nick this so there's no
name for the algorithm that people
usually refer
- as the bearish logic algorithm we're
optimistic a lot / grabbing all right so
let's say we wanna do that delete on 38
so again I don't take a right latch in
the root I take a read latch all the way
down and then when I get down to 2 D
here I acquire the real at the right
latch on on on H I recognize that I'm
doing a delete therefore I'm not gonna
do a split and merge so therefore my my
gamble paid off
and I don't need to to restart right I
can do my delete without having to take
right latches right
same thing for insert so insert 25 I
take the relapse on the way down I'm
sorry
I take a real a CH and do crabbing all
the way down and then I eventually get
to see here where I take the right latch
on F this one I recognize that I'm gonna
have to do a split so I abort the
operation and just restart it start from
beginning and take take right latches
all the way down so he said shouldn't
you start at the point where you last
released the latches on the way down so
that would be in this case here at C
right so question is so it'd be a -
sorry we need my two nodes like -
sibling - keys yes correct
yes but how do you get how do you get
CNF again you can't he said I said you
can maintain a stack of the punters that
way you got down here I can't do that
because I can't say page IDs again these
ABCDE these are the logical identifiers
for these nodes but they may end up
being put into different pages so
because I didn't I don't hold any
latches on these things anybody can do
anything
and therefore the location of the page
ID for these these nodes may now be
something different so now you see page
1 2 3 announce 4 5 6 in my stack I go
look for page 1 2 3 and now it's
something completely different because I
can't we can't assume that the location
of these pic nodes will always be the
same unless I hold a latch on them the
read latch prevents anybody from writing
them and doing the splits the right
latch prevents anybody from ah else I
also modifying them you always have to
restart yes thank you sorry your
statement is yes say forgetting so if I
assume that is the start over sorry yes
so your question is if we're have if say
we're like maybe like here so I hold the
read latch on this and I hold the right
latch on this and then because I at this
point I need to modify it but also I
don't know whether someone's gonna
change the change something that would
cause this thing to get modified as well
but again everyone's going in the same
direction so they can't do that like
they can't get to they can't make any
change here because I hold the real ash
on that so they can't modify this node
right
yes yes yeah yes yeah question is in
this example here when I got down here
and took the right lateral F to do the
insert and when I recognized oh I got a
split therefore I need the right latch
on this and there and I don't have it so
at the restart
do you just hold this the whole time no
yes yes yes yes yes
she said so say I'd had this example
here I went to cert 25 I got to the leaf
node and recognized oh I got a split let
me restart and take right latches down
but he needs between the time I
restarted somebody else came along and
wants to insert 24 and they're gonna
have the same issue they also have to
split this so they come back as well and
take take right latches on the way down
but now because both of them are taking
right latches only one of them is gonna
proceed at a time so now 25 say the guy
that wants her 25 he gets there first
he inserts this and splits then 24 is
allowed to run it gets down here
it doesn't care that it already got
split again this is a good example
between the logical correctness and the
logical view and the physical view I
don't care my index where my key
actually exists so I don't care that
like oh I try to put it here
so make sure I put it in this here the
next time because I couldn't hear the
first time I want to go exactly this
page you don't care every single time
you come into it you're doing this
traversal from scratch you don't care
how you got there before so it doesn't
matter that 25 inserts here at splits or
maybe 24 came first and splits it
doesn't matter it's still balanced and
still correct yes correct so he said the
second reversal for 24
it doesn't need a right latch because 25
already split it correct that so that
that's more expensive but what's the
alternative right the alternative is to
take right junk latches every single
time so optimistic is not perfect we're
not guaranteed to always do the least
amount of work we need to do because
certainly if I'm again in this case here
my nodes are really small so I'm
splitting a lot if I'm inserting a lot
so I'd be wasting a lot of lot of cycles
a lot doing wasted work should reverse
just to find out I need to come back and
take right latches so in practice if the
contention rate is high and therefore
the optimistic assumption is incorrect
you're going to actually be slower than
this doing the pessimistic thing but for
these data structures in general
probably talking right here at the
optimistic one actually works the best
the for the the hash table stuff I
actually haven't seen numbers in that
case the it's often times the the the
pessimistic approach of taking latches
on the page is this is actually pretty
good cuz it's so simple for this won't
make more fine-grain and and and we get
a big grin but it depends on a lot of
things depends on what the workload is
are we insert heavy lookup heavy
delete heavy it depends on you know the
distribution our values depends on how
many cores we have right it varies a lot
in practice though most data systems
just pick one approach they don't try to
be adaptive because this is with from
engineering standpoint it's way more
complicated yes
so he says for people she knows you
can't use the low-level slot latches
like you can in a page table no because
you could be modifying the you could be
modifying the in the physical structure
of the index itself so therefore I'm
updating pointers so like if I have like
like if I need to have split merge and I
need to have latches for all the keys in
this in this node in order to move them
around so so in general you just take a
latch entire page I think that's true I
could double check that though it makes
things more complicated okay so again
this is just reiterate what we're trying
to talk about again for the this for the
search with the better the better lock
latch latching algorithm same as before
insert delete it's it's giving you you
take relapses all the way down if it
fails then you just come back and
restart so again this is what I was
saying before about how we're assuming
that most of the time taking the real
edges on the way down is going to be
good enough but we're not gonna have to
restart right and therefore if we if we
if we choose correctly with predict
incorrectly then you need that first
time we went down is just wasted work
we're just burning cycles and so we're
not gonna get the the better scalability
or concurrency we may actually want but
I'll say in practice this is this is
this usually worked out nicely alright
so the next thing to talk about is how
we actually support leaf no scans so in
the example I've shown so far with the
B+ tree just like in the hash table all
the traversals were in one direction
they always top to the bottom so there
can never be any dead locks because I
never had a thread trying to come up
from the bottom to the top in reverse
direction and try to hold latches that
holds latches that another thread once
right
so if though now we want to start
scanning on leaf nodes things become
more complicated because now we have
things coming from top to bottom and and
also from left to right so in this case
deadlocks could occur
so let's see how we handle this so the
first thing I'll say is the original
this is before the original B+ tree did
not have these sibling pointers on the
leaf nodes this is what how most people
streets have this now and this comes
from the be link tree that was invented
here at CMU so let's say I had this
really simple tree like this and I have
thread one wants to find all keys less
than four so we take a reed latch on the
root come down here I forget the
relation on C we can release the real a
on a and now we want to start scanning
scanning across all right so say we
reverse order on all the keys in this
node but now we recognize that we got to
keep going over here right so just like
before in case of crabbing when we want
to go horizontally we don't release the
latch that we hold until we acquire the
latch that we want so in this case here
in order to get the latch on B I hold
the latch on C once i acquire it then I
can swing around and then release the
latch on C so in this case here for all
keys less than four is basically keys
from less than forward to that negative
infinity so we know that we're gonna
have to hit the we want to get to this
end of the the the tree there's other
tricks you can do like having like fence
keys or hint keys basically to tell you
for this node here what's the keys over
on this side here and to tell you
whether you even even need to jump there
or not but for this example we don't be
worried about that all right so let's
make it more complicated say now we have
another another thread that wants to
find all keys greater than one well okay
that's fine so the both of them start
they both want acquire the Reed latch on
a that can happen because that can be
shared amongst them and then they this
guy gets to relapse on B this guy gets a
relapse on see that's fine then they
scan all the raqi's and they start going
across and for this point here B wants
to latch on CC wants to latch on B that
could be shared right because the Reed
latches so at this point here they both
acquire alternating one so the different
ones that's good then they slide over
and now they release the latch of it it
just came from so because the Reed latch
can be shared
there's no dead locks right so this
works out fine
so let's talk about now when we haven't
we're rights so Fred one what's that
leap for and threat to wants to find all
keys greater than one so at the very
beginning they start off they can both
get the reed latch on a because we're
doing that the optimistic latch coupling
technique of last crabbing where I at my
root I always choir the reed latch and
only get the right latch only on the the
child node so the very beginning they
both have a reed latch that's fine and
then they both go down here begets the
real a on on sorry thread one gets
thread two gets the real a Jumby thread
one gets the right latch on see because
that's the entry that it wants to delete
so now let's say that t2 wants to scan
across because it's flying all cream
cheese greater than one so before it can
jump into into C it has to get the right
latch on C we're sorry to read lachen C
but it can't do that because the first
thread has the right latch on this node
so what should happen what's that he
says sure wait what else could we do
there's three choices right we can wait
all right again think of that while that
we just spin in that we could kill
ourselves and just restart the operation
or it could be like a gangster and try
to steal its you know take go over here
shoot it in the head take his wallet
take its latch and then take over
alright so raise your hand if you think
we should wait 25% raise your hand if
you think we should just kill ourselves
even less raise your hand if you think
we should be a gangster and steal it
nobody so what's the issue here what
what is this thread know about this
thread
nothing right because all the latches is
just a little some bits in the data
structure this and then something
someone requires it and either read mode
or write mode so there's no global view
in the system to tell you what this
other thread is doing the database is at
a high level sure it says no I'm doing
I'm doing delete on for but at this
lowest level inside the data structure
as our threads are traversing through we
don't have access to that information
because that would be too expensive for
us to go look up again we want these
operations to be really fast because
we're holding this latch on this guy
here you know while we're trying to get
that other latch so we could wait but
that could be a bad idea too because we
don't know what this guy's doing
right we don't know whether you know in
this case here on our example it's just
deleting this one record there's one key
and it meant then it's done but we don't
know that it could also be trying to
acquire the latch on B and therefore I
have a deadlock so the simplest thing
turns out to be the best thing is this
we say we don't want to live anymore and
we use abort and kill ourselves and just
restart the operation right this is the
fastest thing to do because there's
again these latches are super dumb like
there's no information about who's
holding them and what they're doing so
rather than try to reason about anything
we just want to mediately stop what
we're doing and restart and assume they
have time to come back then the last we
want is now there yes since how is it
better than waiting so yeah you can wait
a little bit with a timeout and then
eventually that the latch you want is
not available then you just kill
yourself that's a you could do that as
well but like I'm talking like maybe
wait microseconds so his statement is
back up here he said if we're down here
on c4 thread one doesn't thread one have
a right latch
people that he was like that person cool
game from the table and so his statement
is that if if C really wanted to go in
this direction and do some modification
wouldn't have to have a right latch up
AB up and therefore I this threat would
not been able to get down here to go
across well know right so say the blue
thread starts first it gets the real a
CH comes down here and gets the red
latch that it wants on B then t1 starts
gets the right latch on on on a right
any man gets the right latch on this so
it doesn't know you don't know this like
it can come in any order yes so this
damn it is which is true we could have
starvation here where this thing here it
says I don't you know I can't get what I
want I'm gonna kill myself
tries it again same as you yes and
there's different ways to handle that
that adds additional overhead in
practice I don't think my sequent post
guys do anything I don't know what the
commercial guys but you can do it you
imagine how to do it it's just it's
extra work and it may not be worth it
the simple thing might be doing the best
thing yes what do you like the whole
program I think the process oh no no no
no like it's like so it's like an
operation so this like find all keys
greater than one we restart that
actually um actually perfect next the
next slide so the the way think about
this is that we have this database
system we have this execution engine
that's invoking queries and it says oh
in order to get the two boys I need for
this query to answer this query I gotta
go
to the index and do final keys greater
than one so then it invokes that on the
index and there's basically a retry loop
that's inside the index where I keep
retrying that to do that operation on
that index until it succeeds for four
inserts or things that could potentially
violate an integrity constraint yeah you
have a check to say you know I try to
insert and I couldn't because it would
violate the integrity strain not because
I couldn't get the latch I wanted and in
that case you you abort that up you
board that operation but in general you
just keep you trying this irreverent cuz
eventually it'll go through but to his
point you could lead to starvation or
just burning a lot of cycles trying to
you know torch the bottom and then try
to acquire the latch that you never can
acquire but the main thing i main
takeaway when you get at get out of this
is that because there's a potential for
deadlock here but we don't know there
what the other thread is doing rat we
wouldn't be super conservative and just
kill ourselves immediately we can wait a
little bit sure but we don't want to
reason about what they're trying to do
we just say we can't get in those latch
and really retry because there's nothing
else up above that's gonna say oh
there's a deadlock when we break break
it by killing one of you yes the same is
it wouldn't matter what that what kind
of latch the other thread is having sure
yes in this case here it's this guy has
a right latch I can't I can't get the
real a that fails right so that was the
gangster one right so that was saying
like this guy has the real latch maybe I
prefer read reads or writes and
therefore I want to kill this guy sure
you can do that but how do you actually
implement that in your code
now you need to way to interrupt this
guy in whatever it's doing did then go
steal the latch that's super hard
because again we're doing this these
small critical sections I don't want to
check a global variable says did
somebody hate me and I and I should die
right
so it's kinda corny that is just it's
not worth it in the back yes huh okay so
I think you said here if if this thing
actually when I do the delete I had the
I submerged in the fraud to modify the
route how would that work well again
like I would have to hell out the right
so when I landed here using optimistic
lash crabbing I would recognize oh I'm
gonna have to merge and modify my
parents I got to go back and take its
clue so blacks all the way to exclude
latches all the way down so that Beckett
am yes I say if we're in this situation
here yes we're gonna do some operations
requires to modify a head so we just
obtained blocks on all of the children
we know that as a parent leaves and then
we never actually get it started to read
operation starts than we ever have to
worry about this yes he's actually
cracked so so this is what that right so
what you're saying so if I if I know any
views button here and therefore I may
have to spill over here
I want to acquire a right latch on this
and then I'm and then a right latch from
all my all its children and then that
would allow me to do any modifications
that I want to do which includes
updating the sibling pointers which is
tricky
and then you're saying that could cause
a deadlock because someone could be
coming in a different direction
yes right so you kill yourself there's
no point of acquiring walks
yeah so if this guy had a split I have
to update this sibling pointer too so
you do need to acquire a latch on this
guy as well but again the simplest thing
is like I another thing you can do -
like say two threads exactly same time
to enterprise exact same latches in
practice there's you know there's
nothing there not me in absolute
lockstep meaning like if you bought them
the same time to really come back and
hit the same conflict they're gonna be
slightly different each other but even
then you could say oh I've tried this
before and I wasn't able to do it let me
back off a little bit and that way at
least come in staggered then I avoid
that issue again the simplest thing to
say I didn't get the last I wanted to
kill myself immediately and that avoids
all deadlocks and that's gonna be
different when we talk about today's
locking later on for transactions
because we will have something else can
come and resolve deadlocks for us but we
don't have that here
okay so the last thing I want to finish
up discussing is a is an additional
optimization for handing overflows and
this is this comes from the B link again
the peeling trees want what went first
invented the the sibling pointers and
then everybody does that now in a B+
tree for the most part at least in one
direction so normally every time you
have to do an overflow you have to do a
split in a node we have to update three
notes we have to update the the node
being split we have to create a new node
to overflow into and then we have to
update at least one parent or one our
ancestry - now accommodate that new
separator key for the new node that we
added so the B link tree guys came with
optimization where any single time a
leaf node
of flows you actually hold off on on
updating the parent node so that you
don't want the restart and this restart
the traversal and do the pessimistic
right latches all the way down you just
update a little global information
global information table for the for the
tree and says any time somebody comes
through that part of the tree again
here's how it want you to update it so
let's look at example so say I want to
search key 25 again I do the optimistic
latch crabbing on the way down I get
real a ch's I get to here on C again I'm
when I get the right latch on on F I
hear that I would recognize that I'm
gonna have to split but then rather than
restarting and taking right latches I
just give up the read Lacan see I still
do my insert and add the new the new the
new node but then rather than having to
update this thing I just have a little
global global table for the tree that
says if you if you ever take the right
latch on this node see here's the change
I want you I want you to add in right
and that way the next time somebody
comes through and takes the right latch
they'll do some extra work and finish
updating what we wanted and this is
still correct this is still valid
because if I come along and now do a
look-up on 31 well I follow the the the
pointers down and my pointer for for all
keys greater than 23 will put me here
and now I have to know all right well I
should have this overflow thing if I'm
looking for 31 scan on longleaf note and
that's actually what I'm looking for yes
right so basically so now there's now
there's a in this global thing that
anybody can see when they first start
says oh by the way if you you're doing a
modification and you go um I see take a
right latch work so this guy wants to
now insert 33 I can do real a chah's all
the way down to get to B and then but
now for C I would know oh why I was told
that I should take a right latch on this
let me go ahead and do that now I do
I finished the property
applying that change there and then now
the tree is considered considered valid
right I take the right latching and
complete my operation so it's just it's
like rather than having to do the
restart you update this thing to say all
right the next time you go through
somebody else will take care of it for
me yes how would you identify see and -
what you mean like that like it's a page
ID right logical nudity if you're going
to see you know page 1 2 3 by the way
apply this change for me yes do you
obtain what sorry so back here yeah so
yeah yes and for simplicity reasons
there's different ways to do this in
this case here if we don't have the same
parent then we may not have a sibling
pointer to go in the reverse direction
there's different implementations but if
you want to have bi-directional sibling
pointers yeah so you'd have to update
that that makes things way more
complicated then what I could show in a
class would like this thing that's just
a sibling pointer oh yeah you need you
have the update and say yes the 7 corner
the overflow thing is not there anymore
but it actually doesn't matter anymore
actually
you actually can keep it right because
because up above if I'm looking for
things greater than equal to 31 I'm
never gonna get this known anyway I'd
always get to this one so you don't you
don't actually have to update it yes
[Music]
correct his David is the first person
for this for this position the first
person that will update see applies this
change and because they hold the right
latch on it it's an atomic operation
correct yes otherwise could be changed
yes all right awesome
all right so let's finish up so
hopefully I've convinced you that uh you
know you want to do the latching stuff
but it Centauri hard to do right I lost
over sibling pointers how to keep those
in in sync that's a whole nother bag of
we don't talk about that's super tricky
but again as I said the good news is
that because it's super hard and if you
can do this people pay you a lot of
money to do this in practice I would say
that you know there's there are those
actually surprisingly I mean there's
there's a bunch of current data
structure libraries that are out there
the Intel thread building blocks is one
of them Facebook's folly so in general
for low-level things like you know
internal hash tables and things like
that that aren't being used as part of
you in query processing and storing data
as an index off-the-shelf stuff is
probably good enough all the commercial
systems roll all the high-end systems
roll their own data structures for these
things but for table indexes I think
that having to having building a data
structure that's specific to your
database system is super important
because then you can tailor it towards
whatever whatever your target operating
environment is so the other thing I'll
point out to you is all that we talked a
little bit about hash tables we spent
most or time and talked about B plus
trees but the core ideas that I've
talked about like making sure threads
are always going in one direction to
avoid deadlocks killing yourself right
away if you do encounter a deadlock
maybe optimistically assuming that
you're not going to have have to do
modifications to to the structure and
therefore taking a fast path first all
these techniques are reused all
throughout computer science and in
systems in general so it's not just B
plus trees Abad these techniques are
applicable everywhere
ok all right so any questions about that
Moke we talked about so far today
alright so the good news is that next
class we we can finally start about how
to actually query we know how to store
them we now to index them and now let's
talk about actually how do you you know
run queries on top of them and produce
of results okay all right guys
[Music]
ricochet jelly hit the deli the bottle I
don't know your phone can tap a