a lot to talk about today the this is
sort of continuation on where we are
where we left off on Mondays classes
have a lot of recovery so DJ drop tables
are still in Vegas so you can't be can't
make it today but he'll be back on on
Monday and I said he's dealing with
girlfriends plural problems right so on
Monday we started talking about recovery
algorithms we talked about how to have
the database system be able to restore
the the database to the consistent state
as it existed before the the system
crashed and we want to do this make sure
that we provide the atomicity durability
and consistency guarantees for all our
transactions and I said that every
recovery album we're gonna have in our
database system that we possibly design
is gonna have two parts but first is are
the things we're gonna do while we're
processing transactions to record extra
information or to flush out data in a
sort of certain way to disk and such
that we can be able to recover after a
crash so now we're talking about today
is the second half of if there is a
crash pad we come back and pick our life
back together picking pieces our life
that you know back together and and
figure out what's going on so the the
protocol we're going to look at today is
based on this technique developed at IBM
called Ares so I don't think the
textbook is going to explicitly refer to
in the chapters when they talk about
data recovery in the the techniques
where we talk about today as Ares we're
just stood in the back of your mind to
understand that this is pretty much this
Ares is pretty much everyone does so
Ares was developed in at IBM research in
the late 1980s early 1990s for for db2
and there's this seminal paper that came
out that's that's super long if you
can't fall asleep it's 70 pages so go
ahead and give it a crack and see
whether you can get to the whole thing
you won't um but this thing is goes into
excruciating details of exactly all the
steps and failure scenarios you need to
handle to guarantee that your recovery
album is going to be correct and that
you're not going to lose any data so
it's not to say that nobody was doing
recovery before this paper came out in
1992 it's just to say that this paper is
the sort of was laid down or codify the
exact policies that need to be mindful
walk in order Duke recovery correctly
and then not every single database and
that's out today that's doing
checkpoints and write ahead logging
maybe not be falling to the exact letter
what Ares does but at a high level
they're essentially doing the same thing
right right ahead Logs with fuzzy
checkpoints and then a three-phase
analysis or three-phase recovery
protocol so the three main ideas of Ares
for database recovery are the Fallen the
first is that we're gonna use redhead
log right ahead log to record any
changes that transactions make to data
in our database in these log records and
that we have to flush out the logs that
correspond to the changes to a page
before the page can be written out and
as we said last class this is using a
steal no force policy so what a steal
mean steal says the buffer pool is
allowed to flush out pages to disk or a
dick pages to disk for that have been
modified by transactions that have not
committed yet and no force says that
we're not required to flush all the
dirty pages that that a transaction
modified in order to say that
transaction has committed correctly
instead what we do is we flush all the
log records that the transaction
generated out the disk make sure they're
durable and safe before we tell the
outside world that our transaction has
committed so this is what we do at run
time and we'll have a slight variation
on how we're gonna do this that's gonna
be different when we talk about on
Monday we'll have to see about this
store some extra stuff to make sure this
works correctly then during after after
a restart to recover the database we're
gonna first replay the history on in the
log to redo all the changes that
transactions made and this includes any
any changes that turns out from aborted
transactions we're gonna reapply them as
well and then we'll have to go back and
undo a bunch of stuff to figure out how
to
versus the changes that should be
persistent and then the other change
we're gonna make also too is that when
we start undoing changes both at run
time and during recovery we're actually
create log records for those undo
operations as well so that's something
we also we haven't talked about so far
because all the last guys I just said
hey here's all the updates I'm doing
here's the corresponding log records and
then when I boarded yeah you know I
didn't do anything special so now when
we do a border transaction as either
again at run time or apart it's recovery
we're gonna add extra log records to say
here's the change that we are reversing
and we are need this to ensure that we
can recover but if if we crash during
recovery we can recover from the
recovery right and you Majan this thing
being infinite so this is this is the
extra step we need to make sure that we
can we can handle all scenarios so
today's agenda were to first talk about
how the execution workload is gonna be
different execution process of
transactions during the revver normal
processing is me slightly different so
we're gonna introduce this idea of lock
sequence numbers and the extra steps we
do for commits and abort sand and fuzzy
checkpoints and then we'll finish up
talking about how we actually do the
three phase recovery algorithm as
defined by Ares okay again this is super
hard this is as I said this is probably
the third hardest part about database
systems so again stop me as we go along
if you have questions write it feel free
to interrupt so last class we talked
about writing head log records and we
said that for our purposes here we'll
just assume we're doing physical logging
or physiological logging and not the
logical logging where you just record
the sequel statement and so we're gonna
have the the transaction ID that's
making the change the the object that
they're changing and then the redo and
undo information but now we're include
additional metadata that keeps track of
the order in which these log records are
being generated so we're gonna introduce
this new concept called a log sequence
number the LSM that is just a
monotonically increasing counter that we
assign to every single blog record as it
gets added and so the law of sequence
number doesn't need to be continuous for
a transaction because again depending
what concurrent you told scene we're
using we can interleave these their
operations in any different way
so I might give out log sequence number
one - transaction 1 log 6 sequence
number 2 - transaction 2 and it you know
goes back and forth they don't need to
be all continuous so now with these log
sequence numbers we're gonna modify all
different parts of the system that need
to be aware of what log records have
modified data and whether or not they've
been written out the disk so we want to
extend our buffer pool even further now
be cognizant of what are these log
sequence numbers what are the local
sequence numbers that correspond to the
changes that are made to its pages that
it has in memory so every log record has
a log sequence number but then all
throughout the system will have these
other logs sequence numbers so this is
just a summary table for the log
sequence numbers were going to counter
throughout the rest of the class but
we'll go through these one by one you'll
see then however and abusing them so the
flush LSN is just an in-memory counter
that keeps track of the last LSN of the
log recovering flush to disk and this is
just telling us in our ready head log
buffer in memory how far you know how
far in you know the log records how far
back we know they're all records are
actually Dorobo or not and then for
every page we have the page LSN and the
reckless em so the page LSN will just be
the the last log record that modified
that page but the newest log sequence of
that record and then the REC LSN will be
the oldest log record that modify this
page since it was last flushed so when I
bring the page into memory if I go ahead
the first look first transaction that
modifies it I add that local sequence
number as the REC Ellison and then no
matter how many times I keep modifying
it while it's in memory they've reckless
and is always the same whereas the the
page else and it will increase and then
I'm gonna write this data also out to
disk as well like this so code is going
the header and this is your extra call
extra information to make sure that
we're doing the right things on during
recovery every transaction were to keep
track of the last LSN if that's that's
the last you know log record that it
added and then globally we're gonna have
a master record that we're gonna use to
keep track of the LSN the last check
point that we successfully took
right now remember I said when we take
these checkpoint they're actually
entries into the log to say hey I took a
checkpoint at this time so again this is
sort of reiterating everything I said
before so every page has a page LSN it's
just when the most recent update made to
that page we keep track of the flush LSN
to know how many what what sequence in
the log or what point in the log we've
written those things up to disk and as I
said last class yeah sorry question yes
so I said to the page LS and the
reckless end do they get written a disk
they don't have to but in general you do
it's just an extra safety mechanism in
case you end up missing listen to
something it's the information about the
log record right correct statement is if
you write it out the disk is if you
write the page up the disk with the page
else and Rebecca Ellison isn't that
essentially redundant because now the
the page is durable on disk it's no
longer dirty if it was in memory isn't
that fine and I'm agree with you I'm
just saying it's an extra safety
mechanism
because we don't want to lose any data
and discs are super you know they break
all the time we just want to make sure
that there's enough information around
that if we have to cover and recover and
maybe maybe our law got corrupted a
little better so that the page we got
corrupted we have enough information in
enough locations that we can we can
figure things out yeah now you'll see as
we do the extra bit of recovery process
there's me obvious things we could do to
speed things up and let's talk a little
bit about alert about them at the end we
are not gonna do them here because we
want to be super cautious all right
people get pissed when you lose data so
you don't wanna lose data right okay so
this is just saying what I said last
class member I said that the with the
right ahead log before we can flush out
a dirty page we have to flush the log
record that made that page that page
dirty right
and this is how we're actually going to
figure that out we just use these LS
ends as the watermark to figure out oh
the the last log record that modified
this page is this you know one two three
but I flushed out log sequence number
four five six and four five six comes
after one two three so therefore I know
that whatever log sequence or whatever
log record that made my page dirty that
also got flushed out that just as well
so it's safe for me to flush out this
page so that's how we're gonna guarantee
this so let's look at sort of a
high-level example of all this so again
we have in memory we have our log buffer
which is just always the tail of the log
and it's always gonna be like you know
the most recent changes that may or may
not have been written out the disk and
over there and then now hang we're
actually the other thing we're
introducing also is a log see what's
number again these are just a counter
we're increasing by one then over here
in the our page we have the page Ellison
again that's the most recent log
sequence number of the log record that
modified the this this this page it may
not be the one that made it dirty in the
first place right that's the wreck
Ellison is this is the since I brought
this page into memory what was the first
log record that made this thing dirty
because I need to know like what were my
boundary is then now we have the flush
LSN again this is just a pointer to
whatever was the last Ellison that we
wrote help to disk in the log the master
records and just pointing to the last
successful check point that we took yes
scratch the question is why do you need
page Ella sound here that'll come up
later on why we need this it has to do
with when you're trying to figure out
the as you're replaying the log is the
thing that I'm that did I already write
this thing out that then I write there
already write out the dirty page and
therefore I don't need to worry about
anything that comes comes and before
that the sequence number kingka this is
like a boundary like since I brought
this thing in the memory here's the
range of Ellison's that could have
modified my my page
is the one which makes the dirty yes hey
yellow Sanders it's the last walk
sequence that made the page dirty so
it's here so when I want to go decide
whether I can flush my page I need to
know what was the last change made to
that page if that last change is comes
before the flush LSN and the flush LSN
is this if I know my change is up here
and it comes from for the flush I'll
ascend if this thing's been written a
disk but I know anything before it's
been written a disk and therefore it's
safe for me to pick that page yeah
so during recovery you check in that
range we'll get that in a second when it
comes time at runtime to flush this
thing I check page Ellison okay again
the master record is just the the
location to the last checkpoint and we
use this when we recover to figure out
where do we want to start our analysis
to look at the log to figure out what
was running right because without the
master record without these checkpoints
we have to start from the very beginning
because we don't know anything about
what page has been written out to be
very clear here like I as the buffer
pool was writing out pages
sorry it's flushing out pages we're not
logging that so we don't know what
potentially you know what pages have
been written out the disk if we recover
after a crash we just know the log
sequence numbers that have written out
all right so this is actually just an
example what he was asking about so
let's say that my page Ellison points to
here at blocks he was number 12
my flush ellison points to 16 and my
lava flush this page out right yes
because the page Ellison is less than
the flush Ellison let's say the page
else hand points to 19
can I write that out no because I know
that the log record that corresponds to
the last change made to this page has
not on disk and therefore it's not safe
for me to evict this and again this you
would add this this logic inside your
eviction policy or replacement policy
you would implement in your buffer home
be mindful about what are the flush LS
ends what means pay jealous ends and
keep track of all these things when you
make a decision about what what - a bit
all right so just to recap everything I
said I all love records have an LS M
every single time we make a change we
were to first add the entry to the log
the log record in your local analog
record to the buffer in memory then we
give back an LS n then we can now modify
the page and that's where we update the
page l SN because we already hold the
right latch on the page and therefore we
can we can update atomically and then
every single time we have been a victim
age we just always update this flush
allah send to know that this is how far
in the law we've written things out and
then you can now start truncating the
log above that right cuz you're unlikely
to need it in memory so let's stop right
now we'll meet actually transactions so
again every transaction is gonna be just
a sequence of reads and writes at the
lowest level for recovery that's all we
really care about we don't know anything
about sequel statements when we're doing
physical or physiological logging we
just see reads and writes instead of
these when the transaction finishes it's
finished when it's either be either
commit or abort
so the assumptions are gonna make to
simplify our discussion today or the
following so the first is that we're
gonna soon that every log record can fit
into a single page alright and that just
means that we can do an atomic write on
a page that has an you know all the
contents of a single log record we don't
worry about our log records spanning
multiple pages it's not hard to handle
that you just have to add some checksum
and say this is you know this is what
segments of this log record is on this
page versus that page if you don't see
both of them then it's considered not to
be atomic but for our purposes we just
assume it's a single page we assume that
we do four kilobyte page writes that are
atomic we're also going to assume that
we're only doing single versioning in
the database system and we just use
strict to pl so we don't worry about
weird commercial anomalies and as I said
before we're also doing
steal no force just sort of implied is
you have to have that in order for all
this to work so when a transaction
commits now we do exactly what we did
before we're going to write a commit
record
to the law and once that commit record
is durable and in flush to disk we can
then tell the outside world that your
transaction has successfully committed
right because everything all the log
records that that this transaction
produced will have to get written to the
log either with before this commit
record so we know that everything is
durable the transaction internally
though is not actually fully completed
yet so even though we told the outside
world it's committed we could still
maintain some internal metadata about
what that transaction actually did and
we'll see this in a few more slides like
will keep maintain a table that says
here's all my active transactions and
when we actually complete all of that
all the whatever metadata or internal
bookkeeping we need to have for that
transaction when all that's done we're
going to add a new special log record
called the transaction end and this is
just telling the database system in the
log on recovery that we will never see
anything else about this transaction
ever again once we see this transaction
end and therefore we can remove it from
all our internal bookkeeping tables so
unlike in commit where we we have to
flush that to disk before we can tell
the outside we've committed we don't
need to do a hard flush on or fsync
on the transaction end we did append it
to a log buffer and it just gets written
out as part of the normal process now
this so just to see how this works right
so this is our simple demo so here we
see we do a transaction commit then we
flush up the log right now we update the
flushed LSN to now point to the last log
sequence of less log record that we
generated and now at this point we can
tell the outside world that our
transaction is safe our transaction is
durable is committed we're done but then
at some later point we'll do some
additional processing and then
eventually we'll write out a transaction
end message right and this is just
saying at this point in the log when we
do recovery we will never see this
transaction ever again for commit
there's not that much there's not really
anything we're gonna do special in
between the commits in the end for the
abort we'll see why we're going to need
this and likewise as I said before since
we know at this at this point there's
nothing really in here
we actually still need to have it hang
around like the commits already been
flushed out we could just trim the log
and and reclaim this memory and we use
it and that's that sort that ping pong
effect I thought when we talked about
last class when we did group commit I
once why I know this log buffer is empty
because I flushed everything out then I
can use that to fill it up again and
then I read out the other buffer so for
boards this is the me different than we
did before question no transaction and
just as an internal marker for the
recovery algorithm that's to say that
you will never see this transaction ever
again you will never see any additional
log records for this transaction because
because we've seen abort it'll make more
sense when we do abort because there's
stuff that you do after aborts that be
the outside world doesn't see it's not
like a query you executed but it's stuff
we have to do to reverse the changes
it'll yeah give me a few more slides yes
this race of what right so at this one
here when does it get flushed out and
it's the buffer pool replacement policy
right what - it's right so one is you
need to free up space you have to Vic to
page its mark dirty if you flush it out
the other one could be the background
writer which I think we talked about it
briefly and some database systems
they'll just be a separate you have a
separate process or thread in the
background that occasionally walks
through the buffer pool finds all the
dirty pages and then just write them out
ahead of time it doesn't a victim it
says hey let me write you out and then I
flip your bit to say you're not dirty
anymore
so that way when the buffer will replace
in policy runs and it wants to evict a
page hey I got one that's art that's
marked clean I can just drop it not have
to write it out but that's independent
of what we're talking about here right
that's again in some ways that's the
beauty of the right head log is that we
can separate the policy other than of
what we have we have big things other
than making sure we don't have big
things that there's no log record out
the disk or we can separate that
decision process from from
from the right head log part yes sorry
so the statement is if the flush LS n is
less than the page LS n then you can't
evict that page because you know that
whatever this thing the last log record
you wrote out is prior to this one
so therefore the log records that modify
this page is not out on disk yet so this
question is if your victim policy is
running you say oh my flush LS n is is
less than all the page LS ends for all
the picture all the dirty pages in my
log all our data pages my prefer pool
all my pages my purple are dirty what do
I do you have to stall you have to write
up a disk you can't there's nothing else
you could do and that's what the
background writer supposed to be it's
sort of like if I know I have some idle
I o cycles I could write this things out
ahead of time so I don't have to stall
I'm not on the critical path as I
execute transactions right again the
worst thing you could do is I'm running
a transaction it acquires a bunch of
locks then I have to do a bunch of disk
i/o because now that just the backs
everybody up and everything it's slower
so they if I can do some things in the
background now it's not on the critical
path while I'm holding locks and
transactions can complete more quickly
and but how you balance that between
like flushing this flushing the the log
flush flushing the background stuff
that's the tricky thing that database
systems have to figure out we don't let
the OS do it for us okay so for aborts
aborts are gonna be serve a special case
we're gonna have under Ares where we're
gonna reverse changes for for
transactions but we're actually going to
end up adding log records to keep track
of that we will we have reversed those
changes this is way different than we
talked about so far like every time he
said oh we abort a transaction rollback
says changes we just assume that we can
undo some stuff in memory right now we
need to keep track of everything that
we're doing as we reverse transactions
so we're gonna add an additional field
to our
our log records called the pre bel SM
and this is not required but this is
just gonna make your life easier at
runtime because now you can know how to
jump back to find the next thing you
need to reverse for a given transaction
I to avoid have a sort of scanning
scanning everything essentially you
think of this as like for every
transaction you're generating a linked
list to say for every aborted
transaction here's the linked list up
here's all the changes I need to reverse
so I need to I know how to walk back in
one by one and reverse them so we have
our simple transaction like this again
now we have the pls n and the previous
LSM and so for the first else and for
the first log record for this
transaction t4 since there's no previous
Ellison at the begin statement we just
set the the previous Ellison to null so
this transaction runs it makes some
changes but then it aborts so now what
we need to do is reverse those changes
I'm going to add log entries for these
and then once we know all those log
entries have been are durable out in a
disk we can then add the transaction end
message again this is what I was saying
this is saying that the transaction MS
is a is denoting that there's nothing
else that it could ever come about this
transaction later on we've we've
reversed I've done everything we've
needed to do so for this this part here
when you're talk about Nexus know how we
actually record the changes that were
reversing as we go along so these are
called compensation log records or CLRS
so CLR is just it's like an update
record but it's it's it's reversing the
change of a an actual update record when
the transaction actually ran yes yes
so your question is why do we even have
the previous Ellison what is this
actually buying us yeah her question
your statement is could you just check
for this simple example just find all
the things that are t4 and then just
figure out those things I need rivers
yes but what if I'm running like a
high-end system is doing a million
transactions a second and I crash now I
have and any given time when I crashed I
could have maybe a hundred thousand
transactions in flight so to avoid
having to scan everything over and over
again to find you know exactly what I
need to reverse this is just a helper to
get us there so it's not required for
correctness it's could use it for
convenience yes
why do we need to reverse so for this
example no but how do you know in real
life in real system what did I say I
said we we don't know we're not logging
what pages we write to disk we don't
know anything about what we've got
written to disk because the eviction
policy is doing its own thing that's why
we're gonna play it safe I'm just
reverse everything so the CLR again it's
gonna be like an update log record where
it's gonna have before and after value
but it's gonna be tied to an update
record that actually occurred during the
transactions regular life time and then
we're gonna have this undo next pointer
which again just for convenience who can
tell us what's the next LSN that we need
to reverse so that we know you know for
every given transaction we would know
whether we've actually processed all the
ones we need we need the process to
reverse all this changes so the CLR is
gonna be added to the law just like any
other log record but they're gonna be
added after the transaction gets aborted
and then once we went through reverse
everything then we add the transaction
end
so unlike commit with commit I have to
flush all the log records to disk before
I tell the outside world I've committed
if a transaction gets aborted we
immediately go back to the applications
that you were boarded they don't need to
wait around to to write anything up the
disk because who cares right they try to
go read that their changes are not going
to do that long as we're running with
the correct kernel protocol
so the CLR just get logged any other
record and then they just get flushed
out you know eventually it's at some
point so let's look an example how we're
gonna UCL RS and so because I'm running
out of space on the slide because we
have so many so many meditative fields
I'm now going to show this in a tabular
form so here we have one transaction t1
it just does an update Oh name all right
and then it aborts we don't care how how
it aborted whether the the transaction
application said to a border or the
database systems current protocol said
to abort it we don't care it's all the
same so now when we want to start
undoing its change right this is during
the regular execution time this is not
during recovery this as we're as
processing transactions we're gonna
create a CLR entry that's gonna be tied
to the the update bet it did and again
it looks exactly like the first one it's
just that the before and after values
were reversed so before the value was 30
and then after the update was 40 so now
what we're doing in a reversal or
setting the the old value back to 30
right and then we had this undo next
record that allison that says what's the
next thing we need to undo to completely
reverse this transaction but in this
particular example here the undo Ellison
goes to the begin statement so we know
there's nothing else for us to reverse
for this transaction so we can go ahead
and add our transaction end record yes
this question is did I say that when you
abort you community go back to the
application and say your transaction
aborted and that you don't have to write
flush any of these things out to disk
correct yes statement is I said that if
you really tell the outside world you
aborted but then you you create these
log records you reverse the changes but
then you crash up here you're right so
you yeah you can lose these do we care
he's shaking his head no why well yes
you're gonna bore it but like something
more fundamental correct
so the the page that got modified but
this transaction is not on disk so who
cares half of what sorry yes who cares
can you undo it because they didn't
commit right so again we'll see this
when we do a for example if I don't see
if I crash here and I don't see what was
the final determination of the
transaction where the committed aborted
ain't aborted right that's the beauty of
the right ahead log this is a single
source location to tell us what was the
final outcome of what happened in
transaction so we got here say we got
here and we aborted we tell the AUSA or
we aborted we crash before we do all
this stuff who cares because the
transaction got aborted we don't have to
guarantee anything's durable we come
back and is as if it wasn't there
because we'll reverse any changes that
could have gotten written up to disk
correct so if the page got written to
disk you would have seen you have to see
all these things anyway so we know how
to put it back in the correct state if
necessary yes here yes so so say all
right so say they said they told us roll
back from the terminal from from the
application then we could append this
log record into the redhead log in
memory go back and meet e tell them that
it aborted and then now start cleaning
up all its internal changes right so we
don't have to we don't have to wait to
do any clean up all the things that it
modified we can tell them it aboard it
right away
I commit and commit says I have commit
it
if the Davis didn't tells him tells you
you committed it has to guarantee that
everything's durable so it has to be
ready any log record that that
corresponds to the changes that it made
has to be written a disk up into the
commit we don't care about transaction
end that's internal for us neatly come
back yes I think about why like who
cares that I aborted why why do I care
that you're gonna go do much I stopped
to clean things up why should I wait for
that so this question is for any if any
transaction wants to modify the same
page that got modified by Board of
transaction do they need to wait until
the until the the log record that
modified it got written out the disk no
right because if I like say I board here
I say this isn't this isn't a page page
a I abort here I can merely release what
it can to assuming today's locking I
release the right lock I have on that
page any now other transaction can come
along start modifying it so they start
modifying what is that going to do
that's gonna create new log records bump
up the page LSN for my page and
therefore that page can't be written out
the disk until my new log records of
every not the disk so who cares who
cares that this is of the transaction
modify you you cry if I try to do if I
try to read the the change may if I'm an
aborted transaction I have to reverse
them yes before I'm allowed to read
when we say written a disk of written a
memory yeah sure yes you have to yes
you'd have to reverse that I mean he way
that's true always if it's single
version yes multi version know because
Multi multi versioning right who cares
because you now you just have a version
that doesn't exist anymore you you
ignore it yes in single version yes
you'd had you at the reverse these
things yes yes same is let's say I have
a transaction that makes a lot of
updates have the updates get you you
apply all the updates but half of them
got written out to disk how do I reverse
those changes now they're out on disk
and it because it's the steal policy I'm
a lot of commits right out I'm rather
flush out dirty pages yes you'd have to
bring them back in and reverse them when
you actually do that whether you do that
immediately on abort or whether you do
that you know lazily like oh when
somebody the next time someone goes to
reads it then I'll reverse it
yes I love this question there is some
do don't send a hit on on on YouTube
complain like like professor Pablo I
like your class I like the material but
all those pesky students keep
interrupting me asking questions bad
dude right let him begin to CMU and come
ask questions all right all right so now
for our board advocating we've already
said this we're gonna write a board
record to the log for every transaction
and then we're gonna play back the
transaction updates in reverse order for
the transaction and then for everything
in that we're going to reverse we add a
CLR entry to the log it's tied to the
original update that occurred during
normal operation and then we store the
version of value
and then once we complete all these
transaction these CLRS once we've done
them all they need to do for this
transaction then we can add the
transaction end message so CLRS will
never need to be undone well we could
only redo them during during durham
recovery because it's like a one-way
update okay so now right so what have
you covered so far but now we know we
have long sequence numbers we have these
CLRS and we know do how to keep track of
the Ellison's at various locations for
us to figure out what has been written
out the disk or not so now let's talk
about how we're going to bring along
some additional metadata to figure out
what was running at the system at the
time and use it a better checkpointing
scheme so in our last class i said that
checkpoints are necessary for us to be
able to figure out at what point can we
figure out at what point can we start
recovering the database because without
checkpoints we potentially have to go
look through the entire log if we have
one year's worth a log with no
checkpoints we may have the potential
replay one year's worth for the law
which could take a long time so let's
look at two bad ways to take checkpoints
and we'll see why fuzzy checkpoints are
the better way so if I discuss one of
these bad ways last class and I said the
technique we were going to use was to
just halt the execution of of any new
transaction and then take to take the
checkpoint and this will guarantee that
my pages they're written out the disk as
part of that checkpoint are are
consistent there's no torn updates from
a transaction that was running halfway
through right so basically what happens
is on the on the front end on the
network network layer we halt the
execution of any new transaction and
then we just wait for all our workers to
finish executing any transaction that's
already running so this is obviously bad
because we we have to wait until
everybody you know to all its
transaction to finish we can't start
executing anything new so we have one
transaction it's gonna take five hours
to run they've made the wait for the
five hours to finish wait for it to
finish before we go ahead and take our
check line and then during that time we
can't execute any other transaction so
our system looks completely unresponsive
from a recovery standpoint this is this
is this is great because the
the check point is consistent as I said
there's no intermediate updates it's
exactly as it was when you know it only
contains changes from committed
transactions so a slightly better way to
do this would be to pause transactions
while they're running while we take the
checkpoint so we're going to mean what
this is any transaction has a query
that's modifying the the database we
just pause it any time they try to
acquire a write latch on a page we don't
we prevent that and they have to stall
any read-only transaction can still run
they can read whatever they want because
that doesn't interfere with that
checkpoint and then there's concur trail
protocol up above to figure out whether
they're allowed to read certain things
we can ignore all that but it's all the
right transactions we're just gonna
we're just gonna pause them so it would
look something like this so say I have
in memory I have three pages I have a
transaction that checkpoint would occur
at the same time so say this transaction
is going to update page three and page
one so there's going to start at the
bottom here apply its change to page
three and then before it can update page
one the checkpoint starts so we have to
stall our transaction right because
gonna try to acquire the right latch on
that page one you can't do that because
the checkpoints occurring so it just
stalls so now the checkpoint all it's
really doing is just a sequential scan
or a scan or every single page and our
buffer pool and isn't it miss flushing
them out the disk so our checkpoints
going to write out page one to three
with the modification that the
transaction made to page three been the
checkpoint finishes our transaction get
Sun stalled and then we now update page
one all right the problem is now our
snapshot in our database for one query
this transaction executed we saw half
their changes so our checkpoint or the
state of the database on disk is not is
not consistent so in order to handle
this we want to record some additional
metadata to figure out what transactions
were running at the time we took the
checkpoint and what pages were dirtied
in our buffer pool while we took the
checkpoint so that we can use that
information to figure out later on oh
well this guy updated page one and I
missed it or my checkpoint so I knew
that I didn't make sure that I want to
replay any log record of this guy
to put me back in the correct state here
back yes now be very careful in language
here checkpoint yes yes his question is
in my example here I show in wrists like
a brute force or a coarse grain right
latch on the entire system so this guy
has to finish his checkpoint before this
guy's allowed to go or could I say well
I'll just release the right latch on
page one and then lon update it yes but
you still have the same torn up day
problem I'm not serious I'm using this
as a straw man to say that what you say
this is a bad idea and we'll see how to
do it in a better way
but that's an obvious optimization yes
this question is when I say we care
about do we care about dirty pages which
is gonna be the dirty page table do we
care about transactions that are paused
or any dirty page in the real system is
any dirty page in there in the waiver do
fuzzy checkpoints we're not actually
nopales transactions yes what's his name
it is you don't need the the dirty page
table and the actual transaction table
because if you just replayed everything
and then reverse them wouldn't that put
you in the correct state
yes I think I agree with you but that's
gonna be super slow because you cuz
you're gonna have to update your gonna
bring back every single page modify it
right well where's with this metadata we
can avoid that now not true you have to
go farther back potentially give you
more slides we'll get there because you
don't know what's been written disk all
right so right so there's the a
transaction table and the the dirty page
tables we're gonna record this
information when we take the check when
the check point starts we're gonna write
it out with fuzzy check points when the
check run ends and then we'll see these
two cotton these two concepts come up
again when we do recovery we're gonna
basically replay the log and populate
this information to figure out what we
need to commit or undo so in the actus
reus action table this is going to be
for every single actively running
transaction at the time the Check Point
starts or to record its transaction ID
its status and then the last LSN that
was created by this transaction so the
status is either what it's running its
commits committing right so it's
committed but before we get to
transaction end or it's something that
we think we have to undo it may have to
undo we don't know yet right because we
it's because it's we don't know what
what its final outcome is gonna be and
again when we see a transaction and
message we can we could we can remove
this from the ATT because we know we're
never going to ever see it again so
that's why there's no like completed or
finished here so this would this be
hanging out internal memory we can
populate this while while we take the
check point but then it's included in
the the checkpoint and message which
we'll see in a second then the dirty PA
was just keeping track of all the pages
that are in the buffer pool pages that
have been dirtied in the buffer pool
that were modified by uncommitted
transactions and for this one we're just
going to record the wreck LSN which is
the the log record of the the first
transaction that modified this page that
made it dirty since it was brought into
memory so let's see a slightly better
version of checkpoints that's using
using this information so we see now in
our checkpoint entry
we and our log record we're gonna have
the ATT and at this point here we only
have one transaction running t2 so
that's the only thing we have inside
there and then we have the dirty page
table and we have P 11 P 23 right
because there's P 11 was modified here
so I peek P 11 P 22 pp11 was modified
here and P 22 was modified here so the
syntax I'm showing now is like here's
the object that was modified and it's
pointing to what what the page number
was right so in this case here we don't
record anything about transaction t1
because transaction t1 committed before
my check point started so I don't care
about it at this point anymore so then
now in the second checkpoint t3 is still
active and then we have to two dirty
pages here because t2 committed before
our transaction started right so this is
still not ideal because we're still
stalling all our transactions in order
to take this right so we're pausing
everything at this point here these guys
are not allowed to modify it and so this
is just saying we wrote out a check
point but oh by the way here's some
stuff that that that could have been
modified during this time to make sure
that you find it so so like the first
one the first check point a scheme I
showed you nobody actually does this one
either
everyone instead does fuzzy checkpoints
systems that support high performance
checkpoints are doing fuzzy checkpoints
so fuzzy checkpoint is just where we're
gonna allow transactions to keep on
running keep on modifying the database
while we're taking the checkpoint and so
in order to record the boundaries of
when the checkpoint started when the
checkpoint finishes to know whether
something could have a written out that
we missed we add a holistic checkpoint
begin and checkpoint n log message
so the begin is just telling us when the
checkpoint started and the end tells us
when it finishes and this will include
the ATT and DBT that that that occurred
during during the execution of the
checkpoint so to go back here now so now
we have our checkpoint begin
Check Point does this thing search for
any things out and then in the
checkpoint end we include that we have
transaction t2 because t2 started before
the checkpoint started and then the
dirty page table tells us that D 11 was
modified during during the checkpoint as
well right we don't need to include t3
here because the t3 started before our
checkpoint started
sorry started after I check my started
so the once we have the checkpoint and
written out to disk successfully and we
can which means we flushed all the pages
out that we wanted to take you in the
checkpoint then we go ahead and update
our master record to now include the the
point to the checkpoint begin because
that's going to be our anchor point
where we start our analysis during
recovering because we're going to know
at this point here right here's all we
flushed all the dirty pages but we kept
track of maybe ones that we may have
missed because because they got modified
yes what do you keep the checkpoint what
sorry what do mean where did he keep it
when you say when you mean like the
wrong record it goes in the log but win
it and when it ends you shove it in went
and when you when you have scanned
through the buffer pool and written out
all the dirty pages to disk and after
you flush them out
you f sink right because you make sure
it's durable then you add the log entry
here and it's committing I'm using
committing that quotes because like a
regular transaction I flushed the log
record for this to disk yes this
question is am i holding any locks on
the entire database why I write this
thing out now
putting me in here
like while you are writing a duty a
deputy to the law yes we are not writing
them to the log right now that's why it
does not matter like those rights or
they can by your writing attn DVD then
it will be long right because you wrote
like transaction t2 is earning and yes I
think I think what is saying there is a
sort of stop the world moment here where
you briefly flush this thing out but
that's not that's a blip it's a minor
thing correct yes they can change
whatever else they want to change yeah
in the regular buffer pages yes okay so
now let's do recovering after all that
after 40 minutes of minutiae of log
scene with some murders and fuzzy
checkpointing let's talk about actually
recover this and then and given that
everything we've set up now that we have
all this extra metadata that we're
recording
recovery actually is not going to be
that bad but the tricky part is just
figuring out where you start each of
these phases in the log so the analysis
phase you're gonna look at your master
record for the database on disk and
that's gonna give you the location of
where the last checkpoint began in the
log so you jump to that location and you
scam forward to time to time through
time till you reach the end of the log
and then you're just going to populate
the DP te na TTE to keep track of what
think what was going on in the system at
the moment of the crash and then that's
gonna figure out your news that to
figure out what transactions you need to
abort
which one's actions you need to make
sure that you commit then in the redo
phase you're gonna jump to some
appropriate location in the log where
you know there's could be potential
changes from transactions that did not
make it safely to disk and you can start
reapplying those changes until you get
to the end of the law
and you're gonna do this for any every
transaction you see even ones that are
you know rent about boarding because on
the analysis phase you see everything
you know to the first pass so you know
what's gonna commit what's gonna abort
so then in the redo phase just for
safety reasons we're just gonna do you
know reapply everything then then the
undo phase now you're gonna go back in
reverse order from the end from the
beginning then the log up until some
point to reverse any changes from
transactions that did not come that you
know did not commit and when the undo
phase is done then the database is now
in a state that existed existed state
that existed at the moment of the crash
with no partial updates from from
abortive transactions and all changes
from committed transactions have been
applied to disk in the back yes next
slide yeah okay
so again three pages analysis redo and
undo so the very beginning we look at
the begin the figure out where the begin
checkpoint is in the master record and
that's where we're gonna begin our
analysis right so let's say that this
log record here is the start in the last
checkpoint because again that's in our
master a long record we know where that
where that is and then now we're to scan
forward through time and look at these
log records and build out our ATT e and
d PT and then now we got to figure out
well what for the redo phase what is the
smallest req Ellison in the dirty page
table that we found after do our
analysis right so this is telling us
this is the location of the first log
record the oldest log record that
modified a page that may have not been
written a disk so when we redo we jumped
at this point and reapply all our
changes and then now in the undo phase
we start at the the end point and go
back in time up until some point where
we know that this is the oldest
transaction that got a border that was
actively running while we took you know
took our checkpoint and we reverse all
those changes so the errors are sort of
showing you the boundaries of how far
you get to go back in time in the log
so you know I'll go through the issues
more precisely in context Ellis ends one
by one but is this clear at a high level
what we're doing analysis goes for in a
time redo goes forward a time and then
undo goes backwards in time and for undo
I may not be undoing every single log
record I see here right it's just for
just for the transactions that identify
in my ATT after the analysis that should
not have committed okay so this sort of
summarizes are more concretely what I
just said so analysis phase we're gonna
scan the log forward from the last
successful checkpoint anytime you find a
transaction and record during an
analysis we can remove it from my ATT
right otherwise for any other record if
it's first time I've ever seen this
transaction we add it to the ATT with
the status of undo because we don't know
because we're going forward in time we
don't know whether it's gonna abort
later on if we see a commit record then
we just change its status to commit like
I said one is sinless and we can remove
it and then for any update record we're
gonna look to see whether the page that
that's in the update record that's being
modified is in our DBT if not then we go
ahead and add it and we set the reckless
end to be our Ellison because this is
this again this is telling us this is
the log record that first made this page
dirty when it was brought into memory so
now at the end of the analysis phase the
ATT is gonna tell us what are all the
actor transactions that we had running
in the system at the moment of the crash
and the DP T's are gonna tell us what
are the dirty pages that could have been
in our buffer pool that may have not
been written a disk and we're doing this
we have to we have to build this this
table because again we're not logging
out every time we do a buffer pool flush
to a page on the disk we're not
recording that in the log or the log
records or not that tell us you know
potential will get modified and we're
trying to reconstruct it yes this
question is how do I know for sure
whether pages be written to disk like in
the log or in the real world like on
hardware or analog
you can't because I there's no
information that tells me that it's been
written it's not entirely true when we
see redo we'll seasons in a second but
in general look if you know the LSN of a
wall record you're looking at is less
than the reckless end of the log of the
page as exists on disk then you know
that that your change got written out
the disk but to the page the page got
read not the disk then it got dirty
again by another one but your thing got
written out before then all right so
quick overview of the analysis phase and
so here I'm just showing you the with
the ATT into DP t or gonna look like at
these different for these different LS
ends so begin our checkpoint we don't
know anything so the ATT and GPT are
empty then we do an update in bulk
sequence 20 so for this one here we have
transaction T 96 it's the first time
we've ever seen it right because again
we don't have a begin record here
because it began before a checkpoint
started so we see that and we update our
ATT to say hey we ever turns out in here
RT 96 and the status is a candidate for
undo because we don't know whether it's
going to commit or not and then we see
that it modified page 33 so we add that
to our dirty page table with there with
the req Ellison of our log record here
then now our transaction ends and now we
get more information about the what's in
the extras actual table on T V T so now
we see that there was a t97
that we didn't see in between our
checkpoint so we know that there's some
one transaction up above this checkpoint
the checkpoint start point that did some
stuff that we may need to go look at as
well and then there's also a new a new
page 20 that was also modified so you
want to include that in our our DPT as
well so now we see T 96 commits here so
we flip its status to be committing and
then when we see the transaction and
message here then we know that we can we
can remove it from ATT
but now at the point of the crash you
see that there is t97 still hanging out
here with it with a new candidate status
so we know that this transaction made
some changes up above our checkpoint
that we didn't see in our log that we
need to go back and make sure we reverse
because we don't know whether those
pages got written out to just yet yes
your question is is it possible for the
after the analysis phase the ATT and EPT
are empty so therefore you know that
nothing there's nothing was dirty could
you just say I'm good
yes yeah and actually you would just
sort of see that because it would be
nothing yeah if it's empty then you know
there's nothing everything it made it
out yes your question is if during the
in between the checkpoint is do I am I
not a lot of right out dirty pages out
to disk the boobies at the desk yes I
don't I think yes but I actually don't
know the answer that I think yes because
like why wouldn't why would the the
bomber pool manager ever need to write
out dirty pages well I need to Vic some
stuff to make space where the checkpoint
essentially is just doing that yeah I I
think the answer is yes but I should
double-check that
so his statement is that during the
checkpoint the powerful manager is not
all the rotten loud to write out dirty
pages to disk because you may not
missing the term hey feel like answer is
yes but I actually don't know I mean you
think about that all right so again
after the analysis phase we have ATT and
DBT that's telling us what's what what
was going on at the time of the crash so
now in the redo phase we want to repeat
history so we're gonna
apply all the changes from some point in
the law where we know that there was a
dirty page that was modified that was
potentially not made about to disk so
we're gonna reapply all these changes
for even the even the aborted
transactions and any CRR we see from an
aborted transaction we're gonna redo
them as well so this as I said before
this is gonna seem very expensive
because we're gonna be reapplying
changes we may technically need may not
need have to reapply you know for
example for a transaction we know it's
gonna board who cares about you know
bringing a page in making doing update
and then reversing in the CLRS
and then you know if that was the only
transaction that modified that page I
could just skip that transaction so
there are optimizations like that you
can do but again we're just going to
ignore that because you want to make
sure that everything is is sort of clean
and correct so as we do the read who
pays then we start from the log record
containing the smallest reckless and the
DPT because again that's the that's the
first log record that modified a page
that dirtied it up that we may not have
made it out to disk then as we scan
through for every single ball record of
CLR we look at all LSN and we're gonna
redo the action unless the page is not
in the dirty page table in which case we
know that our our modifications are
flushed out the discs at some prior
point or if it is in our dirty page
table but our records
LSN is is less than the pages record
lawson and that would mean that we made
some change to the page then the page
got written out the disc but then some
other transaction made you know maybe
that made it change of the same page and
then that second change didn't get rid
not the disc and so that's why again we
if we record the reckless end write out
the disc we can recognize what actually
got you know what changes actually got
modified so to undo an action we just
reapply the the change and we set the
page LSN to to the records love worker
sells n it's just as we would normally
do during regular execution of you know
the transaction but
during the normal operation we're not
doing any additional logging we don't
worry about flushing it and you anything
extra right we can sort of do everything
asynchronously so then when we get to
the transaction end message we'll just
go ahead and and remove it from the ATT
and if we want to be super careful we
could flush everything at that point so
now the last phase is the undo so this
is just undoing all the transactions
that we saw at the ATT after the
analysis phase that are hanging out with
the the undo flag or undo Canada flag so
we're gonna go back and reverse order in
in we're going to reverse their changes
in log sequence order see even though
transaction t1 ran before tt her t1
abortive and t3 aborted if we see the
look the the log records 43 first well
we will reverse them first before we get
to t1 and every single time we reverse a
change we're gonna add a CLR message
this is the allows to recover database
if we're crashed during recovery because
we know what we actually reversed so
this gives a lot of hand waving a lot of
text look let's look walk through a
simple example here so here we have now
a right ahead log going forward in time
and we see that we did a checkpoint and
it finished and then we have t1 did a
modification on page five t2 to
modification page three but then t1
aborts so during the normal execution
what do we do to abort this we create
the CLR that says we want to undo the
change from this this one here and then
once we know that that's been applied
then we go ahead and add our transaction
and message to say that this transaction
is fully done so now I'm also not
showing the previous Ellison but that
you can think of that this is a linked
list to tell you for a given transaction
how to walk back through its updates and
be able to reverse them so now let's say
at here we do a bunch of changes for t3
and t2 but then we crash so in the
analysis phase we would come back and
populate the ATT into DP team so this is
I'm running out of space so this is a
truncated version of a log so for
example here I had 40 45 inches upper
lines now
14:45 on one line right and there's
there is the CLR followed by the
transaction and message so let me come
back
are you a TD tells us that we had two
active transactions t2 and t3 and then
we have the last LS ends that point to
the last modification that they made so
we're going to look at the transaction
that has the be the greatest req Ellison
to start doing on deuce so assuming
we've already we've already done
everything right and now we're going to
undo this thing and we're to add new log
entries to reverse these changes because
these transactions aren't allowed to
commit so we look at this and say t2 is
last LSN it's 60 t3 s less LS n is 50 so
we're going to we want to reverse the LS
n 60 first so we go ahead and create the
the CLR write this to reverse this
change and then we add this undo next LS
n the point to that the next LS and we
would need to reverse for this for this
transaction here right and again the
thing is a logical pointer for
convenience to tell us where we need to
jump to next then maybe we add the CLR
for for transaction t3 right and this is
the last thing we actually need to undo
for this transaction so therefore we can
go ahead and create the transaction end
message right away right and at that
point we're going to flush all the dirty
pages that this shows actually modified
and the right have log to disk so at
this point we know that we never need to
recover or undo this transaction ever
again to reverse anything because the
log already contains everything you need
you to reverse it so we'll redo it if we
crash again but we want to undo it
anything so now I say we crash here
right we're doing recovery we're in the
undo phase we crashed and restart all
this gets blown away because this is
just hanging out in memory so when we
come back we and our ATT would say well
we only have t2 sitting around at the
end we make sure we need to reverse that
so and the next thing we need to reverse
the starting point for our reversal is
here so for this we just we've already
applied it during the undo phase so
there's nothing to undo because you
can't undo an undo you just redo them so
you redo undos but you don't
undo undo okay so the undo next tells us
the next thing we need reverses up here
at 20 so we add and you see all around
for that then we have our transaction
end message because it's the last thing
we need to do we flush the log and then
we're done at this point here after this
has been flushed that your new pages
been flush we know at the database is in
a consistent state as it existed at the
moment of the first crash with no
partial effects from any aborted
transactions yes this question is would
it be worth doing a checkpoint at the
redo phase that would so that would make
it so you would do that if you assume
you're gonna crash very soon in the near
future again otherwise it's just
excessive disk writes so nobody does
that if it's if it's 1970s porto rico
and you don't have power yes you do that
the question is is it we required to do
this flush here now that's an
optimization become amid that yes yeah
well next slide alright so i in this
example here i showed what happens if
you crash during undo if we crash during
the analysis phase what do we have to do
with that nothing right there's nothing
to do because it's already of just
breathing log we just come back and do
it all over again if we crash during
redo what do we have to do in the back
nothing exactly yes right because you
just come back again redo it all over
again including the CLRS that you
generated front from if you if you undo
things previously so it's only on the
undo phase where you potentially have to
go figure out what was i undoing at this
given time so related his question is is
there a way to avoid all those extra
disk flush every single time we have a
transaction end right and it sort of
related his question as well right you
just assume that you're not going to
crash during recovery and there
or you're just gonna flush the changes
from the in the in the look in the dirty
pages use a a sacred maybe flush them
out the disk when I think you finally
say the data says online and ready to
start processing new transactions I I
think most systems would do take another
checkpoint then but you don't have to
correctness reasons you don't have to so
how can we another way to produce
improve performance during the undo
phase well we've already talked about a
couple of these we talked about you know
figuring out that this transaction
aborted it's the only thing that
modified this page therefore I don't
need to reverse any changes on that page
another approach would be to actually
lazily replot apply the the roll backs
for transactions o at runtime so you do
the you do the analysis you do the redo
then you figure out what you need to
undo for every single page but then
rather than applying those changes you
just sort of keep them around somewhere
in memory and then anytime a new
transaction comes along and it wants to
read that page then you go ahead and ply
the log so the idea here is like you
must have like instant recovery that you
say alright I'm back online
even though my Davis is not in an
incorrect State no transaction can read
those pages that have not been rolled
back yet correctly and only when you go
ahead and read them then you actually
apply them the idea there is like if you
have a large database and the the undo
the you'll for the undo phase you only
modify a small portion of it rather than
blocking access to the entire database
why you undo this small number of pages
you merely come back right away and let
anybody read whatever they want it's
just you block them when they try to
read things you haven't rolled back yet
I don't think anybody actually does this
optimization and then the last one would
be just the rewrite your application so
you don't have long-running transactions
as you minimize how far back on the log
after the last check point you have to
go and then replay that if you can cut
that back down then the redo phase and
undo pay is will much faster okay
everyone everyone you know ready to kill
me or fall asleep or what or go out and
build your own database all right so the
main idea is for areas we covered our
against right ahead log using steel no
force with fuzzy checkpoints which is
essentially just taking a snapshot of
all the dirty page IDs so we think we
know which one's got modified and then
we're gonna redo everything since the
earliest paid dirty page we had in our
right head log and then we undo the
transactions that did not end up
committing before before the right head
log finished and then we add these CLR
so make sure we record all the undo
operations were doing for for updates to
the database and the log sequence
numbers are the way we're going to use
to figure out whether the log record
that modified a page has been
successfully written to disk or not all
right we have like three minutes let's
just do a quick demo to show you that
this actually does work so there's gonna
be my sequel and we're gonna have one
table let me turn this off too so sorry
let's suck so we're gonna have one table
that just has a single row that has ten
columns
right one two three four five six seven
eight nine and then we're gonna have a
simple Python program that is in a
single transaction it's gonna take the
first column and just slide it over to
the next one and then you know it's
gonna increment every column by one and
so we're gonna let this run oh right and
just to prove that it's actually working
we go select again right we see it's
incrementing one by one all right so our
transact it's running in an infinite
loop I mean down here we have the log
message the log from my sequel to tell
us that it is actually running so what
we're gonna do is a hard kill on my
sequel kill - nine all right that's
going to kill everything and lo and
behold you see that the log actually got
tripped it says that we crash and then
this is running Ubuntu it has a service
that says if like my sequel crashes it
automatically restarts it for you but
you can see we got disconnected up here
and then our Python code got
disconnected here so this proves that
when I did the kill - nine that like it
killed everything so let's actually go
look in the log and see what it says the
details all this doesn't matter but Lona
holed up in here says database was not
shut down normally starting crash
recovery start apply a batch old walk
records in the data so this is just
percentages so this is doing Aires this
is saying like hey and they go look a
log figure out what's running and go
ahead and reply them so now when we go
back and look inside of our database we
connect it to prove that we don't have
any torn up dates for our transactions
we should be guaranteed that every
column is one more greater than the
previous column right and lo and behold
in this case it is my sequel works okay
I don't know what other way to show you
a demo of the database crash other than
that it's the best best I could come up
with okay yes
like what when I killed it why did they
recover right away that's a Ubuntu thing
it's your bunch of has a service it says
this if this thing crashes it'll restart
it yeah it's not special to my sequel
it's the operating system doing that
yeah okay all right so this point you
can say you know you could quit CMU you
have enough information in your brain to
go out and fake build a reliable
transactional database minute system
because you knew recovering new
transactions you knew query optimization
you can do database storage right this
is this is what I've at this point in
the semester these are the core things
you need to know of what a database does
so starting next week on Monday now
start talking my distributed databases
all the same concepts that we talked
about so far the semester still still
have the same problems the same same
issues that we think account for
internship and database just now we have
to account for the network which can be
slightly more tricky ok so again at this
point even though like say oh I won or
contributed databases you need to
unchain the single node databases first
and this is the point you know what
they're actually doing ok guys
[Music]