[Music]
so it's Wednesday night fights over Mack
banged Oakland so is the other guy I
decided that rather than me filming the
second lecture all over again in a motel
room I just that it would be better just
to show you guys what I did in 2018
because that was front of a live
audience and I felt that I did it I
could do a better job and whatever do by
myself
so with that that's why I'm just really
showing the 2018 lecture here for the
second lecture and then when then we'll
be heading back to CMU and then starting
Wednesday next week we'll have live
lectures again so take care today's
lecture is on advance sequel and by
advance I mean going beyond what you may
or may not already know about basic
sequel right it's it's 2018 sequel was
invented in 1973 I imagine most you have
seen some sequel throughout your life so
I don't feel it's necessary to teach you
the basics of it so I'm gonna spend time
actually talking about the more
complicated or interesting things you
can do with sequel Hey so just to pick
up where we left last class we were
discussing the relational model and
relational algebra and we sort of
mentioned that the with relational
algebra
Cerreta the goal was sort of at a high
level to describe what the answer we
wanted that the theater system would
compute rather than the exact steps of
actually how to do it all right so the
way to think about this is like say we
want to sort our data if we have to tell
the day system exactly what to do we
have to provide it you know with the
quick sort of bubble sort algorithm but
with a high level language or
declarative language would you say hey
we want you to sort this we don't care
how you actually do it but this is the
answer that we want and we'll see this
throughout today's lecture and then
going forward throughout later in the
semester this is one of the advantages
of using something like Secord or
declarative languages we don't have to
tell today's system exactly how to do
things
it can figure it out on its own and that
frees it up to figure out what the most
optimal way it is to actually execute
the query that you want to execute based
on the data that you have and and it's a
harbor that's available to you so we'll
see this later when we talk about the
query optimizer but the query optimizer
is this complicated piece of machinery
inside of a database system that's gonna
take our sequel query and convert it to
the most efficient plan and we'll cover
how they actually do this later on but I
will say is that if you if you you know
if you get involved in doing research on
query optimization or just help you know
working on Cori optimizers you can get a
job yesterday because this is the one
thing that all my friends at Davis
company companies email me about open
over again do I have any students a new
query optimization but has some and they
all get off go off and do awesome jobs
this is the one thing that everybody
wants because it's really hard to do so
that's not the focus here right just in
the back your mind will see examples as
we go along where a query optimizer
could try out different things to try to
come up with different plans well we'll
discuss how you actually do query
optimization later on so the the history
of sequel as I said goes back into the
early 1970s so you may notice that I say
sequel
some people say SQL write the part of
the reason I say sequel is because in
not that I was alive in 1970s but the
original name of the language was
actually spelled out as EQ UAL sequel
and this was invented by IBM as part of
the system our project right so it stood
for the structured English query
language so if you remember from the TED
Cod paper I said that tena Ted Cobb was
a mathematician right he devised that
relational algebra and relational model
but he didn't actually define the
programming language you would use to
write queries on it right you can't
write queries using relational algebra
right it's sort of you know there's
there's no it's very difficult to write
that in the keyboard to do that he did
later define or come up with his own
query language called alpha but that was
much later in 1970s so back then when
people said hey there's a relational
model idea we should actually try to
build a system to do this people had to
come up with their own language that
could implement relational calculus or
relational algebra so at IBM they came
out with sequel
this is part of the system our project
which is a sort of one of the first
relational database systems that people
were trying to build in the 1970s the
other major one was ingress that came
out of Berkeley so you've ever heard of
Postgres right
Postgres was invented by the same guy
that did ingress so it's called Postgres
as in post ingress the thing that came
after ingress so the ingress guys had
their own language called quell and this
was developed by one of my advisers Mike
Stormbreaker
he claims it was much better than sequel
and the IBM guys didn't know what they
were doing of course most people have
never heard a quell right I said it
didn't actually win IBM won so back then
again it was spelled out as eqtl IBM
later got sued for I think you know
copyright infringement trademark
infringement there was some guy in
England that had the the term sequel
spelt out in the full English word for
his programming language so it is
shortened it to be sq SQL so what
happened was the reason why we use
sequel today because IBM it's not back
then iBM is and what it is now right
everyone thinks the bate the big tech
companies like Microsoft Amazon and
Google back in the 1970s 1980s IBM was
was the juggernaut so essentially
whatever IBM did or said this is the way
we're gonna do it that ended up being
the standard so when IBM first released
their first commercial relational
database system db2 so they never
actually released system or was just
sort of a research prototype but then
then finally made db2 or at least that
db2 supported sequel so that essentially
became the standard and the reason why
Oracle sort of took off and got as big
as it is today is they were sort of
copying what IBM was doing in the 1970s
in more ways than one we could talk to
her that later and they did they had
sequel so when IBM came out with db2 and
had sequel Oracle was right at the right
place at the right time said we now
supports we know we support sequel - so
it became an ANSI standard in 1986 and
became an international standard in 1987
and now the short burden just means the
structured query language so sequel even
though it's from 1970s it's not a dead
language it's not certainly static it's
sort of like you know Steve s applause -
keep
new specifications every so often it's
the same thing in sequel every so often
there's a new specification where they
add in new features and new
functionalities to to the basic language
so the the latest standard is defined in
sequel 2016 and you can see over the
years at the add new versions they add
new features right so 2016 they added
JSON polymorphic tables they add XML
stuff and then 2003 1999 added regex and
triggers typically what happens is
there's a standards body that the
members are all from the major database
companies and the major database
companies come up with their own
proprietary features and extensions and
then they go in the standards body and
push to try to get their version of
certain functionality as part of the
standard right so this is although there
is a sequel standard nobody actually
follows it to the T right because
everyone sort of has their own
proprietary things that got invented
before the standard came out said this
is how you should do things so if you're
gonna claim that your database system
supports sequel the bare minimum you
need to have is actually what is defined
in the sequel 92 standard so this is
what the basic sequel that we know about
today select insert update delete create
tables transactions things like that all
that's defined in sequel 92 so again if
someone someone says their data system
supports equal chances are they that
really mean this and then the more
advanced databases both an open source
and and the commercial ones they add
they have a bunch of more features from
from from the newer standards and then
there's this great website here it's a
bit dated now but it's going at its some
random dude who basically looked at sort
of the top four top five database
systems and just look to see how they
differ on various sequel features it
compares sequel functionalities and
we'll see this as we go through today
there'll be some examples where the
standard says one thing different
database systems do other things it's
usually my sequel and this is just an
even though there's a standard nobody
actually follows it exactly right
there's no database system that I'm
aware of that would claim that they're
you know certify for sequel 2016 right
they have bits and pieces of things
so sequel itself technically is not a
single language it's sort of a
collection of things in a particular
it's a collection of a DML DDL and DCL
commands so DML will be would be the
datum innovation language would be the
commands like insert update delete
selects like the things that actually
manipulate the data that you can store
in your database the DDL is the way you
create tables actually define schemas to
actually store things and then the DCL
is the way you sort of do security
authorization to grant you know who's
allowed to read what you put what data
there's a bunch of other things like how
to define views how to define integrity
to be strange referential constraints as
well as transactions these are all part
of the umbrella of sequel right and
within that there's these different
categories of commands so the one
important thing that I want to point out
here and we'll see this throughout
today's lecture is unlike in relational
algebra which is based on set theory or
sets sequel is actually based on bag
algebra so the way it sort of thing
about this you could have like lists
sets or bags so a list can have
duplicates but there's there's a defined
orders if I push something to my list
that's its position in that list a set
is unordered meaning the elements don't
have a position but you can't have
duplicates if I try to insert the same
thing into a set it just gets over the
old run gets overwritten a bag has
neither a set position or ordering but
it also allows for duplicates right and
we'll see why we've got to do this as we
go along because if we want to actually
define order on our elements or if you
want to make sure that we don't have
duplicates essentially the database
system has to do extra work to to
provide that for you and so the idea is
that only if you explicitly ask the
database system to provide you ordering
and provide you to remove duplicates it
won't actually do it and this actually
make things be a be more efficient all
right so the outline for today is we're
going to cover aggregations group bys a
bunch of operations on strings dates and
times then we had to do output control
and then the more complicated things
have been nested queries common table
expressions and window functions so for
homework one you'll need to use all of
these except for the window functions
like it's gonna be doing homework one on
sequel light and only actually the
latest version of sequel light as of
last week just added support for window
functions but everything else sequel
light should be able to support okay all
right so for this we're needs a sample
database comprised of three tables so
sort of it's a mock University so we're
gonna have a student table where
students have student IDs names logs and
GPS will have a course table with course
IDs a name and then we'll have an enroll
table where we have a certain foreign
key reference from the student table and
the course table and along with the
grade that the student got in the class
all right we'll use this as our running
example as we go along all right so the
first thing we talk about our
aggregations right and these are pretty
simple to understand it's basically a
function that you define in the output
list of your select statement that's
going to take as input multiple tuples a
set of tuples and it's gonna compute
some kind of aggregation on top of that
and produced a single result right so
the sequel 92 standard defines average
min max sum and count and again think of
this is like in case of count you're
gonna take a bag of tuples as the input
and you're gonna count the number of
tuples there are and that you're a
produces a single output that has that
that count right it's again so this is
what's in the basic standard the the
later version of the standard and in
other database systems they'll have
other things like median mode standard
deviation right in the github different
aggregates and some of them actually
that allow you to find your own
aggregations as well so let's look an
example like this right so say we want
to discount the number of students in
this student table where the login ends
with at CS I'll cover what like is means
later on but essentially it's just
looking for a wild card here right so
the first thing the most important thing
to remember about aggregations is that
the aggregation can only appear in the
output list of the select statement
right so I have it here in the in this
it's saying this is I want to produce at
the output I can't have it in these in
these other parts here right cuz it
doesn't really make sense right because
you're computing aggregation after
you've sort of applied a filter to
figure out what tuples actually match
your where clause but the same point out
here is that in case of count again we
just want to count the number of tuples
the login field here doesn't actually
mean anything right because we're just
counting the number of tuples it doesn't
matter whether you know what the login
actually is at the point after we do the
filtering so we can rewrite this just to
have a star right the star is a special
you know special keyword in sequel the
basically says all attributes for the
tuple begin go even further and say we
can actually replace the star with a one
right count the number of tuples by just
adding one every single time right so
this is a good example where we have
three different queries that all produce
or semantically the same to produce the
same result but the data besom could
could choose different flavours or
different variations of this in order to
derive that answer and some of them may
have different performance differences
this one's pretty simple so the most
differences would be smart to realize I
don't need a copy around the login here
I can just replace that with a one right
most of them will do that but from what
complicating things it may not always
work we actually can combine the
aggregate multiple a grits together in a
single query so say for this one we want
to get the number of students and their
average GPA where their login ends with
at CS right so now you see I've combined
it average GPA and count in my output
output list for my select statement and
then it'll produce my my result like
that right pretty straightforward I can
also add the distinct keyword to tell it
to only count the distinct elements or
values of attributes for for my tuples
so this is saying count the number of
unique students with unique logins from
the student table where the login ends
with at CS right and so I had the
distinct side of account now this one's
sort of nonsensical to some way
because presumably no two students can
have the same login you know login
account otherwise you'd have problems
but in other cases you know you can
apply the same kind of thing for other
scenarios and it would work the way you
wanted to work in this case here we
produce the same result so the one thing
that now you want to may want to try to
start doing is now that I'm start doing
aggregations I want to get additional
information about my data outside of
just what I'm computing in my aggregate
right so say that I want to I want to
get the average GPA of the students that
are rolled in the course and I want to
know what that course ID was right so in
this case here I've now added the course
ID to my output list outside of my
aggregation right didn't take a guess
what would happen here would this work
or not raise your hand you think would
work raise your hand if you think it
wouldn't work see of you why correct yes
so Judy said is there's not a single
course ID for all my tuples that are
competing my average align right it's
all the students are taking all the
different classes what course ID to
actually put is the output right it's
the sequel standard say this is actually
undefined and in most systems you
actually will get an error with this we
can actually test this right so in this
there we go I have three three terminal
setup all right so this is running a
machine back in my office I have three
panels the top one is Postgres the
bottom one or the middle one is my
seagull and the bottom one is seagull
light
it's as much easier for you to type from
this machine here so I can log into that
right okay so the query was we wanted to
select where was it
just get the average GPA of students
enrolled in each course
right so select average sgpa eCourse ID
from enrolled as a student as s where
eise to deny d equals a student ID right
so Postgres says you can't do this
because as he said the course ID and I'm
highlighting here so you can't see it so
the course ID is not defined it's not
part of the aggregation right so it
doesn't know which course ID you
actually want so now if we go down and
try this in my sequel my seagull gave us
an answer right but is that correct no
right because because what course ID do
the pick I picked a random one right and
then now we can try in sequel Lite same
thing sequel Lite gave us a different
course ID so you see they both competed
the correct average but they chose
different course ID all right and just
because I know that my seagull guys
watch these videos and complain I will
say that so this is running my sequel in
and so my sequel traditionally allowed
you to do loosey goosey things like this
right so this would be running it what
they would call it traditional mode but
you can set the sequel mode to be more
strict so now if I run that same query
it throws the same air that Postgres did
so by default the least my sequel 5.7
when now throw errors in older versions
they didn't do that right okay
so a way to fix this is to do goodbye
so with group I what's gonna happen is
now we're gonna define how we want to
essentially buck it together the tuples
in our output based on one attribute and
then now we can then compute the
aggregation
on the tuples in each bucket right so
again what I wanted to do was get the
average GPA per course if I add now in
my group by clause I add the the course
ID what will happen is when I first
execute the query this is essentially
what I would see after the join but now
with the group by clause I'll combine
together the the two posts based on the
course ID and then for each of these now
I'll compute my aggregate right and now
I can group them by course ID and that
corresponds to the buckets are generated
from before right so we have to use
group I if we want to extract
information about the aggregations we're
computing right and so just like before
any time we have a attribute that we
won't appear in our output select clause
it has to appear in the group ID
so here the student name we're trying to
throw that in in our output Clause it
won't work because it has to be in our
group I'd calls
now this one is sorted to get
nonsensical it's technically correct
sequel it produced a result but from a
human standpoint we know doesn't mean
anything good well like what does it
mean to group by course ID and then the
student name to compute the average GPA
right the student's GPA is gonna be
their GPA okay so now you may think
alright well maybe I want to do them
with some more some additional filtering
all my aggregations so that I don't look
at you know I don't produce every single
result as part of the output so you may
think that you out want to put it
use the aggregations in your where
clause so here now I'm now I'm computing
every GPA but I'm added in my where
clause something that says filter out
anything where the GPA is is not you
know greater than 3.9 this is look only
trying to look at the courses with
average GPA is greater than 3.9 right so
this doesn't work because in our
can't access anything in our
aggregations in our where clause because
we don't have them yet in our where
clause right so again the way to think
about this is the where clause is
filtering tuples as we go along and
after we do our filtering then we can
actually then computer aggregation so we
can't compute we can't use an
aggregation to filter tuples because we
haven't computed the aggregation yet
right so the way to get around this is
to use the having clause it's
essentially like a where clause but now
you can reference anything in your
output list so I've taken my average GPA
and I've aliased it to AVG GPA and I can
publish that down on here and this will
produce the answer that I want right
computes the aggregation is just like
before and then it applies additional
filtering on it so now not in this
example but there's other examples where
you can do sort of certain optimizations
in the system based on what you know is
in your having clause again this is the
great thing about declarative language
you know everything all ahead of time
what the you know what the programmer
the person wants in their answer so you
can use hints about what you knows could
come later in the query plan to help you
do certain refinements or reduce the
amount of work you have to do as you run
the query so instead of using average
GPA say I wanted to do account where the
number of tuples are less than some you
know first each group less than some
value so as I'm going along as I'm
computing my aggregate if I then
recognize that oh my having Clause says
filter anything less than ten two pools
if not if I now hit tuple number eleven
for a group I know that I never need to
count anything else for that for that
tuples that come later because it'll
never pass that having falls so I can
just throw away those tuples as I go
along because it's wasted work right if
you're writing this in a procedural
language like Python all right well you
had to write these steps but it's you
know by by yourself the you know the
Davidson is not going to know what's
gonna come later on because it can't
peek ahead right but in a declarative
language like C code we can do that so
the next thing we want to talk about is
how to handle strings
so this is a table that sort of
summarizes the the different variations
of how strings are handled in different
database systems so the the sequel
standard specced says that all strings
like some varchars chars text fields
they have to be case sensitive and the
way you declare them is with single
quotes and most systems follow this
right the red herrings of the oddballs
are both my sequel and sequel light so
in sigil light the strings are sensitive
but you can have both single and double
double quotes - to mark them in my
sequel it's case insensitive and you can
use either single or double quotes now
my problem is that when I started using
database systems back in like 2000 I was
using my single three and it's like it's
like you know ingrained in my memory to
just use double quotes because that's
what we use back then so I'm always had
to correct myself every time I switch
over another native system to go always
go back and use single quotes my Seco
again has the mode you can say to follow
the stand it'll get better and they then
enforce the single quote requirement but
I think by default you don't get that
right so in the siegel standards say you
want to take the name you want to take
the name of kanye and have it matched
with kanye with you know mixed case in
in in the single standard you had the
upper case using the upper you know the
upper function to make this match work
and my sequel you don't have to do that
right because all all the strings are
matching or case insensitive now I
showed this before how to do light
clause but I think it's a lies you do
the first string matching alright so
like is basically doing you know trying
to match some wild card in your string
with with with another string so for
whatever reason instead of using star
like most other things they use the
print a % so % means any one or more
strings and then the underscore means
exactly match one character alright so
say I want to get all the course or the
all the course IDs from the role table
that start with
tene 215 445 721 I would use the the
amperes the % like that and say if I
want to get all the students where the
the login ends with at C and then some
wild card I will use a single underscore
for that so the seagull standard also
defines a bunch of string functions
there's a again the standard things you
would expect like substring upper lower
trim or these are all part of the sequel
9q standards and move systems will have
this but of course there will be a bunch
of other stuff that are proprietary in
each different database system so the
thing to point out unlike aggregation
functions with string functions and you
know mathematical functions and date
functions they can appear anywhere in
the in your in your queries so they can
be in the Select output list it can be
in your predicate s-- alright they don't
always have to be in the in the select
portion they can mean you're having
clauses so here we have you know the
first guy first query is gonna take the
name and take a substring and just get
just get the first five characters and
then the second one we did is to show
before of doing matching where the the
uppercase version of the student name is
begins with Kay kan so again string
functions are for the most part the
basic ones will be pretty much
standardized across all systems where
things get weird as when you want to
start doing a concatenation so the Seco
standard says that you use two double
bars to concatenate two strings together
and most systems follow this in my
opinion I would say Postgres in Oracle
probably followed the sequel standard
the best out of all the systems sequel
server and db2 are probably next single
light then probably my sequel is the
worst so you want to say to concatenate
the student name and add es to it do use
double bar in the sequel standard in
sequel server from Microsoft you use the
plus sign in my sequel they don't have a
plus sign they don't have the double bar
they only have this concat function were
you basically defined as the input
parameters the things you want to
concatenate together they have something
else that's kind of weird to where you
can actually
if you don't put anything between two
string literals that'll concatenate them
together so to show you what I mean by
that so here we have my Siegel so I can
do something like this a n dy space PA
VLO right nobody else does this as far
as I know let me double check that
before I lie to you
let's try it in huh yeah toka first
Chris doesn't like it
sequel server doesn't like it either
right only my sequel does that all right
so now we're things get really really
bad is when you have date and time
functions right so a date basically you
can just records the timestamp without
the time timestamp is is the time now
they vary on the granularity of the time
they may be tracking sometimes in
seconds sometimes it's in milliseconds
or something even more fine-grain than
that
but where things get get wonky is how
you actually start manipulating them and
extracting them extracting information
from them right and so the syntax for
all these different systems can can can
vary wildly so for this example we want
to do is I want to show you how to do
what I consider a seemingly easy
function or easy operation get the
number of days from today to since the
beginning of the year and we'll see how
to try to do this and on these three
different systems okay so the first
thing is that we want to get maybe what
the current time is now
I just kill my wife I okay back okay all
right so the seco standard defines a now
function can everyone see that or now in
the back guys can you see it okay cool
so you call now and it gives you the
current timestamp so we can do that in
in my sequel and we can do this in
sequel light what you can't do in a
single vibe all right all right so
there's another way to do this
they have another function called a
current timestamp right except Postgres
doesn't have it but they had the keyword
current time Stan my sequel has the
function and it has the keyword all
right single lane who says it has the
function raise your hand so who says it
says it has the keyword all right it's
mixed all right they don't have the
function they have a keyword all right
again simple thing like what's the
current time
it varies all right so now again what we
want to do is we want to count the
number of days since the since the
beginning of the year all right so as a
building block what we can try to do is
maybe just get what the number of days
is from from today so in this query what
I'm doing is I'm taking a date listed
here's a string right so I'm taking the
string for today's date and converting
it into a date and then I have the
extract function which will extract out
the the day field of the date right so
as expected you get you get 29 all right
we can try that in the and the other
guys it gives you 29 they don't have it
all right
so but now we can see that like alright
well if I can if I can cast a string for
the date into a date what happens if I
just subtract them right I said I'll
take today's date and subtract the it
from the date from the beginning of the
year and in Postgres we get it 240 days
all right my sequel 728 I don't know
what that means right like it's not like
240 times 2 or some you know some
multiple there right it's it's a number
right it ran but it's not what we want
right so now let's try it in in sequel
light sequel like give us 0 okay so it
works in Postgres and now we gotta
figure how to do this in my sequel well
so what we can do is we we try to
extract the the day from so maybe we
take what we'd bet 728 we had before
right and we extract the day from and
see what that means all right it came
back with 28 so that's not really what
we want so the way to do it actually is
a bit complicated what we're gonna do is
we're going to convert the dates into
UNIX timestamp which is the number of
seconds since the unit's to epoch which
is like some Jan refers 1970 right and
now we're gonna have the number of
seconds from from the current date
number seconds since beginning the day
we subtract them right and that gives us
the number of seconds between now and
the beginning of the year and then we're
gonna divide that by 60 seconds times 60
minutes times 24 days right we got 240
all right
turns out though after I did this the
first time there's actually even easier
way in my sequel they have a simple
function called date div and that
produces you know the same answer all
right
sico light uh-huh for Brianna I think
let me try make this a little bigger
there go in single light they don't have
date if you can't subtract age with each
other the the way I figured out to do it
was convert the current timestamp into
the to the Julian calendar which is the
number of days since 437 be sore for
4370 BC and so you subtract the more
days since that time it's the number
days beginning the year and you get
roughly 240 right all right and we can
cast it to an int and we get 240 right
so these are three super super widely
used database systems that all differ on
some basic functionality of doing date
and time right actually a quick show of
hands who think of these three ones
which one you think is the most popular
miss widely deployed database system
raise your hand you think my sequel
about a quarter raise your hand think
Postgres even less Radian think seagull
light even less the answer sequel light
so a few years ago we had Richard hippie
invent our sequel light so see the light
is amazing it's written by three dudes
right there they is he approximate that
it's been deployed on 10 billion devices
everyone here who has a cell phone right
that isn't a flip phone or an old person
phone is running sequel light on it
right now right a lot of desktop
applications like Photoshop and
illustrator they run sequel light on the
inside right sequel light is everywhere
he said that also to every single AOL CD
if you know what that is all right back
in the early 2000s when the internet was
sort of new in the u.s. there was
company called America Online and they
would every mail everyone CDs for ten
hours free on the internet right every
CD that they mailed out you know
hundreds of millions of them had sequel
light running on it right sequel a is
most widely deployed David
everywhere and here's the most crazy
part it's public domain he gives it away
for free right I mean Postgres and my
Segal are open-source but like Haytham
oh my sequel Oracle owns it all Co owns
the copyright there's no copyright on
sequel Lite right it's an amazing piece
of software okay alright so again the
main takeaway here was that simple
things are hard to do because there's no
stamp you know there's no standard way
to do things even though there is a
standard Tessa fication all right so now
maybe what you want to do is instead of
having the you know in my examples I had
the terminal open every time I ran a
query that the output got printed back
to me and my terminal but maybe what you
want to do is keep all the data you you
you generate from a query keep that
inside the database system so you can
use it in subsequent queries right this
is way more efficient if your if your if
your queries generating a lot of output
you don't have everything sitting down
to your laptop and then push it back up
to do more queries on it so you can do
output redirection to tell it to say hey
don't print it out to me write it out to
this location
so one thing you do is you can take the
output or query and you can write it
into another table right and so you in
the sequel standard you can use into and
this will actually will create the table
for you on the fly so whatever is
produces the output of the query right
again this is declarative the data
system already knows what the schema is
of the table so it knows in this case
here what the type is that this output
is going to be so he knows how to define
a table that has that it can handle
those types right so into basically
takes the output to select and writes it
into a table and in my sequel you have
to use the create table and then inside
of it you define your Select statement
you can also have it output data into an
existing table and for this you use
insert into which looks a lot like we
created into the create table from from
before and then instead of having the
value Clause you actually just have a
select statement just to tell it hey get
this data aren't right into here so the
important thing about this example
versus the previous slide this is about
writing tables in two tuples in two
tables that already exist so that means
that whatever the whatever
to type the number attributes and their
types that are produced by the Select
statement whatever table you're writing
it into has to match that right if the
the Select statement has 44 columns and
your table you're writing into as three
the days and we'll throw in air it says
I can't write into that because it the
Astros don't match up now where things
get weird is when you start having
constraints that are on the table you're
trying to write into and the Select
statement actually violates those
constraints so let's say that I have a
primary key on my table it says I can't
have any duplicate student IDs and then
my insert query here tries to start and
start inserting duplicates some database
system will throw an error immediately
as soon as it sees a duplicate and no
tuples get written some of them will
just keep going and ignore the ones that
that failed other ones will will insert
the ones that succeeded and just ignore
the ones that failed or maybe just crash
right away right so again the seco
standard says this is the syntax it to
use but how all the systems actually
implement it will vary widely in
addition to output redirection we can
also do output control remember I said
the beginning Seco is based on bag
algebra I mean it's unordered but
there's many times where you want the
ordering in your output Clause and so to
do this you add the order by clause I
have seen is basically specifying how to
sort the results that are being
generated by by this query so in this
example here I'm gonna sort the tuple
started sort of the tuple main role
table based on their grade and by
default even though I don't specify
whether I wanted ascending and or
descending the default and sequel is
that you get ascending now you get
output like this but I also can add
additional attributes to my order by
clause do more complicated things so in
this case here I want to do my order by
by grade in descending order and then
after that I sort them based on the
student ID in ascending order right and
I would get output like this now the
important thing to point out here also
too is that unlike there in the group by
clause
where any attribute that I wanted my
output list had to appear in the group
by clause in order by you don't have
that restriction right it actually goes
both ways in this case here I'm sorting
by the grade but the grade isn't part of
the output right it doesn't matter right
and it knows how to how to how to find
the data that it needs as its processing
the query and do whatever sorting
operation that you want to do on it I
can also do more complicated things I
can put any arbitrary expression in my
order by Clause as well so I can do
order by 1 plus 1 right and that's still
valid it knows how to handle that
another common thing you want to do is
is limit the number of tuples that are
produced in your output right and of
course there's a there's a limit clause
for this he basically specifies says I
for all the results that you of Mike my
query only provide me back some number
of them like 10 right and this is very
common for things like you know say like
search results you'll see it show just
10 and then you click the next button to
go see the next 10 all right this is
being controlled by it by limit and
actually all set so limit just says
limit the number of tuples all set is
going to tell you that and what all set
of the number of the tuples you're
producing as your output should you skip
before you start figuring out how many
you should limit right again if you
think of a webpage to show you ten
results you click Next to see the next
10 they're using a limit with an all set
to make that work now because it's
unsorted again is no guarantee that when
you click Next if you're using offset
you're going to see you definitely gonna
see different tuples because that's
another invocation of the query and the
results may be different in different
order the second time so in this case
here you would combine that with an
order by Clause so that you're
guaranteed to go you know see the first
10 followed by the second 10 and so
forth right
and there's optimizations you can apply
whether you're not you have an order by
Clause if you have a limit Clause so if
I don't have an order by clause and I
have a limit I know that as soon as I
see sent 10 to polls I'm done I don't
need to go look at anything else if you
have an order by then you have to sort
you have to see everything ahead of time
to sort it then you can apply your limit
and your
set ice again I considered that somewhat
basic sequel in previous years I
actually skipped all this but I I think
it's a portent maybe to go go over it a
little bit cuz you have to understand
this for the homework but now we want to
talk about more complicated things this
is what I would consider advance sequel
so the first thing I want to talk about
is is nested queries so the way anything
about nested query it's basically
allowing you to specify queries inside
of queries right and you can take the
output of one query and use that as the
input of another query all right so a
simple example like this I'm doing a
select I want to get all the names of
the students that are enrolled in least
one course so I have my outer query is
defined based on the student table and
then the side of that I have inner query
that's and it's gonna get the student
IDs from the role table right so we
could write this as a join this is sort
of sudden another way to actually do
this and in actuality when it comes time
to actually implement this inside the
system most query optimizer will try to
rewrite this as a join right because it
the worst way to actually execute this
is to essentially have two for loops
where you loop over every single tuple
in the student table and for every
single two but you then reimpose the
same query over and over and over again
my sequel used to do this the more
primitive Davian systems you should do
this but the the right way to do is
actually just rewrite this as a join
alright so you can sort of think of this
inner query as like a function that's
can produce some set of tuples as your
output and then you can apply whatever
predicate you want on that in the outer
query so we'll walk through a bunch of
examples of this and see how it works
so the alright so the first example I
want to if maybe I want to get the names
of all the students exist in that
enrolled in 15 for 45 so the way to
construct a nested query is I think it's
always important to start maybe with the
outer query and think about what's the
actual answer you want to produce like
what are the actual attributes you what
you want to see and then you worry about
how you're actually going to filter them
and get what you want so the outer query
we know that we want the name from the
student table and then where we get
those values we'll figure it out
so in the inner query we can write it in
as English as the student ID
and the set of people about take 4:15
4:45 right so for that part we know how
to write that query pretty easily right
we just feel throw out all the tuples
some enroll table or the course IDE goes
15 for 45 so now the question is how do
we combine them with the the outer query
with the inner query again we can
rewrite this as very easily with the
join but for our purposes here we want
to see how to do it as a nested function
so for this we can use the in operator
and we do a matching on the student
student ID so a way to now read this is
that the for every single student in the
student table
so this first student ID is matching up
with a student table I want to see
whether there's a match of that student
ID in the set of all student IDs that
are in the role table that take the
course 15 for 45 so we exit the inner
query we produce the set of all student
IDs and then for every single tuple in
the outer query we check to see whether
it exists in that set right now this
visit shows you why I was saying before
the stupid way to execute this is for
every single tuple in the outer query we
execute the inner query over and over
again like that's stupid because we only
need to produce the inner query once and
then we can reuse it for every single
tuple and in the outer query so I show
it how to in the Attic see if I used in
those other operators you can use so all
basically says that every single tuple
that's in my inner query must must
satisfy my predicate any means at least
one of them needs to alright so in is
essentially the same thing as equals any
is there any tuple that it equals what
my predicate or about my tuple attribute
is checking and then exists says at
least one rows returned and actually I
don't care where that matches I just
care what to see whether to ball got
produces as a result so we can rewrite
our example for getting all the students
in 15 for 45 like this right instead of
using in we say equals ending so now you
read this as the student ID from the
student table check to see
whether it equals any tuple that exists
in the set of student IDs that are
produced by from from the enroll table
right now the inner key the nested
queries don't have to only appear in the
where clause they actually can appear
anywhere right so I can rewrite the same
query like this where now I have my
nested query in the output of the Select
statement so this is a good example this
is essentially reversing what I did
before in terms of what tables are going
to access so now the way to read this is
that for every single tuple in the
enroll table where the course ID equals
15 45 15 4 45 I'm gonna then do a
matchup in this student table where the
student IDs are the same right there's
essentially doing a join inside my
output of my select statement right
because now this d'un ID is being
referenced here from the student table
and that student ID is being referenced
in there okay there's another good
example again I essentially reversing
the order of how I process my tables
right and they produce the exact same
result but they may have different
performance characteristics based on
what my data actually looks like it may
be the case that this is actually faster
to go through the enroll table first
instead of the student table and
therefore we could rewrite it if we
wanted to to choose one versus the other
and a good optimizer could do this for
you okay all right let's look at
something any more complicated now
alright say we want to find the student
record with the highest ID that enrolled
in least one course right seems pretty
simple but let's think we actually do
this so the first approximation would be
something like this select the max
student ID along with the student name
from from the join and rolled and
student table where the student ID in
the role table equals the student ID in
the student table will this work why why
not
what's that yeah there's an aggregation
function without a group I and we're
referencing a column that's not in the
aggregation right
so again sequel standard says that this
shouldn't work let's find out alright so
again we have I gotta disconnect first
cuss at the top so we've run our query
here again Postgres and here's the
standard it says get as exactly as he
said so you have student ID student name
appears but it's not a part of a group I
so you can't use it right in my sequel
same thing it produces that error but if
we now run it in what they call
traditional mode right so older versions
of my sequel would do this now we run
this query and we get an answer right
we had the Mac student ID and then we
say that the name best student is Tupac
all right let's try it in sequel Lite
run one it produced an answer it also
produces 53 688 as the next to 90 but it
says the that student belongs to Justin
Bieber right and actually I don't know
what the right answer is let's see here
yeah so justin bieber is the right one
right whereas my sequel make sure i'm
giving you the same data right Tupac is
actually the lowest alright so it got it
completely wrong alright so the right so
this doesn't work in the sequel standard
it runs a single byte and and and my
SIBO if we turn off that strict mode
thing so way we can do this is a nested
function as again let's build it
constructively so we know do you want
the student ID and the name as the
output but it's the where clause that
think we have to figure out and this one
basically says that we want to get a
matching tuple that is greater than
every other student ID that that's
that's in our table right so we know the
inner query shall should be basically
the student ID from the enroll table we
can be more more sophisticated maybe put
a distinct there but it's all the same
but now we need to figure out how to
match the student ID from the student
and an outer query the student ID from
from the inner query and for this we can
use greater than equal to all right it
has to be greater than equal to because
we make sure that we match ourselves the
student that actually is that does
actually have that the highest one right
we can rewrite this in other ways as
expected right we can rewrite it with
the in clause like that and actually
compute the max student ID and the inner
query right now basically this is saying
match the student ID that is the max
student ID produced from from the enroll
table right we can go even further we
can rewrite the inner guy to be like
this right we do an order by and the
student ID and just rank them in
descending order and then do a limit one
so some systems will actually just
rewrite this one to be a max anyway just
scan everything keep track of which
one's the max and it produces the final
output don't even bother to do them
sorting right again same query rewritten
in different ways one more example we're
gonna find all the courses that have no
students enrolled in them so we take our
outer query as a Select on the courses
and then we know our inner query
basically says when a find note would
have no tuples in the enroll table
so for this one we want to use not
exists basically says we don't want to
match anything in our inner query and
all we need to do that for the inner
queries is just just grab every single
tuple and here now we're actually
matching up the the course ID in the
inner query with the course ID from the
outer query so you can only do this in
one direction so if you're the inner
query you can represent the outer query
if you're in the outer query you can't
reference the inner query right unless
you pipe it out or redirect it to a
table so any questions about nested
queries again they're very powerful many
tens you cannot write what you want to
write in in in a single query without
using nested queries yes her question is
can you think of an inner query as a
nested for loop yes but no so we'll see
for loop it has a notion of like
ordering it's it's really a set right so
all those operators like in X exists any
those are just trying to say for the
entire set of tuples that are in the
inner query check to see whether any of
em matches you're not you're not really
iterating over every single one if you
think of the outer query sort of as a
four because you're iterating every
single tuple but then the set portion
the evaluation of the inner query is
always at server and a bag or set set
level makes sense okay window functions
so window functions are I would say
they're new but they're like fifteen ten
years old now so they're not like not
brand new a lot of systems don't support
them but the major ones do so a window
function is sort of like an aggregation
where you're going to compute some some
function on on tuples but rather than
doing it on you know a subset of the
tuples and collapsing them down into a
single result you sort of do this in a
incremental fashion or on a moving
fashion and then you still produce the
two
as the output but along with the value
that it produced from the window
function right so the basic syntax is
like this you have the function name and
then you have an over clause
so the function name will be our
aggregation functions and other special
window functions we have which I'll show
the next slide and then the over the
over Clause defines how we actually want
to slice up the data right this is sort
of like combining together the
aggregation and the group by but in a
single clause so the function is like
the aggregation function the over is
like the group I so the aggregation
function should be all the things in the
sequel standard that we talked before
min max average count some the special
wind functions to do things like
introduce a row number to the current
row so to keep track as the tuples
that's being output and it marks them
with what order they're they're coming
out and then rank would be the order of
the position of a tuple if we're doing
sorting alright so say what I want to do
is I want to go do a select over the
enroll table and I want to produce all
the tuples as my output but I want to
just mark them with the row number of
the output alright so I have my row
number row number function and then for
my over Clause I just leave that blank
and then what I end up with is a result
that looks like this
all right I have all the data that I had
before but now I had this special column
here row num that's just again the order
of the tuple that that that it was
produced in the output so sort of like I
compute my entire query and then I do my
window function to go over the results
and I and then I add in whatever the
computation that I want to generate so
just like a group aggregations we can we
can combine things together or group
them together this is what the over
keyword does for us so for this we would
use partition by to specify how we want
to group things all right so in this
query here I'm doing the same thing as
before where I want to combine them
together based on the generate the row
number and for how they produced in
their output but then I'm gonna group
them together based on the course ID
right so my output would look like this
right and so now again it looks just
like the aviation where now I'm grouped
together
based on the order right pretty simple
so let's look at something more
complicated so I can also order by these
I can order them instead of partitioning
them and this is essentially defining
how we want to do our ordering produce
to produce our outputs if we do this
ordering then we compute whatever this
the window function is that we want to
compute on that so in this case here
this is a sense you can do the same
thing I did in previous slide where it's
going to more of us
group them based on the course ID but
this is doing this by using ordering
rather than partitioning all right so
let's say we want to compute want to
find the student with the highest grade
for each course so what we have here is
now we have nested query so in the outer
query we're just going to well on the
outer query is server in the inner query
we're going to produce some table result
but now this is a good example we're
having a nested query inside of the from
clause so I have from here and then I'm
taking the output of this inner query
and I'm gonna map that into a sort of a
temporary virtual table called ranking
that only exists for this tuple right so
instead of writing it to a table that
are exist we're writing into a temporary
table I don't stay in memory because it
may actually go out the disk but a
temporary tuple table for this this
query that then gets discarded when the
query is over so in the inner query what
we're gonna do is we're going to go over
the enrolled table and for every single
tuple we're gonna split them up based on
the course ID that's the partition
clause and then we're gonna sort them by
their grade in ascending order and then
what we produce the window function we
invoke is rank which is the order that
they exist in the in the sort of ranking
and then we take that output write it
out to the ranking table and then in the
outer query we can then do additional
filtering based on the their rank so
this is only produce the tuples that are
that
ranked first right so this is finding
the students the highest grade for each
course right so the thing to point out
here is I have I'm referencing in my
outer query this ranked attribute here
which actually doesn't really exist in
the database again it only exists within
this query I'm seeing a lot of blank
faces so let's maybe pop up in the
database and see we can do all right so
for this so Postgres is the only one
that actually supports this my sequel
eight supports window functions and the
newer version sequel Lite support window
functions but for simplicity what does
do my and Postgres alright so this is
the query that we had before right let's
break it up and make it and just do the
inner query first and that way it'll be
sort of easy to understand right so
we'll just go back and run this so again
what this is gonna do is going to go
over the enroll table it's going to
partition each record based on the
course ID so you see that here where for
15 for 45 appears first then 7 21 then 8
26 and then now within each of these
partitions
it's the N going to sort the tuples
based on their grade in descending order
or sorry in in ascending order so be
pump comes for see Abe you'll come from
C and then there's nobody else taking a
26 so the B's by itself right so that's
how we got that output in the form that
we redefined so now the rank function is
gonna be computed based on where each
tuple appears in the sorted output list
so in this case here this first tuple
and within this partition this guy came
first so he gets Rank 1 this
I came second so he gets ranked too
right if I change this now to be in
descending order
it doesn't still does the same thing but
I could do an order by again and now I
want to go in descending order right
well this is this this is doing the
order by this did the order by after I
did my window function so it doesn't
make sense but the the the main thing in
the the rank is different rotoma because
the row number two says where do you
appear in the output the rank is where
do you appear in the sorted order okay
yes say it again sorry he says if you
have a rank without an order by will
just return a random order well you'll
still get it ordered by what you have
until get them probably split by
partitions it doesn't have to be because
it's unsorted but that's what you'll get
but now here yeah so there in this case
here there is no sort ordering anymore
so everyone has the rank of one right
but it still group them up together
based on what I'd find it as my
partition and that's more of an artifact
of how the database system actually
executed the query rather than the
semantics of the query itself his
question is what is the rank function do
the rank is the rank of the rank
function produces the rank of the sort
order right so if I change my window
function to be row number okay I have my
partition but but it's one two one two
one right because within each partition
that's what I read peer so I've removed
actually the partition by then it should
go through one through five right like
that if I change this now to rank
everything should be one one one right
because there is no soil order
everyone's first
yes our question is a pointless view of
rank without an order by yes because
there's no there's no sort order so
there's no ranking all right cool all
right so the last thing we want talk
about is si si es complex table
expressions so this is Polly again Mike
this is I find this very interesting
this is probably one more complicated
things that you can do in sequel and
it's gonna look a lot like nested
queries in that you're taking the output
of a query I'm using as the input for
another query but we'll see in a second
what you can do with CT ease that you
can't do in Annessa queries yes so her
question is in the case of this is it
this particular query or it is in
general so a question is is there a
particular advantage of using rank with
a window function over using a group by
so again if you use a group by that's
not going to generate the same you're
not going to get the tuples as part of
the output anymore right so if I go back
so say I do this one here right row
number by partition by so if I go back
and I say I want to compute now like the
the max grade some enrolled group by
course ID like I no longer see what the
original tuples were could they get
collapsed together in the aggregate
function the window function still
produces all the tuples that word in
your output but I can now see them as I
can still see them as the output so if I
go back here and if I this may or may
not work but let's see so maybe I try
max grade petition my course ID yeah so
here I'm not didn't quite work either
what's that sticking oh you know why it
might be oat now they didn't like it
there's the rank oh yeah because I'm an
idiot sorry yes it did work I was what I
wanted min yeah so the highest grade at
15 for 45 is was was a B right so I
still see my original two bows I still
see one student got a C one student got
a B but the max for that group was B so
I didn't lose the original tuples now
you and your application code have to
derive meanings from this output you
know get the one field that you won but
this has allows you to get and still
keep the tuples in a way you can't with
a group I that's a good question yes
this question is can you use row number
after use an order by so something like
this right and then maybe order by oh
yeah there yeah sorry that's why there's
the as rank so let's do this row num oh
I'm a idiot sorry no one can see this
how can you yeah sorry my screen shows
one thing this shows another that shows
this okay we're good right right
now if we if we remove the partition by
and now we can maybe put descending
right so now we'll get 5 4 3 2 1 right
the plate replace the rank with the row
number what do you mean let's do this
online because I want to get to see two
E's cuz he knew it for the homework
before we keep going okay we can try it
afterwards okay all right so she sees
the way basically is gonna work is that
you have introduced to this whiffed
clause there's whiffed clause it's like
a query that's gonna actually before
your your regular query so we have width
and we're defining the name or a CTE and
then we have our ask clause and whatever
is inside of the parentheses after the
as the output of that query would then
get sort of maps to the this are the
name of our CTE and then in the Select
query that comes below it can reference
it does it just as if it was a an
existing table right so in this case
here what will happen is I see te that
invokes the query select one all right
so let's don't have to have a from
Clause this just out pollutes this
produces a single tuple with a single
attribute with the value one and then
this other we're at the bottom to select
star on it and there's outputs that
single tuple so I can start doing more
complicated things I can now bind the
the name or the output columns from the
queries inside of the CTE to given names
and then I can reference them by that
name down below in my in my statement at
the bottom so this this CTE produces a
single tuple with two attributes with
the values one and two and then these
get mapped to the name column 1 column 2
and then in the Select statement below I
can just add them together right pretty
straightforward
so let's go back and try to do that
example we did before where we want to
find the name of the student with the
highest I student ID that's enrolled in
least one course so for this I have my
CTE and the side of that I'll do my max
on the student ID on the enroll table
again that produces one tuple with that
max student ID and then down below I can
do a join where I'm gonna reference the
the CTE that was generated above me and
I just combined together the max ID that
came out of this which is defined here
with my student ID and then that
produces that produces the one tuple
that I want right again this is another
example of how to do the same query the
same at a high level semantically the
same query just written in different
ways so now you may be saying well how
is this any different than a nested
query right the answer is you can do
recursion in a common table expression
that you can't do in a nested query so
bear with me here but this query is
going to produce a sequence of numbers
from from 1 to 10 like a for loop right
so now we have with recursive we have
the keyword and then inside of our CTE
definition we're gonna do a union
between a single query that produces the
value 1 all right a single tuple with a
single attribute 1 and then we're gonna
then Union that with another query that
actually references ourselves so that
seeing here we're gonna vote on our own
CTE and then we're gonna take whatever
the counter is that's produced by this
and add 1 to it and produce that as the
output all right and we keep running
this until our where Clause actually
gets tripped up where we try to go above
10 and then now we stop producing 2
pools so now we have the answer that we
want that we can then reference below in
our CTE yes you know it's basically
Union right it's Union with you know
with duplicates
you mean by default sorry you need to
start a union without duplicates Union
with duplicates Union without all strips
keeps duplicates Union with with out all
removes them might be that way we can
test that though okay so let's do this
in Postgres so for the alright so this
is this is the one query that this is
the query that I showed you right and we
produce the list of tuples right with a
single value one dn't one does hat right
let me try to kill this alright that
better alright but it be careful about
CTE s with recursive because again net
because you can essentially have
infinite loose so in this query here I
no longer have that counter where it's
greater than ten or produce check any
tuples where they're less than ten this
will run actually forever but what I did
first was I define a toll Postgres to
again I'm highlighting here and you
can't see it at all post past that any
query that runs longer than 10 seconds
automatically kill it so when I ran this
query now it no longer has the where
clause to prevent it from going you know
looking at tuples beyond ten and so
essentially runs forever
Postgres recognizes that we're stuck it
and a query that's taking too long and
go that goes head and automatically
kills it yes so suits all right so
select one just does this right so now
if I do select one Union all select one
right I get like that
so if I think I remove the all yeah you
get it's a without it removes duplicates
right so you know will give me
everything so essentially what's
happening now is I'm calling my CTE say
whatever the whatever tools you have in
the current value take take the output
and then add one to it here right the
the plus one there so this is invoking
on on our our our source CTE called
source for every single tip one their
take its output add one to it so in
order to get that tuple it has to go
then invoke that CTE which then produces
back one yeah it won't let you in bogey
because it knows you're trying to
reference yourself those questions what
happens if you if you try to remove the
recursive calls again its sequel its
declarative we know everything you're
trying to do so you're trying to access
a CTE table that's defined by yourself
and it doesn't let you do that for
cursive let you do that so let's try it
now also with let's try it by removing
the Union all and see what happens the
call apartment and still produces the
correct answer yes you don't you don't
need the Union all right so in this
example here again I'm synthetically
generating a two table that has a single
value of one and then I invoke a query
to get that tuple and add one to it but
then generates a new tuple which and
that can then invoke again and add one
to that and I keep doing that until I
don't produce any more matches right
because any the current ends because
I've reached my limit of ten yes
this question is why why are there not
duplicates because the first time you
devoted you had one six second time you
invoke you would have one and two let's
do this offline let's walk through it
because again we am Braddock we're out
of time
all right yes quick this question is do
people use for courtesy teas is that
very common yes absolutely yes so this
is actually finished up very nicely so
the the second point I'm trying to make
here is that in an ideal scenario you
always want to have do to be able to
compute an entire query without having
to bring any data locally or not having
to go back and forth right so in a it
also provides by running as a single
query
although the complexity that makes it
harder to new query optimization but if
you tell the gaming system everything
you want to do with this sort of piece
of data then they can do a global
optimization on that so by having a CTE
you're not having to have additional
logic be somewhere salicin outside the
David system it will go back and forth
you're saying here's everything I want
to do so CTE are actually very common
especially in newer applications
recursive CDs maybe less so but
definitely cetys but it's another way to
write a nested query alright the other
major thing that I want to point out is
that again the language is from 1973 or
1974 but it's still widely common you're
commonly used it's being updated all the
time and learning sequel is important
because you're gonna see this again
throughout your entire life pretty much
every single system database system that
you know it with some minor exceptions
is going to support some variant of
sequel Oh
I shouted to settle the case a machine
on little bits of broken bar goes in
crushed up kids
let the cows in the demo I'll try he's
witzy nines in my system I'm blessed
let's go get the next one good never be
son ricochet jelly hit the deli food
report one naturally bless ya what
rappers like the laser beam the balls in
the bush say nothing like a king wrap
the bottle of us a nice sympathy goes
don't feel like drinking that quality
you drunk you can't drop cross he was
alive and at the stake don't know your
phone can tap a