[Music]
so as hopefully you've noticed I'm not
Andy Andy and KB welcomed their first
child last week everyone's doing well
and we're just we're extremely thrilled
to see the Andy Pablo parenting
experiment so the clicker stopped
working so last class Andy talked a lot
about acid properties of transactions
focusing a lot on isolation in
particular reasoning about whether
schedules are serializable and we talked
about conflict serializability and view
serializability and with conflict
serializability we were able to to
verify whether whether a schedule was
serializable based on being able to swap
operations around or looking at the
dependency graph and being able to say
yes this this schedule is serializable
or whether whether it would violate the
serializability guaranteed and then
there was this other notion of view
serializability which most applications
are actually no systems really support
because it's this this concept of being
able to produce results to the
application that look right to the
application but actually aren't
serializable as we've defined them it
wouldn't be conflict serializable so i
think he gave a couple examples one
would be like counting all the number of
accounts that had a positive balance
while he was shuffling money around
between the accounts and because the
accounts never dropped negative we got
the correct result but it wouldn't
technically be a conflict serializable
schedule I think another one was just
doing blind writes in two accounts and
because the last write that we cared
about was the one that got executed it
counts as view serializable but it's not
actually conflict serializable so there
was a lot of time spent on like how do
you verify these schedules but now we
want to care about is how do you do this
stuff in real time because
he's got an example here so an example
of this is not conflict serializable
because of we have this right on a and
then another read on a unrepeatable read
this is not conflict serializable so
that's basically what Andy talked about
in the last lecture I'm gonna try to
make up for time here because we're
starting a little late so as I was
saying we need a way to do this on the
fly in a real system we don't get the
full schedules of transactions when
they're submitted when clients connect
to the database and they start a
transaction we don't know what the
queries are going to be aa priori so we
can't look at what the clients going to
do and predict whether their operations
are going to be serializable or not so
we need a protocol we need a we need a
system that's going to allow us to
execute these transactions in parallel
because we want parallelism in the
system but we still need to guarantee
isolation between these transactions so
I think Andy briefly mentioned this idea
there are pessimistic approaches and
optimistic approaches today we're going
to look at two phase locking we're going
to use locks in the system this is a
pessimistic approach because basically
you're gonna have to ask for permission
from the system before every operation
so before you can do a read or a write
on a tuple you're gonna have to ask for
a lock on that object optimistic will
get too optimistic stuff in the next
couple lectures but today it's all about
pessimism with locks so this is just a
kind of just a high-level what I was
just describing an example of before we
can do a read on a we're gonna go to a
lock manager and say I want to lock on a
this lock managers sort of your central
authority on on whether you're allowed
to access a tuple or not it maintains
metadata about who holds locks and and
enforces the the lock protocol in the
system so tyonne's gonna begin it's
going to request a lock from the lock
manager on a it gets the lock as no one
else holds it t2 begins let's imagine
we're in a
Oh threaded environments so we're only
executing one of these transactions
we're only making progress on one of
these transactions at a time so t1
begins gets the lock on a we switch to
t2 it begins it wants the lock on a
because it's eventually going to do a
read and a write down here and it's
denied by the lock manager because t1
already holds that lock
the only thing t2 can do here is stall
what the behavior is is is kind of up to
the implementation but there's there's
gonna have to be some sort of stall
because you can't get the lock that you
want t1 proceeds does its write does its
read releases its lock the lock managers
now going to basically tell t2 you can
get the lock that you want on a it's
gonna grant it t2 is going to do it he
it needs to do and then it's gonna it's
going to release the lock so
conceptually that's how we're gonna use
locking in the system there's a there's
a little bit more nuance to it than that
and we'll go through that through the
rest of the lecture make sense we're
good so today we're gonna we're gonna
look at the lock types first we're gonna
start with two basic lock types and then
we're gonna get into our first proper
concurrency control protocol two-phase
locking
we're going to talk about how we reason
about deadlocks and how we're gonna
solve that problem and then we're gonna
introduce the notion of hierarchical
locking which is going to allow us to
take fewer locks in the system to be a
little bit more efficient about how we
use locks and then the last thing that
actually is a mistake we're not gonna
get to isolation levels today he didn't
make it last year and they're not in
these slides anymore so we'll get to
isolation levels I think we'll handle
them in the next lecture so I think
you've seen this slide before and II
presented this this is from work by Gus
grapha he showed it when you were
talking about protecting concurrent data
structures with latches so I think
concurrent B plus tree indexes hash
indexes things like that and I'm pretty
sure this slide exists just to get Dave
Anderson to stop making fun of us
because he says database people are
weird for calling locks latches and but
they are distinct terms in our
world before he was talking about and he
was talking about
like I said laches to protect threads
from kind of trashing the the memory of
your concurrent data structures today
we're talking about locks which are
protecting logical constructs in the
database so things like databases tables
tuples they're designed to protect
transactions from conflicting with each
other and probably the the key
distinguishing part is that in with
latches we avoided dead locks with
programming discipline we were writing
the logic on how these latches were
acquired with with things like latch
grabbing in the B+ tree how we could
reason about what the operations were
doing so we knew how to safely acquire
latches in one order and then make sure
we respected that order and release them
in the correct order as well to avoid
deadlocks with locks we can't do that
because we don't know what the what the
transactions are gonna do what queries
they're gonna run so we need to be able
to handle the clients issuing queries to
the system that would result in a
deadlock and and we need to talk about
like what are we gonna do then because
it's it's pretty simple to as well shown
a demo a little bit later in the lecture
it's pretty easy to put the system into
a deadlock yeah so like I said we'll
start with two basic lock types we have
shared locks and exclusive locks shared
locks are used for reads exclusive locks
are used for writes these are kind of
similar to the readwrite latches I think
that we're talked about in the
concurrent data structures the
compatibility matrix kind of represents
if you already have a shared latch can
you hand out more shared latches to that
yes exclusive latches are more or less
incompatible with any other latch types
you can't hand out multiple exclusive
latches you can't hand out an exclusive
latch to something that already has a
shared latch and that's that's the basic
compatibility of the of these latches
or excuse me these these locks I
shouldn't call them latches because Andy
will get mad at me
so the basic semantics of how we're
going to work with locks is as I was
describing for with that example you're
gonna go to a lock manager and you're
gonna say hey can I get a lock on this
object the lock manager is gonna decide
based on its internal metadata whether
you're allowed to have that lock or not
and then it's up to the transaction to
release the lock when it's done the
transaction managers or excuse me the
lock managers not necessarily putting
any sort of constraints on how long
necessarily you have that lock for so
it's up to the transaction to make sure
they come back release the locks when
they're done with it and then it updates
an internal metadata I don't think
there's a there's a Andy's not doing a
walk manager project this semester we've
done one in the past but like the basic
implementation is there's an internal
table probably a hash table that keeps
track of all the possible locks and that
are taken in the system and then as
requests come in you put them into a
queue you process them off the queue and
you go forward from there so it's a cool
project but I don't think you're doing
one this year so let's look at an
example with these shared exclusive
locks that we defined before so t1
begins it wants to do both a read and a
write on a so it's going to go straight
for the exclusive lock so it's going to
go to the lock manager give me the
exclusive lock lock managers like sure
no one else has a lock on a it's all
yours
t1 completes the operations it needs to
do on on tuple a releases the lock
because it's done t2 comes along and
says I want to do a write on a so it
wants the exclusive lock now lock
managers like sure no one's got that
lock it's all yours
do whatever you want it does it's right
it unlocks a and then t1 wants to come
back and just do a read so we only need
a shared lock once again ask the lock
manager give me the law does its
operation releases the lock so as we
described in the last slide transactions
are responsible for for locking and
unlocking
the walk managers just kind of here to
kind of direct traffic and make sure
everyone's doing what they're supposed
to be doing does anything jump out as a
problem with this schedule what's up
right it's not isolated so in particular
when t1 at the end does it does another
read it's it's getting an unrepeatable
read it read tuple a it did a write on a
but then it goes back and it reads a and
it's actually seeing the the the value
that t2 wrote so we have an unrepeatable
read anomaly we can't have that so we're
gonna need to be a little bit smarter
with with with what we do with our locks
we're going to need a little bit more
discipline and an NA and a protocol
applied to to what we're doing here
right so Andy added one more cool
animation to show this is a problem this
is here's your here's your unrepeatable
read so we're going to use is is a
protocol called two-phase locking and
it's gonna allow the database system to
hand out locks in a manner that always
guarantees conflict serializable
schedules this is a big deal because now
we don't have to try to limit the
parallelism in the system we can try to
run multiple transactions at the same
time and we don't need to know what the
transactions are gonna do ahead of time
to be able to decide if they're conflict
serializable where the system can run we
can do operations and we can hopefully
get high throughput on transactions
without generating unci realisable
schedules or violating our isolation
requirements this is all work that came
out of IBM in mid 70s for the system our
project it was led by Jim Gray who later
went on to win a Turing Award so this is
pretty groundbreaking stuff this is at
the time they were building one of the
first relational database management
systems so there was no textbook on how
to do this stuff two-phase locking is
what they came up with
turns out it's a pretty good idea most
systems use two phase locking now
so you're probably not surprised to see
that two phase locking has two phases
there's the growing phase and then
there's the shrinking phase so in the
growing phase of a transaction it's
allowed to acquire whatever Locke said
it needs it goes to Locke manager gets
everything that it needs and then it
performs all of its operations and then
the second it releases a lock tells the
Locke manager I'm done with this lock
the transaction is now in a shrinking
phase it is no longer allowed to acquire
anymore locks so in an example we'll see
how this how this helped us out how this
prevents the anomalies we're concerned
about and I think yeah so get another
way to think about it is this this
visualization x-axis is time this is the
lifetime of a single transaction y-axis
is the number of locks held by that
transaction so in the growing phase it
can continue to accumulate as many locks
as it needs the second it releases a
lock it's gonna go into the shrinking
phase you get no more locks so this is
this is an example of a violation of
two-phase locking because the
transaction released some locks and I
went back and acquired some more we
can't have that yeah it it would cause
the same sort of problems we saw in the
previous example where we had an
unrepeatable read where you release the
lock when they went back acquired a lock
and and you get anomalies because of
that so here's an example with with two
phase locking transaction one's gonna
begin like before it needs an exclusive
lock because it wants to do both a read
and a write on the tuple it could start
with a shared lock and upgrade it there
was a notion on an earlier slide of
upgrading we'll talk about upgrading a
little bit more later in the lecture but
we're gonna start for now with an
exclusive law goes the lock manager gets
the lock t2 wants the exclusive lock it
can't have it because t1 still holds it
so we're gonna keep holding onto that
lock till we're done with all of our
operations we're gonna do the extra read
that we wanted in t1 then we're gonna
release the lock t2 has been stalled
this whole time not able to make any
progress because it didn't get the lock
on on
a lakh managers gonna say ok t2 you get
what you want do you're right and then
t2 is gonna unlock and then commit so
the great thing about two-phase locking
is if you follow this protocol you will
get conflict serializable schedules the
there get the dependency graphs are
guaranteed to be a cyclic this is great
this is exactly what we want it does
have a slight problem though and that is
cascading abort so we'll give an example
on the next slide but the idea is it can
because two phase locking alone does not
guarantee that you don't get dirty reads
you can you can lead to cascading aborts
so this is the same schedule as before
we're going to access to different
tuples we're gonna get the exclusive
lock on a and the exclusive lock at B
that's because all the way down here
we're gonna do operations on B and we
have to get all of our locks before we
start unlocking anything because we're
in two-phase locking so t1 does the
operations it needs releases lock on a
t2 gets the lock on a does a read and
then also does a write and then t1 abort
but there's this problem now that t2
read a value that from t1 that is now
not actually in the system because the
transaction aborted it didn't commit so
we have this dependency now that because
t1 aborted you now have to abort t2 as
well because it read a value that isn't
valid anymore so that's what we mean by
by saying two-phase locking is
susceptible to cascading aborts and this
is this is
the reason this is a problem is because
you could be wasting a lot of work so t2
could have you know because it read a
value in t1 it could have done a bunch
of operations on the system and now
because t2 has to has to abort as well
you're increasing the complexity of your
rollback logic more and more stuff needs
to be rolled back in the system just
because one transaction aborted it leads
to another transaction board you can
kind of see how this could Domino
through the system if you have a bunch
of transactions running that are
simultaneously reading values from each
other and then one of boards so another
thing worth pointing out is this is a
valid schedule under under two-phase
locking
it's yeah it's basically kind of what I
stated already you can't let information
from t1 leak to the outside world
because it aborted but it would be a
permissible schedule under two-phase
locking so we're gonna have to solve
this somehow and yeah like I said this
is all wasted work t2 could have done a
bunch of complicated logic and a bunch
of more writes into the system and
because we have to abort it we wasted a
bunch of time so a couple other a couple
other things about about two-phase
locking that we want to point out there
are schedules that are serializable that
two phase locking actually won't allow
two phase locking is a little bit more I
guess I'll say conservative or yeah
we'll use that word because there are
serializable schedules that two phase
locking will try to will we would not be
allowed and because of the locking we're
gonna limit the concurrency the system
slightly as I mentioned we have this
problem with with dirty dirty reads that
can lead to cascading aborts we're gonna
solve that with a modification to two
phase locking called strong strict two
phase locking it's also called rigorous
two phase locking
the terms are kind of used
interchangeably I think the textbook
refers to both and we have this other
problem which is common with a lot of
locking protocols that we can lead to
dead locks so we're gonna need to solve
that problem with either a detection
mechanism where we can detect when we
enter into a deadlock State
or some sort of extension of the
protocol where we prevent ourselves from
ever being able to go into a deadlock
state so again going back to kind of
what we did with laches with concurrent
data structures we make sure we acquire
the locks in a very specific way that
makes it so that we can guarantee we're
never going to enter into a deadlock
scenario so we're going to tackle the
first one first we're going to talk
about strong fake two-phase locking
it's sort of a misnomer because the
second phase doesn't really exist
anymore all strong strict two phase
locking says is you don't release any of
your locks until the end of the
transaction when you're going to commit
the growing phase is exactly the same
you keep acquiring locks as you need
them but you don't release any locks
until commit time and this is going to
allow us to prevent any unrepeatable or
excuse me any dirty reads from
propagating across transactions which is
also going to solve the cascading aborts
problem for us so yeah the figure is
kind of updated but as you can see like
the shrinking phase it wherever you want
to define it as like the last the last
lock you acquired is the start of the
shrinking phase but basically there is
no shrinking phase everything gets
released at once at the end of the
transaction yeah and the the word
strictness does have a specific meaning
in when we're talking about concurrency
control it basically means anything that
you wrote none of your rights are going
to be visible to to any other asset any
other area of the system any other
transactions things like that until you
commit so so in this context strict has
a very specific meaning and like I said
that solves our cascade cascading aborts
problem because no other transactions
are gonna see values that aren't
committed to the system yet so they're
only looking at committed data
everyone's happy and and like I
mentioned before this simplifies your
abort logic because
abortive transactions only have to put
back their values you don't need to
worry about all these transactions in
the system potentially reading
uncommitted data and then they each kind
of have to store their own metadata
almost or methods to be able to roll
back the the work that they've done the
simplifies things a lot by not having to
reason about multiple versions in the
system
you only have one undo to do if you if
you wrote a value so we're gonna look at
a simple example andy owes his bookie
money I guess so he's gonna move a
hundred dollars to is to his bookies
account and then the second transaction
is just gonna gonna compute the sum this
echo command is is made up it's not a
real statement he just wants to
demonstrate that you're reading these
values out we could have done something
more complicated but we want to keep the
example fairly simple first we're gonna
look at it with I think just basic
walking then two-phase locking and then
strong strict tooth days locking so with
the two locks that we defined at the
beginning and we're not if we're not
using two phase locking we can see
spoiler alert you're gonna get a you're
gonna get a wrong output from this so
we're start with a thousand dollars in
each account t1 already gets the
exclusive lock does a read because it
needs to decrement his his balance by a
hundred bucks t2 wants to get the shared
lock because it's trying to compute the
sum it can't get it so it just starts
waiting t1 finishes his operation to
decrement unlocks a at that time t2 gets
the lock on a and performs its read and
then unlocks it because again we're not
in two phase locking here so you're free
to acquire and release locks as you need
them it also t2 also gets the shared
lock on B because it needs to do a write
on that which leads t1 to stall because
it can't do the operation or it can't
access that tuple yet eventually t2
releases the lock t1 gets the lock on B
finishes moving the money over to the
bookies account unlocks commits and t2
gives us a wrong output because
did it read an inconsistent state it
read harsh part of the work that t1 had
done and t1 leaked that information to
the rest of the system and said okay
this bank account balances 900 bucks but
it that hundred dollars was missing at
that point when t2 came along and got
the locks that it needed
so with two-phase locking the key the
key thing to notice here is it starts
the same t1 gets its exclusive walk on a
performs the operation it needs but
before it unlocks a which would put it
into the shrinking phase it acquires the
lock it needs on B all the way down here
so it gets the exclusive lock on b t2
stuck waiting around waiting for the
locks that it needs because this isn't
strong strict two-phase locking
t1 actually unlocks it well yeah if this
were strong strict it would it would be
down here at commit time so it unlocks a
finishes this operation on on object B
and then releases the locks and this
actually gives us a correct output same
example with strong trick two-phase
walking like I said the unlocking
happens at the end right before commit
so yeah t1 gets its lock t2 has to wait
the entire time you can sort of see how
strong strict two-phase locking is
effectively forcing a serial ordering
for these transactions by basically
acquiring all your locks holding on to
them until you get to commit time you're
guaranteeing that that any of the
operations that that t2 would have that
would conflict are going to be forced in
a serial ordering make sense I'll go
with yes
and then the correct output again as
well so I think I think Andy showed this
slide before in the universe of
schedules
he showed cereal schedules conflict
serializable schedules you serializable
and then I don't know if he had
cascading aborts in there so this slide
actually I think is he mentions it last
year is actually incomplete what he
meant to show is where two-phase walking
and strong strict two phase locking live
in this hierarchy and I'll see if I can
at least use the laser pointer because a
clicker doesn't seem to be doing
anything nope
so two-phase locking is gonna live in
kind of this area right here it's
guaranteed to generate conflict
serializable schedules but it's going to
be susceptible to cascading aborts I'll
see if we can get this slide updated for
the ones that actually get published on
the site so we actually see better than
just a laser pointer on the video but
yeah two phase locking would be here and
then inside of this box and a round
serial you would have strong trick
two-phase locking because it's
guaranteed not to have cascading aborts
we get conflict serializable schedules
we're happy makes sense so now let's
talk about the other problem with
two-phase locking which is that it leads
to dead locks and like I mentioned
before there's a couple different ways
we can try to solve this problem we can
be kind of lazy about it and wait use a
detection algorithm to to find a
deadlock or we can kind of be a little
bit more proactive about things and try
to prevent them from ever happening in
the first place so you've probably seen
dead locks before it's a it's a fairly
common concept in computer systems but
we'll give a basic example anyway so t1
wants an exclusive lock on a block
managers like sure you can have that no
one else has that lock t2 gets the lock
on B because no one else has that lock
now t2 says I want the lock on a block
managers like no
you don't get that but t2 is gonna sit
around and wait for that lock and t1 now
wants the exclusive lock on B and it's
gonna wait as well we have a problem now
both these transactions are waiting for
locks that the other transaction holds
so we need to break this somehow yeah
nice animation we have a problem yeah so
like I said deadlocks are a when you
have a dependency cycle between between
transactions with where they're holding
locks and and we have a couple ways of
dealing with them detection and
prevention here so with deadlock
detection with the systems gonna do with
like a background thread is you're
basically gonna look at the lock
managers metadata and you're gonna build
a waits for graph so ideas every node is
it is a transaction and every edge is a
is pointing to another node that that
holds a lock that that transaction wants
this is all going to be done in the
background you can balance out how
frequently this gets done we'll talk
about that in a minute but the idea is
it's a background task that inspects the
state of the lock manager and says hey
are there any deadlocks use your
favorite cycle detection algorithm and
you have to decide what you're then
gonna do with that deadlock so let's
look at a simple example of what these
with these waits for graphs look like
we'll start with T one wants a shared
lock that T two already holds on holds
an exclusive lock for so T one gets an
edge pointing to T 2 T 2 is going to end
up with an edge pointing to t 3 because
as you can see here it wants an
exclusive lock that T 3 already holds a
shared lock on those are incompatible so
we're just stuck waiting and then lastly
T 3 is gonna end up with an edge
pointing to T 1 because it wants an
exclusive lock that T 1 has a shared
lock on we have
a deadlock so we have to do something
about this questions what's that
so deadlock handling is kind of simple
pick a victim kill it you choose a
transaction and you roll it back how far
you roll that back is a kind of
implementation to find it's possible you
don't and I think this is this is a
later slide but you may not have to to
abort the entire transaction may not
have to undo all the queries that it did
you maybe only you may only need to
partially rollback some of the queries
to release the locks that you need to
relate to to remove the deadlock and
make forward progress in the system the
the last point here is basically saying
that you have a trade-off in the system
with how frequently you're gonna build
these weights for graphs if you're if
the way you're dealing with deadlocks
is detection you have this background
task it's building these graphs checking
for deadlocks it's up to you how
frequently you want that task done you
could do it every microsecond if you
want but you're gonna burn a bunch of
CPU cycles constantly building these
graphs and potentially not finding any
any deadlocks so what you may want to
reason about is okay maybe I want to
check for deadlocks less frequently and
if I do enter in a deadlock state you
know how long do I want to make those
transactions wait what's an acceptable
time out that I could sit in a deadlock
state without detecting it right away
so these are these are always going to
be tunable parameters in your database
system because different workloads are
gonna manifest different deadlock
behaviors so we want to make sure we're
not being too aggressive it may be fine
just to leave the system in a deadlock
state for for ten seconds even but it
depends on on what the responsiveness of
the system needs to be
so victim selection there's a lot of
different things you can look at here
and and certain systems get get very
elaborate with with what they do but
there's all sorts of different
heuristics you can look at the first is
look at look at the age of the
transaction when you're trying to find a
victim that you're going to kill because
at the end of the day you have this
cycle you got to pick one you can start
with the timestamp you can look about
how much work it's done how many how
many queries has it executed how big
progress is a you don't know how close
it is being done but you can least
reason about how much work it's done how
many locks it already holds that's it's
possible that you would have to look at
the number of transactions you have to
roll back that would be in the case of
if you have cascading abort
I don't think I mentioned before you
don't have to do strong strict two-phase
locking
some systems may just do two-phase
locking and live with the possibility of
a cascading abort again it's gonna be
workload dependant you can decide if the
workload is not very susceptible to
cascading aborts or dirty reads you can
just say two-phase locking is fine I can
release my lock sooner that may result
in higher throughput in the system again
that's often gonna be something that
that's configurable yeah so we'll talk
about a couple different ways to decide
a little bit later on about about which
transaction gets killed there there are
a couple different solutions but but but
the other one is is the yeah this is
typically going to be a combination of
things it's not necessarily always going
to be just the age of the transaction is
going to be what determines whether you
get killed or not often one of the one
of the biggest things is going to be the
number of times you've already been
killed which is yeah then the last one
says there because you do want to make
sure you make progress in the system you
need to prevent starvation for these
transactions
and I'm not saying like any one of these
is exactly what you're going to use to
kill a transaction the the commercial
systems get rather elaborate and can
build predictive models even to try to
figure out like which transaction they
should try to kill and answer a deadlock
scenario based on all these different
heuristics so it's typically a
combination it's not it's not just the
timestamp I guess is a long way of
answering hopefully your question okay
so your question is why would you sorry
I want to make sure I repeat back for
the video your question is why would you
always want to kill in what scenarios
would you want to kill the transaction
with the lowest timestamp always yeah I
suspect it's it's still always going to
depend on the workload depending on
what's causing the deadlock what sort of
a situation is causing it but yeah we'll
formalize a little bit like in a few
slides on what gets killed and and why
but I think in the case of Postgres in
the example we'll see the highest time
stamp gets killed I think I think it's
just it's just an example I'm just
saying like one you're a stick you could
look at
like I mentioned before it's possible
you don't need to abort the entire
transaction you could completely abort
it or you could do some sort of minimal
abort where you only rollback the number
of queries in that transaction that will
allow you to release the deadlock and
make forward progress in the system
again this is something that's going to
depend on the workload how much work
you're throwing away and whether it just
makes sense to have transactions
resubmit all their queries or if you can
slowly unwind parts of it in order to to
free the system up in the deadlock and
make forward progress let's see if we
can get a demo working pardon my typing
on this surface keyboard cool looks like
it's working so we'll start with my
sequel we'll have two terminals open we
have a pretty basic table set up called
transaction demo that's horrible you
can't see what's happening there but
basically we have two tuples in it
primary key ID one and two and the
values 100 and 200 pretty simple we have
two tuples this should be really easy to
put to put us into a deadlock State so I
have no idea which ones those are if you
press all the buttons
I'm glad I was standing next to you we
got that on tape producer Juan everyone
so we've got these these two tuples in
our table transaction demo first thing
we're gonna do is set our time out here
so like I was saying before you can
adjust things like like how frequently
you're gonna detect for deadlocks so in
this case we're gonna try to change the
the lock wait time out here you know DB
is the storage engine for my sequel as
of I don't know my sequel five I think
or something like that
so the first terminal will begin a
transaction the first thing we're gonna
do is try to update the value of tuple
one oh actually I missed a step
we need to explicitly tell my sequel we
want to run in the serializable
isolation level so that's going to give
us conflict serializable schedules we
haven't talked about isolation levels
yet like I said I think that's going to
be in the next lecture but we need to we
need to tell the system we want
serializable isolation level go back
begin our transaction and we're gonna
like I said update the value on tuple
one switch to our other terminal we're
going to start a transaction we're going
to update the value on tuple two
so so far no conflicts yet t1 holds a
walk-on tuple 1 t2 holds a lock on tuple
two we're gonna go back to two
transaction 1 here and we're gonna say
okay I want to update the value on where
IDs 2 and it just waits all I can do is
stall it's waiting for the lock and then
we can go back to t2 and say I want
update the value on one t1 holds that
walk already we should get a deadlock
and sure enough we get a deadlock my
sequel yelled at us rather quickly
not a ton of debugging information but
deadlock sound while trying to get the
lock try restarting the application and
you'll notice that t1 which was waiting
for the lock on on value 2 as soon as it
does the system detected a deadlock with
t2 it killed that transaction t1 got the
lock and made the progress that it need
what do you mean why there was no I
there was no isolation we can check so
I'm just gonna kill but I'm gonna roll
both of these back and we'll begin and
[Music]
we're gonna update the value in ID 1
we'll go down to t2 begin a transaction
update the value or ID is 2 and then
we're gonna just do a select star from
transaction demo in t1 ah so it can't
get the latch or excuse me the lock and
it's just gonna it's just gonna hang
there
if we do a rollback we see that the
value t2 was never written to the table
because it didn't commit and t1 was able
to make its forward progress by getting
the shared lock cool good question yeah
yeah I mean in practice you're probably
gonna see strong strict two-phase
walking because the system can't reason
about whether it should sort of eagerly
start releasing laws because it doesn't
know what what the client's gonna do
next so you could but I don't think any
systems do this you could speculate
about starting to release locks early
but you might get it wrong and we we
can't be wrong like we have to make sure
we guarantee these these isolation
guarantees sure well that's that's not
actually true so like like I said we'll
talk about isolation levels in the next
lecture too there are scenarios where
you may be willing to run with with
lower isolation guarantees and you can
start to introduce certain anomalies
back into the system if you are
comfortable with them or if at the
application layer you have your own
logic to reason about that sort of stuff
you can lower isolation guarantees if it
improves the performance of your system
yeah strong so strong trick strong
strict two-phase locking or rigorous
two-phase locking is one we need to use
if we want to guarantee we don't get any
dirty reads that could result in
cascading aborts as well
so that's my sequel we can take a look
at Postgres real fast and we'll do a
similar demo Postgres there is one other
cool thing we can do here so we're going
to set the deadlock timeout to 10
seconds the demo itself is is let me
just make sure I created this table cool
same table exists two values with
Postgres we can actually we're going to
begin each transaction by saying we want
isolation level serializable as you can
actually it's not not necessarily a
session wide setting you can actually
add a transaction granularity define
which isolation level you want to run at
and again I keep saying isolation levels
we'll talk about that in a future
lecture t1 is going to begin Oh already
begin that's right we're just gonna do
the same operation we're gonna update
value or ID is 1 we're gonna go down
here do the same thing where value
equals 2 go back to t1 try to update 2
we wait looking for the lock that we
don't have yet and then we're gonna
force a deadlock by asking t2 to update
the value related to 1 and there was a
slight lag there I don't know if you saw
it but it compared to my sequel which
instantly it was like this is a deadlock
Postgres kind of waited a little bit
before it was it yelled at us and said
hey you have a deadlock in the system so
like I said these are tunable parameters
you can you can adjust how aggressive
the database systems gonna be with with
looking for dead logs
Postgres gives us a lot more information
it tells us exactly which process was
waiting for what kind of lock held by
another transaction which is another
process
Postgres I think this is this is a big
reason and he loves referring to
Postgres because it's basically a text
book in
the wording you get back out of the
system is exactly what you would see out
of a database textbook and kind of the
behavior that would help us kind of
understand what's going on here there's
one more thing we can try and getting
low on time but I will do one more thing
so I'm going to roll both of these back
I'm going to set the timeout to 20
seconds because there's one more thing
we want to try to see let's see if I can
get one more terminal cool hopefully
this still plays it may be tough the
deadlock timeout do the same thing begin
transaction and serializable on to the
terminals this is going to be slight
race against the deadlock detection
algorithm so what I try to do here is is
demonstrate some of the internal
metadata that Postgres presents to you
and how it's tracking these sorts of
things do that and did my team accession
just died
it died cool
this still have a connection no
interesting well that's that demo cool
we're a long time anyway but the idea is
if we'd been able to put the system into
a deadlock state I was going to query
the catalog and it was gonna be able to
show which transactions were holding
locks which locks they're waiting on
which transactions and processes those
belong to
Postgres is great let's go back to this
stuff so like we talked about before the
alternative to doing a detection
algorithm is to prevent yourself from
other going ever going into a deadlock
State in the first place if we can come
up with some sort of system that
prevents this from happening we don't
never need to build weights for graphs
we don't need this background task that
that then needs to make decisions about
which process we're gonna kill and or
which transaction we're gonna kill and I
suspect this is probably what my sequel
was doing because my sequel immediately
yelled at us that we had a deadlock or
immediately detected it didn't prevent
the deadlock but it immediately detected
it as opposed to the Postgres which kind
of had a bit of a lag to it with with
the detection so a very simple way to do
this is to assign priorities based on
timestamp so older transactions are
considered higher priority and then you
kind of have two different protocols you
can follow you have this wait die system
which basically just means old
transactions wait for young transactions
so if the requesting transaction has a
higher priority it's gonna for a been a
holding transaction so holding
transaction is younger than it but the
older transaction wants its lock then
the requesting transaction is just gonna
sit around and wait otherwise the the
requesting transaction is going to abort
the other system is called wound weight
you can think of it as young waits for
the old requesting transactions
they have a higher priority than the
holding transaction the holding
transaction of boards so basically the
requesting transaction comes in steals
your lock and makes forward progress
alternatively the requesting transaction
just wait so this is probably confusing
it's it's a little bit clearer I think
on an example on the next slide so we
have these two scenarios these two
schedules we want to look at we'll look
at the first one first t1 and t2 t1
begins first so t1 is gonna have the
higher priority than t2 the t2 gets the
lock first so t2 gets an exclusive lock
on a t1 wants the exclusive lock on a
it's the older transaction it has higher
priority so underweight die T one's
gonna wait for that lock and under wound
weight T t1 is basically going to come
in kill T to steal it's lunch money and
t2 has to restart or whatever it needs
to do whatever the application needs to
do with that applicate transaction in
the second schedule t1 once again begins
before t2 so it has an older timestamp
it's higher priority but it got the lock
first t2 wants that lock under weight
die t2 is gonna abort and under wound
weight t2 is just gonna wait so what
these two policies are doing is they're
basically defining the same sort of
logic that we used for latching and
concurrent data structures where this
concept of we only take latches in one
direction and we release them in in in a
discipline manner as well like if you
can apply some sort of ordering to how
you acquire your locks which is
effectively what this is doing you you
can avoid deadlocks entirely so one's
weight dies basically saying okay we're
gonna we're gonna order our timestamps
in one direction and how we hand out
locks and then in moon weight it's
basically just the opposite as long as
we're consistent you can't mix these
things if you start mixing them you're
gonna get dead locks in why you're even
doing this because then you would need a
deadlock detection algorithm and
you you you didn't solve any problems so
the question is why is this called wound
weight as opposed to some sort of
opposite of weight die I have no idea I
really don't like the naming of this I
find it very confusing yeah if you're
confusing but if yeah if you're confused
by the naming I I'm with you I think
that's why Andy kind of adds this just
sort of simplification of like old
weights for young or young weights for
old because yeah wait die wound wait
it's it's a weird nomenclature any other
questions so this was sort of what I was
talking about before these schemes
guarantee no deadlocks cuz you're
basically enforcing walks being handed
out in a single direction or locks even
being able to be stolen in a single
direction so if yeah we've talked about
this already so when a transaction
restarts what would its new priority be
my guess is what would its timestamp be
it's got to be the original any guesses
why if you have a transaction you start
and then it gets killed by another
transaction coming in let's say because
it's priority will increase the older it
is you want to maintain its age yeah
sure as opposed to just resetting of age
right so in that's right
in one word starvation we can't have we
can't have transactions being starved so
when you restart the transaction we want
to make sure it's still used with the
same timestamp so that eventually with
with which it which Eve which ever
deadlock prevention ordering we're going
with we want to make sure progress gets
made at one point another the other
so we have ten minutes so this is we'll
see how far we get like so far this
doesn't seem very efficient like what if
we have a transaction that needs to
update a billion tuples we're gonna lock
manager a billion times like going to
the lock manager is not cheap you're not
implementing one this semester but you
can envision if you had to implement
this in a system you're going to need
data structures that are protected by
latches it has to be concurrent it's on
the critical path of what every
transaction is doing we can't make all
these trips to the lock manager so what
we're going to try to do is introduce
some some sort of hierarchy or grant or
change the granularity or allow
different granularity of locks in the
system so we can apply locks - tuples
pages tables you if you if you knew you
needed to do a billion updates on a
single table maybe it makes sense to
just ask for the single exclusive lock
on the entire table you are going to
prevent other transactions from
accessing it but maybe that's what you
want to do the goal is to reduce the
number of total trips to the lock
manager possible by using this
hierarchical model so to do that we're
gonna have to introduce a few more lock
types and then this notion of a
hierarchy so conceptually like I was
describing you can now take locks at
different levels in the system so
database can have multiple tables
different tables can have multiple
tuples and within different tuples you
can have multiple attributes so you want
to acquire the fewest number of locks
possible to do the work that you need to
do so if T 1 takes the lock on table 1
it if it if it explicitly takes a lock
on table 1 it now implicitly locks
everything below it in the in this tree
this trees again it's a slightly
abstract concept concept this isn't like
a B+ tree or something like that it's
just in the hierarchy of the database
system of all the tables and tuples
you've inserted into the system it's
sort of a conceptual hierarchy in the
system
so Andy's trying to get the balance of
his shady offshore bank account and he's
giving me 1% interest at the same time
cool this is sort of demonstrating in
this this conceptual tree that we have
what sort of locks do we need to need to
take we need all sorts of different
types of locks we need exclusive locks
because my bank account balance is
changing Andy's gonna need shared locks
and then there's this notion of an
intention lock which i think is defined
on the next slide you basically give
hints in this tree you basically take
intention locks at higher levels to give
hints to other transactions about what
you're doing in lower levels of the
system that's gonna try to increase the
the parallelism of the system so like I
said an intention lock is is a is a hint
other transactions and and it'll get
clearer with it with an example but the
basic idea like if you have an intention
shared lock in this tree the subtree
rooted at that node there is an explicit
shared lock somewhere underneath that
same thing with with an intention
exclusive lock somewhere in that subtree
rooted at that in that node there's an
explicit exclusive lock we're gonna add
three more lock types intention shared
which is like I described somewhere in
the subtree rooted at that node there's
an explicit shared lock intention
exclusive same idea somewhere in that
subtree there's an explicit exclusive
lock and then there's one kind of tricky
one shared intention exclusive this is
an explicit shared lock on this node
which means that so you have shared lock
on everything below it in its subtree
and somewhere in that subtree you also
have an explicit exclusive lock so you
can imagine if you wanted to do a read
on an entire table and then maybe update
one value you would get a shared
intention exclusive on that table
because you're gonna take a shared lock
on the entire table and say I'm reading
all the values of this tuple or of this
tape
but I'm only gonna update one value so
you have an exclusive lock on one tuple
further down it'll make more sense with
with an actual example I think but are
there any questions first example our
compatibility matrix gets a little bit
more complicated not a lot to say about
this other than I think the tree
actually seeing an example is a little
bit more clear but basically the
semantics are similar to to share an
exclusive walk compatibility just apply
do it to a tree the LOC protocol is
basically just saying in order to get a
shared lock you have to hint at least in
the parent node that you have an
intention shared lock same thing with
exclusive to get an exclusive intention
exclusive shared intention exclusive you
have to hold an intention exclusive on
the parent node again let's let's do an
example because I think that's going to
make things a little bit clearer we have
five minutes very simple table or a very
simple example two levels there's a
table there's a bunch of tuples we want
to check andis bank account he wants to
do a read on tuple one so he he wants
he's gonna want just a shared lock on
this one to do a read but we're gonna
have to take an intention shared at the
parent node first basically as a hint to
say hey below this node I'm gonna take
an explicit shared lock t2 comes along
we want to update my bank balance by one
percent so we want an explicit exclusive
lock on this tuple so we're gonna try to
get yeah we get our intention exclusive
lock on the on the parent node and we
get our exclusive lock on the individual
tuple now things will get a little bit
more interesting I think t1 is basically
doing the scenario I described before
where you're going to do a bunch of
reads and then you're going to update
one tuple
t-too is gonna read a single tuple t3 is
going to scan all of them I apologize
for going a little fast I realize this
is probably a little confusing but we're
getting a long time so t1 like I said it
wants to read all the tuples and do an
update on one so it's gonna get a shared
intention exclusive this means I'm
taking a shared lock on the entire table
so I can read all the attributes they're
in all the tuples in this table and the
intention exclusive part means I'm gonna
update at least one of these tuples down
there in this case it's tuple n so
because this is shared intention
exclusive all these tuples are
implicitly locked in shared mode and
then this is the only one we actually
have to take an explicit exclusive lock
on because that's the only one being
updated t2 wants to read a single tuple
we're gonna need the shared shared lock
on this guy which means we need
intention shared at this level that's
all good we can do that the last
transaction is the one that's gonna have
problems it wants to do a read on all of
them it's gonna want to shared exclusive
shared law excuse me explicit shared
lock on the table
can't get that because it's not going to
be compatible with the shared intention
exclusive because there's a write
happening lower on lower in the table t3
has to wait so basically it wants this
explicit shared lock on the table can't
have that
all can do is wait so I may have gone
too quickly the the example operations
changed when I got to this one with
three transactions this is no longer
doing like the read Andy's Bakic out
bump my account balance by 1% tyonne's
reading all of the tuples and then
modifying one t2
was just doing a read on a single one
and then t3 is the one that's trying to
read the entire table so yeah it's a
different example I'm sorry about that
if I went kind of quickly so in practice
it seemed complicated but it's actually
pretty helpful because you can reduce
the number of locks that go or the
number of trips to the lock manager you
you reduce the number of lock requests
dramatically and like we mentioned
before there's this concept of lock
escalation so if you already have locks
and shared mode you want to bump them to
exclusive locks because you've decided
you want to do it right on the tuple you
can do that once again this is this is
designed to reduce the number of trips
the lock manager and also doesn't
violate two-phase locking because you
can upgrade your locks you don't
actually release the lock so in practice
in real systems you you're not sitting
there telling it which tuples to lock
you can give hints like I said if you
know you're gonna do a bunch of
operations on a on a table and you you
want to hold the lock the entire time
you you can't explicitly lock the table
so it's not part of the sequel standard
but here's examples on how to do it in
like Postgres Oracle db2 sequel my
sequel these guys all use the
nomenclature that we're learning about
now which is shared and exclusive and
because my sequel loves to be different
they call them read and write blocks
because they want to be different
there's also this notion of select for
updates so if you're doing a read on a
tuple that you eventually want to update
you can give a hint to the database
system that says look I know because
you're doing a read you're gonna request
a shared lock I'm gonna do a write later
on just take the exclusive lock now and
hold it for me so you can you can do
select and add this for update that
basically tells the system take the take
the right lock or excuse me take the
exclusive lock right now and you can
also tell it just to take a shared lock
I don't know why you would ever do that
because by default it probably should
just take a shared lock if you're doing
a read
to finish things up like the slide says
it's used in almost every system out
there at least most convert most most
widely deployed to commercial systems
sequel server my sequel Postgres to
phase locking is is big deal but it's
also not too difficult to implement and
it gives us exactly what we want gives
us our serializable schedules we just
have to be disciplined about whether
we're gonna try to detect our deadlocks
and handle them or we're gonna try to
prevent them entirely in the first place
next class I think it's going to be Dana
talking to you guys about time stamp
ordering which is good
he's wixi nights in my system cracking
up I'm blessed
let's go get the next one then get over
the sofa dressed now good never be son
ricochet jelly hit the deli for a boat
one naturally bless ya what rappers like
the laser beam the balls in the bush
Sena ka-ching wrap the bottle of us a
nice sympathy go don't feel like
drinking a pony - you drunk you can't
drop you at the stake don't know you
forget a pancake