[Music]
welcome to News EMU 1545 6:45
introduction to database systems my name
is Andy I'm the instructor for this
course as I said on Piazza I can't be in
Pittsburgh right now we are getting
ready for Matt's cage fight on Wednesday
so we had to be out here in LA to
prepare for that fight so rather than
just not having classes this entire
first week I wanted to record this while
I'm on the road posted online and then
that way when we start having in-class
lectures next week we can get started on
the good stuff so before we get into
today's lecture I first want to talk
about how Oracle is helping us out this
semester with course of course
development so Oracle is actually won
the first relational database management
systems that came out in the 1970s and
I'll explain what a relational database
is in a few slides there's one of the
original ones but it's still widely used
and sold today right it's probably the
second most deployed database system in
the world it's certainly the most
deployed commercial system in the world
and so even though it's from the 1970s
and there's other systems of the 1970s
that are still sort of around or was
actually still under active development
and they're adding a lot of you know
interesting new modern features to it so
this course is about me what I'll call
it to me is traditional database
management systems or a classical design
and the interesting to see when they
come and in the semester to give a guest
lecture talk about some of the stuff
that they're adding to Oracle today you
know how they sort of go beyond you know
what we'll talk about in this course and
sort of look any more more advanced
topics so the for this lecture here I
want to first talk about these or the
overall outline of what's expected in
the course but you as the student taking
it and then we'll finish up giving them
a half lecture on the relational model
and the relational algebra and this sort
of be the background you need to have
for the various topics we'll discuss
throughout the rest of the semester
so if you're if you're a student
Carnegie Mellon then the probably the
foremost thing that's on your mind is
the wait list so unfortunately this year
they gave me a smaller classroom in
Margaret Morrison than I wanted so that
means we can't take a large number
people I think the max it says max
capacity is 100 I think it's like 96 is
in the room we can being flood that
number a little bit but I mean the main
takeaway is here we can't accept
everyone so the wait list now I think is
a 115 when I checked earlier today so
unfortunate that means that if you're
not enrolled in the course at this point
the likelihood that you're gonna get in
is is very low the people will drop the
course over the next week or so and then
we'll take people off the waitlist but
unfortunately ant take everyone so
you're more than welcome to order the
course just let me know that you're
auditing but we can't officially hold
that have that many people so the way we
will enroll students as current students
drop out will be just on your your
waitlist position on s3 on a registers
website so again I'm sorry but it's just
everything's available online so you're
more than welcome to follow along if you
want
all right so 1545 645 is at its core the
course is about the design and
implementation of database management
systems so that means that this is not a
course on how to use a database to build
like an application like a website or
something like that or have actually had
administer a database how to deploy one
set one up we're not doing any of that
we're really focusing on how do you
actually build and design the software
that is a database vendor system so if
that's not what you're looking for if
you're not looking to know how to have a
better database management system then
there's two other courses that you
should consider at senior that are
outside of SES and the one in particular
you may want to look at is 95 7 or 3 at
the Heinz College I think is Information
Systems and again that's about how to
like set up and administer a database
management system but you don't really
understand they don't really go into
detail about how you actually built the
software the other thing too that people
often ask is about there's a usually
another course at CMU
ooh 15 415 615 something that I and
professor Christopher Lewis has taught
in the past that is not being offered
the semester I don't know whether it's
gonna be offered in the spring probably
unlikely
so right now I think the only course is
available in SES would be this course
4:45 and then a 26 in machine learning
machine learning or cross-listed in the
cs department so again meets there's
always there's only Christmas myself we
can't teach everything so unfortunately
there's there's no other database class
other than this one all right so the
course outline is that we're going to be
going through and discussing then you
know how to build a disk oriented
database for an assessment and I'll
explain what a dis coordinate system is
in a few lectures which basically we're
just writing data out the disk we assume
the database is on disk so it's sort of
broken up the outline for the the topics
we'll be discussing is broken up and
sort of into layers of the system right
so we'll talk at a high level what
relational databases are and then we'll
talk about how to store them have x
equals on them how to run transactions
on them how to recover them if there's a
crash or we need to restart the system
so up to that point up to recovery
that's the core knowledge you need to
have to understand how a database
management system works and then from
there we can then build on that and
start talking about more you know more
advanced topics like distributed
databases or various other types of
databases that are out there or
extensions of relational databases so
again like the way to think about this
is we'll go through every single layer
of how to actually build the system and
we'll finish up and recovery and so at
that point that's the basic you need to
understand of how a database system
works and then we'll talk about how to
you know how to extend them to scale
them up or scale now of running and
running them and in the cloud
environment so the right now the course
website is online along with the
syllabus and the schedule so the basic
outline there's a lecture twice a week
and then with each lecture there's a
there's readings that go along with it
but better supplemental that extend the
kind of things that that I'll be talking
about as well also provide some
mention in a second so at all times
please refer to the course webpage that
should be up-to-date you know it have
been up most up-to-date information on
what's going on so unfortunately we
always have to talk about academic
honestly I'll go a little bit more
detail what I mean about this as we go
along but when you ever have a question
and you don't underst
please contact me so that we can discuss
whether what you're doing could be
considered you know plagiarism or
stealing somebody else's work right so
in general again this is an advanced
course so everyone should be aware that
you don't copy coding fine don't
randomly on the internet you don't copy
from each other but just you know be
very careful because we will check for
these things and as I said all the
discussion and announcements for
projects lectures homeworks will be you
on Piazza will do grading with great
scope your final grade will be posted on
canvas because that's what see me once
but the the detonated discussion will be
on Piazza and there's a link on the
course web page now a little that'll
take you to our page there is a textbook
assigned for this for this class
database systems concepts so this is
actually a new edition that came out
this year I've looked at pretty much
every single database systems textbook
fit that's out there in my opinion this
one's actually the the best one it's
it's it's the most up-to-date and as I
said well we've above I've lecture notes
for topics that aren't covered in the
textbook I have to MIT me I haven't
looked in a detail of the seventh
edition to understand how much it
differs in the sixth edition so if you
want to get the sixth edition I'm fine
with that
I don't think there should be any major
difference I just may not know exactly
how to you could look at last semesters
chap last semesters or starting last
year's course and see for the different
topics with the chapter numbers because
they have changed and I'm actually not
sure whether you can buy this book
anymore like you can't buy it as a bound
book they sent me you know a bunch of
page loose loose pages or you know three
three-ring hole punches in them so I
don't know what the bookstore has I
don't know whether to available online
it in the sixth edition but it's
probably good enough
right we won't we won't be we won't
any homeworks or any problems out of the
book directly right well we'll provide
everything for you all right so the
breakdown for your grade in the class
will be the following
so homeworks will be 15% then it would
be course projects which I'll discuss in
a second that'll be 45% so for those of
you that are CS undergrads because the
project grade your final grade is
comprised of 45 Senate projects that's
why this course counts for the system
software elective for for the CS
undergrad curriculum and then there'll
be a midterm and final exam both at 20%
and then there'll be an extra credit
which I'll announce in a few weeks when
you can get an additional 10% bonus
points and that's that's entirely
optional so there'll be five homeworks
throughout the semester the first one
will be a sequel assignment you will
give you a sequel like database you have
to write some queries for us but then
everything after that will be pencil and
paper because it's a way to work through
those sort of more theoretical side of
some of the things that we're talking
about but it'll be like filling out
multiple-choice and then you just take a
picture of it and upload it to could
great scope and will provide great that
way so again the first assignment is
sequel just because of you know we
actually won't be writing sequel for the
rest of the semester because the course
projects don't require it and I think
it's good for you to guys to touch it at
least once at least my big band stuff
we'll talk about it next neck semester
so again because is about saying all
these homeworks should be done
individually as well as the projects but
it's one emphasized this that like
you're not allowed to work in groups and
try to figure things out it's not like a
Theory class yet all these are
assignments can be done and should be
done individually alright for the
projects this is the one I'm pretty
excited about so throughout the course
of the semester you will build your own
database storage manager from scratch so
you'll start adding you know pieces one
by one and start building out aids or a
full-featured a database storage manager
so the key word there storage manager
and not a database system because you're
not gonna be able to run sequel or have
a query parser
but you'll be able to run queries that
are hand coded that will provide you so
it's it's it's more complex than the
sort of that simple key value store but
it's not like a full-fledged system so
the key thing about this is that it's
very important for you to you know keep
keep up to date with the projects
because every project is gonna build
after one after another so you sort of
have to have the first project working
correctly in order for the second
project to work correctly and the third
and so forth so this particular system
that we're using this semester is
written entirely in c-plus 17 doesn't
mean we're using all the advanced
features of sleep of law 17 it just
means that it's you know it's not like
you're you know C 2099 so traditional
single plus you may have learned in
other classes so because this is
Carnegie Mellon and I assume this is
advanced class I'm not ignore the TAS
are going to be teaching you or teaching
how to write or debug C++ I sent up a
self-exam on Piazza if you feel like
you're uncomfortable with you know those
are the gnarly aspects of C++ then you
should try to figure out how we try to
start learning this stuff now right you
can't come to us as the TAS office hours
and say hey you know what is the stack
trace mean you know the this time is
really expect it to be discussing the
serve them the more high-level important
database concepts that you're trying to
implement in your code so the all the
projects this year will be implemented
on this new academic system that we've
been working on called bust ugh
so all the source code will be released
on github of course obviously it won't
have the implementation of the piece
that you chose to implement but you sort
of fill that in so at a high level it's
a disk based or disk wanting a data
management system that'll support
volcano style query processing different
parts of the system have a sort of a
pluggable API so that we can plop in
different you know replacement
algorithms are given different index
data structures or different logging
schemes or control schemes so it's
designed to be that way so that every
year will switch up the project's
entirely
and have it be different form one year
to the next and will slowly build out
the system further and further with new
features and functionality so that you
know after a couple years we'll have a
full-fledged database minute system so
you guys are sort of the first ones
starting off with these first set of
projects and then next year what will
modify them in it'll be different all
right so this for this reason we can
make it open source because I'm not
worried about people you know people
next year finding your your crappy
projects implementations and copying
their code because it's all the project
of being entirely different so this is
what I was saying before the last slide
that you're good in basically storage
manager the database system doesn't
support Seco at this point and nor will
and this the semester but you'll be able
to write queries but you'll write them
in sort of physical operator form rather
than and you know in sequel and then
translate them because it's not
something we're doing just yet so the
name of the system is bus tub I will
explain offline what that means but we
had a nice logo logo made and again what
announced us on github we'll post a link
on Piazza in a week or two wellmy now
it's the first project so I'm pretty
excited about having this the everyone
work on this this semester all right for
the late policy for the homework and
projects every student is allotted for
slip days so basically for any homework
or project you say I you know I found my
daily you can decrement affront from
your account
so the be on a on each homework and the
project submission you just say how many
late days you use how many ladies you
left so sort of allow yourself to keep
track of what you know have how many
late days you have so after you run out
of slip days then it'll be you lose 25%
for every on the and the Simon's total
points every time it's it's it's for
every 24 hours that it's late so again
this wouldn't keep attracting us as we
go along in the semester
obviously if there's medical munitions
or other issues that come up please
contact me and we can accommodate you so
again as I said before now all these
projects and the homework should be done
individually they're not group
assignments you're not allowed to work
it out together and submit a single
submission
together
you should be doing everything
individually now some code for some
projects may be still online from from
wish or from previous years
don't take that we're gonna run it
through boss the players plagiarism
checker if we catch you running their
shitty code unfortunately you know we
got to report me to Warner Hall so don't
do that because this you know you know
it's stupid it'll up your life and
it makes everything harder right just
don't don't plagiarize okay and yeah if
you're unsure check the academic policy
or policy for academic integrity or
contact me if you're unsure about what
to do and this includes also for the
extra credit and just because it's extra
credit and it's optional doesn't mean
that you can't also get caught for
plagiarism so don't do that as well and
I'll remind you every single time we put
a new project out every single time you
know we we tell why the extra credit
okay all right so if you want to go
beyond the kind of things we're talking
about this this course if you really
like databases which I do you have no
idea how much I love databases the if
you want to go beyond the course
material there's two sort of ways to get
involved in database research or other
database topics going on at Carnegie
Mellon so the CMU database group has our
weekly meetings on Mondays at 4:30 in
the gates gates building own a floor and
this is other students visitors from
companies and people in Pittsburgh from
abroad coming and giving talks about
what you know the the kind of researcher
kind of work that they're doing if you
want to get involved in the development
of a sort of advanced system we have our
team meetings on Tuesdays at 12 o'clock
also in the gates building so we're
building in addition to bust up a bust
up sort of the academic system we have a
new sort of full-featured database
payment system that we've been doing for
for several years now that again if you
want to get involved in this kind of
stuff you should come check that out and
I'll send a reminder on this Piazza
it will say also to if you want to take
the advanced class fifteen seven twenty
one in the spring all those projects are
based on on this this new this other
system we're building so if you want to
get
that and sort of learn learn how that
system works and get involved in the
early days of this thing no by all means
come to this okay so with that that
that's that's it for the course I mean
please if you have questions about
things post posted coach them on Piazza
and I'll respond all right so now let's
talk about databases the databases are
super important in in real life because
they're used everywhere so many but
every single complex are energy and any
computer applications you can think of
at the end of the day
deep down inside of it there's going to
be a database right if it's a mobile
phone application if it's running your
desktop if it's a website right if it's
some kind of complex computer simulation
the end of the day there's always a
database everyone has database problems
many things can then just be reduced
down to database problems so a database
the definition I like to use is that
it's a it's a collection of data that's
related to gathers in some way that's
trying to model some aspect of the real
world right it's not just a bunch of
loose files you have randomly sitting on
your laptop right and that in some ways
that the database but it's not really
useful one because you can't ask
questions about it so this data is
usually related together or have some
common theme to them and it's trying to
you know model some aspect of something
that's going on in reality so the
example I always like to use for this
class is that say we want to have a
digital music store by something like
Spotify or the iTunes Store right and so
we're so backing this application will
be a database that's going to keep track
of the various artists we have and their
albums right so the what we would put in
this database would be basic information
about their artists and then information
about what albums that those artists
have released all right so that's that
cool right there that's that's that's a
database so let's see how we actually
could build now an application that
could store this information so let's
say that you know we don't know any my
database management systems right we
don't know
my sequel we don't let Oracle we don't
let post guys we don't buy any of that
so we in our own application we're gonna
write this code ourselves so the
simplest database we could implement and
manage in our application would be just
one where we store our data and a bunch
of comma separated value files or CSV
files and then in our application code
we're gonna write the the procedures the
methods to read this data and extract
information we need to answer four
questions or queries for them right so
the way to think what this is like for
every for every entity we have in our
application or in our database like the
artists and the albums will store them
in a separate file like artists CSV
albums CSV and then we'll have some code
that knows how to open that file up you
know parts each along to extract the
different attributes about you know that
these things these files are storing
right so let's say again we have two to
two entities in our in our in our
database right of the artists and
artists has a name a year in the country
and then we have their albums we have
the name of the album the artists put
out the element in the year that put it
out right so again if we're just joining
this as a CSV files we would have
quotation marks for each attribute then
commas that would separate separate them
so let's say now we want to write a
query that could look at the artists you
know the artists file and try to figure
out the year that Ice Cube went solo so
Ice Cube was a founding member of NWA
here in LA and then he left them because
the money disputes anything he went solo
so if we can we had the CSV file has
this artist information you know we
could write some simple Python code that
would just iterate over every single
line of the file right we would have a
function that would parse it just
basically split the line split each line
up by by its commas and get back an
array of attributes and then we just
check to see whether the first attribute
equals ice cube and so then we'll
convert the second attribute to an
integer whoo that's the year we just
print that
right really simple
coded answer this particular query so
some problems with this approach so and
this will go through these problems of
why you don't want to manage data like
this in your application and then
there's a motivate for why we want to
build it sort of a general purpose or a
database minima system that can handle
all these things so the first question
is say you know how can we ensure that
in our application that for every single
album that an artist puts out the artist
field in that album album file is is
guaranteed to be the same but how do we
know that we don't have a spelling
mistake for IceCube right and then if we
end up doing that how to be you know if
say Ice Cube changes his name how do we
make sure we fix all those things right
the next issue is how do we ensure that
the data we're storing is a valid is
valid for the different type right so
the album year should be a four-digit
number but what happens if someone puts
in a random string in that place right
maybe anybody can open up a file and
modify it cuz it's just a regular file
on disk but now our application does
that parsing and it sees a random string
one expects to see an integer and it's
going to throw an error because that's
like someone modified this data in a way
that I know is not expected and then the
next issue is what if we have now an
album that has multiple artists well
that's problematic because the way I set
up my file there's only one artist
expecting field right so I could try to
store that within the quotation marks a
bunch you know a bunch of college
separated that is inside of that thing
but now I need to go look every single
time I'm looking at the attribute and
say is this is you know is that is the
artist name an array itself or is it
just you know just a string so again you
have the way all the specialized logic
to deal with these these particular
problems in your in your application
so implementing this is not easy right
so how do we actually find a record so I
showed my simple example was a for loop
to iterate and parse every single line
to find the record that I was looking
for and so you know my my sample file
had three lines so that's not big of a
deal all right so that can be done
pretty pretty fast well you know what if
I had a billion billion Allen's do I
really want be opening the file every
single time scanning and parsing every
single one to answer every single query
no right because that would be really
really slow
now next issues that would have say you
know our application in that show here
was written in smooth it looked like
Python code but whatever now I want to
use write another application that's
written in another language and then I
want to use that same database all right
so let's say that the example code I
showed you was running on a web server
open up a file parsing it producing the
answer but now I have like a mobile
phone application that wants most access
to the same database
well my Bowl phone application might not
be written in Python might be written
another language therefore neither
duplicate all my logic to parse that
file in my in my web app or whatever
other application and of course now how
do I start sharing things right that
that becomes probably not problematic as
well all right so again same thing what
if what if I have two threads or two
programs a few processes running at the
same time that want to write to the file
at the same time what's gonna happen
right if if I don't do anything special
then the first guy will write something
then the second guy might just overwrite
it and I'll lose no changes the first
guy so in that now I start losing data
or my data ends up being becoming
invalid because it's getting garbled so
that's that's problematic all right the
the last issue is how do I ensure that
my data is safe so let's say that I'm
updating a record I open a file I start
writing to it but then before I finish
writing my update the machine crashes my
program crashes what happens right
should that update be there should it
only be half updated I think how do I
reason about what the correct state
should be
what if I again I want to say well I
don't trust the machine that I'm running
on so therefore I want to replicate my
database my files to one two different
machines so that if one machine crashes
the other one can just pick up and I can
run keep running without anybody
noticing
I say All American use a distributed
file system but you know those things
aren't general-purpose usually and that
can be difficult to do so for a variety
of these problems as well as others this
is why you don't want to write the kind
of stuff that we talked about a parsing
a file and reading it in your
application you want to offload this or
you want all that sort of complex logic
or how to manage the data in the
database you want a day management
system to manage that for you so a
database management system is
specialized software that allows
applications to store and analyze
information in the database without
having to worry about the underlying
details of how to do that right and it's
it's it's software that can be reused
from one application to the next so that
you're not reinventing the wheel
all over again so a general purpose the
administers from the kind of things that
we'll talk about in this semester are
designed to allow applications to define
create write queries against update and
minister of databases right and for our
purposes we'll assume our databases are
stored in disks they don't necessarily
have to be like this in memory databases
or the GPU databases or other things
like for these we discuss those things
yeah but just just know that just be
there's there's a variety of different
databases out there that can do a bunch
of different things to have search be
specialized in different ways for a
variety of applications so again I I
love databases I want I think alike
anuses all the time I love writing my
Davis's or reading my databases um
and you may think this is crazy why
would anybody love databases of data
systems so much so you have to
understand and think about this at CMU
it's a we're a large school we have
courses and everything right you know in
this courses for operating systems
course and fernette
bringing things like that but data
basement systems are sort of a special
class of software that are so important
that like there's full-time people like
me that teach of course just on this
right like a web browser is important
but there's no class I'm like how to
build a web browser at least a little as
far as I know right whereas like
databases are so prevalent and so widely
used everywhere that like and they're
really hard to you know work me and
getting them that correctly that you
know we there's an entire course in this
course and talk about how to how to
build it so again I think they're a
unique piece of software that our class
of software that is definitely a hot
area right now you know the end of the
day machine learning these data you
store that in the database and you know
so at every single application as I said
well at the end of the day there's a
database underneath it running almost
everything so this is why of course like
this and my opinion is super important
all right so databases are obviously
systems are not new you know the first
one came online I think in like 1965 at
General Electric and you know people
were sort of in the early days of
computing and then people quickly
realized hey it'd be nice to have
specialized software ok there's been a
system that can manage large data sets
for us so you have to understand back in
the day it's not like how it was now in
the early days and some things that
we'll talk about this course that we
sort of take for granted now because oh
of course this is how you want to do
certain things back like in the 1960s
1970s it wasn't obvious that this is the
way to do things so in particular the
story I like to talk about is back in
like the mid nineteen late 1960s there
was this guy Ted Cod who worked at IBM
research he was a mathematician when he
got hired to work at IBM research in in
New York and he noticed that people that
were working on databases spent a lot of
their time rewriting their database
application over and over again because
the
there was a tight coupling between the
logical layers of what's in the database
and the physical layers of how the data
system was actually going to store it so
what I mean by that is like say you have
a database you wanna store in this data
system and you have to tell you David
Bennett system oh I want you to store
this as a hash table I want you to store
this as a tree and then when you did
that and then expose a different API for
you based on what data structure you
chose but then now say you change your
mind on oh yeah I told you I was a hash
table but I really want to run range
queries on that so now I want to do a I
want to be you know stored as a tree so
what you have to do is dump all your
data out change your application code to
now make calls for the tree it's the API
it's at the hash table API and then you
have to reload all your data back in
write this again that whatever you told
the data vendor system how you want it
destroy the data so the tech con
realized that this was kind of stupid
right this is problematic because it was
the people basically refactoring the
code all over and over again every
single time there was ever a change like
this so now back then humans were
cheaper than the computers and so but
you can easily see how this was not
scalable and nowadays computing is cheap
with Amazon and Microsoft and Google and
the cloud computing and humans are
expensive thing
so it's this problem is eat more
problematic you know this issue is even
more problematic today and then it was
back in the 1970s but Ted cotton you
know quickly realized that people were
wasting their time in fixing up sulfur
that they didn't need to
so what Ted cought proposed was this
thing called the relational model so he
had the first paper came out on this in
1969 but the one that everyone's cites
is this one from the communications of
the ACM that came out in 1970 so most
people read the one that relational
model of data for large shared data
banks but this this is sort of the
seminal paper that started the whole
relational data model revolution of
saying this is how you want to store the
a missplanit systems so this is very
influential influential and this is this
is sort of the backbone of what
in this course so there's sort of three
key tenants of the relational model that
Ted Cobb proposed so the first that we
were going to store the database in
simple data structures as relations so a
relation doesn't mean like you know I'm
you know I'm related to my parents or
whatever it raisin is essentially its
anomalous for a table it's the the
relationship can be actually stored in
the tuple for for that given table so
again we would define at a high level
that would store all our tables at our
database as these relations and then we
would access to them through a
high-level language meaning we would
write in the exact code that we want the
dataset execute in order to retrieve the
data that we wanted we would just say
hey we want you to compute this answer
please do it for me we wouldn't xxa
actually haven't do it so this idea was
actually pretty was really revolutionary
because back then everyone was writing
explicit procedural code you know here's
the for loop to iterate through the
table and find the data that I wanted
the example that I showed in the very
beginning this is how people write
database applications before the
relational model and you know this is
actually pretty controversial at the
time because everyone was saying there's
no way software can ever produce a query
plan that's as efficient as what a human
can do this is sort of the same argument
about that people made in nineteen
seventies about compilers and they said
oh you know no compiler could ever write
you know generate machine code as
efficient as handwritten assembly and of
course nowadays nobody writes or very
few of you people write low-level
assembly everybody writes in you know in
high-level languages and the compiler
does a pretty good job producing a a
machine code executed more efficiently
than what is healing to do same thing
was said back then right they a compiler
or a database system could produce a
query planet as efficient whether human
could do and which nowadays we have very
complex query plans now fertilizers
aren't perfect but they can probably do
a better job and what most humans could
do and then the last key idea was that
the the physical storage or the physical
storage strategy for a big
database was left up to the
implementation of the database minute
system so again we define our database
through these high-level structures as
relations but how those relations are
actually stored is really up to the
implementation of the data system so the
relational model doesn't say whether it
should be in memory should be on disk
how she laid out on disk or how to
organize memory all that is is
transparent to the application and so
now the benefit of this is that if you
know for some applications their
database you know may 1 be stored in one
way and then an and then over time if
the application involves it may be
better to store it in another way and
then we don't want to rewrite our
application because we're still writing
at a high level language like sequel and
we're still accessing these relations
but underneath the covers this new
system can start moving things around
for us or changing its layout or
recompiling certain things changing data
structures and we have to change and
their application code so we have a
clean now separate clean separation
between the logical and physical layers
which is absolutely what we want all
right so the relational data model is is
not the only data model though it's
certainly the most widely used data
model and in my opinion I think it's the
best data model but there's you know
there's different data models for
different types of work listen it's the
relational data model sort of a
catch-all that can come with a lot of
things it's not to say that the other
ones are are bad or wrong it's just a
relational model nine times out of ten
that's probably what you need so the
again the data model is the high-level
concept of how we're going to describe
the data in our database and then the
schema that provide for a given
collection of data in database is the
definition of what we're actually
storing it so I'll show what I mean by
this in a few slides but the data model
is essentially the high-level concept of
how we organize the data and then the
schema is to say alright what the what
did the data were actually storing with
this application for today's given data
model so again as I said the relational
data model is just one
of several other data models I'm sharing
a small sample here then most DBMS
systems that you know about today and
the ones we'll cover in this course my
Siegel Postgres Oracle db2 sequel server
sequel byte all of these are relational
data data database systems did use the
racial data model if you're familiar
with the term you know sequel the no
sequel systems are usually these key
value graph document or JSON or column
family data models and again I'm not
saying necessarily that the relational
data model is better than these other
ones there's certain application domains
where some of these like it could better
describe the data than the relational
data model and the relational data model
has certainly adopted some of these some
concepts or ideas from these other data
models in newer versions of it it's just
you know the relational data model can
model all these things it just good
bearing with baring benefit advantages
over there yeah sort of the basic data
models alright you can also store to
raise matrices that's considered a data
model this is mostly what this is this
is what people using machine learning or
there's some databases that can store
matrices in arrays they're not that
common people usually use like data
frames or you know sort of things
that'll be example of a matrix data
model the hierarchal and never data
model in the multi-value data model
there's a bunch of these other ones
these are more esoteric these are what
the original data models were used in
the 1960s and 1970s
you know sort of around the same time
the relational data model came out you
almost never want they almost never will
see these things you if you're like a
new startup or building an application
for the first time you definitely want
to use any of these things they're
mostly and legacy applications and it's
just the remnants of old software I I
would say this is not necessary to even
consider them so again for our purposes
we're focused on the relational data
model that's what we care about in this
course and that's best we're gonna focus
on cuz
again the relational data model can be
used to model anything tonight so the
relational data model is comprised of
three parts so again the first is the
structure of the relations this is like
this schema how we're going to define
what are in our relation is what their
activities are whether types are and so
forth then we'll have the integrity
constraints that will define to specify
what is a valid instance of a database
given given the structure than given
given the schema you provide and then
we'll have a way to manipulate and
access the data in our database right
how do we actually run queries that can
either extract information or or modify
the contents so let's look let's go back
to our music store example and look at
some you know some concrete examples of
what a relational model Davis looks like
so again in relation is just an
unordered set of elements or records
that have attributes that represent
entities instances of entities in a
relation so again an artist has a name
has a year in a country and we can see
in our relation example here wait wait
we have you know for each record is sort
of one row in this in this diagram and
we have all the those attributes so we
would refer to a record in the
relational data model as a tuple right
it's going to be the set of attributes
that for that instance of an entity
within our relation so in the original
data model sorry the original relational
model produced written like Ted Cod in
the 1970s all these values had to be
atomic or scalar values I mean if it
couldn't be arrays they couldn't be
nested objects and so forth always had
to be sort of you know with one string
one integer one one float so again
that's what the original data model
relational data model but you know in
recent times you know you now can store
our raise you now can store JSON objects
in relational databases that that that
particular restraint has been
now there's also gonna be a special
value in the domain of every Ashford
different store they'll call the null
value that means that you know the value
is unknown so that'll cause some problem
when we start running sequel queries but
pretty much every everyday management
system supports reports relational
database system supports in all values
but how do you actually store them is
left up in the implementation and
there's a bunch of different ways to do
that which i think is pretty interesting
all right so then just so we you have to
understand the parlance we'll say that a
an area relation is one is a table that
has n columns right so I'll use the term
relation and table and unchangeably they
mean the same thing for our discussions
I'll say two pools sometimes as a record
or trying not to say row because that's
something very specific when we actually
start to talk about storage models so
but all of those works been used
interchangeably as well alright so one
thing we also have in a relational model
is primary keys so primary key is going
to be a unique attribute or set of
attributes that can uniquely identify a
single tuple so in this example here
there's a we actually don't have a
primary key on friend there are
attributes because there could be other
artists called the wu-tang clan there
aren't but there could be right there's
nothing in our in our in our in the
world that prevents somebody from
calling them calling them that
themselves that so we can introduce a
new ID field
as a unique primary key so that you know
if you're looking at the tuple with the
ID 1 2 3 you're explicitly looking at
you know the original wu-tang clan so in
this example here this is like a
synthetic key that I introduced into my
my-my-my relation my schema here right
there in a real artist they don't have
an ID 1 2 3 this is something we're
using in our daily basement it's system
for this particular rate relation to
uniquely identify the tuple so there's
different ways to generate these things
so there's some systems at least in the
sickle Siegel standard you can
automatically generate these auto
incrementing keys so at every single
time
certain in tubal there's some counter
that increments by one so that that new
tube will get that unique identifier
other systems if you don't specify a
primary key internally about crate one
they don't really expose it to you but
like they'll use that to keep track of
and this is the particular physical
record or physical to boat that you're
looking at all right for this example
here it's a synthetic one that's exposed
through the logical layer so they could
be goodness couldn't be through it auto
increment key there's also foreign keys
in the relational data model so foreign
key is a way to specify that an
attribute from one relation has to exist
in at least one tuple in in another
relation so this is how you're gonna
maintain integrity across different
relations so that you don't insert
things that map to unknown or non
existing entities in another table so
going back and to to our example here so
we have the artist we have the album and
so for the album relation we may want to
store multiple artists that could all
collaborate on a on a on an album
together so we have this artist field
now here but in this particular example
right for this mixtape there's multiple
artists so how do i cant encode multiple
values in the artist field because i
said they had to be scalar so instead
I'll make this separate cross-reference
table here where I'll have a foreign key
reference from the artist ID that is
part of this album and then album ID
that they're involved in so now I can
store multiple artists on a single album
and the David minimis system will keep
track of the whether these albums and
artists IDs actually exist in the real
relation so that prevents me from
inserting an album that has artists that
don't actually exist right the Davison
can can can protect me from inserting
bad data again I bought haven't
implement all that extra code and myself
in my application which again we're
leaving from running really hard code
alright so now we want to talk about how
we actually want to get data out of our
database right again I show that simple
example I'm writing before loop
but I said that was a bad idea we won't
we don't wanna have to keep doing that
for application so what do we want to do
so the DML is a way to manipulate the
data and and and you're accessing it or
modifying a way to produce it the result
of I'm looking for so there's two ways
we could do this so the first is
procedural meaning we'll specify at a
high level strategy of how the data
system should find our particular result
that we're looking for so I don't mean
exactly like the procedural code the
Python example I showed before but just
sort of a high-level say hey this is
this is what we won't need to execute
the other approach is called non
procedural or declarative and this is
where we're gonna say this is what we
want this is the answer we want the data
system to generate for us but we're not
gonna specify how to actually produce it
or actually how to go about and getting
it so we're gonna say hey at a high
level do this and we hope the data
system can do it for me to figure out an
efficient way to do it for us so the
work talk about now is relational
algebra this would be an example of a
procedural language and relational
algebra is it's not hard to understand
it'll come up later on when we talk
about query execution but you know and
this is what - what Ted controversially
proposed in 1970s an on procedural
example would be something like
relational calculus and so we don't need
to discuss this at all not because I
don't you know I don't think it's
actually necessary at least for our
purposes in this course but lay tional
cabs will come up if you be certain on
in detail about query optimization
because you have to use calculus to to
derive efficient query plans and do
pruning and things like that so again
for this for this course we all need to
focus on relation algebra I'm just
bringing up relational calculus to say
that it exists that it's out there it's
an example of a non procedural language
but for our purposes here we don't need
it all right so Ted Cobb proposed seven
fundamental operators in relational
algebra so these again these are the
fundamental operations we have to
retrieve manipulate tuples in a relation
to produce answers that we're looking
for
so one important thing to mention is
that
this algebra is based on on sets so the
set is an unordered list or unordered
collection of data where you cannot have
unique values now when we talk about
sequel sequels not going to be based on
said algebra even though it uses
relational algebra as the underlying
operators for doing query execution and
I'll explain again when we talk about
sequel next time what that means so the
way this is going to work is that each
of our relational operators is going to
take in one or more relations as this
input and then it's always going to
output a new relation and so the idea is
that we're gonna compose complex queries
by chained together these relational
operators together to produce the answer
that we're looking for so these are like
the primitives you would use to do some
operation on the data on tuples and then
to produce a comp more complex query and
we put them together so just select
projection Union intersection difference
product and join so again these are the
fundamental ones and we'll go through
each of these so the first one is select
select is basically taking a subset of
the tuples that satisfy some selection
predicate so you can sort of think this
is like a filter you say here's for a
given input relation here's the
predicate that I want to evaluate for
every single tuple and if it evaluates
to true meaning the predicate is
satisfied particular tuple will add it
to our output output relation for this
for the Select operator so the easy way
to remember this the word select starts
in s and so the relational operator is a
sigma which also starts with s so you
would say here's I want to I want to for
this given input relation here it's a
predicate to run and may produce our
output so during a real simple example
here say we have a simple relation has
two attributes a ID and B ID and so we
could do a select operator like this
that says find me all the tuples where a
ID equals a two and then our output
would be a new relation with these two
tables and the same schema or the same
attributes as the as the input relation
I also can combine together using
boolean logic
together more complex predicates so now
you say where AI D equals to and B ID is
greater than 1 or 2 and again we're not
specifying in the order in which you
apply those predicates right because it
could be more expensive to do one versus
the other
that's all left up the Daytona system
just to decide on its own what to do
so now if you know sequel the way this
would rewrite this in a sequel that for
that second example if you think of the
Select operator I'd like the where
clause right as you say we're a AI D
equals 2 and B ID is greater than 1 or 2
right that that's the that's a
translation of that of this select
operator into into sequel here all right
so the next operator is projection and
and here what we're doing is we're gonna
generate a new output relation that
contains only a subset of the specified
attributes from our input relation right
so you would say here's my in population
and then my projection is here's the
asteroids that I only want you to admit
to police in the output and again
projection starts at the P it uses a
lowercase PI symbol so it's very easy to
remember that there's no which one it is
so again here's our simple example with
relation R with a IDBI D so in this case
here I can have a I first do a select to
just produce all the tuples of our where
a ID equals 2 and then now in my
projection clause I can say I want the B
ID value subtracted by a hundred and
then well as the a ID value so I can
reorder my attributes any way that I
want and then I can manipulate that an
energy way to want with the any kind of
arithmetic or kind of string function
operator so again in sequel it would
look like this so you have in the output
Clause that your Select statement you
say be ID listen hundred in a ID and
then then the where clause is just which
get it in the Select operator our Union
operator is where we're going to take
two relations and we're going to produce
a new output relation that contains all
the tuples in either the first relation
or the second relation or both of them
right you just you just combine these
two relations imagine
right so if you do the Union on R and s
you get a giant you know you get a
company here basically concatenated S on
to own are as the output and so for this
particular operator you have to have the
same attributes with the same type in
the two relations you're trying to Union
together whereas in this case here if s
had you know had a third attribute you
wouldn't be able to be Union because it
wouldn't match so in sequel there is a
Union all operator so the Union one is
is not exactly the same as the Union
operator in in relational algebra you
have to add this all qualifier to get it
to do what exactly what you want to do
so again what we'll discuss what the
difference of these two is in the next
lecture
there's also intersection same thing so
now what you're doing is taking all the
you're taking for both the good for 2
input relations you're just going to
produce the output relation that has
tuples that appear in both the two
implications so again taking the Union R
and s here we'll just produce a single
tuple that has no sorry a single
relation that has one tuple a a 3 and
103 so again you have to have the same
number atrs - the same type in the same
name in relational algebra in order for
this evening to work and then there's
the intersect keyword and in sequel that
would do the same thing difference is
where you take all the tuples that
appear in the first relation but not the
second relation so again I can take the
are the difference of RS is just all the
tuples that don't appear in an S that
appear in R so in this case 8 a 3 1 or 3
appears both in R and s and so it's
excluded in the output but a 1 a 2 don't
appear in s so they're in the output and
in sequel you use the accept keyword
except except operator to perform the
same kind of operation all right then
the second last one new is the product
operator so this is also sometimes
called a Cartesian product or if you
know sequel this is I think called a
cross join so basically you just want to
generate all combinations
of all tuples from the two million
populations so you're basically just
taking the cross product means to and
just producing a giant output of every
single unique combination of all of them
so again in in sequel use cross join or
if you don't actually specify that what
the joint is at all you get this output
here like that so you may think this is
kind of stupid this is like what you not
I don't want to do you never want to do
this but this actually appears sometimes
in testing some testing applications
when you want to say give me all the
unique combinations of different
configurations of the I think I'm gonna
actually trying to test and this is a
really simple way to actually do that
all right the last time got to talk
about is to do joins so this particular
joint is called a natural join it's not
the kind of joins we'll talk about in
the future but not necessarily type of
jewelry type in the future but this is
very explicitly talking about a natural
join so way the natural join works is
that you for every single tuple in the
output out one relation you see whether
it matches all the attributes in the
other relation that have the same name
the same type so the common guys of them
right so in this case here if I want to
do a natural join on R and s I look at a
ID and see whether I find a match I look
at the a ID and are see where that I've
got a ID match and s and then if I do
then I check to see whether I've also be
ID match from R and s and then if I do
then that's produces the output here so
again a 3:103
exists both an R and s both an S and it
compares to the output so in sequel
there's a natural join operator like
this again notice I'm not specifying how
I want to do the join it knows that I'm
looking to see whether ID matches based
on just the name here so the reason why
this is different than the difference
because there could be additional
attributes in our and ask that don't
they don't have the same name in you
know shared across the two relations and
so they'll they won't actually produced
in the output so the scheme is allowed
to be different as long as there's some
common common attributes that you're
doing then after joint on we're in the
difference and the difference operator
you have it
you have to have exactly the same
actress of the same type all right so
these again these are just the original
main seven relational operators
relational algebra operators that Ted
Kapur pose
since then there's been a lot of
research and a lot of additional stuff
that people have added rights and like
there's things like doing sorting order
pies where we know we want to do that
sequel the original relational model
puzzle doesn't talk about these things
relational algebra proposal doesn't talk
about these things but peanuts since
extended that relational algebra
included clue these other ones so doing
rename assignment duplicate elimination
aggregations of group bys sorting
division so again we may see some of
these will see certain see aggregations
and sorting later on you know it's just
to say that there's placeholder algebra
algebra operators that we have may have
to consider when we start doing query
playing our doing query execution all
right so to finish up I just want to
sort of point out one particular thing
so the relational algebra is still
pretty high level compared to like our
for loops as before because we're we're
not specifying anything of what good to
have the data stored in terms of like
its data structure and so forth we're
just saying it at a high level hey you
know scan this table and do a filter
right but it's still at the end of the
day it's still kind of telling you what
steps in the order would you should
perform these steps so again let's say I
want to do a join machine RNs and then I
want to filter out any tuple where you
know filter only produced the tuples
where the B ID equals one or two so I
have two examples of two relational
algebra expressions to execute this
query so the first one here I do the
natural join of R and s first and then I
do my filter on B ID it was 102
and then in the second example here I do
the filtering on s first where B ID
equals 102 and then I think the output
of that relation and then I do the
natural join so again you may think at a
high level these are at a high level
these are the same thing they're
producing the same result but the
forms characteristics of the how
efficient that they will execute these
two query plans to be vastly different
right like say I have a billion tuples
in r and s and there's only one tuple in
s where B ID equals 102 so if I do the
join first I'm gonna take a join of
billion tuples of the billion tuples and
then I'm gonna scan through and just
find that one tuple where B ID equals
102 whereas in the second plan I could
do the scan on s first find that one
tuple where the ID is 102 and then now
I'm joining that you know with that one
tuple with the billion tuples and our so
again even though we're not going at the
low level like you run this for loop and
do that it's it's still still specifying
relation out of the steps we actually
want to the day 7 used execute for our
query plan so what we really want to do
is be able to just say at a high level
tell the database system hey this is the
answer I want you to compute and not
actually specify how you want it to
compute it so I want to say hey go just
get me over to patron from rns or B ID
he goes 102 didn't say whether you
should scan s first or join join with
our first I say this is the answer that
I want and the reason why we want to do
this is again because now in our
application we just specify this high
level answer we want the system to
compute and in you know if our table or
if our database is really small today
and then it grows really big a year from
now I don't have to change out of my
code the database could figure out oh
well you had a small team small database
before I want to execute it one way but
now you have a billion tuples in s and
maybe I want to do the filtering first
but I didn't have to change my
application code to make it do that
right the day says we could do this for
me so this is what we're gonna try to do
by in running queries and particularly
willing to run sequel and so the key
thing to understand is that although
sequel is the standard way people
express queer
four run the relational model it isn't
the only way you could do this it just
happened to be the one that everyone
uses and you know standardize on and
actually when Ted Codd wrote the the
relational model paper first in 1970 he
actually did mean proposed sequel he
made me propose any high-level language
he just said hey here's a relational
algebra he then later proposed his own
language called alpha that you know it
was at a competitor sequel in 1970s
course net you've never heard of it
because no one ever used it and actually
the 1970 there was two other competing
there was another competing language
let's see well there's other thing Clark
well out of Berkeley for this system
called ingress and they both look
similar there
quele and alpha and and sequels sort of
look similar to each other but because
the syntax is very different um it just
so happen again sequel just sort of one
out it's what everyone uses today
because IBM invented it so the way you
think about this is that again this is
what I showed the very important this is
like the lowest level way you could
actually actually this query of finding
all the the you know finding one Ice
Cube went solo but instead I could just
write a really simple sequel query like
this and say this is the answer that I
want you to produce and then the data
center could then figure out oh I I want
to write it in this particular for loop
you know cuz that's the best way to do
this okay and then if I add indexes then
the query plan could change right so the
beauty of the relational model and
sequel is that we can write these
high-level queries that we want and then
over time as the database changes as the
database system self changes or our
workload changes it can adapt and
improve itself about every us having to
go back or change our application
against for this reason is why I'm super
excited about the relational model and I
think it's always the right way to go
all right so just to finish up here and
again I realize it's it's all for me
sitting in the bathtub giving me this
lecture so I patient you guys sitting
through this so databases are ubiquitous
databases are stupid important databases
are everywhere so no matter what you do
throughout your life even if you don't
go you know you know even you know going
the theater databases you know in the
field of computer science of Cuba
programming I guarantee you throughout
the rest your life you're gonna come
across databases and
it's gonna be important for you to
understand how they actually work on the
inside right because when things don't
you know things aren't working the way
they should be think they'll be working
you need to know
oh it's written this way this is what is
actually doing so that you can figure
out how to actually improve things so
the we discussed the relational model we
discussed relational algebra and we
showed how we these are the primitives
we can use to essentially use them as
the building blocks to generate queries
that we can execute on a relational
database to update it and drive answers
so we'll see you later on algebra again
later in the semester when we talk about
query optimization query execution but
just in the back of your mind as you
write sequel queries for the first
homework you should be thinking about oh
well how would you know the database ISM
is translating these into relational
algebra so everything about how is
actually doing it how would actually
execute these things okay I almost
forgot one last thing the most important
thing you need to understand about
databases throughout this through the
rest your life is the following when you
look back at the 36 chambers understand
who were the original nine involved in
it you have the RZA the GZA inspector
deck Ghostface Killah masta killa you
got meth man ol Dirty Bastard Raekwon
but the other important thing too is
Cappadonna was in jail at the time so he
was actually original member of the clan
but because he was in jail he couldn't
he couldn't be on the 36 chambers so
that's the most important thing you need
to understand throughout this entire
semester okay all right guys see you
next time in the Mexican Barrios in
crushed-up kids
I'll Drive he's misty nights in my
system racking up I'm blessed
let's go get the next one then get over
the net will be son ricochet jelly hit
the deli for the boat one naturally
bless ya what rap is like a laser beam
the phones in the bush say not even like
a chain wrap the bottle of us a nice
nifty gold don't feel like drinking a
pony - you talk you can't talk cross
he's alive and if the sake don't know
you can't a bang