[Music]
hi my name is Dana
so I'm another one if Andy's PhD
students and probably going to be the
last of his PhD students to present to
you before he gets back so today I'm
going to be presenting the light your
very last lecture on concurrency control
so before we start a couple of reminders
the first is the project three is is due
on Sunday November 17th before midnight
we also released homework for last week
and then will be due on November 13th
before midnight any questions before we
begin all right so um today we are going
to talk about multi-version concurrency
control just make sure I just this here
so the first thing I want to point out
about multi-version concurrency controls
that it's name is a misnomer and this
may cause some confusion because it's
not actually a concurrency control
protocol like the ones that you've been
learning about in the past two lectures
which are timestamp or during OCC and
two-phase locking
rather it's a way to architect the
system when you have concurrent
transactions running by maintaining
multiple versions so recall from last
week your discussion of optimistic
currency control where transactions
maintain a private workspace and anytime
they read or wrote to an object it will
copy that object into that private
workspace well in the multi-version
concurrency control is similar to that
idea except here instead of having a
private workspace for each transactions
where we maintain these different
versions we're now going to have the
version to be part of a global database
and we're going to determine whether
some version of it is vision is visible
to a particular transaction
so MVCC is used by almost every new
database system that's been built in the
past ten years or some variant of it but
it's not a new idea
so it actually it's actually decades old
and the first reference to the idea was
in a dissertation by PhD student MIT in
1978 so it wasn't until the early 80s at
the first that the first implicate
implementations of it actually came out
and those came out of a company called
Dec and they were called our DB VMs
which stood for relational database for
VMs or VAX which was an old operating
system and the other product was called
inter base so Dec used to be a major
computer company it was bought out by a
Compaq in the late 90s and then a few
years later bought out by HP so it's no
longer around but it did some major
pioneering work and database systems so
both our DB VMs and their base were
built by a guy named Jim Starkey who was
also credited as being the inventor of
blobs and triggers so he's a big deal he
later went on to co-found nuodb which is
a new database startup and it also
happens to use in BCC so Dec our DB VMs
was bought up by Oracle and is now known
as oracle rdb and it was an inner base
was eventually sold by Dec it went
through a few different holding
companies and finally was open sourced
and so now it's known under a different
name now it's called Firebird so it may
not be as well-known as my sequel or
Postgres but there's one of the earliest
open-source databases out there and Andy
had this little fun fact in there from
last year or so I'll go ahead and
say it so if you if you've ever wonder
why the fire for Firefox web-browser is
named Firefox it's because they were
originally called Phoenix but then they
had to change that name because it
conflicted you know with another system
or another product so they changed it to
Firebird but then they had to change it
again because it conflicted with this
database system so finally it was called
Firefox so the main benefit again like
what you have to understand about MVCC
is that writers don't block the readers
and the readers don't block the writers
so it's only when you have two
transactions trying to write it till the
object at the same time they have to
fall back and rely on one of the
concurrency control protocols like
two-phase locking so again you only need
to do this when you have a write write
conflict so with a high level the way
this works is we're going to assign time
stamps to transactions when they arrive
in the system and then we're going to
provide it with a consistent snapshot of
the database as it existed at the time
that that transaction arrived so this
means that they won't see changes from
transactions that have not been that
have not yet been committed in their
snapshot and just to clarify this is a
virtual snapshot so it shouldn't be
confused with you know if a physical
snapshot or copying the the full
database to another location and then
running that transaction on it so again
this is um this is just virtual so MVCC
is really useful for read-only
transactions because the sequel dialect
allows you to declare when a transaction
is read-only and if you do this then the
database system does not require you to
get any locks or maintain the readwrite
sets and this works again because it has
a consistent snapshot and will only see
the changes that existed at the moment
it started
and this makes these read-only
transactions really efficient and also
really fast to do yes
I'm even just like I mentioned a minute
ago like it's it's essentially just
maintaining like a version table our
version made it data information and
it's very similar the OCC where you
understand the read and write sets and
we're going to clearly go over this in a
lot of detail in the following slides
this is gonna be the the topic of this
lecture yeah so it's the we're talking
about two reads here they will read the
the same snapshot the same version so
snapshot you know it's more commonly I
think referred to as the version you
know the tuple or database object well
can so if you so bear with me for just
like you know three minutes probably
less and we'll actually that is the
first thing we're gonna cover and I'll
I'll answer any other questions you have
afterward all right so just to finish up
on the slide another advantage of MVCC
is that you're able to support something
called time travel queries so these are
queries to actually let you ask the
database system for example what was the
state of the database you know three
days ago
three years ago and using these and
using this versioning they can actually
answer these these sort of queries
all right so the idea of time travel
queries was first was an idea of
Postgres and it originated from Postgres
in the 1980s but postcards actually
removed these time travel queries from
from their from their current product
like as soon as you know people outside
of academia I started using Postgres
more heavily can anybody guess why well
so the reason why is because essentially
what you have to do to actually support
time travel queries is you never throw
away old versions so you never garbage
collect right so over time you're you
know the more and more transactions that
commit your your disk base will be
filling up very quickly and eventually
it will be full and probably very
quickly depending on the speed of your
transactions and the the other thing is
that time travel queries are not really
needed by a lot of applications like you
can't you never really look at you never
go to a website and say like ok I want
to know what this webpage looked like
three days ago well I'm not the most use
cases but Andy mentions that like one
common use case for these time
travelling queries is in the financial
industry so the reason is because you
know do - I know pursuit you know
whatever whatever rules and regulations
they have to follow they have to
actually maintain in the past seven
years of transaction history so these
time travel queries actually allow them
to very easily query the database and
figure out why you know some of money
what their what their total revenue was
or whatever they want to look up you
know over the past seven years
all right so um and the next few slides
we're going to go over two examples and
what I really want to emphasize here
before we start is that MVCC is
independent from concurrency control
protocols so the purpose of these
examples is just to basically show you
how we you know update versions and
timestamps in the table and also
basically like how sorry how we figure
out which version how we figure out
which version is - is visible to the
particular transaction right which
version of the tuple is physical is
visible so this first example we'll see
how this is going to work so right now
like the first thing to point out is
that now we have this version field
right so we can see in this version
field but it's assigned to a zero so
this means object day version zero right
so we can assume that some other
transaction has written the value one
two three to the database and whatever
attraction transaction wrote it how the
time was assigned a timestamp of zero
and we'll go over why in one second so
we also have a begin and end fields and
so these are just timestamps it doesn't
matter if they're logical physical
hybrid as long as they you know they're
always increasing and follow the other
you know and I guess our our ballad
timestamps right like you learned in the
past few lectures alright so
let's begin so when a new transaction
arrives to transact we're going to be
looking at transactions t1 and t2 so
here T t1 arrives and it's assigned a
time stamp of 1 right so now we're going
to begin okay so for the first thing we
want to do is what I do a read on a so
what we're going to do is we're going to
consider you know time transaction once
time stamp which is 1 and we're going to
take a look at our table and figure out
which tuple is visible to it by trying
to find by finding you know where its
current time stamp is between the end
and between beginning and end so in this
example the beginning is 0 and the time
step of 1 is between 0 and the end which
is infinity right so it's going to go
ahead and breed version a 0 all right
all right so now we have transaction t2
and we're going to assign the time stamp
to so the first thing we want to do here
is we want to write a so at this point
what we're going to do is we're going to
create a completely new version of a
which will be a 1 right because we're
just incrementing the version counter
and right and so what we're going to do
here is the beginning time stamp is
going to be set to the time stamp of t2
the enzyme sample again be set to
infinity and then the last thing we're
going to do is we're going to update the
end time stamp of version a 0 to also be
a time stamp of to write for transaction
2 all right so one thing you might have
noticed that we're missing so far is
like with with just either the
information that we had so far before we
before this transaction says table
popped up the one thing that we're
missing is that we don't really know the
current state of the transactions in the
database so for example you know the
transactions here are currently active
but what if they abort
you know then you would have to go back
and reverse the timestamps accordingly
if it was aborted right so as you can
see here we're just going to start
filling out the transaction status table
at this point both transactions are
active then finally we're going to do
this read on a so what version is it
going to read anyone right hey sub-zero
because again it's timestamp still lies
between the beginning and end here so
it's gonna go ahead and read version a0o
and finally its gonna commit so at the
very end after this commits then the
then transaction t2 will come it will
update the status table and we can blow
it away eventually so for the second
example we're gonna start with sort of
the same setup right so we have
transaction t1 with a timestamp of 1 and
transaction t2 we're assigning a
timestamp of 2 and it's the same stay in
the in the database table and so far
we're just starting transaction t1 we're
saying it's timestamp to 1 and it's
status is active so first we're going to
do a read on a I think at this point
it's pretty clear that we're going to
read version a0 and next we're gonna do
a write on a so again just like in the
last slide we're going to create a
completely new version I'm inserting in
our database table where it's gonna be
version a 1 with value 4 5 6 and the
beginning timestamp will be a 1 right it
will be whatever this timestamp is and
the end we will assign to infinity again
and the last thing to not forget is that
we need to go up to a0 and assign the
end timestamp to be the current
timestamp of transaction t1 which is 1
alright so now we're going to begin
transaction 2
so the first thing we're going to do is
a read on a so in this case which
transaction is it going to read or sorry
which version is it gonna read excuse me
a 1 and why is that right yeah somebody
I guess yeah so in this case um it's
gonna be oh sorry
for a yes so one thing that we have to
pay attention to and this is a little
tricky right now one thing I forgot to
mention that the start is I understand
you guys didn't have time to go over
isolation levels so and II wanted you
guys to just review the slides and also
the lecture from last year so I'm just
gonna provide some high-level hints for
isolation levels for when you go over
those slides and the homeworks right but
it might not make full sense at this
point but basically like at a very high
level depending on the isolation level
you have it may choose either version a
0 a 1 but let's assume it's sort of it's
the strict serializable or excuse me
serializable isolation which is sort of
what you guys have been using up until
this point and this point it will it has
to read a 0 because a 1 has not yet
committed alright so now we're gonna do
a write on a and so in this case what's
gonna happen next
well again here we have a write write
conflict right so assuming we're using a
to be lt2 is gonna have to stall until
t1 commits all right so let's keep this
going so now we're back to t1 we're
going to do a read on a and in this case
it's gonna just read the same version
that it wrote couple minutes ago right
and it's gonna go ahead and commit
alright so now we can go back here and
we can go ahead and now we're going to
create the new version a 2 with value 7
8 9 we're going to assign it the time
stamp of 2 with an end time step of
infinity and we're going to update the
end time stamp of a 1 to 2 as well
right so at this point you know whether
whether the weather t2 actually commits
or not is really dependent on the
concurrency control protocol as well as
the isolation level so that's something
to keep in mind but really this this
example the purpose of this example is
just to show you how we update the
object versions maintain the transaction
status table and also figure out which
tuples are visible all right any
questions on this all right so as I
mentioned if you say oh yes oh well so
this again this is a very high-level
example right now and there's actually
we're going to go into how you actually
store this information later on in this
lecture so that's with you like so that
that will answer the question basically
it's in some cases yes you do need to
consider locks it really depends on how
you're actually storing this version
information so if if we don't cover it
in a few slides because there's multiple
ways to do this so I don't want to just
list them all out now we don't cover it
in few slides please ask your question
again
all right so um so again like MVCC or
its variants are used in almost all new
database systems and these are just you
know some examples of the systems that
use in VCC but what we really want to
emphasize for the rest of this lecture
is that MVCC is a lot more than just
maintaining the time stamps that I
showed you in the previous two examples
there's a whole bunch of other design
decisions that you have to make in order
to actually implement a system that
supports in VCC so we're gonna go over
those next so what exactly are these
design decisions specifically it's what
concurrency protocol you're going to use
how you're going to maintain and store
the different versions which relates to
the question that was previously asked
how are you're going to clean up the old
versions once they're not visible to any
transactions anymore and how you're
going to ensure that the indexes point
to the correct version all right so the
first thing we'll cover is a skip that
one okay so that's what I thought okay
so the first thing we're going to cover
is concurrency control protocol right so
this is basically I'm looking at the
sorry I'm not used to this presenter
view my bad okay
concurrency control protocol this is
this is our first consideration right
for our design decisions so these are
the concurrency control protocols that
you guys have been studying for the past
two weeks in the past two lectures and
again when when you encounter a write
write conflict you need to use one of
these protocols whether it be two phase
locking OCC or timestamp ordering to
figure out which transaction should be
allowed to write to that object and what
isolation level you're running at so
we're not going to go into much detail
on this since you've just been covering
it very recently so the next
consideration is version storage so for
virgin
version storage what we need to do is
figure out for two for a particular
tuple version what should actually be
visible to us right so let's assume for
now that we're doing a sequential scan
on the entire tainment bolt and we want
to know where to find the version of a
tuple that we want so the way we're
going to implement this is we're going
to maintain an internal pointer field
that will allow us to find the previous
or next version we'll go into that more
for this particular logical tuple so you
can think of this is sort of a linked
list where you you know you can jump on
into you jump on it and land on the head
and then you can follow the the pointers
in the linked list to find all of the
different versions they're currently
being maintained
so indexes always point to the head of
the chain and oh my I did it again I'm
so sorry okay technical difficulties
alright so um indexes like it says here
will always point to the head of the
chain whether the head is the oldest
version that the newest version of that
tuple depends on the implementation so
there's different approaches determine
how we're going to store these different
versions so we'll go more into that next
so the persons simplest approach is
called append-only storage all right so
this just means that every time we
create a new version we just copy the
old version as a new physical tuple in
our tablespace and update it so then we
update pointers to say here's the next
version and we're going to go over
examples of all three of these in the
next few slides so the next approach is
called
time travel storage and this is where
you have one master version table that
there's always during the latest version
of the object or tuple then you copy out
older versions into a separate table
that we're going to call the time travel
table and then at that point you just
maintain the pointers from the master
version of the table with the latest
tuples to the tribe to the time travel
table and so the last approach which is
the one andy prefers and things as best
is called delta storage so you can think
of this as a dips and get we're instead
of just copying the old version every
single time and updating it you're just
going to maintain you know a small delta
of the modifications from the previous
version so well first go over in an
example of the append-only storage so
again this is the simplest approach and
this is also what Postgres uses so each
new physical version is just a tuple is
just a new tuple in the main table so
let's say we have a transaction here
that wants to update object a right so
the first thing that's going to do is
it's going to find an empty slot in the
tablespace and then copy the values from
the current value of a which is a 1 all
right that's the most recent value I
into that table saw it and then next
it's going to copy the modified value
into that table saw it and are we done
yet not quite
the final thing we need to actually do
is update the pointer to point from the
older version to the newest version that
we currently installed
[Music]
okay so another aspect we must consider
your in order to store this version so
Oh in this example we a is considered
the head of the Virgin chain and in this
example we're specifically ordering
these oldest to youngest right so an
alternative would be you can order them
youngest to oldest so if you if you're
looking for the newest tuple in this
case you actually you you get to the
point of where your get to version a
zero and again you have to follow the
pointers all the way down to the newest
version a to some exams all right so um
so like I just said the previous example
used oldest to newest but you could also
use newest to oldest
and there's performance implications and
trade offs for both of them right so
with oldest to newest all you need to do
when there's a new version is to just
append to the end of the version chain
right this is very simple append the new
tuple and update the pointer to point to
the the newer version from the older
version to the newer version and this is
a really easy operation to do but if you
do newest to oldest then what this means
is that you have to add the entry and
update its pointer to point to the old
head right but now you have to actually
update all of the indexes to point to
your new version so it's again like we
said a few slides ago indexes always
point to the head of the version chain
right so this means a lot more updates
in some cases alright so for
time-travels storage this is the next
approach we'll cover and here we're
going to have a main table that always
has to lay this version of each tuple
and then we'll have another table called
the time travel table
and this is where we're going to
maintain older versions and copy older
versions as they get modified in the
database right so for this example let's
say the transaction wants to update
object a again same as last example then
we're going to copy a 2 into the free
spot in the time travel table and then
update the version pointer to point to
the oldest version of tuple a then we're
going to overwrite the master version in
the main table to be the new version
value and finally we need to update the
air diversion by and then finally we
need to update the pointer to point from
the new version a3 to the version that
we just installed in the time travel
table which is a 2 yes it would be an
append table all right so now we'll move
on to the the last approach that we're
going to consider which is Delta storage
which again this is used by both my
sequel and Oracle and like I mentioned
it's the one Andy thinks is the best
option so what's gonna happen here is
every time you do an update you're just
going to copy the values that were
modified into this separate Delta
storage segment that you see over here
so to update a we're first going to
update its version value into the Delta
storage right so we're gonna copy over
its value so instead of storing the
entire tuple we're just going to call
we're just going to create a delta the
States you know which part which
attributes and the tuple were actually
modified so in this case there's one
attribute so that that was now reflected
in the Delta storage segment
then we're going to update the actual
value in the main table and also update
the pointer from the new value into our
Delta storage so similarly if we uh if
we want to now install a new value and
new version then we need to do something
similar to the time travel table
scenario which is specifically we append
the new version update the value again
and now we're seeing its version a3
right but we have but we also need to
update the pointer from a3 to now point
to the most current value of a2 and
additionally we need to update the
pointer of a2 to the point to the older
version now anyone Tim is the time
travel example so when you want to read
an old version well you really what you
essentially have to do is you have to
replay the deltas to put the tuple back
into its original form so in this case
if we wanted to if we wanted to read a 1
we would start with the value of a3 and
then we would follow the pointer that a
to apply the delta and a2 and then apply
the Delta 1 and that would get us back
to the original value so this is another
good example of the trade-offs between
reads and writes so reading old versions
and the append-only approach is really
easy which is one nice thing about it
it's easy to implement right because you
just find the version and the tuple is
already ready to be turn so in addition
to being easy to implement you also
don't have to put the tuple back
together you don't have to apply Delta's
to get it back to its correct state but
with Delta storage rights are going to
be much faster because we don't have to
copy the entire tuple if we only make a
change to a subset of the attributes so
you know if you just have one attribute
like we do here this is you know clearly
a trivial optimization but in many
tables you
might have you know dozens of columns in
which case this can matter a lot but
again yes with the Delta storage the
that is the benefit but the disadvantage
is that you have to replay the deltas
again to put the tubule back together
into its correct value so one take away
you can go from this is like we
mentioned earlier Postgres Postgres will
be faster for reads right because well
post course will be faster for reads and
the and my sequel B will be faster for
writes for this exact reason alright so
the third thing that we need to know
about on our list is garbage collection
so all of these old versions are
accumulating as transactions are running
and finishing and at some point we know
that the particular version is not being
is not visible to any other active
transactions right so what this means is
if you're thinking about the table with
the begin and end time stamps and the
time stamp version it means that there
are no active transactions with a time
stamps that fit between that begin and
end range right of from older versions
so at this point we want to go ahead and
garbage collect these versions in order
to reclaim space so two additional
things that we have to worry about are
how we're going to look for expired
versions and when it's safe to reclaim
them so these are topics that we're not
going to cover in this class but they
are covered in the advanced class if you
do choose to take it so there's two
approaches that so these two approaches
that we're going to look at specifically
the first one is tuple level garbage
collection and the second one is
transaction level so tuple level means
that we're essentially going to do sick
you'll see ants on our tables and use
the version timestamps and set of active
transactions to figure out whether the
version is expired and if it is then we
go ahead and prune it so the reason why
this is actually complicated is because
we not only do we have to actually look
at the pages in memory but we also need
to look at the pages that we've swapped
out to disk because again we want to
vacuum everything right so we'll go for
a vacuum background vacuuming and
cooperative cleaning in the next slide
so the second approach is transaction
level which we're really not going to go
into much detail about but the general
idea is that you have transactions that
maintain their readwrite sets and you
know when they commit so the versions
are right so in this case you have the
transactions again they're maintaining
the rewrites that we read write set so
you know exactly when they commit and
thus you can figure out when they're no
longer visible and can vacuum them so
the first will first go over an example
of how a tuple level garbage collection
works so let's say we have two threads
running in the system where so
transaction t1 is assigned the time
stamp of 12 and transaction t2 is
assigned a tenth time stamp of 25 and
then over in our version table you can
see we have opposite object a which is
assigned version 100 has a begin time
stamp of 1 and an end time stamp of 9
and then we have a few other versions in
there for object B so with vacuum
background vacuuming what we're going to
do is we have sort of a set of threads
that run in the backroom and they
perform this vacuuming where they
periodically just do a full table scan
of the table and look for which versions
our reclaim Abul and it works with any
type of storage here so
for background so here see HIPAA
background thread
there goes into the to goes to the
transaction thread in and says what and
it basically queries what the current
transaction timestamps are so in this
case it's gonna be 12 and 25 right then
it's going to do a sequential scan on
the table to figure out whether the
tuples would ever be visible to them all
right so with a 100 be visible to them
hard to say because we don't know yet
what they're reading or writing but oh I
see okay sorry let me back up so again
sorry in this example we're just looking
at the time stay at the beginning and
timestamps here so here we gather the
timestamps of 12 and 25 from these two
transactions and then we again look at
the beginning and end timestamp so they
will never be able to use a 100 or B 100
because the timestamp does not fall
between 1 and 9 whereas they do follow
well the timestamp of transaction t1
falls between 10 and 20 so I could
potentially use that that value and at
this point we know those two tuples are
safe to reclaim so we go ahead and do so
um so one optimization here well one
obvious optimization here that we can do
is we can actually maintain a bitmap for
dirty pages and so anytime you modify it
you can just flip the bit of the page
that you modified so again we're meaning
we're maintaining a bitmap for all of
the pages in the database pages
specifically if we modify a page we'll
flip that particular bit which indicates
that that page is dirty so this you know
takes a little bit extra storage but
it's just a single
for all of the pages in the database and
anytime you want it in so when the
vacuumer comes around it immediately
knows which pages it actually needs to
vacuum right so it will go ahead and
vacuum that page and then reset the bit
to zero so vacuum vacuuming again is
typically ran as sort of a cron job that
runs periodically but in some database
systems for example Postgres you can
actually invoke vacuum manually from the
from the sequel prompt for example and
it also has configuration parameters
that you can set such that it will the
system will basically start up a vacuum
thread if it if over you know 20% of the
pages are dirty for example so there's
different way to implement this there's
different ways to optimize it for
different workloads okay so the other
approach we're going to look at is
cooperative cleaning alright so and this
is basically where the threads as
they're executing queries when they come
across old versions that they know are
not visible to anybody else it's their
job to actually clean them up as they go
along so again these are these are
threats are actually executing
transactions they and they're going to
actually check the versions that they
that they Traverse across whether those
should be whether those are be whether
that space is ready to be reclaimed
because they're not visible to any
transactions anymore and if it is they
will go ahead and reclaim that space so
one thing to note is if you consider the
two orderings that we discussed earlier
oldest to newest and newest to oldest
would would this approach work for both
of those no right when why is that
that's it that's exactly right yeah so
in the case of newest to oldest you're
not going to be looking at any of the
old transactions so you will actually
never end up reclaiming those so it's
important to note that a cooperative
cleaning only works with oldest to
newest ordering all right so now we'll
just go through a similar example here
so let's say that the wave in index in
transaction t1 wants to do a look-up on
object a now so it's gonna again it's
going to land on the head of the version
chain which is the oldest value and then
it's going to scan along until it
figures out which versions are actually
visible to it so if it recognizes a
version that it's looking if it
recognizes that one of the versions that
it's currently traversing it's not
visible to any other transactions then
we'll go ahead and mark them as deleted
and reclaim the space and then at the
very end of us also update the index to
point to the new head of the version
chain so we'll just go through these
steps so here we find the value right
and so we can see the version a one is
can be reclaimed and then we reattach
and then we recreate the pointer from
the index to the new version head right
so ordering is is actually important
here and the ordering that's actually
done on the that's actually on this
slide is not quite correct so when you
actually perform these operations what
you would do first is actually update so
the first thing you would do is mark
them as deleted right but you're not
actually reclaiming the space yet the
next important thing is that you
actually update the index pointer to
point to a two before physically
deleting them right
claiming that space because otherwise if
you have other transactions running
concurrently they might find an empty
pointer that points to nothing yes yes
yeah essentially yeah so it's going to
maintain some information so they can
figure out so it's going to know the set
of active transactions and be able to
compare those timestamps with the begin
and end time stamps that in the version
table correct alright so again
transaction level a garbage collection
we here we just maintain the readwrite
sets of transactions and we use them to
figure out what versions are not visible
anymore and then we claim the space and
that's really all we're going to say
about about transaction level garbage
collection so any questions on garbage
collection or anything else up until
this point all right so now we're going
to move on to the to our final topic in
design decision which is index
management so as I mentioned before the
primary key index is always going to
point to the head of the version chain
anytime we create a new version version
we have to update the version chain or
we have to update well we have to update
the index to point to the new heads at
the version chain right so this gets
tricky when updating the primary key
because now it's it's actually possible
that you could have two version chains
for the same logical tuple the way you
implement this is when if you want to
delete the primary when you want to
update the primary key you did this as a
delete followed by an insert of a new
logical tuple and there's some
bookkeeping you need to maintain and and
you also need to understand like how and
when to rollback when necessary but for
secondary indexes this is actually more
calm
complicated and this will be what we'll
talk a little bit more about so with
secondary indexes the two approaches we
use to make sure that our indexes
reflect the the correct value in the
version chain are to maintain a logical
pointer and here so here you have some
kind of false identifier for the tuple
or some kind of unique identifier for
the tuple that does not change and then
you have some layer of indirection an
indirection layer that map's the logical
ID to the physical location in the
database and anytime you update the
version chain you just have to update
the indirection layer rather than
actually updating every single index all
right so the actual approach is I think
it was I used in some of the slides
earlier I think which is to actually use
physical pointers which is when you just
point directly to the head of a new
version chain so every time the version
chain gets updated you have to update
every single index right so the
difference between the physical between
using physical pointers and logical is
you basically have this indirection
table and the benefit of the indirection
table is that you do not have to update
every single index every time you update
your version chain so all right so in
this example we'll say we have a simple
database and we're using a pendant
version chain which is running newest to
oldest right so for the primary key
index if I'm going to do a lookup on
object a then this will just be a
physical address right for the for the
primary key which will be just a page ID
and offset so you know which page to go
to and then you take the offset that's
typically what this is it's going to
point again to the head of the version
chain right and anytime you create a new
version you always update that
the primary team right all right so for
secondary indexes again you could use
the physical address but there's the
same issue anytime you update the tuple
you have to update the secondary index
to point to this and and you know this
is again like this is similar to some of
the two sort of the Delta storage idea
that we saw a few slides ago yes if you
have one attribute or if you have one
index or one secondary index then this
is not a big deal but it's very common
for OLTP databases in particular to have
many to have many some secondary indexes
on a single table so every time you
update the version chain you have to
update all of those secondary indexes
which for OLTP you can imagine might be
12 or you know a few dozen mmm um and
this of course is expensive because for
example if it's a B+ tree then you you
know are traversing the B+ tree you're
taking watches as you go and then
finally you have to apply the update so
again like we send the previous slide
instead of storing the physical address
in the secondary end index we're going
to look at two alternatives so the first
is to just store the primary key which
is literally just a copy of the primary
key as the value and the secondary index
first of all the dress here we go right
so here we're going to have the actual
value that we're going to store in the
secondary index is going to be a pointer
to the primary key index so now when you
want to find a tuple um you just get you
first got the primary key index either
the secondary index and then you do a
lookup on the primary key index just as
you would to figure out what the
physical address is and then every
proceeds as in the first example with
the physical address so anytime I update
the tuple and the head of the version
chain you can just update the primary
index and automatically updates all of
the secondary indexes right so this is
one example of logical pointers and this
is what my sequel does and Postgres
actually stores the physical address yes
um
a secondary index see if your your
primary key index right which stores
like the key for your immediate table so
your secondary index is going to I guess
be a reference to that case so yeah so
in this case so like if you so if you
have a table a right and the ID is your
primary key then maybe in table B you
have a reference to table a2 to table a
dolt IV right a the attribute column in
that table right and so you might create
a second this is what's called a
secondary index on that particular item
so if you want to think about something
more concrete you have a table of users
your user has an ID your user has a list
of items that it has purchased so for
each of those items you might store the
user's ID in it or you know something
that it's just typically used for truck
okay any other questions
hmm think of my beginning of him I said
here okay so the last approach which is
also another example of using a logical
ID is basically you just have some
synthetic values it's like a tuple ID so
this would typically be a cow you know
an incrementing counter to serve as the
tuple ID and then you have a hash table
that says how to map from that tuple ID
to the address
so so basically you're going to get the
tuple ID out of the secondary index
right buying a dress yes so you're going
to get the tuple idea of the secondary
index and then you're gonna and then
you're going to figure out where the
physical address is and then the hash
table here will point you to the
location of the physical address so you
can read that value and again similar to
the approach we looked at where we were
just storing the primary the primary key
index this is another example of logical
pointers which means that if each time
we have a new version or each time we
update the version chain we can actually
avoid having to update all of the
secondary index right so we the only
thing we have to update in this case is
the hash table and the pointers that
make sense all right so this table is
actually really interesting um so this
is a this is a table from a paper that
was published by Andy and a few other
students I think a couple years ago so
what they actually did is they looked at
a number of systems so they looked at
some older systems you know like Oracle
Postgres on my sequel and they also
looked at some much newer systems within
the past ten years so for example like
hyper and nuodb hyper would be an
example of an academic system so they
tried to get a variety of systems here
and
and the table lists which of these
design decisions each of these database
system makes so let's see if Andy has
any exciting things so I guess he says
the spoiler if you guys want the spoiler
is the or the take away the spoiler is
that Oracle and my sequel the way they
do in PC they actually found like Andy
and some students actually found this
way to be the fastest for OLTP workloads
specifically and actually found Postgres
to be the slowest although personally as
both the user of my sequel and Postgres
I like Postgres quite a bit but I'm also
not running you know commercial database
systems with the production workload
traces so you know once you get at that
scale it probably matters all well it
definitely matters a lot so okay so this
brings us to the conclusion so today
again we talked about multi-version
concurrency control and again as you
just saw in the past few slides there's
a lot more to this than just figuring
out you know what time stamps to assign
and what versions are visible to the
different transactions so you know of
course you need to figure out how to
store the versions how to update them
how to update the indexes correctly and
the other items that we covered here so
right for next class just to just as a
reminder don't come don't come to class
on Wednesday because nobody will be here
so you guys have next ones day off and
then I think the following week Andy
will probably be back although that's
not certain but we will start logging in
recovery Oh
[Music]
the next one will be son ricochet jelly
hit the deli for a boat one naturally
bless ya what rap is like the laser beam
the pawns in the bush say nice delicate
chain wrap the bottle of us a nice gold
don't feel like drinking head boney to
you drunk you can't cross the line and
if the sake don't know your phone can
tap a thing