[Music]
[Applause]
let's get started compilation is an
awesome topic there's a lot to discuss
alright so this is just what's on the
docket for everyone here project to
checkpoint
I think he's he'll post it on great
scope I think it's not already up it
posted today we're trying to figure out
we looked at to see ways to make the
accomplish and go faster
it wasn't anything obvious but like when
you submit this it won't it run like
clang format and clanked ID but it won't
run the the full linter so it'll be so
you make sure you run that yourself
because when we run it from this has to
pass that so again the first checkpoint
just be insert will figure out the
delete and then scan key and then this
one will be has to be full concurrency
and again this one he's not checking for
concurrency because great skip only
gives you a single thread will do more
exhaustive tests in the final final
analysis okay and then on Wednesdays
class all now announced what's but what
about our sort discussing project three
and I'll propose some topics that you
guys can look at certainly some things
we've talked about so far so things
we'll talk about today are Jemaine or
applicable topics you could explore but
then with the first class after Spring
Break on that first Monday we'll have in
class presentations where every group
will come out and spend five minutes to
say hey this is what we're gonna do okay
so you should least I mean I realize you
stopped the bill to beat the the B+ tree
to start thinking about what it is that
you actually want to want to possibly
build for project three okay and if
you're not sure about potential topics
and want some further clarification you
know I'll be around spring break and we
can meet necessary okay all right query
compilation is super important it is the
one of the main techniques that our
people are using in modern systems
database systems today to get best
performance so you know this is why we
spend the entire lecture
on illness so we'll first talk about
some background about what is it what
what you know cogeneration why we
actually wanna do this do the
compilation then we'll talk about the
the two techniques the cogeneration of
transformation basically source the
source compilation and then we'll talk
about the JIT compilation using the LLVM
because that was in the hyper paper that
you guys read but certainly this is not
the only way to compilation so we'll
look at some real work techniques
including popping of post graphs and our
own database system and seeing what the
the cogent quiet looks like for for
these different systems okay so last
class or a couple classes ago we've been
talking about how we're gonna get our
system to run as fast as possible and we
said that the you know the way we could
do this is is is reduce the number
instructions we have to execute alright
and also get more instructions per cycle
so if you start to talk about how hard
this is this is to really get you know
good speed-up just based on own
instructions this is a back of the
napkin calculation that the hackathon
got hackathon guys did for their paper
when they were explaining why they were
doing cogeneration compilation in their
system and it basically says that if you
want to have your data and go 10x faster
then you need to execute 90% fewer
instructions this is doable right this
is something you know not just you know
maybe turning compile optimization flag
to get you know better better better
binaries but through careful redesign of
a databases architecture we can achieve
this but if we want to get a hundred X
faster now we have 2x X 99% few
instructions now this starts to get
really really hard and so what today's
class and then Wednesday's class and
then after after the Spring Break when
we start about a vectorization these are
the techniques we're going to use to
allow us to execute a few instructions
to do the same amount of work so that we
can try to achieve this this 100x right
because Intel it's not graduating up the
clock speed anymore they're giving us
wider seamy registers more specialized
instructions there's more things Intel
is gonna give us this noon clock speed
so we have the designer system in order
to try to achieve this and there's not
going to be a magic
in GCC and clang like Oh 100 that we can
use to make this happen again it's us as
the data system developers have to
design the system and again for 20
people pay us a lot of money to do this
well that's good so this is why we want
to do code specialization or query
compilation so the idea of code
specialization is that instead of having
general purpose code in our database
system to process queries or do whatever
task we want in our system we're gonna
generate code that is specific to the
one task we're trying to process or
complete and for our purposes today it's
always gonna be a query so we have a
query and Retin rather than running this
through a general-purpose system we will
then generate code that is hard coded or
baked just to execute that one query the
reason why this is gonna be better for
it for for performances because in the
general purpose system you're gonna have
all this indirection we're gonna have
all these if causes or switch statements
to deal with all the little impossible
datatypes or operands or predicates or
aggregations you could be executing why
you process the query and that means
that as I look at every single tuple and
I call my a great function there's me a
switch statement that says if my data
type is this do this and my data type is
that do that we don't avoid all that we
strip it down to be just the exact
instructions I need in order to execute
that query so this is gonna be tricky to
do and it's not to say that people when
they when we write general-purpose data
system code they're not doing this just
because they're dumb they're doing it
for mostly software engineering reasons
right you're making it so the code is
reusable so you don't have to have this
you know duplicate operations over and
over again you know adding two numbers
we're adding to two floats and we also
write code in such a way that's easier
for people to maintain and support but
the problem is gonna be as I said before
is the way we write code that's easier
for humans to understand we're actually
gonna be the worst way you can actually
write code for for the CPU so I'm gonna
show a bunch of examples I'm going to
use this simple three table schema ABC
write a B have primary key integers and
some value
and then see just has to foreign key
references to the primary key at a and
the primary key and B so I show a bunch
of examples doing three bay joins on
this table on the foreign keys so let's
see now how we could process this query
here a three-way join with with a nested
query learned ester aggregation using
the interpretation model the iterator
model that we talked about before right
so again we have a group I or
aggregation or a group I for B inside
this this inner query and then we're
gonna do a join on on a B and C so the
query plan would look like this right
this is for our purposes here this is
just the logical plan we're not saying
what the joint album actually is but we
can this assume that it's a hash table
we're not saying how we're doing the
aggregation assume and also it's a hash
table so if we go back and use the for
loop iterator model approach that we saw
last class the way we'd execute this
query is in just a bunch of for loops
where and one operator they iterate over
the the target input in this case here
we're scanning B for every tuple in B
then we shove it up into the next
operator to do the filter and this
shoves it up to do the join right so
again this is gonna be slow for an enemy
database it's still gonna be slow for a
displaced database because we're copying
a lot of you know all the data from one
to the next yes we can combine these but
you know we're having all these next
calls and these MIT calls like all these
function calls are gonna be expensive
for us right and we have to do this
right we have this general-purpose
evaluation or value eight predicate
functions because the we don't know
actually know what the predicate
actually looks like we just know we're
gonna have the source sort of this
expression tree that we want to evaluate
and all this code here the do that do
the iteration over the next over that
every tuple from the child it just calls
this function it's it's not doing
anything special it's not doing anything
in line right so again there's a lot of
overhead from all these next calls
because we could have there are
different types of indirection but the
expression itself is also going to be
expensive as well right so we just take
this inner part here right where B dot
Val equals question mark meaning it's an
input parameter this is a prepared
statement so at runtime someone's gonna
pass in the value for this parameter
and then we're going to add one to it so
typically you a you you you represent
these predicates is through these
expression trees and the way to think
about this is that the the day to day
system will enter the root and invoke
whatever this operator is and say hey I
want to evaluate this expression tree
from the root and then it and then has
to now traverse down into the tree and
evaluate all its two children and start
pushing results up so say we come down
here we look at the equal operator we
start going to the left child we see
that expression here is a tuple
attribute on P dot Val so we do look up
at the current tubule we're looking at
because we're calling this you know
value eight predicate function for every
single tuple as we scan along so we say
alright I want B dot Val so now I gotta
look at my table schema and say alright
well the the Bao attribute is the second
one or the second attribute so I need I
know how to jump over here to get get
one thousand and then I produce that as
my output now I have to first down to
this this side of the tree this says I
want parameter 0 so I go look up my my
parameter array find the first one and
that's 99 so I get that there then this
is just evaluating it constant so I just
take one shove it up here add these
together I get a thousand then now I can
do my I can do my comparison and the
result is true so again I had to
traverse this tree for every single
tuple that I evaluate so have a billion
tuples I'm making one billion times you
know whatever for for jumps for for all
these different expressions you know
function calls and we're doing this
because again as humans it's easy for us
to reason about how to represent the
where clause through this tree but again
that's gonna be slow because because you
know all this indirection so this is
what again just these two things of oida
ng that that the interpretation of the
query plan to deal with all the in
direction of the different operators as
well as the predicate so we're at the
value eight inside those operators are
the main two things we're gonna try to
get rid of through Co specialization so
all right so again the idea is that
anytime we have a CPU intensive task in
our database we want to then convert it
or compile it into machine code that can
then we can exude directly so it's like
again
roll the switch demons would get rolling
if clauses other than you know checking
where the predicate evaluates to true
and it comes down we stripped down to be
exactly what the the query wants with
minimal lookups in in directions so I've
already shown how to do this for access
methods or evaluate predicates or
operated execution we can also do it for
store procedures or prepared statements
right with the logic appeal sequel we
can then convert into machine code only
Oracle really does this predicate
valuation we also solve other parts of
the system like logging operations like
on recovery if I had to replay these log
records rather than me looking at the
schema and then having indirection to
say oh my schema my log record has these
types and these values therefore I'd
know how to apply them to the database I
could compile or coach but I have Co
specialization methods applied to making
recovery work faster no Davison actually
does this one predicate evaluation is in
is probably the most common followed by
a Pareto access methods operatic
extrusion and then it's only a few
number systems actually do this and this
is actually something we're exploring it
in our own system right so I've already
said this before but why we want to do
this well we can do this because we know
what the attributes are in our in our
database ahead of time right and the
relational model you get to declare a
schema so it's not like we're looking at
arbitrary JSON fields or arbitrary CSV
files
we know exactly what the schema looks
like we know exactly what the size of
the data is that varchars have to be
treated differently but at least we know
that we have a fixed size pointer to
that large arm so therefore we can
instead of having all these function
calls to do lookups and say you know
give me the you know I want this
attribute from this tuple and therefore
I jump into this function that knows how
to do the arithmetic to find the value
I'm looking for I guess in line directly
the address math to go get exactly the
data that I'm looking for likewise we
all that predicates are known ahead of
time because we're given the where
clauses or we're given whatever whatever
is in our projection list so we know
exactly how to then instead of
representing it as a tree we can
represent exactly to be the the
you know the predicate that we're
actually trying to apply and then
likewise we want to get rid of all the
function calls we have inside loops so
that we have this tight kernel that we
don't then doing any branching inside of
it we iterate very quickly over and over
again and this with some benefits from
the compiler in this case because you
can do some unrolling and in some cases
it could can do some auto vectorization
which we'll cover on on Wednesday all
right all right so at a high level of
the DAT a system that we're talking
right now looks like this so I haven't
shared this picture before but this is
basically the pipeline within a real
database system of when a query shows up
right so say there's a networking layer
here at sequel query shows up first
thing we're to parse the sequel and from
the part sequel we get an abstract
syntax tree this is just the tokens like
to select the names by all the strings
that are inside the the Siebel itself
then we run this into our binder and the
binder does a lookup in the catalog to
replace the the string tokens of the
names of objects in the database with
internal identifiers like so if my table
is called foo the abstracts index tree
we'll see Oh someone's doing lookup on
something called foo I do look up my
catalogue say well foo corresponds to
this table and here's an internal
identifier to allow you to find it more
quickly in the future so then you pass
along now this annotated ast into our
query optimizer which then is going to
come generate a physical plan but there
could be more steps we'll see this later
in the semester but for our purposes
today we only care about that the
optimizer generates a physical plan
which we then now feed in some to some
compiler or the trance flyer or the the
cogent engine whatever you want to call
this that's going to take the physical
plan which is going to be those of that
operator tree and then it's gonna spit
out some kind of native code or byte
code that we can then interpret all
right so now the idea is that we take
the physical plan we've gotten from this
and we convert it into source code or
native code that does exactly what that
query wants to do without any
indirection
ok so now how you actually run this
compiler it's gonna vary between the
different systems and what this actually
is coming out of this thing
can vary to the different approaches
that we'll talk about today as well all
right so one thing I also say too is
like the in the cases where we are going
to actually compile the
the the physical plan into like machine
code that we can then link you know or
execute in a saturated system process
because we're the as us as the database
available where the wrongs writing this
this translation step we don't have to
have any security concerns because it's
not like we're taking arbitrary C code
from the user and running inside our
data system which would be stupid right
so because we control this step we don't
have to do extra security checks to make
sure that like we're not gonna have like
buffer overruns or malicious code and
things like that this is code that else
as the davison developers will spit out
so we we can assume it's sanitize unless
you know somebody on the inside tries to
take us down right we can assume that
this is safe for us to run directly
inside our database process and we don't
have to sandbox it at all we'll see when
we talk about UDS like in some
commercial systems like in Oracle for
example you can write UDS in NC which
always easy super dangerous because you
can jump to any address base uh you know
in your process so in that case they'll
fork off a sandbox and run it there so
you can't hurt the real database system
but again in our code we don't worry
about this yes question is how do I know
with the if I have a global data
structure how do I know where the global
data structures are in the compiled code
the compiled code can invoke anything in
the it'll get linked in with anything
that's running a setter data system so
you wouldn't want to have it like you
know had this arbitrary memory address
that has the object that you want you
would have a way to link it and say well
here's the function I could call commit
that can again give me access to the
object that I can do what I want yes
it's the same thing is like if it's like
arbitration of his boss like I can link
it with an existing library and be able
to evoke into that library it works the
same way like the avi of Linux or
whatever property system you doing
handles all that for you alright so
there's two approaches this there's
transpilation and and the JIT
compilation so translation also call it
source to source compilation the idea
here is that the day
a system will have specialized code that
admits new source code so like it'll
have C++ code that spits out C++ code
then you then run that people that that
new source code through a regular
compiler link that in and then that and
run that and that's that's your your
database that's your query and you're
gonna execute all right the other post
is a compilation where instead of
generating a you know direct like you
know higher-level source code we're
gonna want to generate this low-level I
or medium in intermediate representation
thing to like the LLVM ir or the JVM
bytecode we're gonna MIT that directly
and then we can then invoke that inside
of our data recently you can either
compile it or interpret it so I had a
high-level the end result is still gonna
be the same that we're going to take our
physical query plan and generate
executable code that is you know baked
just for that query plan whether we're
doing that because we generate you know
C++ code first or generate this little I
our first the the compilation time is
gonna differ between these two and
there's also software engineering
difference as well but at end the day it
still be the same thing this I mean this
is no interpretation of or having these
different lookups for for the different
types of indirection we could have
working on arbitrary data types that the
the query plan we're generating or it
comes out of a compiler is baked just
for that one query okay so we'll go
through these one by one so the one of
the first database systems in the modern
era and I'll explain what that is when
we talk about system are when the first
data system in the modern era that's
doing cogeneration was this thing called
high Q out of the university Edinboro
and like I said what do we do is like
for a given query plan that the
optimizer gave it it would write out a
C+ code that implements the X cubed plan
for that query and all our predicates
and all our type conversions are all
baked exactly into the query plan based
on what the schema is for that given
table and then maybe do a fork exact on
GCC
have-have GC spit out a shared object
the link that into our database doesn't
process and then we just invoke that to
execute the query so the way to think
about this is the the source code were
generating here it's gonna have a like a
main function but suppose that we called
name it's gonna have a function that
that the name is known and has the the
parameter signature is known to the
database system so when you get the
shared object and want to invoke the
query you know you just call that one
function then it spits back whatever
whatever the result is right so as well
seems to go along you're obviously gonna
pay a big penalty for in performance for
having to fork exact GCC because that's
firing up another process there's a
context which GCC wants to read its own
config files and if you're doing this
for every single query over never again
it's gonna be slow and this is what the
JIT compilation is gonna solve
let's see roughly how this works so we
have our query here select star from a
where a dot Val equals question mark
plus one so for the interpreted plan
it's that you know the sort of for loop
that I showed before in the first
example right we're gonna warn as
iterate over every single tuple for the
new tuples we have gave it to one I give
an offset of that way in our private
predicate and then admit its output so
in the first step here when we invoke
this function what it has to do is go
look in the catalog and figure out what
the the schema looks like for the table
then you got to calculate the offset
based on the tuple size so I know that
jump to the block and up to the fixed
like offset and then I return the
pointer to the tuple now you can cash
this first one here you can try to avoid
having to go get the schema every single
time but these other ones here you still
have to do but now the big cost is gonna
be an hour and when we valid our
predicate because now we've got to
traverse that expression tree and pull
all the values up and see whether it
returns true or false and then if so
then we made our tuple all right so what
haiku is gonna do is have a template a
plan where the this is all Python but
they're doing this they're doing their
temples in C++ where they know that they
have to do an iteration or scan over a
over a table and
that's really gonna be different is what
are the the predicates are there
different values you're gonna have to
substitute you know when you want to
evaluate the scan right so the tuple
size the predicates offset and the
parameter value like these are the
things that are going to be told to us
when we invoke the query but everything
else the predicate will change you know
could change from one core to the next
but everything else is with me always
the same from one scan the next so now
all I need to do is take these values
and take this template and just the cat
one time it'll fill these things in for
me this one here I just check to see
where that values are true or not the
same thing I just get it from here and
then I can evaluate this so again I got
rid of the look up for the for the to
get the tuple and I got rid of the look
up to evaluate the predicate so I
removed the two functions that were
gonna cause us to have jumps inside of
our for loop and now the the the the CPU
can can iterate through this for that
very quickly yes how how were using the
credit the predicate offset so it's
we're the so we have to get the
predicate offset is what attribute in
the and the tuple do I want to evaluate
so I would have to know I want I went
before was a B dot value so so this will
tell me and what offset the two boys
beat yes oh yeah this predicate because
I because what do you mean look I know
correct so it's quite here it's question
is how did I convert a bow into question
mark plus one how do I convert that into
this so the I had to make a pass through
the query plan that comes out of the
optimizer and figure out what what is
the predicate is that it's actually
doing and I convert the expression tree
into this line here so you may think
well isn't that doing
look up you'll have a billion two bowls
I only do that once right whereas this
case here you have to do it a billion
times right so it should be obvious why
again why does this is gonna be a big
win for us because everything's baked in
there's no additional lookups and we can
just iterate very quickly over every
single tuple evaluate our predicate and
produce the output yes so this question
is how is this like for the predicate
the whole thing yeah correct
we'll get there so his question is in my
example here when the query shows up
it's gonna generate this this this
structure every single time so if I
actually in theory if I know doning
query plan cashing it back to the same
query over again it's gonna pre generate
this thing open over again
compile it over and over again and so
couldn't you recognize that oh well I
only have to do so many things in a
database of some light like there's only
so many predicates sigh you know equals
less than greater than there's only in
the forum's there's only so many things
I'm gonna do execute a query could I
need to pre generate all those
primitives is the word I'll actually use
and in that way at runtime I don't have
to generate C++ code I just invoke these
functions directly
that's what vector wise does we'll see
that in later in the class
yes that's actual what we do in our
system especially the number of
predicates dependent on the depth of the
tree but I think his point is like say
like what am I doing here
Val equals something right and so
instead of having again having a
function instead of having this if calls
here to do this I could have a function
says take two integers check to see
whether they're equal and pre-compiled
that
nobody but you decompose them right to
like just like the conjunction clauses
no now it's an array it's not a tree a
equals one and B equals two and C equals
three each of those ones could be a
function called you know something
equals something and I invoke them in an
array one after another I don't want to
traverse any tree one we the
vectorization was about when we have a
better wise but like well gets in a
second the compilation cost is what's
gonna kill this approach it right so if
you don't have to now compile something
equals something every single time you
execute a query and his example can you
catch that or the copilot wants in this
link it yes yes this what vector buys
does all right right so related his
question is well how can my generate
query code invoke and touch other parts
of the system if I don't know where the
memory addresses is again well this is
just Cephas loss code we're gonna link
it in with our database system shared
object so if we expose an API it allow
you to go get access to the internal
components of our database system then
our our you know our cogent query plan
could invoke and touch those things as
well
I said like if I need to access that
like transaction manager I have a
function that says you know for my
current execution contact give me my
transaction manager and now my my on the
on the fly code can invoke that and you
know check to see whether it's a lot of
commit or not things like that so it's
almost as if like it's just the same
thing as the coab you'd write in our
database system but we're writing this
and compiling it on the fly at runtime
so us as the data system developers we
don't know exactly whatever query is
going to show up but we can still do you
know we can still invoke the pieces of
the system and actually make it
happen right so this this is this this
can be problematic in a and a JIT system
LLVM because of its c++ then you have
these mangled pass to the functions like
if you ever looked at else people plus
what the functions actually look like
when you when you look at their names
like in gdb unless they do on mangling
you know these long strings with like
the class name and like the function
name and things like that if that can
get a bit gnarly so you need to you need
a way to bridge in to do the Davison to
do that in in their world because
they're generating C code it's it's not
an issue or steeples cuz it's not an
issue because they just vote the other
functions as if it was all being
compiled at the same time right the
other nice thing you get about this
translation approach is that it makes
debugging a lot easier because now if I
crash in my my my generated code I can
just use gdb and all my standard
debugging tools to figure out why I
crashed and that's actually a big gonna
be a big problem for the LLVM stuff how
you do it you do have to have do a
little extra work to figure out like
well what is the simplest code that
generated this T plus code that crashed
yeah that you have to make that jump in
at debug symbols or hints about how that
happened but again it's it's not as bad
as it is in LLVM all right so let's look
at some experiments that they did for
haiku to understand the the benefits for
their approach so this paper is big old
I think it's 2010 now but I like it a
lot because they they generate all
different variations the way you could
do translation or you could build a
davis system and they put it all in a
single engine and compare against all
them so they're gonna have five
different approaches so the generic
iterators would be like the textbook
implementation of a database system
where you have like the volcano model
and you're calling these functions
inside the four loops two by eight
things calling next 10x over again then
they're gonna have a slightly more
optimized version where now you have
iterators that are specific to the
different types of columns you could be
accessing or a trees you'd be accessing
in your database and you you can
evaluate the the predicate before you
pass it up to the next operator
the tree they are basically doing
predicate push down then you have these
hard-coded implementations where like
they had a grad student implement like a
best-effort approach with like the
generic iterates and predicates
equivalent to this one and then a more
optimized version that's equivalent to
this one but again it's like hard-coded
just for the query and not like a
general-purpose engine and then the last
one is what they're they're you know
they're source-to-source compiler code
generator engines gonna spit out for
queries the way to think about this the
optimist heart could one is what he was
asking about like can i pre compile all
the predicates and types ahead of time
and now I'm just sort of linking
together these different functions so
that's one that's what this one is so
for this one
they are running I think it's just a
scan or join query over to 10,000 tuple
tables to produce 10 million and so what
you see is that for the case of the
generic iterators the surprise it
performs the worst and then as you get
over here the the different thing about
my is hard-coded one of the Haiku one
are they're about the same because the
the the Haiku like engine is spitting
out C++ code that is roughly equivalent
to what the hard-coded one can do so the
idea now again for any arbitrary query
instead of me time to write code by hand
over and over again I can have the
engine generate that code directly write
the the other thing you point out to is
like we have a lot more memory stalls
here in the generic one just because
there's so much like indirection and
we're doing these jumps and we don't
know exactly what what piece of memory
are gonna read ahead you know ahead of
time whereas in these cases again the
for loop is super tight we can rip
through things very quickly and then the
hardware prefetcher could bring things
in a memory ahead of time for us yeah
yes
so it's great shame it is this basically
says that this argues for the case that
you almost never want to inline small
functions are not inline them for the
inside the for-loop kernels yes
how did agree with that yes yeah I think
for small functions yes yeah I think
alike if there's predicates that are
really expensive or really large or like
functions you really large but I
actually I think the compilers these
days actually do a pretty good job for
figuring out what the in line so in the
case of like haiku when is when it's
cogentiva source code I don't think you
want to put explicit like inline hints I
think you want the compiler do whatever
wants to do I think that's the sort of
the conventional wisdom now for C++ you
don't add in mine anywhere you let the
compiler favorite things out okay what's
the downside of this approach well it's
gonna be the compilation cost now right
so for this one they're gonna compile
with o 0 + o - o 0 basically as no
optimization so 2 is with the most
aggressive optimizations that are
considered to be safe and obviously
there's more passes when you do o - so
therefore the compilation time goes up
so this is 40 PCH right ISM this is not
the query execution time this is just
the compilation time all right so now
you're trying to get into problems
because in the case of Q 3 it's gonna
take me 600 milliseconds to to compile
it for some cases the query can be done
in maybe 100 milliseconds so I'm
spending more time doing compilation
than hi I'm actually you know when I'm
spending on actually actually didn't
query right so this is the this is me a
problem with this approach and we'll see
mem sequel later in this in in the class
but like mem Seco actually their first
implementation actually did this and
when he looked some of the early blog
articles which they've since from Ruby
you look on the archive you can still
find them right they would have examples
where like you run a query and it takes
one second to run even though it doesn't
know work because they're a fork
exacting GCC from there there's there's
the C++ code there Jen
for that query compiling it then linking
back in and run it but they did a good
job caching everything so that when you
execute the same query again and they're
in their examples they would show the
company action each time would be now
zero because they can just reuse that
binary over and over again okay so the
as I said the beginning the operators
that the way we can organize our query
plan tree is useful for us to reason
about as humans makes the code reusable
makes the code easily extensible but
it's again it's not gonna be the most
efficient way to executors and in case
the haiku stuff again even though we
could execute see puzzles code that
would be a more efficient way to execute
these queries it's going to be slow for
us to compile right a big issue also too
with high q-- is that they're not gonna
support full pipelining they're still
gonna generate on a per operator the
drink of the for loop for that one
operator still having a MIT function to
shove it up to the next operator who's
then is gonna have its own for loop to
process things now make a new predicate
push down so that when you do the scan
on the table though evaluate the
predicate but everything else up in the
query plan again it's gonna be like that
next call you have you know you have to
run your own for loop as well so to
understand what how we can get better
performance with pipelining we'll go
back to this three-way join query and
now we're gonna divide it up into lists
of pipelines and again a pipeline is a
portion of the query plan where I can
take a single tuple and ride it up as
far as I can up into the query plan
until I reach some point where I can't
continue up in the query plan until I go
get get the next two will get all the
tuples that are coming within my
pipeline so the easiest one to
understand here is a pipeline to I'm
scanning B then I'm applying my
predicate but now I want to do my
aggregation on the group I but I can't I
can't go past this this operator until I
get all the tuples into my hash table
for my aggregation because I'm computing
the count so I need you know what is the
count another more tools that I have for
the you know the group by clause before
I can pass anything up over here in the
case of pipeline for over here I geeks
can see and assuming I've already built
the hash
able to do the joins on a and B I can
take a single tuple write it up here
check to see whether it if I do the join
it matches yes so then I can run it up
here and check to see whether I can do
the join a and whether it matches has
the idea is again we can have the
pipeline go look cuba go far as account
and you know up in the and until
we had a pipeline breaker right so this
is what hyper does so hyper actually has
two main ideas and the paper do you guys
you guys read so the first is that
they're gonna do this push based query
plant or processing model but then
they're also going to do just in time
compilation of the query plan using LLVM
right and so when you read the paper
hopefully didn't read the appendix I
should have warned you ahead of time
because there's all this ll Mir I don't
understand it like it's not really
useful the core material what's actually
going on in the paper was was the the
front body of it so again what the
reason why they're gonna do this push
based model is that more than is keeping
things in your CPU caches now you can
keep tuples and values in your CPU
registers which is even faster than l1
cache so now as I as I go up the query
plan in my pipeline if I'm just having
the same tuple in my CP registers then
that can rip through it very very
quickly right
the for those who don't know actually
who here has heard of El Elyon before or
here is not heard about him before
ok perfect so LLVM is originally stance
with a low-level virtual machine
although you shouldn't think of it as a
virtual machine like not like VirtualBox
to vmware originally started at UIUC in
like like 2000 or 1999 and they were
trying to build a tool to investigate
like dynamic compilation techniques for
programming languages and they ended up
building this like toolkit that's gonna
have all these different that components
you would need to been a full fledged
compiler the idea is that rather than
having a you know being compiled in
filament one programming language it
would sort of have different front-end
plugins you can then take different
programming languages build a front-end
for it that can then convert it to the
LMI r and then from there you can then
compile the
the into machine code so Apple is
invested heavily in this they hired one
of the main guys at a UIUC in like
2004-2005 and he basically runs their
you know they're all the work they do
I'm clang and LLB I'm based on this all
right so again what's gonna happen is we
can take any arbitrary language and
convert it down to this low-level IR
that's gonna sort of look like assembly
but it's designed specifically for the
sort of the virtual machine that that
that LLVM provides and then on the back
end they can then compile that IR into
whatever your target target is a is so
that it supports x86 or support arm so
you can take any arbitrary language
convert it to the IR and then have it
spit out to any CPU I say that uh that L
of M supports right so important thing
to understand though is that in the case
of hyper hyper is gonna have C++ code
admit L of him ir directly so haiku was
tabbing seamless code generate seamless
code Piper is having Steve of Cisco
generate IR but the rest of the system
just like in haiku does not need to be
written in the same language that the
that the query plan is generated in so
the rest of hyper is written in C++ and
it can still make also C++ code but you
have to mangle the the function names
the class names as I said there's you
know LM doesn't do that for you were
free but you can still have the IR code
call in to your simplest code you still
get the same benefit of everything
running in the same dress base right so
now let's go back to this query plan and
see how we would generate a source code
that would do the the push the the the
push up approach in hyper so now for for
these think of these of these different
for loops as the different pipelines and
again the idea of a pipeline is it's
it's a for loop or a bunch of for loops
that can take a single tuple and keep
processing it as far as I can up into
the query plan first so if we're doing
the scale on a is just a fourth open a
and then we evaluate a predicate and
then we can materialize it into into our
hash table right then now we do this we
jump over to pipeline B we can then do
scan through that ply up right
get a hash-table then we can then
materialize the output of the of the of
the aggregation table on being but that
now here in pipeline see we have three
nested for-loops
so we're going to take a tuple in C and
then try to do a join against it in on
against B and if that matches we try to
do the join against it on on a and then
then that that's is correct then we can
we can spit it up as our output so for
one tuple and C we can do the the join
and a of joining B and then produce an
output if necessary we don't have any
switch turn up to another tuple yes his
question is is is there multiple ways to
generate these pipelines and if so is
there always going to be an a optimal
way to do this
the typical optimization strategy is
that you you well there's two things one
is are there different ways to generate
this query plan yes
right cuz that's the quarry optimizer
does and so from our perspective in this
class we're just rying to say well the
optimizer gave us a query plan how can
we generate pipelines for it and in that
case it's a pretty simple heuristic to
decide where these pipelines that it
should look like and the typically way
you do this is the you start with like
the left side of the tree they have any
join that's a pipeline feeding to the
join and then on the right side you try
to have the pipeline go all the way up
until you hit a head a pipeline breaker
so the conversion process to introduce
your question yes there's different ways
I can generate get pipeline from cilium
fiscal plan like I could have a pipeline
in here that have a new pipeline it'd be
stupid but I could do that but the
heuristic to find the optimal one for a
given physical plan is it's pretty
straight forward the harder decision is
like should I join a b or b a like all
that before okay
so again what hyper is doing hyper is
gonna take instead of generating the
pseudocode they're gonna generate the ll
than ir that does exactly these steps
compile this as one giant function all
the pipelines to
and then now it's just stages all right
I'll run this for loop and when that's
done now I jump to this part or just
it's actually not a jump it's just you
know just executing sequentially then I
do the this for loop then I do that for
loop and then I do this last for loop
for the pipeline right so in our new
system we can actually compile these
pipelines separately in this version of
hyper everything was compiled all at
once so you had to have all the IR
generated for the for the entire query
plan for all your pipelines generated
together and this giant function then
you fire it off to two LLVM so let's
look at some before Midsummer's
comparing two different versions of
hyper one is doing the LLM IR and then
one is doing the the high Q approach
where you're spitting out so Fusco and
then for quiz second GCC then we have
the vector wise approach which is using
his precompiled predicate method that he
mentioned Monet DB would generate it
generates what looks like an IR but then
they have an interpreter for it they
don't actually compiling into machine
code and then Oracle does does nothing
it's just interpreting the query plan
and the same way we always do it right
so this is also not measuring the
compilation time this is just saying
like assuming I have everything compiled
ahead of time how fast can I go and so
because the in the case that lol M
version of hyper they're doing more
aggressive more pipelining right they're
making sure that the pipeline is as long
as possible that they can do selecting
slightly better than this version and
the Oracle is always going to lose again
because it's always doing the
interpretation right for the case of
like for q1 q1 is it's it's there's no
join it's a single table it's just a
bunch of aggregations so that one you
can do more efficiently if you coach and
everything q5 is a is like five or six
joins and the output is pretty simple so
you don't get as much big of a benefit
because the major cost in executing this
query is always going to be the join
that's gonna be precompiled anyway you
know to probe a hash table for example
invoke the hash function so in that case
you're not gonna get that big of a
benefit for for the gun cogent side of
things
all right so let's now look at the
compilation cost so now this is not a
true like apples to apples comparison
because I'm tea I'm like taking the
numbers from the haiku paper and mashing
it together with the the hyper results
so they're not running on the same
hardware I think like the hyper guys are
running on like a Z on this is running
on a Core 2 Duo from like you know
2008-2009 the scale factor is still the
same they're still compiling the same TP
CH queries it's sort of the relative
difference is what matters right just
because they have a slightly newer CPU
you know it's not going to magically get
faster so that is just showing you that
not having to then parse the C++ code
run through your you know your a ste and
your tokenizer and then compile it as
you would and GCC or clang but is
emitting the IR directly then being able
to run your operation pisses on that
inside the LLVM that's gonna be you know
orders of magnitude faster or these one
order magnitude faster than then GCC so
for this reason I think the the element
compilation approach is the right way to
go if you have a sleepless loss based
engine well seem examples some Java
based database systems they'll do this
sort of the same thing they'll MIT Java
bytecode directly instead of me know
emitting Java code then compiling that
ok so where is this compilation cost
coming from so you know 37 milliseconds
it's not as bad as 400 milliseconds but
it's still a lot right my mic my query
some queries can run in less than a
millisecond but I takes me 37
milliseconds to compile it assuming I
can't cash it ahead of time then I'm not
really getting any benefit so what's
happening here so the issue is gonna be
the compilation time is going to depend
on the query size so this means the
number joins we have then I'm rheticus
that we have number of aggregates I just
saw how complex the query is the more
things we're trying to do then the
compilation time is gonna go up and now
it's sort of this trade-off between like
well if my queries gonna run for 30
seconds who cares if it took it maybe an
extra second to compile because I'm
still gonna get a big win in terms of
performance numbers that we saw over
/ Oracle but for other queries that are
really fast maybe the the amount of data
they need to process you can rip through
very quickly because it's a calm store
you know the accomplish in time could
start eat eat into the extrusion time so
for all to be applications this won't be
an issue
imma take a guess why why would we care
less roll the TP says less joins yes
that's one of it yes yes but as you were
saying the same thing so he's saying the
execute the complexity of the query is
relatively easy compared to or lab it
means they have less joints right so yes
the oat any queries gonna be way less
complex you're not gonna do a hundred
table join it's gonna be like knee look
up Andes record thumb from the index and
go get you know some basic information
and maybe do a join with a foreign key
table there's another reason as well
caching exactly and all the T
applications weren't actually the same
queries over and over again like I load
the web page and Amazon they do a query
lookup and the index to get my record he
goes business Amazon it's the same query
just a different key so you can cache
that either as prepared statement or
like you know pre compiled code and
we've invoked that over and over again
right for OLAP this this is gonna be an
issue but where that trade-off is when
you know if you know haven't decide oh
this is good enough to compile which is
just interpreting that's hard to figure
out right because at the compiler level
one more generate and we're doing code
gen we have a rough idea how much data
we're gonna access but those estimations
can always be very wrong yes sorry get
over him what's her and with in memory
if it's in memory then it can be really
fast right we can run like so the I
think I think this is like scale factor
one so this is like doing you know this
is reading one gigabyte data in 35
milliseconds so multiply it by you know
whatever terabyte is 1024
and memory this is an issue for disk
based system the distance always going
to crush you so it matters less which is
part of the reason why Oracle probably
is never done this at least for for the
traditional and is based system correct
yes in memory the the compilation time
or the you know all that function
lookups me a bottleneck now with that I
would say also to like so Postgres is a
system we'll see this in a second they
do compilation too as well now as of
like 2018 but the end they have this
little parameter you can set to make
decisions about should I actually
compile or not based on what the extra
should cost the query it's actually
gonna be so let me get actual give it
what I'm gonna talk about what hyper
does the motivation for what Hyper's
gonna do here was they were trying to
just like us they were trying to support
the post that's wire protocol and post
has catalog and so there's this contrary
a commonly used tool call PG admin which
is like a PHP interface to configure
your Postgres installation so the way
all these like these these you know
visual database tools work is that when
you turn them on they connect to the
database it immediately run a query a
bunch of queries against the catalog and
figure out what tables do I have what
columns do I have what indexes do I have
so they can expose that to the DBA to
manage the database so when you turn
that when you would in hyper case when
you would turn PGM and on point at hyper
it would be this long pause at the very
beginning right we're talking like maybe
10 seconds because the PG admin fire of
all these queries that then had to run
through the elevate and compiler just to
figure out what tables you would have
whereas the key around was regular post
rest it doesn't do any of that
compilation so when you turn on PG admin
it would be much more quick you know
boot up more quickly so to solve that so
let's do so those queries aren't that
complex but there was just a lot of them
and the compilation cost was eating
eating all your time so this is a paper
that came out in 2018 from the hyper
guys at won best paper in ICD I think
this is actually a this is actually a
really good idea
we tried doing this in peloton but when
we killed off peloton we didn't we do
something differently now we we do
something slightly different in what
they're doing but the idea here is it's
a really good one so what they're gonna
do is when a query shows up they're
still gonna generate the IR just as you
normally would but then rather than
firing off the LLVM compiler waiting for
that to finish and then start executing
the query they're gonna have a IR
interpreter think of this is like a VM
that's can then interpret that IR and
start executing it so they have the
German guide Thomas wrote it in parently
in two weeks you basically take the the
the byte codes that LVM spits out and
it's IR and you just implement a virtual
machine to execute it so now it's gonna
make all the same function calls to the
rest of the system make all the same
invoke all the same operands and
predicates as you normally would in the
cop-out engine but it's running it as an
interpreted as an interpreter so it's
not like you have to build two separate
engines completely you just have the
interpreter execute the same
instructions that the compiled version
stuff well so now the interpreter is
running then in the background you start
compiling the query and then when the
compiled query is ready you just slide
it in if the query still running to
replace the the interpreter execution so
again they're using morsels though so
what would happen is every single time a
a thread a worker thread would complete
a morsel it would check some flag and
say is my compiled version ready if yes
then invoke that if no then I just keep
running might might in the interpreter
so now for those queries that could take
a long time to compile but will execute
very quickly in those cases the you
could finish them off just do the
interpreter and not wait for the long
compilation stuff to finish so they're
actually going to do have usually three
stages of different different types of
compilation can do based on what type of
optimizations are going to do so again
the sequel query shows up and so in
their case their optimizer maybe takes
you know 0.2 milliseconds then they have
this cochon engine and that's taken 0.7
milliseconds
all right because you're traversing the
tree spitting out the IR and then the
first thing that'll do is they'll
they'll pass off the IR to the
this bytecode compiler or interpreter
and execute that and so some cases that
could finish up in 0.4 milliseconds
sorry sorry it's compiler so you're
taking the IR and converting it to a
bytecode that they can then interpret
that takes four milliseconds then the IR
also goes to the Allium compiler but
they turn off all the the optimization
passes like unrolling loops and peephole
optimizations all that's turned off so
that complete in six milliseconds so now
that's gonna be a little bit faster than
this one so when this one finishes then
you can replace this with this but then
they're also gonna then if it runs even
longer then they'll run it through all
the optimization passes of the hello and
provides by now you're doing like dead
code elimination and sub-expression
elimination and the peephole stuff that
then they can then run it through the
compiler and then this picks out the x86
code so the idea is that I start
interpreting right away on the byte code
if it finishes before you know right
away then I'm done if this thing
finishes before this excuse execution
finishes then I just start executing
this but then I also fire off this this
this pass and then if this is if this is
done if this is not done by the time I
get this then I replace it with that so
you're sort of staging how fast the the
execution engines gonna get and the idea
is that rather waiting for this thing to
finish which in this particular example
here 25 milliseconds plus 70
milliseconds rather not executing any
work during this time I think these get
some work done it's not gonna as if it
as efficient but it's better than
nothing so they have some some numbers
about cpc-h for those three stages again
this is going to show you the relative
difference from performance between the
between the the bytecode interpreter or
the unoptimized LVM and the optimized
LLVM so again you're getting an
automatic two difference between the
optimized compiled version and the
interpreter so that that's reasons why
you want to have both the other benefit
you do get which they don't talk about
so much in the paper is that since again
these it's the same eye are the same
through the the bytecode is executing
the same query that were executed here
if now there's a bug in how I generate
that IR rather than
you know looking at the compiled version
of the query plan which in this case
here you're not gonna have debug symbols
you're not going to have a stack trace
when you crash is you're just gonna land
in an assembly you can least step
through the interpreter with this and
figure out why your query is breaking
right yes team is if there's a pack here
if there's a bug in this applying the IR
into the bytecode or bug in the
interpreter itself then yes you like you
have to figure out what's going on here
but the idea would be that the that LLVM
so like yes the compiler could be wrong
there's a there's a hierarchy of like
what could be wrong like it's always
like like the first thing the blame is
your code then next thing the blame is
maybe the library you're using then
maybe you next blame the the compiler
and then maybe they're very unlikely
blame the hardware so the high
probability your code is wrong like this
thing's not gonna be wrong so but the
point I'm trying to make is like we
don't have to write this this is not
gonna be that difficult to write and
it's not something has to be modified
all the time as we expand your
functionality right if we design the
system such that it's it's sort of
general enough you know every time we
add a new sequel functions not like we
need to modify this so only a you know a
small number of smart people think about
this there's a small number of small
people that can write a Devi system
there's even smaller number of smart
smart people that can write this piece
right and so we pay that person a lot of
money get this right and assume it's
right going forward okay
all right we have 15 minutes I want to
rip through very quickly a bunch of
different real-world implications of
this so as I said at the very beginning
I said oh the high Q was the first
example in the modern era and the reason
I use that as that phrasing is because
IBM did this as many things and
databases as it did in the 1970s but
then they abandoned it but now pretty
much a lot of the systems today are
using this approach so IBM had a
primitive form of cogent and cording
compilation back in the nineteen
seventies for system R Roberts the
system our project was they took Ted
cots paper handle off to researchers at
San Jose got him in a room a bunch
people with brand new PCs and said hey
build a database system build a
relational database system every one
card we know every person with a PC
carved off one piece of it one guy did
storage one guy invented sequel another
woman did query optimization and then
somebody did this cogeneration thing
right and then what would happen is they
would take a sequel statement and they
we have it spit out assembly that would
then in just like a haiku or the IR for
LLVM be exactly the the bacon execution
plan for for that query and they would
have a bunch of templates and sort of
splice things together so it turned out
though that this was a huge panting ass
maintained engineer because back in the
day in the 1970s IBM had a whole these
different mainframes that all these
different ISAs and instruction sets they
had the support so in order to get
system R to work on you know you know
360 or some some other system you had to
make sure you poured all this assembly
stuff which is error-prone so when they
went and started building db2 some
pieces of system are made it into
whatever the version of db2 they built
first like the sequel stuff but all this
cogeneration stuff and abandoned the
other big issue too was anytime that the
other parts of the system changed like
the layout of pages for for tuples or
the indexes you had to go change all of
this assembly code which is a huge you
know nightmare because every time there
was a change you got to change this part
and test it so there's this great
there's a retrospective came out in 1981
that talks about the history of system R
but then the the main developers that
worked at IBM at the time they did like
a panel or
interviews in the late or early 1990s
that talked about you know what was like
building your Davis system in the 1970s
where nobody knew how to build a
database system and one of the things
when you read those interviews they talk
about how this thing was a huge
nightmare and that when they built db2
they got rid of it right so Oracle for
their high end things like the fracture
mirror in memory column store and then
for like Exadata they do something
similar but like if you just download
regular Oracle the disk based version it
doesn't do any compilation for queries
they might do predicates but again that
might only be for the for the high-end
versions of it the one thing they do
compile though is store procedures so
they're going to take your PL sequel
store procedures and convert them into
pro C or prostar C which is their
specialized dialect of C and then
they'll compile that into native and C
C++ code and the the the reason why
they're gonna do this is because this is
gonna have a bunch of security checks to
make sure that your store procedure is
not doing something weird with address
space so they don't they don't run this
in the sandbox thing and run this
directly inside the database system
system process the one thing that
horrible can do that nobody else can do
that's super insane is like actually put
the database operations directly on
hardware
now FPGAs are a thing that you can do
and people have done this from database
systems but those are skin those are
still slightly more general-purpose this
is like they're actually manufacturing
the CPU and they'll put specialized
instructions or with the Aqua database
on the CPU
they bought son 15 years ago someone's
making the spark chips so some of the
new version of spark chips have like
support for or host compression
algorithm or Oracles bitmap stuff
directly on on hardware so that avoids
you know that blows out anything you can
do with cojan because instead of you
know compiling code that does the what
your dailies wants to do you just invoke
the operations on the hardware itself
doesn't get any faster than that I don't
think they do this anymore because I
don't think they make sparks anymore but
this is maybe like four or five years
ago they were touting this that you
could buy Oracle RAC machine from
had son Sons hardware and they would
make your Oracle debase go faster we'll
talk about FPGA is it at the end the
semester for hackathon we've already
talked about Bakic a pal but store
procedures and sequel what was kind of
cool is that they would have they would
pre compile a bunch of these operators
that allow you to have non hackathon
queries touch Hecate on data I can run
those efficiently and the way they would
do this is they would generate C code
from the syntax tree of the query plan
compile that using you know the whatever
the the Microsoft compiler generate a
DLL then link that in at runtime the
same way that the Haiku actually did
this and make sure that anybody was
doing something clunky they would have a
bunch of extra checks to make sure that
you you know you didn't have a weird
predicate that try to do a cup offer
overflow to take control of the systems
now Actium vector is what he was asking
about before so they're not really doing
cogent they're pre compiling these
primitives and this is why I use the
term and thinking about primitive as
some low-level operation you'd want to
do on a piece of data repeatedly but
it's gonna all going to be written for a
specific type so how about primitive did
you a comparison between two numbers or
and one will be for 32-bit 64-bit 16-bit
floats right I'll pre compile all these
primitives then now at runtime what my
query plan is basically doing is
stitching together all these precalc
primitives as if it was a bunch of C++
code that was that was generated on the
fly and now I'm just making calls into
these functions that are pre compiled
and that's gonna be almost as fast or
some cases faster so looking at one
example here right so here's L a
primitive do do it take a take a pointer
to a bunch of in 32 call values inside
of a column take the value I want to
compare against and then I just do do a
less than and if it matches then I
produce in my output buffer and here's
the same function but now I'm comparing
a double so my input column is a as a
32-bit integer but my comparison value
is a double so I just you know I add
that piece in there the copilot will
generate the right Caston code for me
right
so we'll see this next class we'll talk
a little bit the next guys NL so after
Spring Break but you would think all
right well isn't this gonna be slow now
if I'm invoking this function for every
single tuple well that's why they're
passing in a kind of appointed to a
column it's sort of in the name of
vector wise are they're passing in a
vector of tuples that this can then be
vectorized by the compiler using seemed
instructions so now I'm not doing a
comparison between a single scalar and
another scalar I'm taking on batch of
values invoking a single instruction to
execute that more efficiently
all right so again we'll see this we'll
see how to do vectorization neck the
next class but this is this is one of
the reasons why although vector Y is not
a full cogent engine you can still match
the performance of a cogent engine
because you get this benefit here
whereas Viper can't do vectorize
execution it's only tuple at a time all
right so now there's a bunch of database
systems that are based on the JVM that
run on the JVM so spark in 2015
announced they had this new tungsten
execution engine sparks written entirely
in Scala
so inside those source code they have a
way to take the predicates of a inside
of your query because spark supports
sequel and then they'll convert that
directly into Scala ast S which then can
be generated into bytecode and they can
invoke that and execute that natively
inside of the engine how it's running so
SPARC is doing this for Scala again it's
just running the JVM there's a bunch of
other JVM databases that are more or
less all doing the same thing neo4j
spliced machine presto and Derby splice
machine uses Derby so these these two
are kind of the same I was looking at
the neo4j source code last night it's
not very good because there's no
documentation but from what I can tell
it looks like that you can actually
generate the you generate the bytecode
for your query they can also then
reverse it and put it back into Java
source code so if you won the end now
run it through a debugger and figure out
you know why your query isn't actually
working
they can actually support that I don't
know whether these other guys can do the
same thing all right
the others do think about you about
using the JVM because it's doing
just-in-time compilation
I can omit the bytecode
I don't have to run any compiler passes
on it right away then the the hot spot
VM will recognize if I'm extremely this
this this bytecode over now over again
in my for them as I'm accessing every
single tuple it'll then do the compiler
compilation stuff for me so I don't need
to do that multiple stages that we did
in the LLVM the JVM takes care of this
for me but I think it's kind of cool
alright so mem Seco is a interesting one
because they have two versions of their
engine so as I said before the mem steep
one Memphis goes co-founder was at was
that Microsoft when they were building
hackathon saw the early talks from and
you know internally from at Microsoft he
wasn't working on hackathon so talk from
the researchers to talk to how they were
new cogent for hackathon using C so when
you went off in Belton MC call he did
more that's the same thing which is the
same thing as haiku so they would have
code that would generate this the the C
source code for a query plan then fork
exec GCC link in that shared object and
then run that query and as I said in the
early versions of mem Siegel when you
look at their blog articles they would
show examples were like the first time
you run a query be one second because
that's all the compilation overhead but
then second times would be much faster
then raid they were able to make it go
faster is through caching by taking any
query that showed up extracting out the
constants and then recognizing if the
query same query shows up again just
with different input parameters I can
reuse my cache shirt shared object so my
query shows up select star from a where
egg a ID equals one two three I
recognize I have one two three here rip
that out to be a parameter compile that
cache it and then now for another query
shows up with a ID equals four five six
I could recognize that I could reuse the
same query plan and run that and don't
pay that compilation overhead
now we asked them and they told us that
the only thing they were doing here was
just string matching so if my predicate
was like where a ID equals 1 and n be ID
equals 2 I cashed that one but now if I
show up with reverse of like B ID equals
1 and a ID equals 2 then they couldn't
reuse that even though semantically it's
the same query that the string won't
match right so then what happened was
and actually the the
mm single guy Nikita told me that like
had in the earliest of mmm seagull had
they had to do it all over again they
would have not added this compilation
stuff at the beginning because it was a
huge pain for them to maintain I think
they were going to a lot of the same
pains that the the IBM guys were having
yes he said you say - this compilation
is expensive but like how much is it how
much is the overhead of the compilation
versus the execution time the query and
how much can we actually cash things yes
right so like but if we query runs from
one millisecond like if if you ran the
interpreter and it took ten milliseconds
but my compiled version runs from one
millisecond but it takes me 20
milliseconds to compile it then I'm
better off just running the interpreter
mem sequel to avoid engineering overhead
you don't want have to build two
separate engines right so they would
compile every query so to avoid and they
were sort of focusing all that things so
you could hope that most the queries
show up with the same pattern you can
reuse the cache plan over and over again
the question is though how much benefit
it provides or depends on what the query
is actually going to do if I'm gonna
read one tuple then then caching could
help a lot because the queries gonna be
so shortened anyway if I'm reading you
know a petabyte of data caching is
probably not gonna make a difference who
cares right for in memory you know most
you don't have databases running in one
petabyte of memory because that's be
super expensive so most memory databases
we're looking at or tens of hundreds of
gigabytes
I think Memphis Eagles that they had
somebody who was like 14 terabytes or
something like that still a lot like
most squares aren't gonna have to rip
the repeting so as I said if they the
mem sequel guide told me they had the
noose over again they would not started
with up with the compilation stuff but
then they got a bunch of money which
always makes things easier and they
hired the guy from from Facebook that
built the hip hop VM for Facebook so
Facebook famously runs on PHP
PHP is an interpreted language language
and the the default least because when I
do PHP develop a con the day like the
default PHP interpreter is super slow so
Facebook nor get better scalability they
built their own B end that can compile
PHP so mem Seco hired the guy that
invented her that worked on that hip-hop
VM to let that project to go read write
the execution engine to be entirely
based on LLVM so now they're gonna do
when what is in my opinion the right way
to do a LM a query execution engine and
this is basically what we're doing now
in our own system so what they're gonna
do is they're gonna take the physical
query plan the optimizer spits out and
then they're to first convert it into a
an imperative plan that that is written
in a high-level domain-specific language
of DSL that they call MPL the mem sequel
programming language it basically looks
like C++ and we'll see our example in a
second then you take that DSL and now
you compile into a bunch of op codes and
then now you can have these op code the
and either interpreted or compiled now
mmm sequels case I think they always
went straight and did compilation but
you could still have an interpreter the
way that the hyper guys did for for
their IR right and now the benefit you
get from this is if I'm a database
engineer we actually people actually
building the system it's way easier for
hire new people to work on this part and
not worry about this part down here
because I'm gonna I'm gonna assume that
my really expensive really smart people
wrote this part correctly and the
everyone else you know I can I can come
work on this part here so you guys will
be the same thing for your project 3 if
you end up working on the execution
engine most of you if you want to add
new features like new string functions
and your sequel functions or date
functions you don't have to touch this
part here you just need to modify this
part up here right all right
Postgres add support for the elevation
in 2018 first came out in version 11 but
it was turned off by default
and then now version 12 I think as of
last year it's turned on by default so
every query and they have an internal
cost model to decide whether I should do
compilation or not and they're gonna do
accomplishment predicates and tuple do
serialization and basically get removed
reduce the number of get next calls you
think
and in the iterator model so I'm gonna
try to inline everything as much as
possible all right and the way they did
is super interesting is that they took
all the backend Postgres code like the
actual the server itself that they have
written see and they can then convert
that same source code into LEM C++ and
then through that they can then remove
these iterator calls so you sort of take
the function to take you know add two
numbers together and they can pre
compile that in LMC pulse code so now as
I do cojan for queries
I invoke that C++ code and not the
regular Postgres C code right
I overtime I could give a demo but let's
give it we'll do it at the end of a on
more time cloud or impalas in double
images using LLVM so they only do
predicates just like in Postgres but
they also do for record parsing which is
interesting
so Impala doesn't have their own like
proprietary storage format like post
cast my seagull there's always
proprietary you know wrote column layout
of data you know they run a parquet
they've run an Avro they run on all the
Hadoop or cloud-based file formats so
what they're gonna do is in order in
order to parse these these records more
more quickly they're gonna precompile a
bunch of these parsers ahead of time or
if my query shows up and operating on
some CSV file so I know what the schema
is I can then pre-compile the CSV parser
so I don't have to have this interpreter
to look at like you know fine columns or
commas and things like that
I'm gonna skip Vitesse DB I want to
quickly talk about hours so the first
version of peloton we did what L Piper
did we would have our C plus coats but I
are directly we weren't doing full
pipelining they were doing we actually
can do we actually introduced these
these pipeline breakers at different
parts of the query plan because now we
can pass around
vectors R to pool to get the benefits we
have in vector wise this will make more
sense next class and when you solve our
pet you need to hide this so just to
show some numbers this number this is
what my patient Prashant ran so this is
like the interpreted version of peloton
versus like the compiled version with
and without this relax operator fusion
technique and so this is not a good
example of what the benefit you can get
from compilation like this is like if
you're versus not like
the Graybar he repelled town that was a
it was a bad engine right it wasn't good
at all and so I don't get the idea that
you're gonna get a hunter X benefit
performance improvement through
compilation is usually like from any
from 2 to 25 X right but this showing
you here that again we can go from this
is like 88 8 seconds to 800 milliseconds
like that that's a pretty significant
drop by doing compilation here right but
we abandon this because it was a huge
pain because now you need to be an
expert in ela Mir in order to debug
anything or make any changes to the
execution engine because when the query
crashed you land an assembly and don't
have a stack trace and only like 2 or 3
students could actually work on it now
our new system which is currently
unnamed but we have a name we haven't
announced it is we do what mem Siegel
does where we take the query plan
convert it into a high-level DSL that's
specific to our database system
basically looks like C then we compile
that DSL into opcodes
and then we can interpret that off codes
while the compilation occurs in the
background looks like this my query plan
shows up I can then convert this into
some some dialect which again looks like
C like this is doing a scan on foo and
then has this predicate on column a
column B well inside of my my my DSL I'm
doing that operation directly now I'm
gonna convert this into op codes the
exact details doesn't don't matter but
like this is actually human readable
right like we have things like table
vectors to iterate over to polls and get
next and have function calls to to get
integers and things like that so now I
can then take this OP code start
interpreting it at me lean start means I
can start executing without having to
run the compiler then in the background
I run my LM optimized compiler I
generate C++ I gentlemen my shared
object I can then link that in and and
fire it off right
again that was bit rushed I can show
down with this next class all right so
the main takeaway from this is that
query compilation is super important any
every modern data system is going to
want to do this
the column is gonna be it's gonna be not
easy to implement but you need to know
something about compilers and political
systems the Mystique approach as of 2016
is the way to go
and every system now is it's exploring
okay okay what is this
[Music]