[Music]
[Applause]
this will be the the the last lecture
we're gonna do on on multi version
control and again today we're gonna
focus on garbage questions because
that's super important for an NBC
database system so we've sort of out
recovered this in the last two lectures
but let's go into the Mojo detail what's
what's actually what's going on so the
reason why obviously we need to do
garbage collection in an MVC system is
because we have to identify physical
versions that are reclaim Abul and then
remove them right because otherwise
we'll just run out of space I think I
said in the beginning that with time
travel queries Postgres when I first got
my first words created in 1980s they
didn't do any garbage collection at all
because they said we wanted to support
time travel queries I mean you can go do
queries on status to the database as
they were back in time and of course in
the 1990s when people actually really
started using Postgres also had academia
the first thing they did was add back
garbage collection because you run out
of space pretty quickly if you have a
lot of churn in your database so so it's
sort of obvious why we need to do this
so our definition of a plain Bowl is
going to be a physical version where
there's no active transaction that's
running in the system that can see that
particular physical version meaning it's
not visible to that transaction under
snapshot isolation or obviously if the
version was created by de Borda
transaction we don't want that sitting
around forever and we want to go ahead
and clean that up right so the great
thing about multi version control
because we're recording those timestamps
in order to provide snaps to isolation
that we can just use all those same
timestamps to determine when when tuples
are actually visible or not alright and
the idea here is that the the time
stands for using to assign transactions
to understand they're the global
ordering is the same timestamp so user
to turn you know in in Martin versions
or the lifetime of of physical versions
and we just say all right if nobody can
see this then we go want to go ahead
and remove it right so one thing we need
to talk about though is and what was in
the paper you guys read from the hyper
team is this notion that like the
complications that are on arise if you
now start having transactions or queries
that run for a long time again member I
said in OLTP environment the
transactions are almost always
short-lived right update and E's account
on Amazon commit that transaction and
you're done right and so in that world
updating those versions the transactions
that need to made it read those old
versions they're they're not you know
they're not sitting around for a long
time so it's not like there's a
long-running transaction that needs to
see the version of the database as it
exists at an hour ago in a parallel to
the environment we don't have that issue
but now it's when we start throwing in
the analytic workloads and litical
queries then then we have to care about
this right he's gonna understand an
isolation I need to see only the
versions of the the tuples that existed
by they were created by transactions
that committed before I started so if I
microwaves gonna take an hour then I
need to see the snapshot of the database
as it existed for that entire hour now I
can run under lower isolation levels
like read uncommitted the entry whatever
I want who cares but if you want to
provide snåsa isolation then you need to
do this all right so again the issues
gonna be what we talked about in the
first lecture about what to call
traditional grabbers question that was
like all right I look at my timestamp
and of all my active transactions and if
anybody if any version is less than the
smallest active transaction time stamp
then I know I know and go ahead and
prune it but now if I had these queries
that are sitting around for an hour then
that's gonna be you know that's gonna be
a longer amount of time yes yeah
Yeah right covered each tap in the in
the intro class
so the lhp and overlap and in the in the
2000s people basically figured out oh
you actually want to have specialized
systems for each of these and then you
can run your OTP queries in this
database and your OLAP queries in this
database and that way they have
different design choices as different
goals and you can build a system that's
optimized for both of them this age tap
stuff is a bit newer concept hybrid
transactional analytical processing and
the idea here is that I want to be able
to run analytical queries as soon as
data arrives so instead of waiting for
me to use some kind of ETL process to
offload it from the the OTP side into
another database system I'm gonna run it
on as immediately as it shows up so that
that's a more common thing now right
because the longer it takes for me to go
figure out like if you're playing a game
and I want to you know trick you to buy
crap if I have to run it and let it to
my back-end machine and it takes a long
time for that data gets transferred over
then I may lose out on the sale yeah so
his he has a perfectly good statement is
like alright well for these analytical
queries do we really need to run under
snapshot isolation coming just run at a
lower isolation level and is that good
enough
in many cases yes and so this is sort of
a this is sort of a have a service um a
perception in academia that is actually
slightly different all right actually
it's quite different than what actually
happens in the real world so in the
academic world will you say oh of course
you want to run a serializable isolation
or snapshot isolation but then in the
real world most people run it like read
committed cuz that's the default you get
in Postgres in my sequel alright so yes
there are there are some cases where yes
you do want synapse isolation you want
sterilizable queries for this analytical
stuff most the time you don't need this
but even then like it does occur enough
that we had to solve the problem all
right yeah we did a survey of DBAs two
three years ago and we basically said
look like 50 there 60 percent of all the
papers in Sigma novio DB they assume
transactions run at serializable
isolation but then you ask real DBA is
in like like 10 percent
transactions run at sterilized isolation
everybody runs re committed cuz that's
the default you get in in in real
database systems and those who don't
bother to change it unless you know what
you're doing so I say that sample
actuation is bearable you would actually
want to have for analytics you probably
almost never want to have like
serializable analytics it doesn't make
sense
exceptions good enough okay actually it
doesn't make sense if it snaps at
insulation then I see everything as
committed that's I can't have any
anomalies because I'm not doing rights
as well
so yes I'm simulation is like the
highest we'd ever want to go yeah okay
all right so I sort of already covered
this but what are the problems of having
these old versions again assuming we
want to achieve samsa isolation for our
analytic queries or obviously we are
increasing our memory usage because now
we're creating new versions and our
version chains are getting longer but we
can't reclaim that memory so that
they're the amount of storage space that
our David says is is consuming or using
just keeps growing and growing
infinitely right but now that also means
that if we have to know if we can't
reuse the memory that from older
versions because we can't recycle the
the space now we're going to go back to
reallocator and potentially go back to
the operating system through malloc and
ask for more memory and that call is not
cheap and is not free like going to
malloc and asking for my memory is
definitely become a bottleneck if you
have a lot of threads doing this at the
same time our verge of changing to be it
longer again that means for transactions
that have to traverse the Virgin chain
to find the right version that they want
that I'm never going to take me longer
now if you're doing news to oldest and
most your OTP transactions are just
touching the newest version right this
is not that big of a deal for the
analytic queries yes they have to
traverse the whole chain but maybe find
the right version the only system that I
know that does oldest to newest is is
Hecate on so they would have this
problem but if you if you notice a
notice then it's a long traversal to put
the new one at the m that's only a
problem Hecate on but for analytical
queries it takes longer for them to find
the right versions they want
another big issue which we haven't
really talked about so much is this
notion of having consistent performance
and stability in in your database system
in terms of performance if now you have
like these long-running queries for an
hour and then the hour the queries done
and now I need to go back and clean up
all the old versions that are finally
finally reclaim Abul we're now gonna
have this huge spike in the CPU usage
for your garbage collection threads
because they're gonna say oh look at all
these versions I can go clean up let me
rip through that and and you know start
throwing them away and now queries that
are running the same time they might not
have a dip in performance because now
there's contention on the CPU for
resources because because you're doing
garbage collection all right so again
like a lot of times in in the real world
a lot of companies or organizations
they're they're very conservative with
taking one news new technology for
databases because they want to have
consistent performance it doesn't help
you to say like alright here's the
latest greatest version of a new
database system and it's gonna make 95%
of my queries go go much faster but then
the 5% I'm gonna be like randomly slow
people aren't going to want that they'll
stick with the old stuff that they
actually know all right and the last one
is gonna be an issue when we start doing
we talk more about cache locality and
other things so I'm compression so if I
now have all these old versions
scattered around in my my tablespace
then when I start doing if I'm doing
this the garbage section all at once now
I have a bunch of holes in my in my
table that I can refill with other other
objects but when I want to do
compression I want to basically get a
bunch of old data and compress it down
because it's it's read-only if my all
the virgins are sort of scattered around
because I can't keep reusing the same
space over and over again then I lose
this locality and I have to do a bunch
of extra work to combine together
objects that are related to each other
within time and that way they can be
compressed this won't make sense right
now I'll cover this event at the end of
election okay all right so for today I
want to spend a little time at beginning
to talk about we talked about the issue
about delete so this is something we
didn't cover
in the last few lectures I should have
but it's it's in here now and then we'll
focus on the different design decisions
you have for garbage collection which
was in the hyper paper you guys read and
then what's a rock block compaction
which is the thing I was saying about
combining together unused space across
the the data tables in order to you know
compactor will combine them together and
forget memory and then I'm missing the
the bullet point here but I'll finish
off and doing a tutorial on perf which
is what you need to do for project one
okay alright so we've talked about it
doing inserts or talked about doing
updates we didn't really talk about how
to do deletes so in such your easy right
it's it's the first physical version of
a tuple I find a free slot in my in my
night data table and I just insert it
right no big deal and then updates we
already know that a handle right
depending on what version scheme are
using right whether we do Delta records
would be pen only whether do you know
what direction the version chain is we
know how to handle that deletes a little
bit tricky now because you need to
basically record now that this this fist
of this logical tuple has been deleted
and that even though someone may come
along and insert that same tuple all
over again that's technically now in
another snapshot and you don't want to
reuse the Virgin chain and so basically
you need a way to record to say all
right well this thing is now deleted no
other version ship should come behind it
right so again we can't have any right
right complex this is only the first
writer wins so if my transaction deletes
this tuple before I could before I
commit you try to update it I'll beat
you so we need to have the same sort of
correct correctness semantics as before
right so the question is now how are we
actually going to record that our tuple
was logically deleted at some point in
time because we can't delete the version
chain because that's you know then the
existence is gone right so there's two
basic approaches to do this the one is
you maintain a separate flag somewhere
that says that this logical tuple has
been deleted and so you can either just
store this now in like the tuple header
that we talked about before we record
all this timestamps or you can just have
a
per column that's just a bitmap field
that says the the tuple within our block
at this all set has been deleted so that
means now when I start scanning or my
transaction starts reading the database
I always have to check this thing first
to see whether it's actually you know
whether I'm going down a path that
that's it's not believe it or not
alright so in our system we store it as
a separate column that's a separate
bitmap field all right the other
approach is to do a tombstone tuple and
the idea here is that we store a new
physical version a special physical
version at the end of the version chain
or at beginning the end depending what
direction we're doing and then the
somehow to indicate in that in this
special version that it's representing
that this tuple was deleted and then
that per to destroy all the time stamps
and everything you would do before and
that gives you no information about say
when this when this tuple was actually
deleted so anybody that comes prior to
that and earlier snapshot please still
see the older versions so one way to
sort of improve this and make make this
work nicely instead of having sort of
polluting all of the extended wasting
space in their fixed data pool you could
have a separate data pool to store these
two Serna to blows because you don't
actually need to restore the whole tuple
and then the version chain now this
points points to this thing and you
would look and say oh with this bit set
there's some bit pattern inside it says
oh this is actually tombstones tuple not
a regular tube wall this is only really
the issue if you're doing append only
alright so again think about this if I
am doing a pendulum and I have a
thousand columns if I delete that tuple
and I want to create a tombstone to pool
well one approach is I now make a
special tuple in my same table with all
my other tuples for that table that has
a thousand attributes so that's wasted
space just a record that that thing was
actually deleted or it can have a marker
that says hey you know or have a special
tuple space to say this represents a
deleted tuple and that means shared
across different tables because we're
not storing any attributes in the
tombstone and tuple we're just it's a
marker to say this thing was deleted
so in peloton in our I would say not but
loved but whatever the old system we
killed we did it this way
and we would use this special pool
because we were doing a pen only licking
Hecate on and therefore if we now create
a tombstone to pool if we put it in the
same data table would be a big waste of
space and the newer system we use we use
a separate column as a deleted flag yes
this question is why doesn't there need
to be a Oh starting different to sent
ripples for deleted tuples or for
different tables okay is if I delete
three tuples from the same table why do
I need a separate room center table for
each of them because in the tombstone to
boil you're recording the begin and end
time stamp because I need to know when
was this thing delete it now yeah I
think your other question too was well
why do I need to have why can I have as
why can I have a same tombstone table
special table that can be shared across
multiple data tables because we are not
storing any attributes in the tombstone
the tombstone just says hey you're dead
at this time so it doesn't matter what
table it corresponds to but you need you
know the timestamp back on that yeah
yeah
I think I think I think part of the
issue is gonna be that first rider would
win so who cares your market is leading
there might be some ordering issue of
like can I record that's been deleted
and then I stop to go yeah if I do that
then if my transaction that deleted that
tuple aborts then I gotta go make sure I
go back and remove that if I don't
modify the previous tuple other than
maybe the pointer then when I when I
when I bought I stopped update the
pointer yeah you might be able get away
with something like that I have to think
about that oh yeah if it was it was the
student that built this piece of the
system it's not that he liked to cut
corners but he basically did everything
in the most efficient way but possible
which is always not the best engineering
approach so if there's a way to make
that work I would and like do that hack
you're proposing
I suspect you would have done it but we
can take it offline maybe do on the
board and figure out why that would
would not work okay again so again for
this one I don't think anybody does this
other than us because if you're doing
Delta store and if it doesn't store
would do the same thing but he was doing
newest to oldest with a delta store then
this doesn't buy you anything because
you do store in the in the the header
for that tube other things been deleted
yes but that was his state question is
like what about his update the end
timestamp would that be enough to denote
that it was deleted I start to have a
flag somewhere that said the thing was
deleted right but he it's it you need it
end timestamp to represent that there
was a special delete like maybe put you
take the first bit and had that
represent it was deleted you can do that
the I just put an end timestamp in there
I don't know whether that's a delete or
not or whether it's actually a new
version
yeah yeah okay alright so alright let's
now talk about different design
decisions so I wanted this part wasn't
in the paper but I want to talk about
how we actually do clean up keys from
indexes and then the there's only really
two papers on garbage collection for
MVCC systems I had you read the guy's
the one from hyper which actually just
came out a few months ago there's
another paper from 2016 that I had the
students read last year from the SA P
team they're not but they're they're
both okay papers the what I don't like
is that they sort of define the same
define the same concepts but using
different terms like I think like the
hyper guys calls things like precision
and frequency but they you know these
guys called like identification and
things like that like so the concepts at
a high level are the same just the the
the nomenclature they're using to
describe these things will be slightly
different so I'm a mix up as we go along
some bit some Hana the hotter paper and
the hyper paper but hopefully it should
all sort of make sense so let's talk
about how we're gonna track versions the
frequency which we invoke the carbon
Scotch and the granularity we're going
to look at potential versions we can
remove and had a compare of whether it's
okay to put in them or not okay all
right so four indexes again what's gonna
happen is that as my transaction runs
and I'm creating new you know I'm
creating new tuples and putting new
versions I have to store that in an
index because now if I try to go back
and read that same thing that I just
wrote I want to be able to go through
the index and see my own rights if
you're doing OCC was a private workspace
you don't do this cuz you staged all the
rights at the end but the what we've
been talking about is doing the
timestamp ordering approach where you
apply the rights in that in that global
space because that allows you to do
spected reads for other transactions
that are ahead of you in in sort of
logical time so now the problems going
to be is that if i need to abort or if i
need to go clean up versions i need to
make sure that i remove any keys that
correspond to older versions that that I
need to remove right
so the way any basically do this is that
wall transactions running and it's
updating the indexes we just need to
record you know what keys did we insert
or do we do ease to be invalidate from
our index because we're making changes
and then when we go to commit or a
border transaction we have to have the
garbage collector kick in and say
alright well let me go clean up the let
me go clean up the the the indexes
because these are things that people
shouldn't see right so the way hyper got
around this was anytime you would you
modify an attribute that's indexed then
you treat that as a delete followed by
an insert for that for that transaction
because then you don't have to worry
about going and finding the key and
updating the pointer right you just say
this here's the old version from the key
and the index you remove it they let me
insert a new one so we did not do this
in in peloton we did something really
really stupid like we're totally stupid
I don't know why this is one of those
things were like the student did it this
way because it because it looked like it
made performance go better for our
benchmarks and it wasn't till with like
later on we're like oh we gotta go
modify this to could fix some things
like oh my gosh they did something bad
we shouldn't have done this right so
here's what we did in Palestine so again
we were doing append only oldest to
newest that true yes and what would
happen is if I have a transaction comes
along and say they update a right and we
set this key now to 22 well I would do
an append only a pendant new to point to
my tablespace but then I would add a new
entry in my index to say for for key 20
- 2 - here's the version of it so even
though logically they're the same tuple
from the indexes perspective they look
like separate things
alright so then we got into trouble was
way if you try to update the same key
again on the same tuple instead of
making a new entry in the index we would
actually go and overwrite the the
previous version that we created so in
this case here I would replace 2 - 2
with now 33 our 3 3 3 and then now I
would also have update my index and
point to it as well and I kept doing
this every single time I did an update
right so this that's it two four four
and I have an update entry to point two
here so now the problem is when we go
ahead and and how to abort this
transaction we had no idea what was the
other you know 2:00 to 2:30 3:00 that we
inserted and so we could go delete 4 4 4
because we know this is the version we
need to clean up because that's what
we're seeing in you know you know dirty
table space or dirty dirty tuple list
for our transaction but we had no idea
that we've left there's other keys
inside here so we would run this for a
while run some benchmarks and all sudden
you'd get it was a unique index you
would get back an error and say that a
key already existed even though the
digits in the table because we were
leaking these keys from you know from
aborted transactions so you know this is
embarrassing this is stupid you know
this is not really anything specific
about you know paper you guys read this
is just showing that like it's hard to
get these things right even if you have
the best intentions and just not keeping
track of all the keys that you updated
as you know or all the case you you
modify in the index as you're going
along can end up end up losing things so
again we don't do this anymore
this is good ok so let's talk about now
how we're actually going to keep find a
keep track of the versions that
transactions are gonna create there's a
typo here sorry so the the first
approach we sort of talked about we
first talked to these two in the first
lecture
MVCC right this is where we just have
some mechanism where a transaction
threads or a separate garbage touchin
thread can go through our tables and
identify versions that we need to prune
up right the background vacuuming was it
was a separate thread the proper
cleaning technique was where the
transactions or the queries as they were
running if they noticed they had a
version that was not visible to any
transaction then they would go ahead and
clean that so hackathon did this because
they were doing oldest to newest so as
transactions ran and had to traverse the
virgin chain to get to the newest
version along the way they would see a
bunch of old versions that they knew
were reclaim a bowl and they'd go ahead
and remove them
there all right the transaction level
approach is what we used to do in
peloton and this is where transactions
would keep track of all the versions
that they created and then when they
commit they handed off this information
to the garbage collector who then had a
view on what transactions are running
what are their time stamps okay and
excuse me and they can identify which
which you know which versions that were
invalidated by these transactions are
now are now printable the last approach
is an epoch based approach and this is
basically the same thing as transaction
level the idea here is you're gonna ask
you a bunch of transactions and and not
as a batch meeting all exact same time
but you put them under this the same
epoch and this will make well we'll see
this again on Monday when we talk about
the beta retreat but basically it's like
this other counter that's always going
for at a time and we would know that
when we go from one epoch to the next we
would know whether there's any
transactions that could still be seeing
something in the previous epoch and then
if not then we know that anything that
was that was invalidated in that epoch
can be reclaimed well seem again this
more we'll see more about seed this
approach or technique used in the the
beat of a tree on Monday when you read
that paper all right so let's had to be
the verge of tracking at the transaction
level again so my transaction comes
along it's time Sam 10 I'll do an update
on a I create a new version right and
then now because I know that I had this
was the the version that the latest
version that I saw and then I created my
new version so therefore I know for this
transaction a 2 is now potentially
reclaim below so if my transaction
commits then I know I can go ahead and
clean up a two sides record that in my
transaction local space for my old
versions and this is just a pointer to
this location here and this can work
these pointers can use these pointers
because we're not gonna end up we're not
moving this thing around right we're not
doing compaction where we can be moving
it from one block to nuts we just say
that this thing has to stay there now I
do a an update on B same thing I had the
old version that I know that I created I
create my new version after the previous
old version I update that now in my old
version list then when my transaction
goes ahead and commit
I just pass this information along to
the garbage collector we then look at
and say well the commit time stamp for
this is 15 so I know for these versions
here anybody that's less than 15 its
highest time stamp less than 15 should
be able to see them right so if now
there is no transaction that has a time
stamp less than 15 but I know that these
versions are removable
I say this is called I think the the
low-water mark of high-water mark in the
paper basically IDs need to know for for
these tuples what's the lowest time
stamp I could have where someone could
actually still see this so if no
transaction has something below that
time stamp then I can remove it yes yes
this question is if I have another
transaction that's running that has a
begin time stamp of what you can't cuz
this guy already has ten so nine okay so
he comes along and he's gonna read a he
would read this one right because nine
is it isn't in between 1 and 15 right so
yeah he read a - you know so again the
garbage doctor knows like it knows what
other it has you have to know what
transactions are running so in the hypo
favorite they talk about how the hell is
this linked list that's sort of my
transaction ID and you can just look at
the head or a depend what order is to
find out what the lowest one is that's
like that's both the low-water mark or
the high more depending what you're
looking at and the idea is that I know
which ones actually running so if
there's a transaction that's running
with timestamp 9 then 9 is less than 15
so therefore it could potentially still
read these things and therefore I can't
reclaim them it may never read B but I
don't know that because I don't know
what the transaction is actually going
to do so I have to be conservative and
lead everything you know leave it around
correct like and again you could use the
the sorted linked list that the hyper
does you could just record a single
value there are different ways I did it
okay
so the next question is how often are we
going to invoke the garbage collector
and again is this trade-off between if
we're very aggressive in our garbage
collection then yes we can go free up
space as quickly as possible assuming
there's not transactions that are you
know sitting around the long time stamps
but the issue is going to be will
reclaim space more quickly but now we
could be end up slowing down
transactions because now the garbage
collection threads if it's running in a
background set up they start using CPU
and that's gonna eat up cycles and make
your queries and transactions run slower
and obviously if we're - we're less
aggressive and run this and - and
frequently and now we're gonna have the
size the database is gonna get larger
because we're not reclaiming versions as
quickly as we maybe should the Virgin
chains could potentially get longer and
that means that it takes longer for
queries to go find the exact version
that they want so if the delicate
balance between the two of these I
actually think the hyper approach is the
better one then the background garbage
collection so again so you run it
periodically you run it continuously
this is what hyper does this is what we
do that's what no systems do so periodic
eyes means that at some fixed interval
or within when some threshold was met
like if I have if I know I have 20% of
my memories being used by on ivory
claimable versions somehow I could
compute this then I kick off the garbage
clutter and go find things right sort of
the JVM sort of does a similar thing
look when you get you to your heap size
when it gets by a certain percentage
then it kicks off so this is just saying
that right again I'd run it in the
background thread and running it every
so often and for some systems like in
hackaton they can identify that if my
load or my churn rate for my versions is
really high then I can make this I can
run this more frequently the the the
hyper poach is that run is continuously
where the the garbage collection
procedures are just a part of the normal
transaction processing or query
execution steps right so in hyper they
did it own commit so any time a
transaction committed then they would
have that thread go through and see well
what can i reclaim what can i clean mop
cleanup
the the steam version in the in the
newer version of hyper this is doing
quick turn pretty oxygen so I call this
the same thing as cooperative query
execution part of cooperative cleaning
the wait saying wait hackathon does
where just add I'm running my queries if
I see things that I need to clean up let
me go ahead and clean them up
but because hyper is doing news to
oldest they don't have the dusty corner
problem that hackathon has where you
could have versions that are never
visited and they never get reclaimed
right if if you read it you'll see it
and you can reclaim it so I think I
would like to do this although the way
we're sort of our system is sort of set
up now our garbage collector is
integrated with this other bits or
background cleanup process that does a
bunch of other memory management things
so I don't think we can switch over to
this I think we're stuck with this but
again I like this better because it's
like alright well if I actually lot of
queries that do a lot of updates well
it's sort of as they put it
self-regulating because I'm creating a
lot of versions as I run queries those
queries will clean up the versions that
that are claimed old and if queries run
slower because I have a lot of versions
to reclaim well that's actually gonna
then end up slowing down the rate in
which I create old versions so I like
that model all right so now the question
is how we're going to organize in
internally the metadata for our garbage
collector to determine whether we can go
ahead and reclaim things right again and
now again there's more trade-offs
between whether we're gonna have sort of
fine grain tracking information to say
here's a single version that can be
claimed within this time stamp or
whether we can combine them together and
just to have a time stamp across
multiple tuples and that can amortize
the storage costs of the tracking
information for this in exchange for
maybe not reclaiming things as fast as
they possibly could be so this is just
anything I just said now right so single
version tracking would be for every
single tuple I know what their version
is and what their timestamps are and
then when the garbage car kicks off I
can make a decision at that point decide
whether it's a it's okay - can we claim
stuff so you get this sort of for free
if you're doing the continuous or
cooperative cleaning because as I scan
along and my
to try to find the version I want then I
would end up cleaning things up as I
find them and I'm already storing that
metadata anyway in the headers of the
tuples or the other records so it's not
like I need to sort the stuff separately
the group version is what I assured
before in that one example with the
vacuum thread and the idea is here as I
say here's a bunch of tuples that were
invalidated by a transaction at some
timestamp and so anything that less than
that timestamp any transaction has a
timestamp less and this could still
possibly see them otherwise they don't
alright
so again there's less overhead to track
things but it may delay the time in
which we can reclaim something and get
memory back so there's a third approach
that was in the Hana paper that you
didn't you guys didn't read but I think
the the hyper paper mentioned this where
you can actually do reclaim all the
versions from an entire table if you
know that there's no transaction running
right now and that could ever access it
so how does this work right because
remember I said here's one example like
there was it could be another
transaction at timestamp nine could it
read a it may read B but we don't know
because we don't know what queries that
transaction is going to execute but in
some cases if you execute your
transactions as prepared statements or
stored procedures then you know
potentially what all possible queries it
could ever execute like a prepared
statement is like a predefined function
that you can install in the database
system say that runs some logic for
transaction like and I'll have
invocations of queries so you can see
what all the queries are ahead of time
not always but sometimes you can if
everything is predetermines actions in
my system and if I know what queries
they could ever possibly execute then I
know what tables they're tough though
they will touch and I see that they are
that they're they can never touch a
particular table then I can go ahead and
reclaim all the versions for that entire
table without doing any you know fine
grained tracking in case a Hana they're
doing the time-travel storage so for a
given table all the versions are sitting
around and another you know another
tablespace so I did blow away that
entire time-travel storage space
without having to do any you know any
examination of their time stamps it's
basically doing like a drop table and
and creating it again which is super
fast again this is this is this is a as
I said a special case or a corner case
right if your transact if your
application is invoking a bunch of store
procedures then then you can do this
most systems do not cannot do this
though right and I don't think if you're
doing the Delta storage or the
append-only storage where the versions
are mixed together with regular tuples
or as Delta Records I don't think this
actually would work right this is sort
of a special case for for Hana assays
heaven alright the last thing we talk
about is how to determine whether
something is reclaimed right and ideally
what we want here is that in order for
our system to be scalable then we want
to be able to examine what are our
active transactions and what are the
reclaim old versions we can deal with
and we want to do this what I haven't
acquired any latches so this what I've
seen before in the hyper paper they
maintain a latch free link list that I
can keep sort of pretty efficiently and
I can use that to figure out what are my
current transactions so an important
concept to understand too is that unlike
in when we're actually running the
queries under snapshot isolation where
we can't have any false positives or
false negatives right of missing data we
should actually see and somehow we miss
it and for garbage collection we
actually can be a bit loosey goosey here
and it's okay if we end up missing
something right so if my garbage specter
runs and at that exact same moment
another thread commits a transaction
with a bunch of tuples that are
reclaiming bunch of physical versions
that are reclaimed well and if you know
if I end up missing at the carpet I
should ended up missing that during its
path of the you know that current
current invocation who cares because the
next time I run around then I'll then
I'll be able to see it so we can use we
don't need to you know we don't need to
have you know super tight protection
over the critical sections of where and
we decide how to reclaim things it's
okay for us to maybe know something you
know at least once and the second time
around we'll see it
so this is now is the important part of
the the the one of the main
contributions of the hyper paper
although they did not invent this
interval stuff it actually comes from
the from the Hana paper but it basically
saying how are you going to determine
whether something is a claimant or not
so for this one for the time stamp this
is what they call a traditional garbage
collection in their paper this is just
gonna I know what the minimum time stamp
is for all my active transactions and
therefore anything less than then that
time stamp is not visible to any of
those active transactions and therefore
I can go ahead and we claim that the
interval approach is that is will be a
bit more bit more crafty and we can then
now look at ranges of time stamps and
identify if there's vert partisan
version change that are not visible at
all and instead of actually waiting for
to you know to take the oldest one out
first and sort of prune it along in time
stamp order we can actually excise out
that range that's not visible reconnect
the Virgin chain and things are things
are perfectly fine because everybody can
see whatever you know what they're
supposed to see so the tricky thing is
going to be is how do we identify these
ranges and how do we do the solid ation
of our virgin chain to remove those
invisible ranges so let's say now we
have a simple example like this we have
transaction one he's gonna read a right
transaction to is going to update a high
and so now we have an older version or a
one that we eventually think we're gonna
remove is this guy who goes has and
commits which it does at twenty five so
now we have another transaction comes
along updates 30 and then commits it 35
it's not at this point here a two is
reclaim Abul because the only other
transaction running is is the first guy
here he's at timestamp 10 so he can
never see 25 or 35 he can't see this a3
either but under snaps isolation he's
not he's not allowed to so we had this
guy here that we need to go ahead and
remove so if we're doing the timestamp
comparison then our garbage collector
can't remove a two because our high
watermark are that the low-water mark
the lowest timestamp of inaccurate
and is 10 therefore 25 is greater than
10 so we can't remove this but if we're
doing the interval based approach then
we can't reclaim this because the
timestamp 10 does not intersect with the
lifetime range of 25 and 35 for this
version 10 can never see this thing so
we go ahead and remove this so for this
approach if you're doing the pen only
storage this is easy to do because all I
have to do now is just update if I'm
going oldest to newest I can just update
the pointer for a1 and now point it to a
3 and then a 2 now is essentially
missing and I can go ahead and reclaim
it and because everything I need to
reconstruct the tuple just say what you
know what is the version of this tuple
at and Pickler timestamp it's contained
in the tuple itself because again a pen
only has all the attributes this is now
harder to do though if you're doing
deltal storage because you may not have
all the attributes so let's look at
example here so say I have one tuple
right that's a timestamp 60 and then I
have a long version chain like this so I
have now my first transaction he's
running at timestamp 15 so again I need
to see a versions of tuples as existed
from committed transactions at time stam
time-stamped 15 or less so I can read a
10 down here my other guy here he's he's
going to read anything above a 55 and
less so that means that this basic chunk
of tuples here are potentially reclaimed
not 50 but all these other ones are here
our reclaim a little but but now the
problem is because we're doing Delta
storage some of these have touching
attribute - some of these are touching
attribute one so when we do our
consolidation we sort of need to take a
union and of these different Delta
records and only have the latest version
or latest modification to a particular
attribute in our final compacted or
consolidated Delta record right so in
this case here I update attribute to 3
times 77 88 99 so when I create now my
consolidated version the latest version
of attribute - is 99 and therefore I can
discard these other Delta
here but this guy down here modified
attribute one so I need to know that in
order to understand you know understand
order to recreate the version this tuple
at timestamp 50 so I had to record that
in my record as well and then the
timestamp I'm gonna sign for this
consolidated Delta record will be the
max timestamp of what I consolidate
alright so again now if I could you know
if I come along this guy wants to read
15 at times to 15 he can still get to a
10 this guy wants to read a timestamp 55
he can still find this one and it will
have all the information for all the
Delta Records that occurred after
timestamp 50 here so now to install it
right well I have the point into that I
just do a compare and swap on the
version vector to now update it here
again first writer wins we're treating
this as this you know it's like an
update but it's like an internal update
so if somebody else comes up this
version vector why we're doing some
consolidation then we fail and have to
restart but let's say again it succeeds
so now my my version vector points to
this consolidated one and then I can
blow away the the rest of the version
chain yes your question is do I require
that these rep these things are
committed again under Delta storage
first writer wins the it's either this
is always going to be the committed
version if the version vector is null or
the latest committed version is the
first one everything else is already
committed as well right so it's not like
this is like an in-flight transaction
because nobody no one can create another
no two transactions can create Delta
records on the same same logical tuple
because the first guy would be able to
succeed yes sorry
yeah question is how do I actually do
the union of do the consolidation of
these Delta records so you would go back
in time he would say I know I have X
number attributes and so I need to make
sure that when I do my pass as soon as I
see sooner that I see all all the
attributes then I know that there's
nothing else that I would care about
that comes after this and therefore that
I you stop the process it because you
have to be able say these you follow the
Virgin chain and say this is what I'm
gonna reclaim but you don't need to
you're not up being the Delta record
with the new Dell record with that
information so we did this as a class
project last year trying to member why
it was tricky I think it's something in
the ordering of reclaiming verbal link
data that makes this challenging because
you would have like this is showing the
string embedded in the Delta record but
if it's a large string then it's a this
is actually a pointer to the variable
length pool and I think we got into
trouble of trying to get the order of
that correct but this would be something
we could potentially explore again the
semester the it really you know if you
sort of do this project
it would really force you to think
through like this verging information
and what are all the corner cases but
this is obviously an over
oversimplification of the of the problem
so okay yes
your question is for doing garbage
question on Delta records do we have to
do this consolidation or cap action
first and then we can clean some no big
so how would you know action one - if
say I remove thread one right all I care
about like if I know that nobody else
can read anything that comes after this
then they're always gonna read the
version up here I'm only doing this
consolidation because I know that this
guy here could read this I need to know
what was the version that came after
that right if I don't event if I'm I
don't need to do this interval
consolidation it's a it's a nice thing
to have but you don't need it for
correctness right because without it
although I without it I have to wait for
this guy to commit or B go away before I
can then prune everything else yes yes
yes so his question is do I really need
to consolidate this couldn't I just yep
remove these guys keep this one and
would that be enough yeah that would
actually still work - it would need the
morning no because I think it would what
are you saying is right so we're back
here so instead of consolidating into
this new guy I keep this and I can
remove these guys because those are
overwritten by this and all I do is now
update this pointer now to this that
would work oh yeah so - yes when I when
I scan I want to get back to see what
the cry version is yes yeah
yeah I don't like the paper covers like
even obviously to devise different
synthetic benchmarks to exercise your
different update patterns I don't know
what real work was actually do you know
say went one way is better than another
when we did this last year I think we
created a new Delta record and then the
tricky thing was you create the new
Delta record yeah the tricky thing is
yeah no matter this the issue was going
to be this these things are sitting in
the the each of the tougher records are
sitting in the in the thread-local
memory for the transactions that ran
them but then now the problem is gonna
be and it would be normally only the
thread would reclaim that memory but now
you have this consolidation thread in
the background wants to be able reclaim
things and you have to like take latches
on protect the memory space and it
actually made up things go slower I
don't know the exact details of we have
notes to know for okay alright so the
the next thing what the sort of finish
up with this discussion is in all these
examples it's sort of obvious that yes
reclaiming memory is a good idea right
we want to get you if it's we don't need
the data we should go ahead and free up
the space but now the question is what
do we actually do with that memory we
just freed up right because say I have a
I inserted billion tuples and then I
delete a billion tuples what should
happen I should I give back the OS that
the the memory for that 1 billion tuples
or should I give back some of it or just
keep it all myself I think it's actually
want to be in in the middle right I
think you'd want to keep some of it but
you do want to give some back right
because I people would end up thinking
their system is broken if I sort of
billion things and then delete a billion
things and the memory you should doesn't
go down all right so for the very length
data data pool we can always just reuse
the the memory spaces right because
we're essentially doing a bin packing
problem to find you know for every
single move you actually need to store
in a Berlin data pool we just find a
free slot and put it in there for the
fixed link data start slots it's a bit
more tricky because
if we start reusing the slots for tuples
you know as we need them as we claim
versions then that could end up causing
us the sort of the the temporal aspect
of the temporal dimension all of our
data is now sort of randomized so what I
mean at that so like say I have a I have
an application where most of the time
people touch the latest data being like
reddit or hacker news mostly will only
comment on the latest posts nobody goes
back five months ago I don't think even
let you and tries to update know write a
comment on a post when five months ago
so that means that now if if I am if I
ignore the multi version and stuff if as
I create new tuples for all these
comments on these articles the they're
approximately going to be located close
to each other and had the same time
because say I'm inserting a new comment
sort of going from chronologically
they're all gonna be related together or
close together in the same amount of
time since when they were created right
it's not like I'm gonna go try to insert
a comment from an article five months
ago and now that's interspersed with
with articles from from today and so the
reason why that matters is because in
ogv workloads the probability that your
tuple is going to be updated is depends
on the sort of the last time there's
access or when it was inserted so if my
my first version was inserted today the
probability I'm gonna update it is
higher today than it will be five months
from now because most the times you only
only update the the latest things so if
now within my blocks of data if they're
all roughly around the same you know
create at the same time write the
versions are created at the same time
then I know they're gonna have the same
probability that they're going to be
updated and therefore it potentially
invalidated and so therefore if I have
data that's from five months ago all in
one block I can now compress it make it
read only and not worry about having to
go uncompress it to update something and
then rerun the compression scheme all
over again does that make sense
like if data is located together they're
all create at the same time therefore
it's all gonna be updated with the same
probability then I can use compression
now to come to reduce the size of that
block of data
and not worry about having a rerun
compression later on so you don't wanna
compress the newer things you want to
press the older things because the older
things are gonna be read-only so this is
sort of the two issues if I if I reuse
the slot anyway that I want as I create
new versions and and we claim old
versions then in my physical layout of
memory it's going to be randomized like
some stuff will be new some stuff will
be old and now if I go to compress it if
there's some intermix with old new if I
compress that block of data then the
there's something in there that could be
updated and then I have to you know do
compression all over again so we lose
that temporal locality we could just
leave leave it alone and basically have
these slots unused these holes in these
that in the slots and this is bad
because and you know ya know how much of
holes and space that we can't we can't
use but we're still allocated that
memory so at some later point we have to
go back and do compaction and and sort
of consolidate multiple blocks with a
bunch of holes and you know combine them
together so they get we get better we
get better utilization and less
fragmentation there's a third approach
that's sort of tied to this like when
you do truncate the command truncate
truncate basically delete without a
where clause but you can special case
special case it because instead of
having to scan through and delete tuples
and basically examine them with without
a where clause and set them to delete
the easy way to do truncation is just to
drop table and then recreate it blow
away all the indexes blow away the table
space and is recreated and that way you
don't worry about any of this locality
information or look look howdy
attributes it's just stuff from scratch
all over again but truncate truncate is
a special case so now to do the
compaction that I was talking about yeah
sorry
the question is for the 5-month example
why am i assuming that i would not that
would compact them all together and not
delete them all together you can protect
you would do both so like there's some
websites where they only expose like the
last 90 days of data to you and
essentially they're doing like a TTL or
deleting data as it gets older in that
case like if all the data is in a block
as it has was created within the same
timestamp at the same time range when I
do that pruning the whole block gets
blown away and then I can recycle it it
was all intermixed then I end up
deleting some tuples that are five
months old and some other tuples that
are three months old they have to stay
now but now I have a bunch of holes yeah
again for compression assuming we want
to keep all their data compression is we
want we want a block of data that is
never going to be updated again we could
still do it if we need to we have to
support that but it's unlikely to be
updated so therefore we can use
heavyweight compression to reduce its
size and then if anybody tries update it
well we'll take care of it but we want
to avoid that so it's all the same size
it won't be updated again it's all Craig
round the same time it won't be updated
again in the future all right so go
patch it again it's basically ideas
we're finding these empty blocks start
blocks that have holes in them all right
this one's half-full this one's half
full rather than having to have full
blocks I can bind them together into one
full full block so ideally again this is
what I've seen before if the if the
tuples are likely be accessed together
in the same window time we want to put
them in the same block because when we
compress them you know the likelihood
that one of them we updated and the
other ones won't be will be low right
there's another technique we can talk
about later on the semester is like if
we now also know that this data is very
unlikely not only is it not likely to be
updated it's also unlikely to be read
then we can start shoving it out the
disk right and start saving memory space
we still keep track of some information
in memory so if you try to read it we'll
go fetch it from disk but you know it's
still but it's the primary location is I
don't dis and the idea here is that at
the beginning the semester I said like
we want to be in memory
toom everything's in memory and we can
run fast but this is sort of bringing
back the disk in an intelligent way and
say well some data can be shoved out
most of the time we're gonna be in
memory but if we ever spilled a disk we
can handle that I think we covered that
on the the second or last lecture nettie
again it's like we're not bringing back
our buffer pool because that's slow it's
just sort of secondary storage all right
so the three ways we can figure out how
to do what's compact right we can just
go look at the time stamp since the last
the two was last updated we already had
that information because we're storing
the begin timestamp for every single
tuple right and we just look at that and
say well these things are all roughly
around the same time so we go ahead and
use that to figure out that we can go
ahead and remove things all right sir
yeah consolidating up action the other
approach is to look at the last time it
was accessed right because in if a tuple
was accessed now at some timestamp Mauri
the more recent it was access that
likelihood to be accessed again in the
near future is greater than if it was
access a long time ago
I sort of it has a decay effect for this
one if you're doing timestamp ordering
the basic time stamp warning protocol
with a retime sample you're recording
every time the thing was read then you
can use that otherwise you have to
maintain some additional metadata maybe
a block level because it would be too
expensive to maintain the access
timestamp on a per pupil basis because
now everything will read is it gonna
turn into a write because you have to
update this this timestamp
a third approach which as far as I know
nobody actually does this but a bunch of
people want to do this is if you can
infer some information about what the
data actually how data is related to
each other across tables or within the
same table then you can then maybe
combine or come back together things
that are going to be access to together
more frequently in the same block
because then you can apply the same
compaction or compression scheme you
want on that so foreign key would be an
obvious example of this if I you know if
I have two tables that have a foreign
key then the likelihood that I'm going
to access the parent table and then
follow the foreign key and get good at
the child table it's very high so maybe
I want to put those guys together close
together in memory so I can do
compaction compression together or
another another exam I heard once was it
was an order processing system where
they wanted to keep everything in memory
but then shoved sub cold orders out to
disk but if the order status of this of
this of his record this order was was
marked as open which could be open for
months at some later point they're gonna
come and access it again so if I can
learn that if the order says equals open
keep it in memory or keep these
locations anything that order status
close got shoved off to another location
then I can I can do this kind of
optimizations okay all right in the sake
of time I think we already talked about
truncate write basically trunk a zit
delete without aware clause delete
everything run your garbage collection
once you know everything is is not
visible and then recreate the table so
we'll talk about this in a week or two
about transaction catalogs so the
catalog an is storing the metadata about
what tables exist what what attributes
or columns that they have so if your
catalog is transactional meaning if I
call drop table then anybody that has a
timestamp before my drop table
transaction can still see the table and
then once they're all gone I can reclaim
the space so if this is all
transactional then doing this doing this
this truncation approach is super easy
same thing actually with compaction
right compaction is what compaction is
taking two blocks and combining them
together we're just moving the physical
location of those tuples in those blocks
into a new location so it's like it's
like a it's like a delete followed by an
insert so if I can do that
transactionally then I don't worry about
any false negative false positives from
transactions that are running the same
time of run and compaction so in our
system our our catalog is entirely
transactional and it makes all this
stuff easy we just we just haven't done
all of it yet all right so to finish up
again the this is just more of the
classic trade-off we see in computer
science and in databases of storage
versus in compute so you believe more
aggressive in doing garbage collection
and reclaim more memory space but that's
going to slow down our transactions
right or we can let our virgins are all
versions accumulate and that could you
know save our computational cycles but
we're spending more memory or spending
the more storage space to handle this
right and so in talking with people that
are running MVC systems especially in
memory systems everybody is willing to
pay a penalty for performance
in exchange for reducing the memory
footprint anyone thinking sy what's more
expensive Ram
Rams more expensive not only more has to
buy also more excited to maintain you
have to pay energy for this so if I can
run my database a little bit slower but
use a lot less memory then I can you
know that can be a bit cost savings so
that's why I like the the hyper approach
in the paper you guys read from steam
because they're running the the garbage
collection as they're running queries
the queries run slower but they're
reclaiming things as soon as possible
and reducing the memory footprint okay
any questions what you see all right
tips are profile okay so I assuming I
don't know at some point you might have
covered this kind of information I don't
think 213 covers this but this is there
be a reoccurring theme throughout the
semester like alright we want to
determine whether our system is running
slow and then if it's slow if so why so
let's look a really simple example here
I have two functions foo and bar in my
program alright so I want to I want to
speed it up I want to figure out how to
get why these guys are running slower
and what can I do to figure out you know
how to make them faster so a really
stupid way to do this would be our naive
way to do this would be run our program
in in a debugger gdb or whatever lld be
for Apple and every so often we just hit
pause on the program look at the stack
trace figure out what function it's in
and has record that and he's every so
often to keep hitting pause and
according to information and then over
time I would have information about what
what function was being called the most
time it's stupid but it would work right
so let's say that I did this I got 10
called call stack samples and then 6 out
of the 10 times I did that pause and
looked they were in the function foo
right so we would know that basement
based on our measurements that roughly
60% of our time of our program was spent
in this foo function
now obviously the accuracy of this of
this calculation would increase the more
time I hit pause like
if I get like a little motor hit Paul's
over and over again I can automate this
I could get more samples and they have a
more you know more accurate measurement
right so now say most the time we're
running foo and so this should be our
target of what we should optimize first
right we have two functions foo and bar
we should optimize foo first because
most their time is being spent and math
so let's say now we're able to make foo
run two times faster what would be the
expected overall improvement of our
system who here's a scene on dolls law
before yeah lesson half okay so I'm
those laws a way to calculate what the
expect improvement will be if we know
what percentage of our program is spent
in a particular function or different
part of the code so if we make this
thing go two percent faster or sorry 2x
faster and we know that six percent of
time is spent foo then we can cut this
time in half
but we're still spending 4 percent of
our time in this in this function bar so
um does law gives us this nice formula
that would tell us the overall expected
speed-up based on our distribution of
the functions that we're invoking and
the speed-up we expect to get right we
run we plug in child the math and we'd
say that we would get at one point four
times improvement so even though I made
that function which is called the
majority of time 2x faster the overall
system speed-up is only one point for X
so we can use on those law as a way to
figure out when we look at our look at
our database system what are we spending
our time and how much effort is it going
to be to make that particular function
go faster and we can then do a
back-of-the-envelope calculation decide
what should be the improvement we check
to see I mean sometimes you just want to
do this I when you're doing your as
you're doing you know performance
profiling and development because if my
function is not like all that often then
I probably don't want to improve it but
all right it's not how many times its
call it has how much time I'm spending
in it so I can use that to figure out
what about sort of high poles in the
tent what are the what are the parts of
the system that we're spending most of
our time in and those are the things we
should target to improve it but as we
assess how to improve it we can use this
form to decide well I think I
getting to be 2x faster what is the real
benefit I'm gonna get them that answer
it's an old adage in systems you want to
avoid premature optimizations so yes
there might be a fancy new lock-free
algorithm we could use for some part of
the system all right that could be
better than what we have now but at that
part of the code is not executed that
often then we're just wasting our time
there's other things we should worry
about all right so now we need to figure
out how can we actually get this
information so my little example of
hitting pause over know again on my
keyboard is stupid right but there's
actually real tools that'll do this for
us so the two main ones that we're going
to focus on is Val grant and call grind
and perf so Val brine is it is a
heavyweight instrumentation and
framework that is basically going to
inject inject things into the binary as
it's running that allows it to collect
information about what part of the
system that it's in and so this will
make your program run slower but you
know this will be I mean Andy Childress
and otherwise you go too slow but like
this will get you show you the yeah this
will tell you we've seen at the code
level where you're spending your time
this will sort of say things at like a
Harvard level so perf is a way to get
out the low-level performance counters
from that enterprise zone x86 and record
things like how many cycles I'm spending
on like individual lines of assembly
instruction or code so both of these can
be used for different things this one
will give you lower level information
like cache misses
cycle counts whereas this one tells you
like instruction counts for for this
tell you interruptions counts because it
doesn't know how long it actually spent
in the CPU whereas purple give you give
you that so you actually wanna use both
but I'll give a demo of perf it's again
Val grind is actually a toolkit a bunch
of other things we can use mem check is
a way to check for memory errors this
thing what this is what the original
version of valgrind was this is check
for things like if you if you have
memory leaks and things like that it'll
find those things we use address
sanitizers as part of clang or GCC from
Google and it's a more lightweight of
identifying these things call grind it
will show you where you're spending your
time in the source code and then
massif is a way to show you sort of
within the total heap space of the
address space of your process what parts
of the the you know of the program is
allocating the most amount of memory and
obviously for us the database portion
will always be larger the largest but
within that we can drill down and say
like how much time or you know how much
space were spending for the data
structures to keep track of things and
indexes and other stuff right when we
when we first build to be Debbie tree
it was allocated memory when he turned
the thing on and when he looked at
massive like even though you put zero
data in to the table the it would show
this huge block of memory being spent
for the be Debbie tree because it
allocated a mapping table for no reason
without actually using it yet all right
so let's see how to use call rent so for
call grind I I think you need to have
root privileges because your
instrumenting the binary and so you're
gonna use this on the command line for
this one I'm there's a instructions on
the wiki how to compile in release mode
without asserts but maintain the debug
symbols so that when you look at the the
trace in call grind or cake a shrine
it'll show you like here's the source
code or here you know here's the
function call here's the line number in
the source code that maintains
information so this compiling under this
mode will maintain all that simple
information without all the extra
asserts that'll slow the system down so
it'll be close as you can get to
actually running the written the real
system the other thing too is here this
is a I push this to the project one
branch last night but now you can pass
in through an environment variable how
many threads you want to run the
benchmark with so by default if you just
run slot iterator benchmark it'll give
you one thread you can set this to say
how many how many threads you want to
use remember for identifying what the
bottleneck is it won't show up if you
have one thread it'll show up when you
have more threads right it'll be really
obvious if you want to run with a higher
thread count and so so you run this for
a bit and then it'll spit out this call
grind file and then there's tools like
cake a shrine that'll give you a nice
visualization and break down a what
calling one so this is actually from the
benchmark that we gave students last
year but the the high-level idea is the
same so in here you can see the
community distribution time where it's
sort of at the top of the call stack
within
in the system you know what percentage
of the time you're spending in these
different function calls and then this
is a nice call graph view that you can
drill down and say well for this
function it invoked this function you
know a million times but I sent zero
point three four percent of my total
time in this but I spent nine percent
here but I go to nine million times so
you can drill down and see like what
function I'm actually spending the most
time on right but again this is showing
you this is like invocations and just in
wall clock time it's not gonna show you
the cycle count which is gonna be useful
as well all right so perfect and that's
collecting the low level performance
counters that form from Linux that the
exit eights provides you I think Mac
just to work I think it should I don't
know max I haven't try it but this just
don't work if it doesn't we'll figure
something out all right so basically
there's a bunch of different things you
vent you can collect from the from the
hardware about your process that's
running and then you can set how how
often you want to sample I say this is
gonna sample every two thousand
occurrences of the event and then as you
run it's gonna record this in this
perfect data file that gets generated
when you when you know after your
program runs so for this one this one
you definitely have to run under root
permissions because you're asking at low
level hardware get these Harvard
counters and there's something that the
OS nomen doesn't provide you because you
can do it for any any process that's
running right so basically what happens
is like there's the internal counters
and the hardware and then when they go
to a certain amount right based on the
the event counter then it records a
sample right and it contains all the
information about about the individual
lines of code and actually at the
Assembly level of what called what again
you want to compile this with release
mode with debug symbols so that when you
look at the per file put it'll show you
the actual lines of code yes
I eat it what will happen is if you run
it a little weak and do a demo if you
have time on a lower core count what the
bottleneck is may not appear because
everyone's not hitting it on the higher
core count it definitely shows up and
it'd be really obvious you can try it on
your laptop first coming up I'll show
you right now I should what it is it's
not none it's a lash right it's not not
a mystery right and what Indus INR yes
yes right so anyway so you run this if
you run perf I think I tried this this
morning if you run with a higher core
account a higher thread count it takes a
long time and then the benchmark won't
even finish and the file is like 10 gigs
so you I'll show you you can kill it off
early and then there's nice third-party
visualization tools I call it hot spot
it's for the Linux I don't know if it
works on a Mac that I'll give you like
flame graphs and show you things that
are more that are a bit easier to read
then like the perf tool but let me give
you a quick demo right so I say this is
again I compiled this with debug info
this is just H top at the bottom this is
the machine we have in the lab with 40
cores so I've already set the
environment variable actually I did not
do that I mean low back answer
so again I'm setting the environment
variable Terrier benchmark threads to 16
and that'll guarantee that that I'll
make it run with 16 threats so again
here I'm not gonna run the slop I'm
gonna run perf the salaat iterate
benchmark I'm gonna record cycle counts
and I don't collect samples every 2,000
and then just biz just the binary that
I'm gonna run right and then this is
just showing me at the bottom right that
shot that I'm using I'm using 16 cores
as expected right so again I'm maxing
out at 100% because there's a bottleneck
in their system where they're trying to
do something over and over again but
they're not actually getting making
forward progress they're not actually
getting worked on so even though it
looks like my utilization is fantastic
it's actually crap because it's I'm
stuck on this bottleneck so again this
could run forever run for a long time
and and take a while so you go control-c
and kill it it'll tell you how many
times that it it got woken up for some
data and then the perf trace was 32
Meg's again from only one a few seconds
it got to 32 Meg's so now I can run I
can run perf report actually here so in
in my directory it'll generate this perf
data file right so after you run perf
it'll spit that out so if I run perf
report again you have to be root for
this right it'll process the file and
then give you a give you a list of where
you're spending all your time for in
your program and because again I ran
with debug symbols on I can see
everything so lo and behold I look at
the very top for the slot iterative
benchmark I'm spending 48 49 percent of
my time in some function here and then
45 percent of my time they look function
here so the rest is just where it
actually did work so this is this is
obviously the bottleneck so what you can
do is you can Joe down purpose a nice
tool you can drill down into this you
say annotate the slot 8 or a plus plus
operator and then now I see source code
and then I can drill down see that I'm
spending 94% of my time for this
function in this test operator and
because what am i doing I'm trying to
try and acquire a spin latch so I'm
spinning on this latch trying to acquire
it and that's why I spent 94%
time on that right that's the bottleneck
and I can go back I think is escape and
see the other one annotate now spending
91% of my time on the same the same spin
match TVB is thread building blocks this
is the library we use some Intel to
provide us the spin match it's actually
a pretty good imitation but again it's
like anything like if you use it
incorrectly you're gonna have problems
so even though it's a great
implementation of a spin latch if you
have it a knack attention point it's
gonna be slow okay so I was sending out
a link there's this great video it's
like an hour long about how to use perf
bit further again this is the same thing
showed you there's a nice tools that'll
give you flame graphs like this but for
this one it's pretty obvious okay and
there's much of other events you can get
back bunch of links here alright so next
class will pick up on indexes we'll
spend a little time beginning talk about
tea trees because they're perpetuating
from a historical perspective well spend
most of our time talking about a lat
tree indexed ahead and the BW tree from
Microsoft and then we'll talk about how
to new version latching for B plus trees
okay any questions thank it in the side
park what is this
[Music]
here called the whole it cuz I'm og ice
you down with the test team hi you look
and it was go grab me a forty just to
get my buzz song cuz I needed just a
little more kick like a fish after just
one slip put it to my lips and rip the
top off April does a nice hot dog and my
heart will be to say I've diced you take
a sake to the prey