[Music]
[Applause]
today we thought that Constitution and
as I said compilation and QWERTY
compilation from glass class and vectors
vectorization are sort of the two main
methods we can apply in a modern
database system to improve query
performance so I'm gonna first start
talk about what vector a vector ization
is what however actually gonna use Sim D
and then the paper you guys were signed
to read was this sort of recipe book or
guide from these the guys at Columbia on
how to take sort of classic database
algorithms to do various things we need
in Saturday to system and implement them
using the Cindy and I like it because
again it covers like you know all the
various things would actually need in a
database system to run analytical
queries the spoiler would be is that
I'll just say upfront that none of it
actually works with some exception
because they're gonna make this big
assumption about their operating
environment which I'll cover when we get
to that and then we'll finish up talking
about project three topics okay all
right so vectorization is the process or
the the method we're going to apply in
our database system to take an algorithm
that was originally implemented assuming
scale or operations and we're you're
gonna take you know one piece of data
and apply one change or modification or
operation to it and the I and then we're
gonna convert that to now being able to
take a vector of data items whether
they're tuple values tuple pointers
it depends on the algorithm and then now
we can invoke a simpie instruction that
it's gonna allow us to apply the same
modification apply the same operation on
those vector of items within a single
instruction right and so we'll see this
though it's not always going to be there
are there is some prep work where we
have to put things into these special
registers and then apply to vectorize
instruction so it's not like we
magically magically can make anything in
our code become vectorize so again the
paper you guys that we're reading was
about how to take very specialized or
take very specific algorithms or
components of the dating system
and and being able to run them in
parallel so it's sort of obvious why
we'd want to do this right because now
we can do more work with your
instructions but one of the big
advantages we're also going to get from
this is that this is gonna be
independent of all the things we talked
about before we when we talk about
parallel query processing because that
was all about how to take a query or
whatever you wanted in our database
system and divide the world cup across
multiple threads now we're saying in
this lecture here how do we take a
single thread and make what it's doing
actually being run in parallel right and
again the speed up you can get
potentially is massive because its
multiplicative right so say I have a
Algrim that I can run on 32 cores at 32
threads so I get a 32x speed-up if I do
a fight you know if I paralyze that but
then now if I'm doing vectorization from
what the work each thread is actually
doing and say I have a four-lane Cindy
register meaning for a piece of work I
can run I can operate on four data items
in parallel with one seen the
instruction so now I'm gonna get also 4x
speed up there so 32 times 4 is 128 so
potentially I could go from a single
threaded scalar implementation of an
algorithm to something that I can run
with 128 2128 X speed-up
now the problems gonna be as as I said
to him earlier before class started we
are never ever gonna cheat thee that the
maximum speed-up like this is our upper
bound and we'll see what why when we go
along again as we have a pair of things
get in registers and out of registers
why we're never actually going to either
cheapest but like this is a good target
this is something that we definitely
want to achieve or try to treat to
achieve so who here is taken in 16 for
18 all right little a little over 1/2
all right who here has never seen Cindy
before ok that's fine all right
so Cindy is a as the classes heap
instructions that the processor is gonna
provide for us that allows us to came to
do these vectorized operations if we do
trash this with sisty which is single
structure and single data a data item
Cindy is going to be single instruction
multiple data items together and this is
sort of
this notion of Cindy versus sisty comes
from flynn's taxonomy of parallel
databases or started parallel systems
from like the 1960s and so every
instruction set for every CPU nowadays
is gonna have and support for Cindy
operations just the name of what they're
gonna call the class of these extensions
or instructions is gonna be different
paper you guys read us all about Intel
stuff and in their world it's SSE or ADX
and paper you guys were deemed favored
it's 2015 I think so they were dealing
with avx2
which is 250 256-bit registers the state
of the art now is 200 and sorry 512 12
bits power from IBM has this thing
called altivec arm has their thing
called neon and then a few years ago the
action proposed something called SPE the
scalable vector instructions
so what's guy should be really cool
about this and I don't know if anybody
actually implements this yet is the way
these they sort of set up the
instructions is that they're not gonna
be specific to any register size meaning
they'll have a sort of a sort of generic
class of vectorized instructions and
then depending on how it's implemented
in the actual CPU you you can then
operate on like you know 1024 bits or
512 bits at a time right when all this
Intel stuff like avx2 or instructions to
do 256 bit simply instructions then 512
soar 5 in 12a and you can't just like
you you can't just take these run it on
a newer CPU and think you're gonna run
on these ones you have to rewrite your
your code to actually be aware that I'm
running on a larger larger size
registers so let's look at a really
simple example of a simpie operation so
say we have two vectors x and y and we
just want to add together the elements
of X with the elements of Y at each each
all set so the way we would implement
this you know in intro to CS class range
or database class it's just we have a
for loop where we know the size of the
vector assuming the same size and then
for every element X and the
corresponding element of Y we add them
together and we write them into to the
output vector Z and so the way we would
this would get implemented or executed
with sisty instructions is just again
taking the for loop ripping through and
taking you know one element from x one
from why invoking one instruction to do
that do the addition and then writing it
to a upper buffer now with Cindy what we
can do is we're gonna take a vector of
elements from these two arrays and then
combine them together in a single
register and then invoke one cindy
instruction to add them together and
print and produce our output buffer all
right so we're gonna take four elements
here so we would say this is a 4-lane
register and assuming we have 32-bit
integers we'll say this is a 128-bit
Simbi register so once we populate this
register we then invoke the simpie
instruction on those two registers and
then it's gonna write out some output
result to another cindy register that's
going to be the same size do the same
thing for the next four elements evoke
the sim D and now we produce our output
yes this question is this question is
loading into a cindy register just as
fast is loading into a like a regular
you know single data item right sure it
depends on where the data is located
like if you're doing that selectively
store thing we talked about that Stefan
can be slower is Miss pans multiple
cache lines it's more work I think the
way I think the way x86 works is you can
only do one or two loads and stores per
cycle so if this thing's really wide you
may have to do multiple loads and like
across multiple cycles whereas like
writing one thing into the to a single
data register is super fast and that's
what I'm saying you're never going to
achieve the theoretical maximum speed-up
just because there's there's overhead of
putting things in here right but
certainly in the case of this you know
it this would be a really good trade-off
because we went from eight instructions
to do it to do the addition to two two
instructions that probably give me a win
for us yes
so this question is if we go to 512-bit
registers in avx-512 that's going to hit
our cache line limit does that mean now
the loads into it are gonna be more
expensive and they started the stores
getting the data out with that and it'd
be more expensive than this because I
can't beat the spammable cache lines if
you're not if you say if you're not
cache a line yet like depends where this
data is also like think of this is like
this is hanging out in l1 so l1 is in
Exodus 32 kilobytes so we could take all
the data you want to store and keep that
in l1 and then it's not like we're going
out then then when you go get it all
right all right so what can we do with
Cindy well I showed some basic
arithmetic operators and again under the
at least for x86 for the sve I think
they start the same issue like like the
register side the size of the register
will be will be fixed but like it
doesn't necessarily mean that the the
size of the Lane has to be fixed so my
example here I had at 128 bits and
therefore I had a simile instruction
that could take 4 integers and add them
together but if I had 16-bit integers
there might be another instruction they
provide to know how to take eight 16-bit
integers and add them together right so
typically the way you when you when you
write Sindhi code you specify like I
know what what with the data type sizes
that I'm operating on we talked about
how to move data in and out and then
there's all these logical instructions
to do comparisons on you know a bit
manipulation we can do comparison
instructions and that will need this to
do predicates to say we know whether
something equals something in our where
clause shuffle instructions is the
ability to take the output of or take
one sim you register and write it into
another simony register all right and
this is give me a big win for us cuz now
we don't have to take the output put it
in l1 and then write it back out into
another register we know directly from
one register to the next and then the
other random things like we'll see in a
second like the the take the data that's
sitting in l1 and then
revert it into the form that the same
deregister ones or if now we have
something in our simply register maybe
we want to write it out to memory but we
don't want to pollute our CPU cache so
these these these streaming instructions
allow us to take the output directly
from this Indy register and put it put
it right into memory without going
through the normal cash in hierarchy all
right so the Bay I main idea what we're
trying to achieve here is by having all
these different instructions you know we
can try to do it as pack as much useful
data we want into our semi instructions
and do as much processing as we can all
in that data while that they're in our
semi registers before we have to go
shove it out into memory right and these
like especially this these these
conversion up or so that the shuffling
operators this is gonna allow us to do
this will change some operations
together you never have to touch CPU
cache and then we can produce the
results that we want right because last
one here is also super important to
because especially for joins like if I
know that I'm doing the join the tuple
matches but there's a pipeline breaker
above me and I can't I can't do anything
with the output of the join I could then
shove it out the memory because I know
I'm not gonna need it again until I come
back and go to the next pipeline so this
these streaming functions allowed me
your streaming instructions allow me to
like use the data that's in the seamy
red shirt and then you know put it out
into memory before going back to it
alright so we'll see after this after
the spring break and after the the
project proposals next class how we can
use some of these techniques and in our
joint operation as well yes the question
is these these seeming structure
streaming structures sound very nice are
they available for non non semi
operations yes I think so I yes I think
if you streaming writes I think that's
what they're called in in x86 yeah ok so
again we're going to focus on x86
because that's the dominant CPU
architecture and this is just showing
you a history of over time how the the
Intel is expand this of course
poor for for you know for Cindy the very
beginning it was called MMX and this was
like it's like super primitive but this
is like I got a Pentium 3 days or
pending two days until we have this big
marketing pitch about hubby's I think
MMX actually didn't stand for anything
Intel's afraid of getting sued so like
they just took three letters put it
together I think now people think of
these as like multimedia extensions but
at the time I think there was a lawsuit
where someone claimed that an intel
stole their MMX name from some other
company but then they found all this
internal documentation that showed like
oh it's three land random letters it
means nothing all right
today I lost that lawsuit but it very
beginning was super permanent right it
could only do some basic operations on
32 or 16-bit integers and this early
version as well it would it would be
this the the CPU wouldn't be normally
executing system instructions but then
when you executed assembly instructions
you had to pause the syste stuff do the
sim D and then start back up the the
sistine after that after MMX when SSE
came out then you can actually do these
in parallel that's what I was saying
before about how with an atom or a tall
order CPU architecture we can have
different parts of the CPU doing
different things at the same time right
you could have executing some similar
instructions on on the city registers
what while we do you know stuff on
regular CP registers what's the MMX you
couldn't do that and in the modern era
it started when AVX came out I don't
think there's any I think this was just
a naming change because they went from
120 bits to 256 bits and then instead of
calling this a vx5 which would make
sense when they called a bx 2 or a VX
whatever like they call it 512 and i've
looked online and as far as I can tell
they have no plans to put out 1024 bits
so this is sort of the where we're at
right right now
and this link here will take you to this
awesome video from the sky James randhir
who was a like a Sindhi designer or
evangelist at Intel and he basically
shows all the awesome things you can do
is Cindy not it's not a database person
it's just like it's showing you how to
actually flex the heart ring get the
best you know get the best bang for the
buck and I highly recommend this video
like it's I think it's like an hour so
long
all right so uh so there's me trade-offs
obviously using Cindy it seems like it's
a magical thing or we're not always want
to use and of course yes in some cases
we will see will get a significant
performance gains if we use them but the
tricky thing is gonna be is actually
implementing an algorithm to use
vectorized instructions is is not gonna
be trivial and as I said in some cases
it's actually gonna because in the
Columbia paper that make certain
assumptions about the environment in a
real database system their assumptions
don't hold and actually Cindy will hurt
you so what we'll cover what that is
okay and again this is this is the issue
we're gonna have of getting things in
and out of the registers are the reason
why we may not always get the speed-up
we we want to achieve okay so now part
of the reason why it's gonna be tricky
is that there's no magic flag and the
compiler that's gonna match take all our
database in from you know database
system all the source code and be able
to paralyze everything right for for
simple things maybe but for the more
complex things we're doing with the
process queries it's just not gonna
happen so again if we want to have
vectorization in our database system
people pay you know people pay you money
to go do this right because it's hard
let's see how we can actually achieve
this so the three ways are the automatic
vectorization from the compiler and then
we can then pass hints to the compiler
and tell us what what we actually want
and then there's also writing our source
code with explicit vectorization using
cpu intrinsics okay so the way to think
about this is like the easiest one to
use is the one at the top because that's
just hoping the compiler figures it out
the more in the bottom is the hardest to
use but we'll have complete control of
what's going into our registers what's
command what instructions were executing
so again easy to use that better better
control but harder to write okay all
right so automatic vectorization is just
saying that where the compiler can
identify when we have chunks of source
code that inside of a loop where the
kernel of the main operation inside that
loop could then be converted into a
vectorized instruction and so for free
loop's this is gonna be easy to do but
the problem is simple loops are not
going to be very common in the the main
thing we want to speed up which is query
execution all right
so in obviously this requires your
Harvard to have the support experience
in the instructions but pretty much
every you know every modern intelligent
net today whether you have 256 or 512
it's actually I don't know the laptops
have probably avx2 but any modern Xeon
you know you buy today will have 512 all
right so let's look an example here so
here we have a for loop here and this is
sort of like the the vector wise
primitives we talked about before where
they were going to have the predefined
source code to do the the basic
operations you would need to execute a
query to process you know process data
so what is this doing this is taking
three pointers x y&z the same thing we
showed in the very beginning and then
we're just going to iterate over every
element X and every element of Y and
write them to an alpha but buffer Z so
my question to you guys is is this
something the compiler can automatically
vectorize your shaking head yes why
what's that he's saying bleep own
rolling but that's not that's not but
that's not that's not in using Sindhi
instructions right so he said after you
loop yeah say yeah you would recognize I
have four lanes in the instruction or
send me registers so I unroll it four
times and then I and then you know then
I can vectorize that who agrees or
disagrees bingo that's it yes so it's
not legal to automatically vectorize
this because he's exactly right that you
don't know what these are at compile
time right and it may be the case that
these are actually pointing to the same
chunks of memory so now you have
unpredictable side effects of when you
actually start doing your computation
yes he said he could do global analysis
to prove that they're different
that's not a static you can't do that a
static statically at compile time you
knew that word sure you can run it and
go you can run your database system with
this function check it right and like
you may never see the case where these
are actually pointing to the same thing
but you don't know that because you
don't know you have you know nobody
you've seen all possible inputs to the
database system
yes you're basically claiming can you do
optimistic vectorization where the
compiler could insert some kind of magic
here
do the vectorized version or somehow do
some an analysis on what these guys are
and see whether this would have gotten
stomped on inside the vectorized version
and then if if if no go ahead and keep
my result if yes go back into the scalar
version I think tom is like well if you
pass like what you're saying so I'm just
showing this global variable but you'd
have to pass that in right to this to
this to this function so that you would
then know and then you have to know that
all right I'm gonna loop through from
zero to two max for each of these things
then check that yeah I that sounds like
a lot of work yes
if you do what sorry if he announce if
you know all possible inputs Haley's
analysis I let's let's talk with that
efforts III don't actually what you're
planning but I mean the really simple
issue is like if my if Z is just the off
the the memory location of X plus one
what's gonna happen here now I take X x
and y and I write that into Z but now
when I come back I'm clobbering for the
second loop now I'm clobbering the the
second element of X and that's gonna
produce completely incorrect results
right we want to be able to vectorize
this such that the output of the
vectorized version has been exactly the
same as the as the scalar version right
so reason why this is difficult to do
for a compiler the handle is it's just
the nature of how we write c c++ right
we're writing this code in a way
describing this algorithm with this
computation we want to do in in
sequential terms and write over one
element at a time take two numbers add
together right into this to this buffer
so that's again that's that's seeds are
sort of not set up to provide the
correct hints to the compiler to
recognize that they could do this you
have to do whatever he's proposed me to
do or the next things that I'm
describing the compiler wins okay
again the main takeaway from this is GCC
and clang are not gonna be able to
vectorize that much ICC from from Intel
their proprietary compiler is much more
better at this but even then in many
cases it's not gonna be it'll do because
it's not gonna know what's going on here
all right so what can we do against we
can provide compiler hints to tell the
compiler that we know that there's this
piece of code that's safe for it to
operate on in a vectorized manner right
and so the two basic ways we can do this
is either tell the compiler something up
that we know about the memory locations
that can we could be ever be passing
into this function or we just tell the
compiler hey you know to take you know
unbuckle your seat belt take the safety
off your gun like like just go buckwild
and do whatever you want I don't care
right so the first one is the restrict
keyword and
this is a flag we can add to in our C
code or sleep a pulse code that
basically says that we know that these
are distinct memory locations and
therefore it's safe for it to vectorize
and anything that comes below this so
this is in the C standard I don't know
whether it's I don't think it's in the
C++ standard but as far as you know as
I've tested before it's like GCC and
clang whoa
we'll handle this right so again it's
basically saying that we're allowing the
programmer to declare that these
pointers are will will never share the
same data or you know the same memory
locations and therefore anything that we
do under here will not have weird side
effects that was unexpected right but of
course it's gonna be up to us as the
programmer to make sure that we know
what we're doing when we when we tell it
hey don't check these things because you
know after it's already compiled then we
have no way to protect you know enforce
that the other approach are these -
these pragma hints and this is just
basically saying that within this
function you don't do any of those
memory checks this is like sort of a
more sort of brute force but a more
coarse grain definition that it's okay
to do vectorization here whereas in a
restrictive or you know it's more
fine-grain on individual elements right
so this one is saying IV depth saying
ignore vector vectorization dependencies
there's other ones I think other
languages like symbiote on Cindy off
okay
I don't know how I don't know how
portable this one is I think this might
be working for GCC I don't know what a
clang or ICC do something different
right or like we're using these other
like libraries like OpenMP they have
their own own Flags it's they're all
they're all I test be doing the same
thing all right okay
so again the main takeaway from this is
that we can we can tell the compiler we
can what we can do what it can do but
it's still all frosted the Davis
developers - to protect ourselves
the last one is through explicit
vectorization we're going to write the
exact same be instructions that we want
to execute and again we have to know
what the register size is we have to
know what the datatype are operating on
and then now there's there's no question
about what to actually do because these
intrinsics are essentially syntactic
sugar that the compiler replaces with
the exact
instruction to do whatever is ever asked
me to do the downside of intrinsic is
that they're not portable meaning if my
code if I compile I write all the x86
intrinsics but I'm not running now I'm
compiling my data system to arm they may
not support that or if I'm compiling my
code and it operates on the avx-512 and
then I try to compile it on a machine
that doesn't have those registers it's
gonna fail or it might actually replace
them with the scalar version of the
operation if it's nice and I may not get
into the vectorization that I'm
expecting so here's the here's the SSE
implementation of the actually this MMX
the EPI this is a Symbian tation of the
same same the same folder and then
adding together two vectors and now you
see what I have to do is there I have to
take my sort of C C++ vectors of numbers
and then convert them into the expected
sim deregister vectors right and then
this operation here is now doing the
addition or loading things in you're
just doing the addition on 32-bit
integers and then loading it into this
the simply vector here right
it's ugly the the double underscore is
is is what is how we do how these GCC
defines intrinsics I think clang does
the same thing and so you you can hide
this with like a library that has a
bunch of macro tricks to make you do
this but there's no sort of one vibrate
everyone uses you looking to get help
you see a lot of times you see explicit
instructions like this okay so for our
purposes in our own system and in the
company of you guys read they're gonna
do this explicit vector vectorization
because they won't have again
fine-grained control exactly what the
CPU is doing alright so now that we know
how to write Cindy instructions what are
the kind of Cindy operations we could to
do so the first thing we need to talk
about is like what direction are we
applying our vectorization so the
difference is horizontal versus vertical
so with horizontal the idea is that
we're gonna apply some operation on all
the elements together that are within a
single vector and then produce some some
single output or scalar output
so like say I want to take my register
has the number zero one two three and
then I can evoke a Sindhi horizontal
instruction that just takes all the
elements in my vector and then produce a
single scalar output that's the sum of
all of them so this one is only found in
the new instructions that support as his
SSE for and avx2 so that's roughly
2015-2016 anything or anything newer
than that should have it the next one is
the vertical one and the idea here is
that we're gonna take two vectors apply
some steam the instruction on them and
we're going to match up based on the
offsets when the in each vector so this
is offset 0 this is also 0 and then
we'll add them together and then we'll
write that out to offset 0 in our output
vector so the Columbia paper is gonna
kind of do everything based on this I
forget why they said they didn't do this
I think at the time I think they
actually the CP they looked on we didn't
have it all right
this once again this this is the more
common approach all right so now so
going forward we're gonna assume that we
have these intrinsics then we're gonna
do these divert the vertical
vectorization and now we want to do a
bunch of different things and our in our
in our database system to construct
primitive operations that are vectorized
and then we'll build up from those
primitives and do the more complex
things like the joins and the scans and
the other stuff that you would want na i
know you know what i have to do when you
process queries so again I like this
paper because it's just it's like
everything like here's all these
different techniques that we have
actually the source code implementations
I have you have you how you design all
these algorithms and data structures to
take advantage of vectorization all of
them we're not gonna need but I want to
cover like sort of the main the main
primitives ok so again I've already just
said this so this is all about how can
we can do primitive operations that are
vectorized then do more events
algorithms and functionality in our
database system the system they're gonna
run on is actually not a full-fledged
database system it's just like a little
testbed prototype that does you know
it's too
hand-coded to do the one operation that
they're trying to measure said means
there's no sequel parser there's new
transactions VOC query processing and it
also means that they're not going to
materialize the output in those cases
which oftentimes is is a big overhead in
in implementations the other big thing
and this is the big assumption that I
was saying before is that in their
operating environment they're gonna
assume that the database fits entirely
in the CPU cache that is not realistic
right because like l1 is like 32
kilobytes l3 is like maybe 64 megabytes
if you have a lot of money like there's
no database that's gonna fit you know
your CPU caches and what you'll see in
the next paper you read after the spring
break is that if everything now does not
fit in the CPU cache this Cindy stuff
actually doesn't doesn't matter at all
right unless you start doing the the the
relaxed operator fusion stuff that that
will read about next like how to
actually you know sort of stage your
operations so that you can operate on
vectors within your CPU caches and then
you can prefetch the next piece of the
next vector you're going to operate on
to hide that latency of the memory stall
and they're all they don't do any of
that it's just like everything's might
CPU cache let me rip through it very
quickly
okay the other big thing that they're
gonna have in their design decision for
their algorithms is that they want to
maximize the Lane utilization so that
for every single time you invoke an
instruction you're always doing useful
work for all the data items in your
vectors all right this will make more
sense when we talk about how they do the
hash table probing but the idea is that
I don't want to say I could put four
elements into my vector but only two of
them are I are one of them I actually
need you have the rest were actually
garbage I can throw away they want to
pack in all you know all unique data or
useful data and every single register
for every single instruction so that
they're maximizing the utilization all
right so let's start with the
fundamentals that they're gonna define
select a low slept of stores and then
the gather and scatter and then we'll
see how we can then use these to do the
scans and hash tables and and the
histograms okay so with selective load
the idea here is that we want to take
some
some some chunk of memory we have in our
in our l1 cache and then we want to
write them out to a register but we want
to provide this mask to tell us what
elements we actually want to store
because without this we do have to take
everything and write it out like all
continuously which means that if we only
want certain items
we'd have to copy it then you know and
in all in our CPU cache then align
things the way we want and then right
into our register so the idea is like we
can take a chunk of memory that has some
things we don't want and don't want
provide this mask and this tells us how
to populate the register all right so
again the lane is like this the mask
offset here corresponds to an offset and
the vector so the first thing we do is
look at the first element the mask the
bit is set to zero so we're gonna skip
what's what's in here right there's
nothing else we want to write out into
this Lane then we get into the one here
and that's gonna tell us at the first
offset that we've been writing into so
sort of thinking like this every time we
have a one there's some cursor here
that's gonna copy out what's in the
memory address of the memory location
and then when we move to the next bit if
there's another one we would move the
cursor over by one so even though this
is offset too or I'll offset one in our
vector we're starting at offset zero
from memory because we didn't knew we
didn't write anything for all set zero
so now this would get mapped into that
and we write it up in here and then the
same thing for the next one there's a
zero so we skip that now we have a 1 and
then the cursor moves over here for this
V and we write it to offset 3 up and up
in the vector right the Selective store
is the opposite of this as where we have
our vector and we want to take its
contents of its elements and write it
out to 2 to memory so again the lanes
match up just as before so we can start
here with a zero and this is saying we
don't want to copy anything then we get
here to the 1 and then it's gonna take
the same offset in the mass for the
offset and the vector then we're gonna
write it to the first location in memory
and then same thing for this skip from 0
the 1 then read it up there right so is
another this is another spoiler of this
of this paper is that
there are no Cindy instructions no Zeon
does not currently support doing this
like like with a single instruction it
has to be emulated doing other semi
operations and every year I always
google to see whether check out Google
to see whether select the stores like
this load has been implemented in in in
x86 and the only thing ever shows up or
free things either the Columbia paper
that describes that the technique my
slides from this class or people in
Korea or Wisconsin stole my slides and
talked about the same thing I will see
what they look like in a second um so
again and this means that you also know
you can't do this atomically this to be
multiple instructions to make this work
and the idea of what they're doing is
the reason why you'd actually want this
again is that I don't want to have to
you know take the chunk of memory and in
and copy things over over never again to
line at the way I want before I load it
and write and load it and take it out
ideally if I could do this in the single
struction that'd be great but it doesn't
exist all right the next is gonna be
this the the scatter and gather right so
with gather the idea is that again we
have our index vector that lines up with
our value vector and we want to take we
want to take elements that are in memory
and then write them out in two different
locations in in our vector right so
think of these as all set from zero to
five so when I look at this thing here
the index vector says at all set to
right which is here right it into the
first lane of my register then I get
here offset one take take you know take
offset one in memory write it out the to
the the the second lane or the first
lane anyone I'll say you're looking at
do this and so far for all the other
ones and again like I don't think
actually I think Xeon now supports both
of these the the selectively gather and
the selectively gather there's a
selectively gather and scatter so you
can do this it'll be a single
instruction but it won't be done in a
single cycle because again l1 can only
do a one or two loads and stores per
cycle so if I have a bunch of stuff that
if I'm populating a large register it
may took a bunch of cycles
laid it up using this technique yes I
know I I don't think Emily does I think
it actually supports this yeah
[Music]
could you use can you use selective
gathering to emulate the selective
loading store from last yeah yes I I
don't think that ketose like the paper
describes it but it's there's again the
main takeaway so it's not one
instruction like this is okay scatter
again is the opposite we're going to
take elements in an a register and then
write them out to different locations
here so for the first element here at
index vector to that I'm writing into
memory location too and I do the same
thing for everything else okay so I've
already said this law before the the
gather scatters are not really executed
parallel because we can only load so
many things in a single cycle the
gathers are only supported in the the
newer words since 2014 was when avx2
came out in the house well prior to that
it wasn't supportive and then again
these are you have to implement these or
emulate them using multiple multiple CPU
instructions okay all right so that's
good to forget stuff all right so we had
these printers now and let's talk about
how we do scans hash tables and your
partitioning for histograms the paper
also talks about how to you join sorting
and bloom filters I don't think of it I
don't whether they talk about how to do
cindy hash functions but we'll cover
that later too as well but we will cover
these after the spring break we'll talk
about how to do this in the part of the
radix partitioning hash join or the
photonic sorting techniques let me talk
about sort merge join so we'll cover
these in more detail after after spring
break and I think we'll also talk about
this but this one's pretty easy to
figure out as well okay so again
nothing's gonna work because they're
gonna soon well because assume
everything is to fit in CPU cache
they're also gonna make this other big
assumption I should mention this earlier
is that they're gonna operate there to
assume all their keys or 32 bits and all
their pointers to tuples are 32 bits
because again they're operating on 201
six bit registers and so for a key and
value pair that has to be 64 bits in a
real data in memory database system the
values are sorry the batteries are gonna
be the to post laws of the tuple
pointers those are gonna be 64 bits and
then keys are often not just gonna be
you know 32 or 64 bits
sometimes you can have a composite keys
and if you have those then then many of
these techniques don't work because now
you can't align things nicely in two
lanes in the semi register right all
right so let's how did you vector I
selected scans so we solved these two
examples before when we talked about
query processing this is how we can do a
branching version and a branchless
version of doing the scan right for the
branching version you have an if clause
will you check the predicate first and
then if it matches then you then you
copy the tuple and in the output buffer
and then the branch left version you
always copy it and then you then check
this you check it by using this you know
bitwise everything you know comparison
operations so it's not really a branch
and then based based on the output of
this comparison that tells you whether
you you increment the offset of the
output vector by 1 or 0 which then
determines whether if you come back
around you overwrite the last one you
you you cop it into because you don't
want it there all right and we solve
this this graph from the vector buys
people where the the branchless version
of the algorithm always has almost a
fixed cost because you're doing the same
amount of work no matter what the
selectivity is of the predicate and in
in the the branching case when you have
low selectivity or very high selectivity
then it'll do better than the branchless
one but in this middle part here you
know the the branch misprediction
penalty we're paying in our cpu becomes
higher and higher and therefore you know
there's cash dolls or the pipeline
flushes of having to you know undo our
mispredicted branch starts you know
comes a big bottleneck alright so in a
vectorized selection scan operation we
can't do the branching version because
there is no notion or no concept of if
clauses in our in our sending
structions so they're going to do a
vectorized branchless version so this is
a gross approximation of what the
algorithm is but now we're gonna scan
through our table and whereas before I
would get one back one tuple at a time
now I'm gonna get back a vector tuples
not saying what that with the register
size is whether it's four four elements
or sixteen elements or eight whatever it
doesn't matter we get a vector and then
we're gonna load the key we want to do a
comparison on again assuming we only
need to look at one key well load this
into a key vector and in Tsim deem and
you know this is just again syntactic
sugar this is not actually really really
how you to write this code there's no
cindy-lou function then we do our the
same comparison we did and the
branchless scan where we're doing the
bit manipulation to see whether we match
or not but then we're writing our mask
out of to our to our register here then
this is saying if the tuple at the
offset in our and our vector we got from
the table if that satisfies our
predicate and we set the one if it
doesn't satisfy a predicate it's set to
zero then now we take that mask and now
do the Select of a store to the copy the
tuples we want that match our match to
our predicate enter in our mask to our
output buffer and then we just take the
we take the cardinality of the number of
ones we have in our mask vector and that
tells us what our offset should be and
again there's more loop out there's more
work if you do outside the for look to
make sure that we don't keep around
things that didn't match in the last
iteration but I'm ignoring that for now
so again this would be a Sindhi load
this would be a Sindhi comparison
there's to be two instructions because
you have to the vector is greater than
equal to and the vector is less than
equal to but again that's just hanging
out in our Sidney registers that's not a
big deal and then this is a sim D store
to now take the the selective store mask
from Deb reproduce from this take our
two bolts I'm ready to our output buffer
and this will be sitting in memory yes
all set in the output buffer right so
here this sells again this is telling
but this we had this output buffer here
and we keep track of I in eyes where the
the starting location of where we should
write tuples that match
right it's actually easier to understand
if you go back to the the scalar version
right there we go
right so I equals zero I always copied
into the current offset I if the tuple
matches then this M flag will be set to
1 so therefore I want to keep whatever I
copied in here so I add add M to I which
is plus 1 so that when I come back
around now I'm writing at the next
offset and I'm not clobbering with the
last thing I copied in if this doesn't
match then 0 then I overwrite the next
time to come around because I didn't
wanna keep the last thing I wrote so in
the vectorized case this operation here
you want to count the number of ones you
have that's gonna tell us how to move
the offset forward and you can actually
do this there's a it's called the rank
instruction you can do this in the CPU
actually very efficiently if you take a
vector of things and say get count the
number ones in it that's a sort of
example of horizontal vectorization
alright so let's look let's look at a
real example of this
ok let's say now we replace our query
put in real values we want to find all
the matching tuples where the key is
greater than equal to 0 and the key is
less than the letter U so let's say now
our table looks like this right we have
the key Jo y su X and so the in order to
use comparison we're gonna first copy
this into our key vector right and
that's this this this step here then now
we do our sim to compare right and
that's this part here and we're gonna
bad our met but get out our mask and
this is gonna tell us which of these
keys actually matched and then now we
have this pre computed all set map right
this is just something we can predefined
and our source code at a time and this
is just saying the offset at at you know
the implicit offset here corresponds to
the offset 0 in memory right and up to
you know 1 2 3 4 5 so then now we use
this to do our sim D selective store and
that skin is what this is saying here if
I have a 1 here and I would know that
the offset I'm matching here should go
into the first location here so now
these are just offsets here so I'm
matching that like alright the tuple
that the vaquita match my cindy compare
at this offset can be found you know I'm
writing what that offset is so now and
then I gotta go back now and say whoa I
have offsets 134 if I need to
materialize the keys up above in my
micro plan tree I'll go back in here and
jump to that offset to copy out the
actual key right is this clear
so in my opinion this this is like the
most useful thing you'll probably get
out of this lecture in terms of like
here's something actually you can do in
in do something could we actually do
this now in our own system and the magic
is this offset a pre-computer off that
thing so again as I said if you go
Google selectively store you'll find the
Columbia paper of my slides and the
people I've copied my slides and the
reason why I know that copying my slides
is they don't know what this is they
always include this ju y su x joy was my
first PG student right that's why his
names in here so you go look at a bunch
of other slides and sure enough like joy
sucks right
joy suck a geek they copy the entire
yeah all right all right I don't care
it's fine all right so let's see what
you performers benefit you can actually
get from this so for this one they're
gonna do four lanes to me registers and
they're gonna actually compare against
two CPU architectures so this one here
the xeon phi who here has ever heard of
the xeon phi well your dad worked at
Intel buddy very few people write Xeon
Phi with a coprocessor that Intel used
to sell that sort of look comes in a
bunch of different form factors the
easiest way to think about it was like
it was like their version of a GPU that
was meant for highly parallel
computation so it wasn't like you
wouldn't get a you know you know
thousands of cores as you would from you
know from from from Nvidia and their
GPUs you get maybe like 60 or 70 cores
but these cores were actually more
complex than a GPU core they're
basically like the Intel Pentium 4
architecture or like the atom
architecture later on so like the low
powered very simple but you'll get more
than you know more of course and then
you get on loozy on so you could have a
sit down so you'd have it by one you
could have a sit down on the the PCI
Express bus like look at GPU but they
had did have ones that could sit up
on the motherboard and a socket like
this one here you could actually have
run the operating system based on you
know own the Zeon 5 didn't need like a
busy on to drive everything and this one
here just has this little Omni path
connector so that you can do like remote
remote memory access to a to another
another machine right Intel killed this
off I think last year or two years ago
they were roughly around than a five
thousand dollars or so high it was an
interesting experiment but for machine
learning the the GPUs already better
alright so the main thing though I want
to point out though is the Xeon Phi
they're going to run here is going to be
a it's an older version of the xeon phi
so it's going to be do in order
execution so you can't do the
out-of-order stuff that the xeon can and
it can't do spec it of execution right
so it's gonna take your your your
pipeline and execute instructions one
after another
all right and and it can't do the just a
to me yeah it doesn't do it doesn't do
branch prediction and you spec of
execution so if you have a jump and if
the flush your des pipeline then you
know that that gets expensive so we're
gonna have four variants of the
selection scan so gonna do the scalar
version with sixty instructions the
branching versus the branchless and then
they'll have that vectorized version
which is always going to be branchless
but they'll do one with an early
mutilation and late materialization this
just means do i need to copy the the
tuple effort i Matt to the offsets do I
need to copy materialize it into a
buffer to pass it up to the next the
next operator in the query plan but
again it's not a full-fledged database
system so there is no other nothing else
after they do the scan right alright so
the first thing here you see is that
this the Xeon Phi is going to outperform
the the Xeon for the the branch in case
and the branch list case because this is
the the scan up is actually it's a
pretty simple instructions we're doing
in our for loop and this thing just has
way more cores but I always think this
is a typo right like it's this thing has
61 course I don't know why I said that
weird number it's not 60 or 62 or 64
right it's 61 whatever right and then
this Z on here I think has it's four
cores with hyper-threading so this has
way more cores the
for this is pretty straightforward so it
can rip through thinking more quickly
but this now shows you a portent
difference between with the benefit get
from branchless versus branching when
you can do in order versus out order
execution so again the the Xeon CPU has
the outer board execution it has the the
spec of execution and the branch
prediction so in that case the the the
the branch list one is is it's gonna do
much better right for this as you scale
up the selectivity all right sorry as
the second biggest lower I don't know
why this doesn't arc like the other one
oh yeah because in this case here you
you run out of CPU cache alright so
think of this is like zero one two five
ten this is like that first part of the
graph I showed from vector wise and then
when you go beyond 20 or 50 that's when
it crosses so that's why that's why you
know they converge there in the case
again the Xeon Phi they don't have that
branch misprediction respected execution
so like copying everything every single
time sucks in their world because it's a
lot of ways to work when your
selectivity is really low alright so
here again when you have the selectivity
at 100% the memory bandwidth on both of
these is what you're paying the penalty
for trying to get the data in and off of
your CPU caches so it doesn't make a
difference in either algorithm for the
vectorize one what you see is that the
in the case of the with late
materialization for both of these it's
gonna perform the best it's no surprise
because I I'm not copying tuples that
match like I'm just doing less work but
you have a more pronounced difference
between the early materialization and
the late winter and versus late
materialization on the two architectures
again for this one because in this world
the because the CPU is it's quite simple
the copy instructions become expensive
and like you know you're just doing a
lot the cost of doing wasted work
becomes more expensive and then
everything converges down to the same
performance when you start maxing out
the memory bandwidth right so here's a
good example also to of like as I was
saying like doesn't matter whether
you're fanciest indie or not like if the
query in the data
are not amenable to doing vectra's
operations it doesn't help you alright
this is also another good example of
what I was saying the beginning about
how you never achieved that the
theoretical and performance improvement
you could possibly get with vectorized
instructions so in this case here the on
the Z on this is doing on roughy 2.5 2.6
billion tuples per second but the semi
version is doing you know rounding up 6
so it's getting less than a 3x
improvement but we said we had a 4x
Sidney registers so this should really
be if we're actually achieving that full
full paralyzation we should have been 4x
faster and we're not because again it's
that cost of moving things in and out of
the registers that we pay a penalty for
just because we vectorized maybe one
piece of it doesn't and the rest of it's
not vectorized that that's going to be a
bottleneck for us ok all right so let's
look at some other things we do hash
tables is another one I think it's
really interesting that they talk about
this and they come up some interesting
techniques again this one we definitely
evaluated and it definitely does not
work once you're at a CPU cache alright
so say we want to do do a probe in our
hash table and we're doing linear
probing so we have and the scale version
we have a single input key well do well
hash it produce some offset for a slot
number in our hash table well go jump to
that all set can take whatever keys
inside of it compare it with our keys
see we match if we find a match we're
done if not then we just keep scanning
down until we keep till we find a slot
that's either empty meaning mean we know
our keys not in there or we find the one
that we're looking for right so the only
thing you can really vectorize in this
particular example you can vectorize
this right there are the the hyper guys
have a vectorized hash function which
I'll talk about when we talk about joins
but like that's not the expensive part
the expensive part is is doing this
comparison and jumping through memory in
the hash table so let's see how we can
vectorize this using vertical or start
horizontal vectorization so what we're
going to do now in our hash table
we're gonna expand out the number
Ellen's restoring purse law so within
each slot we'll have four keys and then
they'll have we'll have four values
so now we'll meet when we take a single
key we hash it we get our hash index we
jump to that location we're gonna get
back four keys then we can do our sim D
compare get get back our match mask and
then we check to see if any one of them
is one then we know we know we have a
match we know how to find the offset of
our matching key if there are all 0 then
we know that there's nothing in this
slot that we have and we just jump down
to the next location and then do the
same vectorized comparison all right so
for this one
this one to me this seems like actually
a really good idea turns out not to be
not to work because they're just there's
so much extra overhead of the cost of
going getting these things and scanning
and ripping through them you know
copying this into the Sidney Bechet errs
like that that's the penalty you're
paying yes so we seem is did we try
software prefetching on this where I'm
here and then I'm gonna assume that I'm
not gonna match and therefore I'm gonna
prefetch the next thing but what if I
match then I did prefetch some crap and
I flew to my CPU cache and then it
doesn't work like this is the cache
servers are so random that it's like
it's hard to say what you actually
should do it doesn't in our experience
it doesn't work confession doesn't help
yeah yeah all right so let's see how to
do this with vertical vectorization so
before we were taking one key and then
looking for that key in you know you
know in the needle the single needle in
our haystack now with vertical
vectorization we're going to take
multiple keys at the same time and do
our search in parallel for them so we'll
take four keys here
we'll run four hash functions and so
this you have to do scaler and there's
no Cindy instruction that do
a four lane hash can we can vectorize
the hash function itself the operations
women have something like there's no
like humor hash or
xxx hash that can be run entirely in Sim
d4 multiple elements so we're gonna run
this as a four lips rip through this we
can unroll the loop if we wanted to and
we'll get four locations in our hash
function or hash table we'd I'll jump to
those locations and then do it the Cindy
gather to put them into a single vector
and then now we can do our Cindy compare
and check to see whether we have a match
and that's gonna produce an offset sorry
produces a bit mass that is me one if
their keys match or zero if our keys
don't match but now what's the problem
here
well so in my last case when I'm looking
at one key at a time it took if that one
key matches I'm done that key doesn't
match then I jumped down to the next one
but now I have two of them match to them
doesn't don't match yes yeah so he said
like and this this is this this notion
of them they always wanted to have full
utilization of all the lanes so these
guys match so I don't need to go look
anymore else in the and the hash of a
seat to find a match for them these guys
don't match so I have to go look for
them so one thing I could do is just
keep these guys or keep you know keep
these keys in my register everybody
jumps down to one offset in and they're
in a corresponding location in the hash
table bring those new keys in and do
comparison and no matter what the first
key and the last key produce as the
comparison I ignored that because I know
that I already found them but now that's
in that I'm getting 50% utilization
because I'm doing useless computation on
those keys because I already knew I
found a match so I'm just I'm doing
unnecessary work again so the other
other thing could be say 3 out of 4
match and so I keep scanning yeah I loop
through the entire thing to find that
that the key the last key doesn't never
matches and now I just wasted all this
work so what they're gonna do is they're
gonna maintain
internal bookkeeping to keep track of
all right well these guys matched and
therefore now I need to go get two new
keys to replace them they're gonna go
back over here replace the input key
vector with the next two elements that
are in our column near on our hash
function and for the this the second and
third key I the hash function is really
just saying take the last location add
one to it cuz I'm moving down to the
next location in the slot array but I
get a new starting location for the the
first in the last key and then do this
all over again jump to those locations
fill up my vectors and then do my Cindy
compare oh right yes just can you go can
you do multiplicative hashing with Cindy
across multiple keys at the same time I
don't know the answer uh we have to
check like yeah I don't know because I
think you know there's a trade-off of
like collisions versus speed I I think
the collision rate might be kind of high
on that we could try alright um so this
is also not gonna work too when you we
know you don't fit your seat the caches
because getting all this bookkeeping
overhead to go back to get your keys and
fill them in it's gonna be expensive
there's another issue with this this
implementation that is a bit more
nuanced on the engineering side and if
anybody caught that when they read the
paper like what's one problem you'd have
at this if you're like the person
building a database system and when you
use this algorithm yes
the cookery show now is ignore all that
the issue is gonna be that the the
probic algorithm is not gonna be stable
meaning for the same data set and the
same query we we could get different
ordered results every single time you
run that query now okay well
relational model is unordered right so
so this is we're not supposed to really
care about the order but like if I'm
trying to actually debug stuff and try
to understand it well somehow the the
data I'm writing to one register gets
you know one location gets clobber but
another one doesn't like if every single
time I'm getting completely different
random results depending on what order
had these things matching my hash table
then it could be hard to debug things I
I somewhat agree with that i i i don't
know how much that that is actually in
issue but this is something they said in
the paper that of all the algorithms
this is the only one that they had this
particular issue like the selective scan
stuff we talked about doesn't have this
problem yeah all right let's look at
some performance results so again we're
gonna roll on the Phi and the Xeon so
they're gonna have the scalar hash probe
and then the vector ax is vertical and
horizontal the along the x axis they're
going to crease the hash table size so
with the scalar version the performance
looks like this and notice that the y
axis scales are different because the
the xeon phi has more cores than the
other one
the when okay and we're gonna see that
again the difference though is that the
vertical vectorization will be much
better for the for the xeon phi because
it doesn't have the it doesn't have the
the branch misprediction error like it's
always gonna sort of programmatically go
through and do the you know the checks
in the right the same order whereas in
the horizontal case your you know you
may have to check you know in direction
or different non-determinism in how you
evaluate the keys in the case of the and
the xeon I forget why there's is the
crossing point here where the vertical
sub got back to got better than the the
horizontal
to point out here is that same before
once everything is not in your CPU cache
all this doesn't matter right so the the
Xeon Phi has a smaller cache than the
than the regular Xeon so you hit this
this sort of convergence point much more
much much sooner so again this is what I
was saying I I doubts over P fetching
would happen in this case and Xeon Phi
least the older version stuff they
definitely not have prefix up or
prefetching that's only in sort of
modern Zeon's
modern last ten years yeah alright the
last thing I'm gonna talk about is have
you partitioning with histograms and
basically the idea here is we can use
scatter and gather to do our histogram
computation in parallel so they say this
is our input key vector we're gonna use
a sim the latest instruction think of
this or like in the same thing as a
radix tree where I just go grab one
digit or one byte of each key and I'm
using that essentially as the hash
function to tell me what my offset
should be in like it's a it's a cheap
poor-man's hash function and then now
what I'm gonna do is I take these
locations and then I'm gonna map them to
some histogram and I'll just do a
Symbian where I take whatever value was
in the vector I'm writing into and I and
I add one to it alright for everything
ever it for every matching element
within that location in the vector I'm
writing to the problems gonna be though
is that I have two keys mapping to the
same location and again with Cindy it's
going to be atomic so the the
instruction is add one to this location
based on the previous value is I can't I
can't
it's not there's no foil to say add one
first time and add one again it's like
add one based on the old value is so
we're losing one of these one of these
updates so our counts are gonna be wrong
so the way they can handle that is you
do a Cindy scatter now to have each of
these guys writing two different vectors
right so this is the first vector for
the first keep for the first element
this is the next vector for the next
element and now they're doing the same
thing we had before with the writing
into the offset of the vector but then
now they're not clobbering each other
because they're only one you know one
lane can write into one vector at a time
so now the only thing I if I need to do
is what the final histogram it is
I just do a Simba had to do the
computation across across this way
horizontally to produce the final result
all right so I think I think this is
kind of cool okay all right there's a
finish up quickly vectorization is super
important for OLAP queries we've already
covered this nothing works when your CPU
cache and then all the inner query
panels and stuff that we talked about so
far plus the stuff we'll talk about when
we start to turn my joins vectorization
is just another tool we can add to speed
things up so in an ideal case an ideal
system you can do query compilation with
vectorization that also supports
parallel queries and in our system we're
almost there hyper actually could not do
vectorization they can only do
compilation and parallel queries right
dr. wise can only do I sort of pre
compiled yeah some cases it helps
sometimes it doesn't help but they could
they could do better ization yes that's
for rights the rights they have only on
a single thread but for OLAP queries or
read-only queries they can run those in
parallel that's the mortal stuff we
talked about wouldn't for the schedulers
okay any question that vectorization all
right let's finish up with Patrick 3 ok
so the project 3 the pot the goal is for
you in your group to implement some
substantial or large piece of software
component or feature in the data system
we've been working on for the first two
projects and the idea is that these
products should incorporate the various
topics and techniques and methods and
optimizations that we've talked about so
far in the course as well as whatever
you interested in your own sort of line
of work or research or your hobby if you
want to bring that in as well then I'm
totally fine with that all right because
I certainly I don't know everything that
you know and think outside databases I'm
very limited knowledge so if you come
along with something that I don't know
about it would be kind of cool to play
with I'm totally down with that the
important thing though is that whatever
you pick for your project has to be
unique from every other group so I can't
have two people two groups also
implementing constraints because the
goal is we want to have your software be
able to be merge back into the full
system so that you know that you know
you go off and
in real-world ago in the and the job
where I couldn't be able to say look you
know here's this piece of our database
system that that I helped implement so
what do you have to do well there's me
proposal
that'll be due after the spring break
then later on before the end semester
via satis update with design documents
will also do code reviews with each
other alright so you talk about this in
a second but you mean you have to look
over other people's code and see whether
they're doing stupid things and a look
at your code to see whether your do
you're doing stupid things
and there'll be a final presentation and
then the code drop which is submitting a
PR on us on github it has a cleanly
merge into our master branch so let's go
through each of these so for the first
Monday after Spring Break everyone every
group will come up here and they'll
spend five minutes to talk about what
you're what you're proposing to build so
this is not just like at a high level
here's what I want to do you actually
should spend time looking at the source
code and try to come up with a good
approximation of what will actually take
for you to implement that particular
feature or component so you should know
what files you need to modify or add
Hydra acts you're gonna test whether
your implementation is working correctly
and then this is why I have you guys
list and every single paper you read
what workloads they used to evaluate
their their their research you should
know about what workload you want to use
for your project so right now we can
support some basic ot workloads TATP
small bank and why says be and we can
support some queries in TP CH but it is
something else you want to evaluate let
me know we can figure something out then
we'll have a checkpoint in April where
again you come back up spend five
minutes and tell everyone what you've
done what you've worked on what the
current status is of your project if
there's any change in your plans because
there's something in the system that
like was broken or not implemented or
you found something else that was super
interesting then you talk about what
those differences are and this is always
fun to you people who discuss like what
are some some prizes they found when
they would start looking into the bowels
of the system like oh I thought it was
gonna work this way but it did this way
I would the be derek she has a memory
leak right well that's not a surprise at
this point but like like things like
that right and it was also super useful
but this is and you'll see this this
definite is happening previous semesters
is that sometimes one group will need
you know sort of one feature like like
we need a settings manager or a locked
away to lock tables in a certain way and
another group might need the same thing
so then rather than you know the two
groups both implementing the same
redundant piece of software you guys
could potentially work together or maybe
one group finished or the other group
and the other group could take their
take their code so this is meant to be
like a collaborative process it's not
like project one or project you or
you're in competition with each other
it's meant to say I we should all be
working together and trying to make the
thing better the design document I'll
provide you guys with the template and
it's just written in markdown it's
basically it's a description of what the
what your feature is or what your
component actually is why you designed
it a certain way you know what are the
different trade-offs that you have to
consider for this implementation and
then future work for if anybody wants to
come along and continue with with your
project you know what could it actually
do if you had more time what would you
actually do and for those of you that
are considering doing like a capstone
and a pen study in the fall semester
this is also a useful point for you to
write down what your state of mind was
at the end of the semester because you'd
go off in the summer and come back in
the fall and you're like what the hell
was actually thinking back in the April
May and this is a good you know a good
reminder for yourself for the code
review again you'll be two rounds of
code reviews again I'll pair up
different groups so to look at each
other's code and we'll just use the the
pull request review process through
through github and I'll spend time in
class to talk about what does it mean to
actually do a code view you know it's
not like things like you know you you
misspelled this word like it's actually
spending time to look at the code and
try to figure out you know are they
making reasonable assumptions or in
their implementation and what I'll say
also too is this is meant to be
everyone's mentor can contribute so I
don't want for the like the first
recurred review one person does it and
the second code review the next person
does it everyone should be contributing
equally and how we divide up the source
code for what you want to look at right
that'll vary based on the project like
certainly sometimes this if you're doing
a I'm gonna file basis sometimes clearly
some from files on War they more
modified than other files and that may
not be a good way to divide things up
but well we will discuss ways to handle
this final presentations will be
whenever we're scheduled for the final
exam I think some Monday at like 8:30 or
5:30 p.m. we're not
we're not at the night where we're not
in the morning with the night so we'll
get Pete so we'll get food but they
think you just show up spend 10 minutes
to say here's what we've actually done
and in previous years a few I'm given
demos if you can do a demo for the
status update that's awesome - like to
show it like hey this thing actually
does do what we say it does and now we
actually support sequel in our system so
doing demos should be much easier for
people not project you project 3 so the
way it's gonna work though is it's not
like other classes where you can write
some code that's sitting in your private
github repo or your laptop and then no
one ever sees that nobody ever cares you
have to make sure your code actually can
merge into the master branch right to
get a final grade the reason why we do
this is just because one you know it
gives you visibility about what you're
doing because if you want to go get a
job at a database company and this one
honestly
email me say hey do you know the student
what do they do and I can point to your
project and here's the actual source
code so we wanted some cases we want to
merge some code sometimes we don't but
at least there's a PR that can cleanly
merge passes all the tests and then we
can point to is like the final body of
work okay we're not a company we're not
you know we're not trying to sell this
software but we're still trying to do
high quality software engineering to the
extent that we can in academia and I
think this is you know actually I had a
student come back he's doing an
internship at a dangerous company now
and was surprised at how messy the
commercial source code they were looking
at versus versus our source code and so
I like to think that like you know going
through this process you get at least
you know appreciate what is it what does
it take to actually write you know clean
and reasonable source code so it has
emergent it's a mess branch and they
have that you know we do all the clang
tidy clang format and the doxygen checks
as well now the tricky thing is gonna be
of course if there's conflicts between
different groups so they modify the same
file how we determine if we're going to
merge things who gets to merge first
this one want to do at random or we're
taking our case-by-case basis our
success rate has been about 50% so 50%
of the student projects in previous
years have merged into the master branch
okay well in terms of resources again
we'll get you more credits for Amazon if
you submit a PR to our main repo battle
fire off builds and Travis and Jenkins
we're probably gonna drop Travis because
we're running the
taking too long but the Jenkins one will
cover like you know OSX and Ubuntu um if
you think you need special hardware
which I think this year there shouldn't
be anything let me know and we can see
what we can do okay all right and yeah
you've already guys know this story it's
a work in progress bunch of things
aren't gonna work some things are made
me broken but we'll fix it as we go
along all right let's see what potential
topics so let's go there's a bunch of
these let's go but want one me one so
the first one is for a query the query
optimizer so we have a full Cascades
query optimizer you'll learn with the
Cascades actually means and a few more
lectures so this project would actually
working on the internals of the
optimizer to add support for more
complex queries more complex
transformations things like outer joins
which I think we this might be fixed but
nested queries we need to potentially
improve our cost model actually be defi
we know we need to improve our cost
model for how we can determine whether
one plan is better than another but I
would say like I can go more details
later on about what kind of things you
could do with this but if you do work on
the query optimizer then you have to the
very first thing you have to do is also
send me your CV because a resume because
this is the one thing all the database
companies want to hire you saw if you
were an intro class last year or last
semester the guy from Oracle came and
he's like yeah we don't JavaScript
programmers we went from one query
optimizer people alright and I also get
emails like this like this is from a
pretty famous database person at a day
startup and he's like emailing a bunch
of people and I was on the list although
I'm not a senior database person
whatever but he's like hey does anybody
know there's like any loose query
optimizer people we could hire and
because they're super hard because like
query optimization was a big thing in
the 80s and 90s and it's like these old
white dudes that are you know that like
you know not very likely to leave leave
companies and go join startups so people
cannot hire these these places fast
enough and like all the nocebo database
companies that were like oh we don't
need a query optimizer we're just gonna
do you know get them sets and JSON like
they then soon realized oh we do need a
query optimization
query optimizer and so people are
struggling to find them so again this
guy was a bit more vulgar with his
request but same thing he wanted to hire
people to do to find query optimizer
query ah people can work at the quarry
optimizer related this for the cost
we don't have any good way to maintain
statistics information about what the
data looks like so then we can feed that
into our cost model to make estimations
of the quality of a query so we would
need a way to collect statistics about
that we didn't feed into the system we
could also do sampling which is another
technique that Microsoft uses where you
just make a small little mini table and
copy something data in and then do your
estimations based on that if that's this
then also been used for a new cost model
that we can hook it to the quarry
optimizer that would be amazing as well
if you're more interested in sort of
like like how do you actually queries we
want to support common table expressions
so right now again we support TPC HT PCH
is from the 90s it doesn't have CT es is
pretty straightforward CPC des is a more
complex to sit the DSN sort decision
support say more complex OLAP workload
analytical work on the NT PCH and this
has a bunch of CT ease but we don't
support any of that so this would be
modifying our parser extending the
parser to support the width and union
clauses modify the optimizer to reason
about you know the the wif clause and
potentially rewriting that to joins in
some cases and then I don't know whether
it's true or not but you may have to
also modify the execution engine to
actually support CTS depending on how
what the queries actually looked like
and I will fully admit I don't know full
I don't know all the ways you can unroll
or D correlate or rewrite CT es there's
a there's a actually a really good
textbook from not the hyper guide in
Germany but his other German adviser so
another German wrote a book about query
optimizers then we have access to that
describe all the various techniques for
this so this is something we could do as
well we also use a port for add/drop
indexes so right now we can call create
index when you create the table and then
as you insert tuples into a table we
will populate it but if the table
already exists with a bunch of data in
it and you call create an index it can't
go back and populate it easiest way to
do that as you pause the execution of
all transactions do they then populate
it and then turn transactions back on
but obviously that that's bad because
you're blocking everything so being able
to do to build the index while you still
up cake up the up
the tables is super interesting a bunch
of systems are just adding like PostGIS
just add this in the last couple years
so this would be really awesome to do be
awesome to do this also with parallel
threads think of this as doing the
sequential scan with multiple threads
and they're all inserting into the index
related this would be multiple T
threaded queries the current the current
version we have that you guys working on
and the system only supports single
threaded queries but there is my PhD
student per shot has a branch that
supports parallel queries but hey he
only has the only heads over the
execution engine side of things if the
idea would be porting over his parallel
query implementation but then been
modifying the rest of the infrastructure
of the system to recognize oh I can run
queries in parallel make sure that you
know plan your plans come out the right
way so they can be paralyzed we could
also start adding support for like the
pneuma where of data placement
techniques that the hyper guys are doing
with morsels once we get to the basic
the basic that in parallel engine
working prepared statements are also
super important we currently don't
support this so again prepared statement
is a pair of statement it says I'm gonna
cue this query over never again here's
some placeholders for some parameters so
you need to like cache that and then you
can invoke it and and and and we use the
plan over and over again so there's a
bunch of different design decisions you
have to consider to when you want to do
prepared statements like when you
actually run it through the optimizer
when you actually decide to replan
things all the various data systems do
different things and this would be sort
of an evaluation of the different
techniques so you'd have to modify the
the wire protocol to handle this and
then make sure and we actually would be
super awesome to is if instead of having
a prepared statement cache and then a
compiled query cache if we can unify
them all together that would be a big
win so my PhD student matt is actually
looking into this now so if we
interested in pursuing this you know let
me know we can start talking next week
or this week we compare these support
the write out log which I think we can
replay the log upon restart this is not
true I think we can reuse to all the
catalogs but as I said you want to also
be able to take checkpoints we don't the
replay the entire log so this would be
added support to do checkpoints so the
I think the simplest way to do this
would be the snapshot isolation
possession checkpoint and you just pick
you back up with this Winchell scan
implementation that's available in the
day system now and again this nagra's
here to see an example where if you can
work in tandem with another team if
another team is doing parallel queries
and they support a parallel scruncho
scans you could then support that in
your checkpoint algorithm and now do
special scans and parallel to write the
checkpoint out and then we want to be
able to load the checkpoint in after we
start then replay the log all right so
it sounds I take a checkpoint I'm done
integrating the full sentiment this is
tricky we want to support constraints
like the Czech uniqueness foreign keys
and so this is this is modifying the
catalogue modifying the the modifying
like that the front of the system David
hand this information modifying the
stores are the excuse change to enforce
these constraints so if I have a check
clause that says like where value is not
you know not negative I have to know
that when I'm inserting something I
complied that predicate and see whether
that was true or not
same thing with foreign keys to
additional things you could do is do
online constraint changes with alter
mean if I add a constraint that says
this key can't be null I've to scan
through and make sure nothing is null
because therefore I would you know if I
try to plug your sharing that would
already be violated at the beginning
that's bad another cool thing to
actually be able to do is extend the
query optimizer to be aware of some of
these constraints like I know that
something can't be negative so therefore
I may want to change how I do my join or
do a scan alright that's the high end
systems that can do this that would
actually be super cool sequences are the
auto increment keys so this would be
added support that we can store
sequences in the catalog and supply
support the next valve function or the
serial type so that we can do easily do
auto increment keys this one is a bit
more tricky because when you caching in
the catalog so that everybody everybody
everybody calling next valve doesn't
always update the catalog you could have
something sitting around in memory that
you hand out in batches
the tricky thing though is you have to
then alright out in the right ahead log
how that that value got incremented so
if I crash come back the counter doesn't
start at zero again I don't I don't have
duplicate values different types are be
interesting to do as well
so we talked about how the numeric type
from the Germans they claim is faster
than the floating-point numbers and then
they claim that there's this book called
hackers delight which is Google you can
find that describes the the sort of the
underlying method for doing low little
bit operations on fixed point decimals
it doesn't describe exactly how to do in
the concept of a database like there's
much other stuff we have to do but the
bit manipulation techniques can be found
in this book
so I'm actually super interested this as
well I don't know how to do it but we
could sit down and learn it together if
you're injured in types I want to do
something more easy enum type would be
another one you could do and this is
just like enum you have in C++ or Java
same thing in the idea what you have to
do is that you would support the at the
cattle will keep track all the enums as
the array modifying the binder to be
able to enforce those enum constraints
so someone gives us a value that doesn't
exist you know we throw an error and
then we have to be able to support this
in the execution engine to know that I'm
operating on an enum and then
materialize the correct value of when it
produces the result to to the
application I'm gonna do this quickly
but you know all the slides are online I
don't have to talk about about this
afterwards so we haven't any talk about
views but I think of them as like a
virtual table like an define a view on a
select query and I give it a name and it
looks like a table then now I can run a
query on that view and treat it as if it
was a table and typically the way it is
the data some handles this is that it'll
rewrite your query into the the to be
doing a look-up on on the actual
underlying you know view query so we'd
have to support the extend the catalog
to put these things we have to modify
the binder to transform the view into
the original query and as far as you
know I don't think we're have to modify
this you stream engine you can rewrite
the views as a nested query and I think
just work and then the optimizer can
just you know D correlate or optimize as
necessary
alright last two concurrent schema
changes would be if I add a drop a
column can I do that without having to
lock everything this is actually super
tricky this is the the second year we've
tried this we have we think now we have
the infrastructure to be able to do this
in a very interesting way because now we
can do like this lazy method where you
say at a column we tell you we added
but we don't actually go through it and
and you know shuffled at around to add
that that memory location it's only when
you insert new things or you try to read
back old stuff then we can materialize
it on the fly
the last one is data compression so we
support Apache arrow and we have support
for the their dictionary compression
scheme which is very straightforward but
it's not turned on meaning we can't take
hot data and convert it into a
compressed cold data block we used to
have that infrastructure but we don't
anymore so this would be adding support
for convert doing this conversion the
reason why we don't have it cuz we
because you have to also update indexes
because you're moving tuples from one
location to another
but then the tricky thing is going to be
is now modified the execution engine in
some way to be able to process the
compressed data directly because right
now we can't do that we would have to
have the data table decompress it before
we can do scans on it which defeats the
whole purpose to compression all right
so how do I get started
form a team which is already sorted done
with project two you should meet your
team discuss your potential topics
potentially look over the source code or
contact me to sort of point you at what
parts of the source code you want to
look at I'm around all next week or send
me an email and have a discuss you know
what are some potential stoppers you can
look up okay all right sorry for going
over time next class I'll post this on
Piazza with more details but you have
your prose or presentations five minutes
and it's a hard limit okay
all right guys awesome thank you see you
cranked it in the side park what is this
some fools say you're here
[Music]
ain't dead here called the hawk
it cuz I mochi ice cube down with the
testy
hi you look and it was go grab me a 40
just to get my buzz song cuz I need it
just a little more kick like a fish to
just one simple just drop them say nice
and my hood wants me to say I'm nice
cute take a say I celebrate