[Music]
[Applause]
other devious companies are still coming
so Oracle is giving a tech talk on
campus this Wednesday I think this guy
is from the in-memory database group
it's from the same group Shashank
Chopin who came in game he am a guest
lecturer in the intro class last
semester so he's gonna come and talk
about I suspect to be very a similar
talk than what we got last semester but
that's at 4:30 over here in a new
assignment they'll probably be pizza for
this because if it's at 4:30 then
there's usually pizza right the 12
o'clock ones unless that's on a Thursday
there's usually not food all right all
right so before we get started
Matt posted on Piazza last night on the
speech or project one that you need to
target and then he'll be setting up
great scope today so you can spit that
so again what will happen is you'll
submit your your project on great scope
the better just prove that actually
builds and then we'll have to run these
offline on the same ec2 instance that
that were telling you to we do grading
sony post on Piazza last night that like
the he used the instance store of the
instance type we give you then it runs
out of space is because we do static
linking in our system so when you build
everything every single test case is
like one gig so you've run that space
there's no way to build the benchmark
without building the tests but it might
be if you just if you just target the
like building the slot iterator it may
not actually build all the unit tests
may just build that one by night so you
should still be ok but there's no way
like you can do it past the flag say and
see make turn off building benchmarks
you can also turn off building the test
but you current that's currently broken
because there's some dependency between
the two of them ok any high-level
questions that project one okay and well
again we'll try to answer on Piazza as
as the week progresses ok all right so
we've spent the last couple weeks
talking about
sort of more OLTP aspects of a database
systems so we talked about how to do
transactions
well talk to how to do indexes and now
we're gonna go to the bottom layer of
the database system now talk about
storage and then going forward from that
to the semester we'll start building up
new layers on top of that so we'll do
database storage then we'll do execution
in query optimization and so forth and
so the the reason why I started with
transactions and indexes first because
in the back of your mind as we go
forward when we discuss other aspects of
the database system you should be
thinking about this in the context of an
MVC system and then think about whether
whatever you know whatever technique or
method we're discussing would this
actually work for if you're doing nbcc
and some things work great there's
there's a single version some things not
so great when they're multi version so
that that's sort of why I front-loaded
the transactional stuff in the beginning
all right so this is the chart I showed
in the beginning of a semester of what a
high level what in-memory database
actually looks like so say we have now
our index our bwuh our index doesn't
matter we do a lookup to find a given
tuple and then this thing is gonna spit
out a block ID and an offset so the
block ID could it be a pointer to the
beginning of the block and the offset
could be within that block but that
would sort of be kind of wasteful the
this thing could just be just a straight
pointer to the tuple itself but now you
get any issues of you start moving
things around so in our system what we
actually do and a student came up this
and was pretty clever we use a trick
from super plus 11 called a line as and
basically this is telling the compiler
in the system to align the starting
address of a memory block at a certain
set so we do this where we have all our
blocks our one megabytes and we use la
line as to enforce this so now the block
ID offset we get is a 44 bit pointer to
some one megabyte block and then we have
20 bits now to jump into some region so
instead of having an extra indirection
layer to say how do I get my block ID to
a block address right we can pack this
all in a single thing the only reason I
bring this up it says in the OL
assessment peloton it was a train wreck
this thing would actually be a pointer
to a pointer
so he had a thing called a tuple point a
pointer and that was it became a
nightmare we had so many layers of
indirection where now this one just
tells you exactly how to go to the block
ID and then or the block block location
and then this is just the offset to it
so again the main thing to point out
though is that all of our tuples are
going to try to stores these fixed
length continuous pieces of memory
whether it's a columns to our row store
doesn't matter these values need to be
fixed length because then we can do this
arithmetic very very easily to say oh I
want the fifth tuple I know the size
every tuple my block I know how to jump
to the starting location for that tuple
anything that could be variable length
will instead instead store it in a
separate data pool we have variable
length data blocks and this sort of
looks like what malloc doesn't need the
covers like the bin packing problem
trying to stick in you know different
regions of memory of different sizes
right so this is just being now a 64 bit
pointer to that location so this is what
we're gonna talk about today we're
talking about like how we're actually
gonna represent stuff in here and then
stuff in here so at a high level what
you think in memory database just is
it's just this is a large byte array we
malloc a bunch of chunks of memory and
then we need a way to now interpret
those chunks or regions of those memory
chunks to infer what the schema actually
is so because we're relational databases
we're told the schema ahead of time JSON
stuff is usually just treated as a
variable of every length data but we
know like I have these in our columns
that can have these types and of these
sizes so now when we jump to an offset
in that fixed length data pool we know
that this is the starting location of a
tuple and we know how to interpret the
flights that we're looking at we know
whether to interpret it as an integer or
a float or you know a timestamp so again
we already talked us before every two
books can be prefixed with the header
that concludes the metadata such as the
visibility will talk about nulls and
sticking that in there but basically
when I jump to an offset to say this is
the starting location of the tuple I'm
really jumping into the header and I can
look at that header and try to figure
out you know what's gonna come after
that we're not going to store any of the
schema information in the header because
that'd be wasteful to do that for every
single tuple the JSON databases that our
schema lists have to do this but in our
world
you know every tuple has to have the
same same same structure the same layout
and so we don't need to repeatedly store
that in the header so alright today
we're gonna talk about do type
representation how do we actually
represent individual elements or
attributes and a tuple then we'll build
off the top of that talk to how we
layout now those attributes for a single
tuple then we'll talk about different
storage models and then we have time
we'll finish up and talk about system
catalogs because again like this is sort
of like an additional stuff that I want
you guys to sort of be aware of and this
is actually kind of cool things that you
can do because you have a relational
catalog relational database with the
schema but the those so the bulk of the
main material want to focus on is
storage models and Panta bhaat
okay so the this is the same I've shown
this before in the intro class but
basically we know all the types that our
database system can support the sequel
standard specifies what the basic types
are and we know then that's what
actually represent the bits to report
each into a value of an attribute so for
integers big and small instants we're
just going to use what C or supercells
provides for us when we say allocate
like an int 32 or 64 or small rent I
there's nothing special there we'll just
take whatever the bits we are when we
allocate that you know variable like
that and that's what we're storing in
our database for floating-point numbers
we'll have this distinction between
floats and reals floats and reals are
just gonna be using the I Triple E 754
standard which is telling you at the
hardware how we're gonna represent
floating-point numbers but this is gonna
have rounding and accuracy issues and
then there's the fixed point decimals
the numerix and decimal types that are
specified in the sequel standard every
database systems are free to implement
this any way they want some are more
efficient than others the Oracle one is
better than the Postgres one but the
main idea is that this this doesn't have
the same rounding errors that you have
in the floating-point numbers time
stamps dates and times types these also
vary per implementation the sequel
standard doesn't specify how you
actually represent these type of
attributes but they do specify that you
know what kind of operations you can do
but can I add two times together or can
I subtract them things like that one
common approach is just
the the UNIX epoch so it's the number of
seconds or milliseconds since the
January 1st 1970 and you use that to
calculate waters board its current date
and time in C++ there's this thing
called time spec which gives you a time
offset and then nanosecond offset and
that's actually 16 bytes larger than
this in our current system I think we're
using 64-bit and 64-bit integers which
is the middle of second since the UNIX
epoch but again from the seat but the
sequel level you don't know you don't
care you just know you have time stamps
you can stick things in and you can do
comparisons on them for the VAR charge
of our binaries text and variable length
fields again in the fixed length portion
of the tuple would store a pointer to
some block of data in the verbal length
pool if the value that we're trying to
store it's me less than 64 greater than
64 bits right if the size of the data
we're storing is smaller than the
pointer they mindlessness store the data
rather than have a pointer to that data
anything larger than that then we'll
store it in a very like data pool and
we'll keep some extra metadata to keep
track of like what are we looking at and
if it overflows to another data pool we
have pointers of those as well so I'll
cover that as we go along so this
quickly I'm gonna talk about the
difference being variable precision and
floating-point precision decimal numbers
so again if you go for a float a real or
double you're gonna get the hardware
representation of a decimal or a
floating-point number
right and that's specified by this 72
our standard that every single PCE every
single CPU has to follow so if you store
a floating-point number on a power CPU
and we represented the same way in x86
the and E&S may be switched like the bit
order might be switched but at the sort
of you know how you keep track of a
decimal point and what's before and
after it it's all specified by this so
this will be really fast because the
harbor is actually gonna have you know
low-level instructions support to take
you know to floating-point numbers and
compare them or atom add them together
it's not gonna be as fast potentially as
giving addition on integers but it
certainly be faster than doing anything
that we can manage ourselves in the
database system but the downside again
is you're going to have rounding errors
so if you write a really simple C
program like this where you take two
numbers to 32 bit floating number
zero point one and zero point two if I
add them together you think the answer
would be zero point three but the
problem is when you actually start
looking at what what's you know with
positions in the decimal you see you end
up with all sorts of weird stuff because
again the harbor can't can't precisely
store zero point three so even just you
know print out zero point three you get
a bunch of a bunch of stuff so this
again for some aspects in in
applications this is fine maybe this is
okay like if I'm storing you know the
the the temperature of this room I don't
need to have you know a super accurate
measurements right ninety eight point
six or ninety point zero is like good
enough but if I'm dealing with like
money or anything that's like scientific
measurements right I don't want these
flot rounding errors then I want to use
fixed point decimal numbers and the idea
here is that the database system itself
is gonna keep track of what what is the
exact value that we're trying to store
and it handles all the rounding errors
or other issues that can come up when
you start doing multiplication and
manipulation so the this is actually I'm
saying here isn't accurate so this is
actually what Postgres does what
Postgres does will store the decimal
point number essentially as a varchar'
like a string and then they have some
extra metadata to keep track of like
where is the decimal point is it
negative or positive what are some
rounding issues so they have these giant
like switch statements to deal with all
these different variations of the type
of operations you want to do and it runs
about twice as slow than the
floating-point numbers the hyper guys
have a low-level sort of bit
manipulation method to distorting fixed
point death moles that is very very
efficient and actually some cases can
run faster than the floating-point
numbers which I don't know how that is
possible but this is what they show us
so I'm not gonna time to teach that I
don't fully understand what they're
doing just yet the the German guy
recommended this book called hackers
delight that shows you how to do all
this little bit manipulation but this is
something you want to pursue for project
three then we should talk yes
banks they use like four bits and then
just missing decimal playing so even
though this go for a stochastic like a
signal decimal position only four bits
oh yeah so that I don't know think about
I know that like for the bank's they
never overwrite datum so like if there's
like if a rounding issue could occur
because the way their application was
written when you computer like interest
or something like grab you can always go
back and fix it by you know rerunning
the computation again so it's not like
you would lose that you lose any data--
by having imprecise precision I don't
know what I don't this is something I'm
really a lot very interested in but I
don't know enough about it to compile
whether you know what people actually
doing other than I know that Germans
have solved it but I don't know exactly
what they're doing yet I don't fully
understand it okay again this is
something you want to do for project
three I be happy to try to help out with
this and I'll you know point to the
chapter in the book that he recommended
okay so the as I said like again the the
database is essentially just a byte
array just come you know a char array or
byte array and then now we need to now
put start putting meaning on to what the
bits were storing in these bytes so say
I have a simple table here has two
fields ID as a 32-bit integer and that's
primary key and then value is a 64-bit
integer so the layout of the tuple would
look like this right I have my header of
some size where I'm storing the you know
the timestamps and everything that we
talked about before and then when the
header ends now I have the ID field and
when that ends now I have the value
field right so if I need now am I in my
database system I want to understand
like I need to read you know this field
right I know how to find the location of
this tuple right because that the index
got me there that all the headers will
be of the same size so I know how to
then jump past that and at this position
here then everything I read afterwards
up to 32 bits will be the eye
Liefeld so how do we actually access
this data when it's just you know in our
in our C code or syphilis code would you
see a bunch of byte array we need a way
to convert this into something that we
can we can interpret as a 30 bit integer
let me take us how you do that and C++
reinterpret cast right so all that's
gonna say now in this is a compiler
construct this is gonna say that all
right when I read this memory address
treat whatever you're reading as not a
byte array but a 32-bit integer so that
now in the compiler knows that when when
accesses it's just gonna access just
those 32 bits right so now for the
variable length data say I have a bar
chart 1024 so again in the fixed length
data array I'll have my header and then
I have the the 64 bit pointer and this
is going to now point to now down to
some memory region here in the variant
like data pool the starting location
that's gonna tell me you know find the
actual value that I want so in this case
here for each of these entries in the
very linked data pool it'll have its own
header that keeps track what is the
length of the data that we're storing
contiguously for this chunk and then if
it overflows this chunk there'll be a
next pointer that jumps down to some
other memory location where we read the
rest of the data right so this is not
unique to American bases that the the
disk based databases do the same thing
if you're if you're if you're varchar'
or textfield
overflows between different pages and
you need it you need a way to how to
connect these all together the other
thing that I did not gonna talk about
too much is that this is gonna be this
is not gonna be null terminated
typically because otherwise your weight
you know you're wasting a byte for those
you know for no reason so in our code we
can't just go to call it like you know
string compare our string length in our
in added a see library to compare this
thing because it's not gonna have a you
know null at the end so it's not truly a
C string so we have to write some
additional we have to write our own
string functions we don't interpret this
thing and understand it okay the other
optimization we can do here is that say
you know say I'm time lookup you know
finally all the the string
the value the value is where the
beginning of the string starts with a
word and II so how would I have to do
that and with this set up I've got to
scan through my table and then for every
single tuple follow this pointer to
somewhere some random location and then
jump you know you know jump it to the
first you know some bytes and see
whether it starts with an D so that
would be really expensive to do because
it'd be a lot of indirection a lot of a
lot of branch misprediction because
there's no conditionals but it basically
I'd be scanning one part of memory then
jumping over to another part and then
going back ask anymore and back and
forth as I would have bat cache locality
because it's not like I can keep
scanning the same you know a bunch of
stuff that I brought into my caches all
at once I got to keep jumping over and
over again so a really simple
optimization is actually to pad out the
the pointer portion that you're storing
in the fixed length data to include a
prefix of the string down below so now
when I scan across and try to find
things that start with an D I could just
look at this thing and see whether it
matches or not and I never have team
touch any of this so we act so this
hyper does this and we actually do this
in our own system so the the pointer
portion of a varlyn field in the thick
fixed-length data pool is gonna be 16
bytes or 128 bits so we store
64 bit pointer to the actual data and
then we use the remaining 64 bits to
store prefix you could also store hash
of the entire string right there's
different methods to do you could use
okay alright so now all right so now we
know how to store basic scalar or scalar
values of fixed length values integers
floats and timestamps now we know how to
store store very length data now the
last thing we got to deal with is nulls
so there's three ways to do nulls at
least as far as I know the first
approach is to just designate a special
value in the domain of a type in the
database to represent null so one thing
you can do say the smallest 30 cubed
integer you could ever store which is
defined in Lib C is in 32 min like this
pound define that will be null so if I
ever see this value when I'm looking at
a tuple then I'm gonna treat that as a
null not really in 32 min
so now up above and you in the above the
storage layer in the database system you
have to account for this like if someone
tries to insert this value you have to
throw you know throw an exception throw
an error because they're you know they
try to store this value and then you've
read it back and says it's you know it's
null then that would sort of be
confusing you basically have a bunch of
extra boundary code up before to make
sure that this is considered out of
range so we did this in a store and
volte B we did this a Mon Ami Mon a DB
does the same thing and then we
originally were doing this in peloton in
the old unit movie building here at CMU
but as far as they know other than Moe
need to be and both of either the only
ones that I know that does this the more
common approach is to use a null column
bitmap so we're going to now do in store
in our header for our tuple we're having
this bitmap field that's going to say
for every single attribute that I have
in my to pool the bit is set the one if
that attribute is known so if I have a
thousand attributes or per tuple then I
have my bitmap you have a thousand
entries so now as I'm scanning the two
point and applying predicates I do a
lookup in this thing to see whether the
accurate I'm looking at is you know is
that bit set to true and if so then it's
null this one is way more common but for
a memory databases in dis databases like
my sequel Postgres sequel server oracle
everybody does it this way this is what
we now do in our own system because now
we're also a column store this is just
now not Murat storing this bitmap per
tuple we just have it for you know for a
single column here's the whole bitmap
for every single tuple it's in a block
alright the last one is all the safe
right I think this one's stupid only one
database said I know that does this and
that's mem sequel and this is where
you're going to store for every single
accurate that's in your tuple you're
gonna have a separate flag to say
whether it's no l'm not so if i have a
32-bit integer that could be null then i
needed a little flag in front of it that
says yeah you know is this thing knoll
or not so why is this stupid yes
says it Bruins drops us no way everyone
has the same flag then they all sets are
fine okay no it's on the issue right
instead of like if I have four
attributes and everyone is 32 bits plus
one bit for the flag then if I want the
third attribute I take 33 times three
and I jump to where I need to go bingo
that's it she says you don't have a bit
addressable memory so you can't get my
32 bit integer just can't make it thirty
three bits because that's gonna make
everything unaligned and you can't
access memory at a bit offsets you can
do byte offsets so if you go now look at
the the mem sequel documentation they
say what's the size of all the different
data types they support so this is from
MC equals six I've recently looked at
you know this is this this chart from
the documentation is maybe like two
years old but recently loaded and
they're still doing this so for every
single int or seven every single data
type the fixed fixed size data type
they're gonna have two potential sizes
the hot of the size of its if it could
be null and the size of its not null so
if we just take bullying right boolean
is true or false
so that's you saw that as one bike
because we can't store single bits so if
it could be null then I have to store
two bytes right same for the other one
site and it's like Prytania inch double
in size doubles in size this one they
get vibed is adding a single byte to
make something actually no take that
media medium in is sorry medium it is
three bytes so they add a single byte
for int and big int they have to have
four bytes because that's - you cash
they do word alignment in x86 so like
again if I store now if you think it was
like the bitmap case or in the going
back here this is the smallest one to
store because you don't take any extra
space you have to store that actually
anyway and just using this actually one
to say oh this this is null this gets a
little bit larger because now I have to
have a single bit for every single
a tribute in my my tuple police in that
case it's just a bit and I wanted to pad
out the bitmap a little but just a
little bit right this one is for every
single attribute I have to Pat it out
yes what is it all being used to mean no
I mean
so in sequel you can have it's a three
type value system so I can have a value
and I could set it like true false or
null and null means unknown I don't know
what the value is because they're
telling you sighs yes yes so his point
okay so his point is correct I we should
i yes I agreed you know what his
statement is Oh am I just looking at
this and saying oh whoa you're using
this extra two bytes just to store null
or are they doing our bar chart trick
and storing some extra crap in there but
what the hell would you have to store
for a single attribute right like right
like and for these pickling tight for
any like I can imagine like in a bar
chart like said like my example where I
Pat it out well like I showed the prefix
like sure the hash I could store maybe
the size up there so I'm looking for
things of a certain size yes the things
I get stored that you that you want to
beat would be potentially to materialise
expensive materialized for a bar char
any operation i could do on these things
for on a single attribute that needs
your super fast like you could say
alright well maybe they're also nails
storing well I mean for out of these you
can't there's none on cents if you if
you need that bit to store something as
as potentially null like say I'm sort of
like this be stupid like the the
negation of the absolute value of
something for so that's cheap to compute
right that's a few instructions but I go
and be able to store that in this anyway
because I still need to store that in
all flag so I don't know what they could
be pre computing and everything is is is
aligned now I've said MEMC go put out a
new version of their column store I
should double check to see whether that
like early late last year
they might have fixed this but but I
don't know they're the only ones I know
that does it does this or did in this
yes
oh these questions what's a bit better
type and why is it eight bytes that it's
a good question I don't know let's go
find out um it's not good use of our
time but I probably like a bit filled or
maybe it's a bitmap bit sequel type bit
data type is an integer data type that
can be take a value 0 1 or null see what
service comes in is one byte all right I
don't know that's good question yes cuz
Siebel servers get distorted as expected
ok let's look at that up later ok
alright so again this is the most common
one this is what we do now there's some
other optimizations we can do now on our
bitmap because everything is contiguous
like if I'm saying trying to find me all
the the Fahmy all the tuples where this
value is null then I can just take this
bitmap if it's stored as a column store
so all for a single attribute I've I
have a single bitmap and all contiguous
and now you do like Simbi operations or
vectorized operations to do counts and
other things more quickly alright where
everything these two guys you have to
still to look at look at the attribute
ok
so let's understand now why the deeper
why they have to do this padding out
right and he's already sort of set it
right because it because of alignment
issues because you can't access things
that like you know funky you know 33 bit
offsets all right so what I'm gonna
describe you now is I do cache line word
alignment for our tuples in our database
but I'm actually gonna be telling you
this are using examples with 64 bit
works or 64 bit cache lines and a real
x86 the cache line is 64 bytes but for
simplicity to make everything fit on a
slide I'm going to use 64 bits as an
example
just understand the high-level cop is
the same just the this the the length of
what the cache line is will be different
let's say now I have a table here right
I have four attributes a timestamp a
char two and a and a zip code in the
case of a char versus varchar' some
systems actually will store the varchar'
and some of this will store a chart just
as a regular bar char but in actuality
if you say well I know can only be ever
two bytes then you store that exactly in
the fixed length data pool a fixed
length tuple slot right so again here's
our alignments we're assuming we have 64
64 bit words so now when I start writing
out this data to our to our tuple write
the IDS 32 bits the timestamp is 64 bits
then this color is is 2 bytes or 16 bits
and then I zip code right so now let's
say I do a query I want to look up on
the the date field again I do my
arithmetic I know what the schema is so
I know what these the size of these
attributes are I know how to do that
simple math to jump to my offset and now
read this but what's gonna happen here
what happens what if my processor reads
something that's not word aligned is it
well he says he said bring the whole
cache line to cache reads that's 1
what else could it do so he said yes so
that's also an issue we're not gonna
about that he says that someone else
could come in and write to the other
half and I only see the first half let's
assume that we have transaction
protection above that or not that won't
be an issue
there's no no to writers so there's
actually three things could happen
so they got the first one right and this
is actually what x86 will do and the
newer versions are armed will do so the
in their world with x86 they're trying
to make you as the programmers life as
easy as possible so if you try to read
something that's not where aligned
they'll do it the multiple reads for you
and then stitch the the value back
together and hand it back to your
program for us now as we said that's
gonna be slow because what should have
been just one read into memory is
or you know to our CPU caches is now
gonna be two reads right so we're gonna
bring a much organic wrap that we
actually don't need like if we just
needed to get this date field we rent
we're gonna have to bring in this ID
field and the you know portion of the
zip code and this the this char array
even though we only just wanted those 32
bits so we're gonna read 128 bits just
to read 32 bits right and that's bad we
don't want to do that so for this one
you under perf you can tell it to one of
the events you can record our unaligned
accesses and actually we run with the
ACN stuff from Google when can when you
run our test cases so if you do
unaligned a memory access like it'll
throw an error and say you can't do that
but you also use perf to take a binary
and run it and count the number of
online accesses that you have and that
can help explain why your program is
running slow Cole grinds not gonna give
you that because Paul Ryan only sees
what what like what instructions you
execute right and what lines of code
doesn't tell you like what the Harvard
actually did the other approach would be
to do random beads basically you're
going to get some random combination of
of data and you up in the program to
figure this out on your own all right
this is obviously way faster than this
this is also easier to engineer on the
actual chip because you're not doing
extra stuff to make to reassemble things
this is what arm used to do in the very
beginning they now do this right of
course this is problematic is now you do
a read and you think you're getting
something that you think you're you're
getting that one field you're getting a
bunch of other crap
the the alternative is to actually do
just reject the the requests like you
try to read something that's not word
align we actually deny the load
operation and we throw back an error so
right so again modern modern CPUs or not
modern it's like the more common CPUs
that you're going to encounter in the
wild will be doing this I don't know who
actually does this anymore this is
mostly like an super small embedded
devices like low-power things which
again like you not be probably building
a full-fledged database doesn't do this
are you actually sequel lightwood perp
I've run all these guys and
and of course it's they've already
checked me these things so this is what
we care about in our world and so we
obviously don't want to do this right
cuz this is gonna be slow so we need a
way to resolve this so how can we make
our thing word aligned what's an easy
fix
Patti exactly yes so what we'll do here
is again we know in our data soon we
know what the word alignment is for the
harbor that we're running on so as we
start now laying out our data for our
tuples we will recognize oh well I can
store it 64-bit words this guy is 32
bits this next one was 64 bits
so rather than spanning the word
boundary I'll just put in a bunch of
zeroes for these 32 bits to Pat it out
so that the next attribute starts
exactly at the beginning of the next
word all right and so now in the in the
upper layers of the system depending on
how you give back data to the execution
engine you could the Storage Manager
could say all right well you need these
fields I want to send you a bunch of
garbage so let me go ahead and now
stitch this back together and a memory
buffer hand it back to you or you have
to have now in your execution to be
aware of the padding going on and your
storage manager so that you know when
you need to jump to the customer date
field that you have to skip over these
these 32 bits that are just padding
what's another thing we can do perfect
yes reordering that's the other one yes
so we we could also basically run the
same thing of a cab in packing problem
where we say I have 32 bits I can store
here to fill out my word instead of
actually just storing things in the
order that they were defined when I
created the table could I just find
another 32 bit thing or 32 bit attribute
and stick it in there and then now I
could pack the rest and only here do I
have to Pat it out to make sure that the
next people behind me follows that the
right boundary of the word all right so
again the upper levels of the system
need to be aware of that this padding is
going on or you need to do some copying
to hide it hide it from it so we
actually do both in our current system
today and so just give you an idea what
and prove it you can get so this is a
micro benchmark that the one of the
students that helped that out
the new version the system two summers
ago this is the first implication we
ever did without any alignment and so
this is just doing a doing a micro
benchmark that tries to insert as fast
as possible and so if you don't do any
alignment then you can run it maybe like
four hundred megabytes a second you
insert four hundred megabytes of data or
if I want to make about two data per
second no sorry not get sorry five
hundred kilobytes yes but then if you do
padding then this bumps up to eleven
megabytes per second but if you padding
plus sorting now everything is nicely
cache aligned and you can even insert at
a very high rate so there is just how
fast we insert in things into memory is
not ready while any log records out the
disk like this just showing that you
know the performance Ben advantage do
you get from this I don't think we have
numbers that show you know well just
which sorting provides you we only have
padding plus sorting so what happens in
our current system is that when you
create the table again we've run this
little algorithm that does basically
tries to figure out the optimal ordering
of columns in the system the execution
engine is aware of these this ordering
this is what the projected column stuff
gives to you but then before we hand
back the result to the application we
make sure that we put it back in the
right order as specified by by this
great table statement I think the sequel
standard specifies that you have to do
this I said now if someone calls select
star they will get the tuples the
attributes for each tuple ordered as
they defined here right because what
happens a lot of times people write
their application when they you know
they have these select star players and
then when they access attributes they
access them based on offsets like give
me the first one the second one the
third one so if I now start shuffling to
order these things because I ran some
bin packing algorithm then that's gonna
break programs so we do an extra step to
make the life easier for the end user so
any questions about this okay so now
let's talk about storage models so the
storage model specifies how the the
database minute system is going to
organize the tuples and their attributes
internally in in storage so there's the
two main approaches are the the
and an energy storage model and the
decomposition model so this is the row
store this is the column store and then
there's a hybrid approach that we'll
talk about a little bit where you sort
of have tried to get the best of both
worlds right in a single unified system
so the the rows store and a saml
approach is what you people normally
think about when we talk about databases
or relational databases right and the
idea here is like I did in all the
examples I showed so far but all the
attributes for a single tuple will be
stored contiguously in some region of
memory and then only when we get to the
last attribute then does then the next
triple begins so now again if I want to
go access the third attribute for the
fifth tuple I know how to do that
address arithmetic to jump to the offset
at the beginning point of that tuple and
then jump to that attribute so this
storage model is ideal for transactional
workloads they're all XP workloads
because in these in this environment the
transactions or the queries are only to
touch a small number of tuples and they
typically also touch all of the
attributes of a tuple there's a lot of
select star queries where account name
Eagles Andy and I want all the
attributes and therefore if it's stored
in as a roast or I can just jump to that
one region or memory scan across and get
all the answers that I need and then
hand it back to the execution or whoever
else needs it this is also where you're
typically going to use the tuple at a
time iterator model and we will discuss
this more in a few more weeks but
basically how we're going to have the
execution engine access to pools this
approach is ideal because again I'm just
jumping to the starting location every
single tuple and handing back that chunk
of memory to whatever operate execute or
neat needs it all right this is also
could be really good for insert heavy
workloads which is more company which is
you know what you see a lot in
transactional workloads like every
single time I log in I insert a new
record to say this is when this person
logged in every time I place a new order
in Amazon I insert a new order record I
inserted all the items that I bought so
in in a row store this is this is super
fast because I can just jump to some
memory location there's some free slot
in my table and there's right out
contiguously all the attributes
so everything I've already said before
the avenge starts fast for inserts and
updates deletes good for queries they
need the entire table this one we could
ignore for now but where this is gonna
be problematic for is when you do
analytical workloads where you want to
scan large segments of the table and you
only want a subset of the attributes
like if I want to compute what is the
most what was the average price of an
item bought from anybody who lives in
the city of Pittsburgh I only need to
access you know the city field and the
price that they bought the some item for
I don't need all the other attributes
for for that tuple so therefore if I'm
doing a roast or then that's me wasteful
because I'm react sesang chunks of
memory that I don't actually need and I
have to keep jumping over and over again
to find the right offset of the atrophy
I want for every single tuple so this is
with a column store the or the DSM
approach solves the idea here is that
for a single attribute in a tuple and
we're gonna store store all the values
for every single tuple contiguously in
memory now my just might not be for you
know entire block of data it might does
not have all that the just that B values
for that single attribute we could have
all the atras together but internally
but always when we store it as a column
store
this is great for read-only queries
because you can scan over large portions
of the of the table at a time but only
accessing a subset of the attributes
alright so this is the stuff we've
already covered so we'll get better
compression through a column store that
we'll cover on Wednesday and for four
point queries and updates this becomes
now more expensive potentially because
now you're have to take the tuple that
you need to insert or update and break
it apart into its individual attributes
and do multiple memory rights to update
all done so the history of of column
stores is kind of interesting so column
stores are super common now any new OLAP
system that's been developed and
released in the last ten years in the
last decade will be using a column store
if they're not been in there they don't
know what they're doing and it's not
worth your time to talk to talk to that
prime but it what knows what seems sort
of obvious now wasn't always the case
so back in the 1970s the first
implication the known implication of a
column store system
was this thing called Kanter that came
out of the Swedish defense division it
wasn't actually a database system as we
know it today was more like this sort of
bat processing system but would organize
the data as columns in the 1980s there
was an actual paper paper that
formalized the idea of what a comstor
database looks like but the first sort
of known invitation was sybase IQ which
came out it was an in-memory accelerator
for Sybase the idea was you had your
regular sized ASC database system then
you bought side by side queue to sit in
front of it
so if analytical queries show up they
would run they would run on that copy of
the data so they were using what is
called a fractured mirror approach which
I'll cover in a few more slides but
basically you still have the roast or
and then this thing sat in front of it
made the analytical queries go faster
I've heard some horror stories about
this in the 1990s that it was hard it
never worked correctly but this it's
still round today and this is what this
is what they were using or even connect
to with an S AP Hannam in 2000s this one
the common story idea really took off
three main ones in the space where
vertical vector wise and Monet DB vector
wise was an improved a memory version of
Monet DB this later got renamed or got
bought by Acton and then got renamed to
vector and it's still around today and
this is actually overly good if you
benchmark it it does still really well
there's certain aspects of vector wise
that we'll cover later on in the
semester
Monet DB is still round as well they are
it came out of CWI the same sort of
school that BB like these guys early in
this space as well and like I said now
everyone recognizes the advantages of a
column store and the widespread all
right so the paper had you guys read the
reason why I chose it because it was
sort of showing you that how to do
updates and support hybrid workloads on
a column store right so in our system we
still support transactions we still
support doing updates and as well as
also doing analyticals analytical
operations but we're designed to be a
column store and so this particular
paper or an assistant work Casper was
meant to show you how you could still
have maintained a column store and still
get good support for otx execution so
the paper discusses
some high-level design decision you need
to be mindful about when you're building
columns for a system to be
identification is how to find tuples in
the fixed length date array hi actually
you're gonna organize the the data that
you're storing in your columns and then
the update policy and buffer location we
sort of already covered these a little
bit when we talk about nbcc it's
basically time where do you if you have
a delta store where do you actually
store these things and then how do you
how do you apply them later so I want to
focus on the first two and this is also
and then we'll then talk about how you
the different approaches for building a
hybrid store where you have a row strut
plus a column store so Casper is a pure
column store that supports transactions
but then we'll talk about things like
the factory mirror approach for storing
roasters and column stores together so
the first issues that we do figure out
how we're actually going to identify our
tuples or how can we get to the starting
location for an attribute again we
assume that all the values will be fixed
length the varchar' stuff is shortened
of every linked data pool but but at
least the pointer itself will be fixed
length and so if everything's always the
same length then you don't need to
actually store any additional emission
to identify what tuple you're looking at
you just use the implicit offset of
where you're looking at in memory to say
this is the identifier for the tuple so
if I want the the second tuple or the
tuple number two in my table I know how
to do the arithmetic to say well what is
the each type of each of these columns
and I want this location so I know how
to multiply the size of the attribute
personally the starting location I want
to jump into to get the values for this
tuple and I can do the same thing for
all the other columns in some systems
however they can't do this so they don't
want to do this and instead they
actually store implicit or explicitly
the tuple identifier for every single
attribute that you're storing in a
column store so for the column a right
for the first people I'll store it's two
pi D and the second tuple
I stored to PI D and so forth and this
is her like a bastardized version of a
column store because you're not getting
all the advantages of doing the fixed
month arithmetic you're just wasting it
for space to store this yes
this question is are the office still
fixed I think so
why so I think Oracle used to do this
because they were sort of grafting on a
poor man's columnstore into the system
right they were trying to keep the
roasts or execution engine but but
operate on columns so they had to embed
these extra things in the newer versions
of a comp store they don't do this
everyone does does this but some systems
actually do do this but it's bad idea
you don't like if you have everything
fixed length then you don't need to yes
this question if you need to sort your
column you still need these IDs we'll
get to that in two more slides but yeah
so like if I sort the column sorry um if
I sort the column here I could just sort
a and not affect BC and D assume you
have a way to like for a given tube
identifier to jump to that exact offset
for each column I think this is why
Oracle did it Vertica does sorting where
when you sort one column that then
cascades to all the other columns so
that going across horizontally lately
this might my illustration here you're
looking at the exact same tuple most
systems don't don't do that pre-sorting
though all right actually this is this
is this is the next next topic right so
next question is how we actually
organize data when we have to make
changes or add new entries so the most
common one is to do insertion order so
we just find any slot that's free in our
in our blocks and we just insert our
tuple in there so there's no locality
there's no ordering of the attributes
it's just sort of sort of random it
isn't you don't necessarily always have
to go in like from beginning to end
in our system we actually we do a
compare and swap on a random location in
a bitmap and try to find the first free
location which may not be the first free
slot but at least in that case you know
you're not having threads all try to get
in inserting into the same location at
the same time the other approach is what
he was referring to is when you with you
insert the tube
into the the columns based on some
ordering scheme it's again vertical is
the most famous one that does this but
this is agree problematic we'll see in
the next slide because if now I have a
bunch of showing up and I need to
enforce that ordering I don't want to
pay the penalty of having to reshuffle
things every single time because that
would be expensive and then the last
approach is from the Kasper paper where
you're going to break up the blocks into
ranges and according to some
partitioning scheme and then within each
block it doesn't need to be sorted but
sort of globally there's this what they
call a shallow index please will jump me
to the location that will have the data
that you're looking for within a
particular range so let's look at the
first one so this is just insertion
order so this is my column store I want
to start this tuple so I just find
whatever the first free slot is for my
tuple manageable and it's add my entry
there right DZ and when this thing gets
full width then I create a new block and
just keep inserting starting into that
so then now if I want to do the sorted a
table the say I take all these columns
and I sort them according to this scheme
so I'm going to first sort a sort all
the tuples by a ascending then by be
descending and then by see a sending so
again we need to have the fixed length
all set for every single tuple be the
same so if I'm looking at four tuple for
right I want to be able to jump into B
at this location and I should see the
attribute for B for the same tuple so
now if I if I sort say I want to sort on
a I have to then propagate that sort
order over to the other columns right so
so I start with a I sort these by this
value but now within for B right honest
to here's all the atras of being sorted
it started all the a shoes with a equals
one and now I sort them according to my
sold over for B for B and then within
that I have now the sort ordering within
C so again now this guarantees that
again if I'm looking at this as tuple
here I'm going across and seeing that
the all the attrex for my given tuple
let me take a guess why you want to do
this sorting
yes she says secondary and indices of
what do you mean so he said if I jump to
a certain place on column B but but but
here this case here I sort it on a right
so if I have a predicate that says find
me all the tuples where a equals a
equals a 1 then I can just jump to this
and scan down and then once I see a - I
know there's never - give me another a 1
and I'm done but in case of B if I find
me all the two boys we're beetles B - I
can't just look in this region I got you
got to scan the whole thing right so
she's saying well once I get here so I'm
looking for B - once I get here now I
see a B 1 I know there's not gonna be
another B 1 for this region a and then
now but now I need to know how to jump
to the next region just like you grab
all the ones from B 1 B 1 then you got
the first one to be to go to second to
those are all relatively so it's not
really second the index would make the
scan go faster right but might like
assuming this is if you're doing
partition right if you know what the
boundaries are so if I if I this is the
boundary for a for a equals a equals a 1
so if I scan looking for the b-2s if I
scan the to p2 and then I see the B 1 I
know there's never going to be another B
2 after this so then if I knew what the
next partition is I could just jump down
here but that's yeah that'd be the one
benefit yes
Furby bell for a yes so we'll see this
actually the answer I was looking for
will see this on Wednesday we're
actually beaver to compress this way
better if everything's sorted so the
most common one common kind of sorting
you do is called run length encoding so
say like this only we only have two
values for B it's b2 or p1 so that I
said of sorting copies of b2 over and
over again I can say I have b2 twice two
times and I b1 you know one time two
time three times right this is like
think of like male-female assuming that
you just have two to two sexes everybody
is either one or the other so if I have
a million students and if I sort them on
on on their sex then I guess a here's
here's you know five hundred thousand
males a five hundred of females and I
just need to store just that that that
small encoding not every single instance
of the value will see this next class so
Vertica does this Vertigo's the most the
strongest opponent of doing sorting they
call these projections by the idea is
that i sort everything on a and then
within the boundary of a value of a then
i sort for the next column so forth sort
of you're narrowing the window okay yeah
yeah vertical does not have any people
treat indexes they only have sort of
projections all right so now if i the
problems gonna be if I keep everything
globally sorted like this if now I want
to insert this guy here well he wants to
go this new attribute wants to go in
this position here but there's some
other attribute it's similar to being
stored there now and in my case here a 2
is less than a 3 but I'm sorting on a so
I need to move these guys down before I
can go ahead and insert my people ready
and that would obviously be expensive to
do on the fly if I have a billion tuples
and my guy lands at the beginning of my
column if I have to shift everything
over or even within a block this would
be expensive to do and this is what the
Casper one is trying to solve so the
idea is that you're gonna have this
index above your your columns and you're
gonna split things into these partitions
based on ranges and then now what will
happen is when I do an insert
I just need to make sure that my my -
boy I'm trying to insert lands into the
right range that doesn't need to be
sorted within that range as long as I
have space that I can put it right in
there and then now I can easily find all
the data that I want when I'm doing so
I'm doing 10 do point queries if I have
to do sequential scans or long scans
like an OLAP queries then I ignore the
index and I just rip through the columns
anyway although you can use them to
guide guide the scan search so this is
an additional component of Casper or
when they have this offline algorithm
but they're gonna examine the workload
of Sam in the data set and then try to
come up with an optimal partitioning
scheme such that for for four tuples
that are accessed through analytical
operations they have larger partitions
because you're not likely gonna update
them and have to do reshuffle things and
then for the for the the data that's hot
it can be updated very soon then you
want smaller partitions so that the you
can find them more quickly using the
shell index all right so let's go the
annex table here so again we have our
column store they have these logic these
partition markers they don't have to be
physically partitioned in their example
they show it sort of just seems that I
and continue to space and these
demarcation points but obviously you
don't want it
you're not gonna allocate you know in
some giant array so this is a still be
organizes blocks but the important thing
to also point out too is that these are
very length partitions and they can grow
and shrink based on how the tuples are
accessed so if I wanted to start this
tuple here it's gonna go into this
partition because we're trying to sort
in a - and I have space to store a -
right here that's fine
that's really fast and we're done but
now if I want to start this other tuple
here and when I start another tuple has
a - well that needs to go into this
position but now within my partition I
don't have any more space so they use
this technique called ripple insert the
idea is like you how I understood is
like you drop a pebble into a lake and
so you see the ripples propagate you're
gonna start moving things around going
going from one partition to the next so
for this one here we want to insert our
tuple into this one this partition but
we don't have any space so we need to
steal some space from the petition below
us so we need to move this guy to the
end of its partition and then now I just
slide down my demarcation point alright
and readjust my range partitions in like
my shallow index and now I can assert
that
people now maybe the case that when we
try to move this tuple to a new position
this partition didn't have more space so
therefore we had to go to now steal from
the next partition and so for that but
that's sort of ripple effect but the
idea here is in best-case scenario I can
assert into my partition and I don't the
move anything around worst case scenario
I have to reshuffle every single
partition but in practice you don't want
to say how often should occur but like
in practice like you shouldn't have to
reorganize the entire database certainly
way less than we had to do it if we were
doing that global and sorted things I
shouldn't beginning yes this is like
sorting based on one - we only know you
can still sort on different attributes
it's just this seems we're not the reefs
or on B and C if I'm sorting a multiple
address so if the paper does wanna give
explanation to us
this thing could this thing could be
multi at multiple attributes and all
it's gonna say is this is the range of
sum this is the range domain that's
being represented by a partition and
that could be almost sure it could be in
a single attribute within a partition
though I don't have the resource re I'm
not keeping these things sorted this is
just telling you hey the data you're
looking for is gonna be in his range but
when you land here go figure out where
it is and again if it's only TP then I
don't want this thing to be huge because
then I got a scan about two columns a
fun exactly what I wanted but if my if
my partition is bounded too much but if
my partition is smaller then the
probability I'm gonna find what I need
it'll be faster because there's less day
to look at again they had this offline
algorithm to kind of to resize these
things based on how things are being
accessed okay
so I've already said this but this one
is sort of reiterate again in for these
H tap workloads for these hybrid
workloads there's a meanness diktter
between hot data and cold data the hot
data are things that just were just
recently inserted just recently updated
and just recently accessed through an
OTP transaction and then we had the rest
is me all this
whole data which are things that we need
them there to do scans and analytics on
but it's very unlikely that we're gonna
have to go ahead and update them so if
we are aware of this and this is what
the caspere thing is trying to exploit
then instead of it maybe just resizing
partitions we could also reorganize or
store the data in different ways
such that the hot data is in a row store
because that'll be fast forms isn't for
transactions and it over time as it
cools off we move it to a column store
because that's what we want to store a
cool data so this is what the hybrid
storage model approach is so I would say
that also up front about this this is
how we originally did peloton this is
what I thought used to be the right idea
I actually I actually now think that the
pure column store where they're doing
the Casper approach or the the hyper
purge that we do that's actually a
better way to go it's not worth the
engineering overhead to have this all
this these extra storage managers in
place to make this work but at least
know how it works because a lot of
systems actually do this so the idea is
that we're gonna have a single logical
database instance where underneath the
covers were to store a hot and cold you
know differently so I'll call create
table and any time I do a lookup I see
one table but underneath the covers the
database system is managing different is
managing different tuples differently so
again the hot data will be in row store
the cold data will be in a column store
so there's two approaches to do this
from engineering perspective the first
is that you actually maintain two
completely separate excuse managers in a
storage manager in your system and then
you have something that stitched
together the answer up above right and
then the other approach is what we did
in peloton is that you have a single
execution and a single Storage Manager
that can operate on both row store and
column store data at the same time right
that you have this sort of indirection
layer that knows how to read the data
from the two different models and can
unify them in a single engine so the
separate execution engine is the most
common one because what mostly happens
here is that people take to existing
database systems and they slap them
together and they build a little
middleware thing on top of that to unify
them so there are two ways to do this
would be fractured mirrors which is the
Oracle
IBM or doing and then the delta store
approach is what hana used to do where
that sort of looks like the when we talk
about the time travel table remember
they had like the the main data table
and the time travel table and the main
data table always had the oldest one and
the time travel table had the the latest
one that's because the main table was
the column store and then the the time
travel table was the delta store so I'll
go through both of these so the
fractured marijuana's Gantt we basically
have a complete copy of of the database
but now stored is a column store right
so it's like a mirrored copy but it's
called fractured meaning like I broke
the mirror because I reorganized the
rows now to be a columns so the row
store will always be the primary storage
of the database all my reads and writes
are gonna go here all my transactions
will update this portion and then in the
background through some process I will
then copy the data out convert it to a
column store and store it in the mirror
and then now when any analytical query
shows up if they only need to touch data
that is bounded within the column store
then that gonna route it over here and I
run more efficiently
yes this question is there Seema is this
data could be a bit stale depends so
sometimes you can and sometimes
sometimes you want to and sometimes you
don't have to you don't you don't want
to do this so if you if it can't be
stale then when analytic where he shows
up you need to recognize oh you need
data that I don't have in the comma yet
so I need to also need to execute that
query on the on the row store and then
put it put it back together so Oracle
does this
it's more like they figure out what
portion of the query needs to run on the
the row store and what portion these run
in the column store and they'll run them
both and then put it all together sybase
IQ didn't as far as I know didn't do
that it was sort of separate from the
roast or you couldn't didn't know we
didn't know about the roast or other
than getting updates from it so when an
annular quote if you ran an ethical
query on sybase IQ it would only touch
this I wouldn't go back get the rest of
the data from this whereas Orko Orko
combines everything I so his statement
is stay honest is okay I think he
brought this up earlier like in what
scenario would you need to have like you
know serializable execution of an
analytical query with up-to-date
information people people want that
that's it it's an people don't want
enough that Oracle decided to do it but
the important thing to point out that in
case of Oracle's case for there in
memory columnstore which the guy beat up
on a Wednesday this thing is ephemeral
so like if this thing if you crash a
comeback or stop this isn't turn it back
on
like it'll BRE propagate the the calm
store by reading from the rows store so
so again all the updates have to go here
this is the primary storage this thing
is propagated lazily yes so his question
is mem Siegel doing this know mem sequel
would do that the delta store approach
and so the way this one works is that
again you have this like Delta stores
row storing things like there was a
pending out like update so log right and
then over to actually the newer version
of M sequel might do this the over into
the new version does this the Overtoun
did the old version is that you call
crate table and you would say I want to
be a row store or a column store but
then if you say all right I want to make
this table now be a row store or sorry
if it start off as a roaster ah now I'm
like in a column store I'm gonna dump it
out and load it back in right so like I
couldn't take the data from a roast or
table and have it seamlessly converted
to a column store Ida have two separate
logical tables the newer version
actually does this where you apply the
updates to this Delta store and
tended to the the columnstore right so
again this you had the same issue that
we had on refraction mirrors if now I
have a query that needs touch data on
both sides then I need a way to execute
on the rostral plus per column store the
now if you're doing a BCC you sort of
like with the Delta store you kind of
get the same thing for free like you
already need to be able to traverse back
in the Virgin chain and find the right
version of it given tuple and that
essentially becomes the same thing as
the Delta store it's just we're going
from in our system we're doing news to
order start an awesome new us so when we
go look in our column as always the
newest version but we still have a way
to go back and reconcile the right or
version by replaying updates in the
dullest or MMC quarters in general from
mem sequel statement is in M sequel are
these things ever flushed out the disk
as far as I know no other than in the
log right but that's that's sever from
this so the the reason I brought up that
so that MVCC stuff is like in this going
back to this keys here the fractured
mirrors you basically build two database
systems you need one that operates on
row stored data and then you need a
column store one looking execution
engine that knows how to efficiently
operate on on you know columnar data
that's gonna be different than how you
do things in a row store data you have
basically maintaining two separate
engines this one here it's a little less
work because again if you're doing FEC
you still need to you need to how to
handle this anyway
this is actually I think the better
approach you know whether or not the the
MVCC approach that we're doing now is is
the same thing but whether this is
constitutive fool in our system with a
delta change the virgins constitute a
full ductile store that's debatable I
think this is just semantics but I think
this is the better approach because now
you're not having this engineering
monstrosity of trying to maintain two
super database systems together right so
with peloton what we did was we were
trying to be clever and we were trying
to have both the row store and a column
store together but
then we have an execution engine above
that that knew how to operate on both of
them and we did this by having this
abstraction layer that we call tiles
that knew how to just operate on these
tiles and didn't know underneath the
covers whether it was a roast or a
columnstore and then the access methods
for accessing tiles of a different type
knew how to put things together access
them efficiently so again the idea was
that we would look at our data see how
the transactions and little queries were
accessing them recognize which regions
were hot which regions were cold we take
the hot data store as a row store and
then take the cold data and store it as
a column store and then now again when I
ask you two queries I know how to you
know put things together as needed so
I'm sure one graph of work basically
everything always starts out as a row
store right so if you're doing a bunch
of doing a work lower your new scans
insert scans inserts so it's basically a
lot o to Bo that polo to B so forth so
with the road layout the scans will be
slower the the inserts will be faster if
you're doing a columnar layout the these
are the the scans are faster but the
inserts are slower because now I'm
breaking up a tuple from strong into
multiple locations and the idea what the
hybrid layout was everything starts off
as a row store but then over time as as
you start doing more scans in the data
gets colder it gets converted to a
column store and then now that speeds up
the scan operations so the rows are just
just as fast as a row store because it
is a row store but then the scans get
faster so we ditched all this because it
was an engineering nightmare and the one
students couldn't understand what the
hell we were actually doing but then
like having to write test cases and
performance regressions for this hybrid
thing was was became a huge became a big
problem for us so we ditched all this
kept it more simple and just went with a
clean column store I think that's
actually the better approach and whether
you have the shallow index that the the
Casper guys are doing above that that's
debatable I don't like the idea of
having additional background
[Music]
background mechanisms to go and try to
reorganize data for you by looking at
the workload I think that should also be
centralized and for this implementation
we didn't have that yet okay all right
so that was kind of rushed at the end
but like the main takeaway again is like
you can do a bunch of it ways to do row
source and column stores together I
argue that at least for the work list
we're looking at I think a pure column
store is a way to go with MVCC but a lot
of times you're gonna encounter the
fractured mirror approach that that's
pretty common for all the big major
vendors okay all right
I want to quickly talk about catalogs so
we're not got time to do demos but
catalogs are super interesting remember
we talked about this at the very
beginning like how do we figure out the
layout of a tuple had renew out of jump
to different offsets well when you call
create table we store the metadata that
you specify it when you created that
table and a catalog and then when we go
access the tool will read the catalog
and figure out all right what is the
layout of of our data so the tricky
thing about catalogs though is that we
actually want to eat our own dog food
meaning we don't want to have a separate
database the main to maintain just a
store a catalog we want to store the
catalog in our own database all right in
our own tables but now it's like a
chicken for the egg problem like I need
to store metadata about tables in the
catalog but I need to store my catalog
in tables right so we have to have this
specialized code in order to bootstrap
the catalogs the Post best one is
actually kind of interesting they take
the they basically have this DSL that
then convert into cuc for C code for for
doing this bootstrapping and basically
inserting all the things you need to
have in order for the catalogs to turn
on I'm not aware what other systems do
because I can actually see the source
code in Postgres and the earlier
versions of my sequels like my sequel
5.7 they just stored that the catalog is
the flat files on disk which i think is
it's the wrong thing to do you want to
store everything in as regular tables
because now you get all the acid
guarantees that you would expect for
regular tuples in data tables so let's
go through some examples of how to do
schema changes and you'll see now how
some things are be easier if you're a
row store and some things be harder if
your column store and vice versa
so if I add a column then I basically
need to scan through every single tube
from a row store and copy the tuple into
a new location and with inserted with
the new column in it some database
systems don't let you insert the column
into any location like you can only sort
of insert it at the end the Postgres
does this so it's like my Siebel you
could specify exactly where you want it
where you want to insert it because
basically what they're doing is they're
copying every single tuple from the old
schema to the new schema for for a
column store potentially it's super easy
yes question you did this sorry Oh calm
sort super easy because I just make a
new column right and I don't need to
modify any it overcomes now it depends
how organized my blocks
but in general it's you know this is way
easier than a row store because I don't
have to touch any existing data for drop
columns same thing well if I'm gonna go
and take the the column out to save
memory then I again go through
everything to go and copy it over in
some systems you can just mark them as
deprecated like Postgres I'll do this if
I drop a column it doesn't actually it
dropped just record them the catalog
that has been dropped you know to ignore
it any query comes along tries to read
it but physically it's still there and
then at some point when they won the
garbage collector for MVCC they'll go
ahead and compact it for column store
again if I'm storing my columns as
separately in memory then I just go
ahead and to free it up and I'm done and
I don't doesn't affect anybody else
change column like if you change the
column type or change constraints in the
column depending on what the change I'm
doing I may have to scan through and
look at every single tuple before I can
make that change again and then pending
on whether I'm a roaster our column
store I could lead the the data as it
exists or I could I had to go change
things like if I go from a 32-bit
integer to it to a 16-bit integer I have
to scan through to make sure that I'm
not gonna have out of bound errors if I
do that change but now maybe I don't
need to actually copy everything and
make a 16-bit column I can leave it as
32 bits some later point I'll clean it
up but you know the conversion is just
sort of done at a logical level indexes
are super tricky this one I don't think
we had time to discuss the semester this
is I will say this is something that
people have tried for I think for two
years now in this class we've tried to
always do create indexes we can create
indexes now again in our system if you
call create index before you load any
table data in the table that's fine the
one you insert data then will update the
index it's going through and populating
an index on already created table that's
when things get tricky because if you
want to do this without blocking answers
because I I could just lock the whole
table scan that puppet-like my index but
you know that could take a long time so
I want it there's ways to do populations
of indexes without having to block
everything while you do this and this is
something that people have tried two
times in this class with Nick success
I'd anybody fun to try this this
semester again drop index is super easy
right you just drop it logically from
the catalog then in the background some
point you know that nobody else is
looking at it and go ahead and drop this
and this we have this deferred event
framework in our system now there's
garbage collection for any kind of
memory app we allocate in the system and
we can handle this already all right
the last one it will be sequences and so
sequences are auto increment numbers or
like the serial key and Postgres think
i'm like a column i have an attribute
where every time I insert a tuple if I
don't specify a value there's some
counter where they're going to add one
to it and then that way if the next
tuple gets inserted it'll have you know
the counter plus one and so forth and so
what's super interesting about them is
that they don't follow the same
transactional guarantees or an isolation
protections did you get from regular
transactions all right we're gonna store
them in the catalog this counter but if
I insert a tuple the counter gets
increased and then I roll back my
transaction the tuple will get rolled
back but the calendar always still goes
up and so what needs to happen is you
actually have to log that to disk
because that way if I crash come back I
need to know where that counter left off
even though the transaction that
modified it may have not yet gotten
written a disk so this is actually
something that students did do in the
old system which is a lot of fun and I
think this
this be good to do again in this class
right
there's obviously optimizations we could
look at from like post grass and other
systems like maybe you only update the
counter on disk forever you know for a
batch of values like every 10 right that
to disk then you hand out new values in
memory and then only when you hit you
hit the upper bound then you increment
the counter in the catalog again okay
we're out of time so I can't do a demo
but we do it out the closet if you're
interesting this kind of stuff all right
so just to finish up so as I said we
abandon the hybrid storage model I think
simplicity for at least for this case is
this part of the system is a is a big
win and the right way to go the the
Delta of versioning we would use under
MVCC plus a column store is equivalent
to sort of the the different approaches
that we saw before catalogs are really
hard this is actually something we got
right in our system now I'm actually
happy to say this
we followed the Postgres schema or the
layout of catalogs and put everything
stored is tables so we get things we get
all the transactional guarantees you
would normally get for tuples so there's
a lot of cool things we can do now that
our catalogs are transactional but we
can cover that more when we talk about
project 3 ok any questions bank it in
the side part what is this
[Music]
here called the okay cuz I'm og I stood
down with the test team hi you look and
it was go grab me a 40 just to get my
buzz song cuz I needed just a little
more kick like a fish after just one
slip put it to my lips and rip the top
off they pull the truck the same as
hotdogs and my heart wants me to say I'm
nice to take a seat I celebrate