[Music]
[Applause]
for today's class we're going to
continue our discussion on multi-version
cooker treat all and so last class we
spent time talking about the four major
design decisions when you build an NBC
database system right Kurt's your
protocol even though control is in the
name over designing again this is how
we're gonna create transactions the
Virgen storage basically every time we
update a tuple where do we actually
store that fit new physical version
garbage collection cleaning up all
versions and then index management
basically how do we keep track of what
are the secondary indexes point to
really either point to the actual
physical version the head of the version
chain or D pointing to some some logic
identifier so for today's class we're
now going to go into more detail and
look at real world implementations of
modern nbcc systems and what will happen
is we'll do this in the context of the
four design decisions that we talked
about last class but we'll spend a
little more time talking about how
they're actually going to do the first
one they actually concur to a protocol
itself all right how they're going to
coordinate transactions but then as we
go along they'll also be other aspects
of these database systems that we'll
cover that are good ideas potentially
for having a high performance MVCC
system that doesn't fit exactly into the
the four design decisions that we talked
about before and so the way we'll go
through and perceive the discussion will
first talk start with Microsoft
hackathon because that was sort of the
first implementation of a modern
in-memory MVCC system in 2011 2012 and
that'll serve as the baseline for us
understanding how these other systems
implement MVCC all right so if you
understand this they're gonna say are
how can we tweak tweak it or do
different things are add add additional
things through that nbcc implementation
that can improve what hackathon original
opposed okay again so hackathons we
focused on OLTP these two here hyper and
hana we focus on old TV was OLAP and
then we'll come back with cicada to
discuss how we do or how to do old to be
again all right all right so who here
has actually ever heard a heck of tom
for that hasn't hung around me right
that's nice okay so like it is it
started off as a research project at
Microsoft and then now action ships in
sequel server today but like when you
read the documentation they don't call
it hackathon I think it just called a
memory storage but if you if you look at
the papers I refer to everything as you
know this project has hackathon so
hecatomb project started in 2008 at
Microsoft as a way to extend the the
lifetime of of sequel server so at this
point 2008 sequel server was 20 years
old and so they started the project to
say well what cleaning what can we do to
improve the performance and modernize
the system such that Mikus our sequel
server is still relevant you know 20
years from now my sequel server it makes
it mix Microsoft bit of money so they
said you know how do we keep that gravy
train going 20 years in the future so
they decided to work on how do you
actually build a new OTP engine
specifically for you know for the CI
server ecosystem so if you don't know
the history of sequel server in 1919 93
92 they actually bought a license to
Sybase and then they support it to
Windows NT and then a little bit after
that then they bought the source code
license from Sybase they end up working
it and at this point they've rewritten
everything from scratch I'm sure all
over again but there are still remnants
of sequels or sigh basis influence in
sequel server today like sequel server
uses T sequel which is a variant of
sequel that's what Sybase used and
certainly now today sequel server is
still considered a this is considered a
state of the art system whereas sigh
basis is more or less in in maintenance
mode ASAP bought Sybase they still make
a shitload of money on it because we had
the the guy that sort of leads the
Sybase project give a guest lecture in
this class last year but you know it's
there no star was saying like oh I'm
gonna build my new system based on
Sybase right nobody does that
all right so they took to start this
project Microsoft got to very family's
database people at Microsoft Paul Larsen
was an MSR he's sort of a famous
database person who's been around for a
while like he invented linear hashing in
the 1980s
and much indeed much work a deck Mike
Zwilling was actually one of the main
people they hired at the very beginning
when they started sequence over to help
them port the Sybase code over to
Windows NT and he worked at unity of his
content on a very influential
influential system called sure
so they got basically the two best
people to lead this project so unlike
Hana Hecate on cicada and a bunch of
other systems we'll talk about this
semester instead of building a brand-new
databases from scratch for the hackathon
project they had to make sure that it
could integrate with the existing sequel
server ecosystem this is sort of more of
a business decision right you have you
know millions millions of people are
running sequel server today there's all
those tools and all these visualization
frameworks and things built on top of
Siebel server that you want to keep
around because that sort of helped you
know help sell the product so if you
threw it all the way from scratch and
build hackathons as a new standalone
system you basically have to re-implant
all that ecosystem so for this reason
they had to make it run aside as an
engine in in in single server the way it
works today is like when you call create
table you can pass a flag at the end
that says in memory and that then ends
up using the the hackathon engine
another interesting thing about their
design decisions they're going to make
is that part of the reason they chose
MVCC and the approach that they're going
to they're pursuing is that they want to
be able to support all all to be all
possible o2b workloads with the same
predictable performance so we didn't
talk about I don't think we talked about
each door of volte be in the intro class
but this is a system that I helped build
when I was in grad school and the way
this works is that you have a single
threaded execution engine that can
actually one transaction at a time of
course you paralyze this across multiple
cores but now that one transaction is
super fast because there's no contention
you don't require locks or latches
because nobody else is running at the
same time I can run almost at bare metal
speed but the problem as soon as I touch
multiple cores our data across multiple
cores then at the hold locks and then
things slow down so some of your
transactions will be insanely fast other
transactions will be super slow and in
the Microsoft world that's a hard
product to sell because basically you're
saying hey go buy our new product give
us a lot of money for some of your
transactions it'll go really great
90% your transactions one run really
fast Kember sending your transactions
will run really slow like you can't sell
that but no one would buy that
hey example I like users like you try to
sell a car say hey this is the fastest
car it's gonna have great fuel economy
it's gonna be it's me you know you
should buy this but oh by the way 10%
are you over to get cancer when you
drive it no one would buy that car right
so for this reasons they they're not
gonna get the sort of moves optimal
performance relative to something like a
shoe or volte be but it'll least be
predictable and this is over at what
mvcc's can provide us so at its core
again it's gonna be doing its can use
time stamps to determine the ordering of
transactions and what virgins are
visible to it but unlike in last class
when we talked about times kept ordering
and and so base MVCC transactions are
now going to have to time stamps so when
we talk about time same ordering again
the transaction gets assigned a
timestamp when it shows up and OCC you
get a timestamp when you validate and
and so in this world you're gonna have
both you're gonna get assigned a
timestamp when you start and then you'll
get another commit timestamp when you
have to pass validation and then we have
to use that again you're using the
information to figure out what is actual
what is actually visible to us all the
two posts are also going to contain two
timestamps we have to begin in the end
and so the begin timestamp is just like
as it was before where it's gonna
represent the begin timestamp of the
actor transaction that created it or the
commit times commit time stamp of the
transaction that committed that
committed that created it and then
what's gonna happen as well see in the
next slide this thing will have to go
back and change because we'll start with
this we create a new version we can
populate it with our begin timestamp for
our transaction but then when we commit
now we have the commit timestamp and now
we gotta go back and update all our
versions and replace the timestamp and
I'll show you how the everything still
works out and we you know there's no
phantoms and there's no issues even
though we're changing timestamps
the end timestamp for a tuple is little
tricky so this is going to be begin
timestamp of the after transaction that
create it created the next version in
the Virgin chain affinity meaning that
it's the latest version and that you
know there's nothing else comes after it
or the commit time Stan
of the committed transaction that
created the next version right then that
invalidated the current one and then it
points to the next one so big and this
one's a bit more confusing but I make
more sense when we when we show an
example okay all right so say we have a
simple table again so Hecate on is doing
a pen only storage oldest to newest and
the Virgin chain and say for this one we
have we have just you know single with
logical tuple for two virgins a1 and a2
so our transaction comes along all right
and at at very beginning we have to give
it a timestamp so it's begin timestamp
in this example here is 25 so now we're
going to do a read on a so we'll land
somehow at this at the head of the
Virgin chain at a1 here how we got there
it doesn't matter whether it's an index
or a sequential scan for our purposes
here we don't care so now we're going to
see whether this version is visible to
us so again we have to go look at the
begin and the end timestamp that tells
us the visibility of our tuple in this
case here 25 is greater than 20 so we
know that this this thing was comes
before us or comes before our our
snapshot for our transaction so then now
we followed the version change pointer
and now we land here in this case here
20 25 is in between 20 and affinity so
we know that this is the version that's
visible to us and this is what we'll
read so that's the same as before as
last class okay all right let's see now
we won't do a write or name so same
thing somehow we land at the head of the
virgin chain we know that this is the
this is the logical we want to update so
we want to find where should we install
our version so in this case here again
25 is greater than 20 so we know we
don't want it this is not the head of
the bird this is not the version we want
to pen afterwards come down here 20 to
infinity so we know at this point here
that this is this is the most recent
committed version and then because this
is infinity and our pointer is null we
know that nobody else is trying to
create a new version after us right now
all right so now we need to install our
new version so for this one we need
careful how we're gonna do ordering
because unlike last class where we had
this sort of take a lock on the whole
tuple and and then do our updates for
this one we want to do everything as
compare and swap so we want to avoid
having to lock this
thing what will they make a change so
the first thing we need to do is append
our new version right it's a pen only
storage we just find a free slot in our
table space and then we claim it and
then we can now install our new version
but now you'll see with that for our
begin timestamp we're doing something
special here so I'm having this little
marker here say transaction at 25 so
what does that mean so the hackathon is
going instead of having a instead of
having us sort of special transaction ID
to say this is this represents the
timestamp of an uncommitted transaction
they're just going to use the begin
timestamp to record that the that this
is the version that was created by this
transaction for both committed and
uncommitted and so what they're going to
do is they're gonna use the most
significant bit and set that to 1 to
mean that the transaction at this time
stamp is uncommitted so I'm representing
that by having the prefix transaction in
front of it right this is just for
illustration purposes but underneath the
cover is what they're really doing it's
just flipping this one bit let me take I
guess why you want to do this
ah so she's saying because this thinks
that the one we know that nobody else
can ever have every time to him that
bigger than us no all right so when we
do the comparison were actually gonna
ignore that one yes help me avoid a
cascading abort no Pakistan's gonna
support spectra to read so we still have
cascading boards so he says this you
could use this to prevent you from
reading something that's not committed
yet by by checking this and they say I
don't want to read this so again their
respective the reads so you want to be
able to read things that are uncommitted
because you're going to assume they
transaction that you read from that
modified this thing is not gonna abort
so you what you want to go ahead and
allow us she says you can read your
other things you updated yeah but I
don't need the bit to figure that out
these are all she good this is actually
very interesting yes go so you're saying
if you if you read this and you see the
one then you know that you read
something that was uncommitted Yama Sara
yes
that's very close yes he says they go
through the constructor and recognize
the other thing this thing is unused and
go ahead and clean it up but not unused
we put something in there he's not
committed yes
yeah but why well what is the one
actually do for us you guys are very
close he says make a light screen now no
she said recovery now all right so well
this is Oliver this is good because this
is like I've eaten paper
oh of course yeah do it this way and
then you guys are coming it from not
having all this prior knowledge so it's
interesting to see you like what you
guys think actually matter
so what we're actually gonna do with
this is that we need at some point we
need to figure out because he was very
close this somewhat we need to figure
out did we read something that was not
committed and if yes we need to know
what happened to that transaction so by
setting this bit 1 Wow while our
transaction another transaction is
reading this it'll say oh I see this
bits at the 1 that means that this thing
is potentially uncommitted it actually
may be committed we just don't know it
yet because they haven't come an updated
this this this this this timestamp to
you know to remove the 1 so we'll see in
a few more slides but there's actually
gonna be this global state map that
keeps track of the the current state of
every single transaction that's running
in the system so if I'm looking out for
specular reads I need a way to figure
out later on did the thing I read
actually get committed or not and so by
setting this to 1 I don't have to go
check to see whether a might actually
allowed to read this I make a make a
little mark in my local metadata like in
my thread that says by the way I read
this a 3 figure out what happened to it
later on because it may and may have not
committed yes so he says what happens if
I go on check when my transaction
commits that they go ahead and read this
what if it's still uncommitted I have to
wait let's do that a few more slides yes
we're not there yet yes he's the
question is to update the original yes
right so did yes yeah yes so at this
point here no one can see this right
because all I've done is I just the
first transaction installed this right
instead of taking a lock on e to I just
said let me go ahead and create this
then now I'll do the compare and swap
here and if that succeeds then I know
that I was successfully able to install
this new version but at this point here
can anybody see this can everybody see
my new version yet why not
I mean fini right so now I need to go
back here and flip that to be my my
timestamp and now my version is
installed it's still uncommitted my bit
is still set to true or so the bits set
the one to denote that this is
potentially from an uncommitted
transaction but at this point here
anybody that comes along that wants to
read data after timestamp 25 should be
able to will be able to see my my new
version yes your question is why keep
track of the begin timestamp and
timestamp here yes like I can track up
like the end timestamp and let's say
like a 1 when you begin timestamp in a 2
right so his question is why do I need
to keep track of this end timestamp here
couldn't I just follow the Virgin chain
and say oh well I know that the the
visibility of this tuple is 20 to 25 cuz
I have it here but now when I do garbage
collection I always got to keep the last
one around Yeah right so if my two boys
super big like super what has a lot of
columns and I'm I'm not actually say
misses point is if you know right so
he's saying if you know this pointer is
null then that should not just be read
as this is infinity yeah maybe
so you're saying so you said that if
there's transaction at time-stamped 24
they should read this what he's saying
that you could infer I think it you want
to reduce in my pointer chasing I think
it's compute versus storage costs so if
I'm scanning along I'm oldest to newest
I see this I don't know the end
timestamp my pointer is not null
I got again follow the pointer now to go
figure out well what is there what
should this actually be and anything
that that's a waste of waste of time
it's not worth it so for safety for bits
it's you avoid that extra extra
computation so his point is back here
this thing set at the one so therefore
the number super high when you do the
comparison you own looking 63 the bits
you ignored us why not change what's
that it still stays like this is our
begin timestamp we only flip that one to
a zero when we get a commute time stamp
which is I'll show next okay okay this
is just mean that'll tell us hey where
we have something that's not committed
you need to figure out later on whether
it actually was committed at all
all right so now our guy commits again
so we're gonna do it's never CC so we're
doing we're doing validation so we need
to go you know go check see we're
allowed to commit in this case here yes
we are so we get our commit time stay
about 35 and so
all we need to do now is just go back at
some later point and flip this to be now
thirty five doesn't need to happen
immediately because again this is saying
that if anybody reads this go figure out
let you know later on in my my global
map whether I actually committed or not
but now if I install thirty five the bit
is set to zero so I know that I'm
reading something that I definitely
definitely was committed and I don't
need to check that map yes boom okay so
let's this question is exactly that's
right so let's rewind now let's go
remove the commit we're back of this D
here let's now bring another transaction
okay
this one is your question so our
transaction begins at timestamp 30 and
it was do a read on a so again follow
the Virgin chain 30 is greater than 20
we don't want this 30 is is greater than
25 we don't want this so then we land
here and this is the version that we
actually want to read again we're doing
specular reads in Hecate on instead of
taking a write latch or right lock on
this tuple I'm allowed to read something
that's uncommitted oscillate later on
make sure I was you know the transaction
that created this version that I've read
whether it actually committed or not but
I'm allowed to do this but now this guy
wants to a right or neck so in this case
here
my timestamp is 30 that's after 25 but
this again first writer wins so this guy
is going to get come down here and
recognize that the the there's another
transaction that's uncommitted here that
created a new version that that I cannot
create a new version after this and
therefore I have to abort my transaction
so again by seeing this thing here I
know it's uncommitted actual in this
case here you you would want to go check
but I think yeah if you go check you
could go see oh it is actually committed
therefore I can't install the version
for this example here 2025 is not
committed yet so this thing would is a
write write conflict so we go ahead and
the board is your question okay yes
[Music]
sorry so what thread cannot read
their threat to is dead at this point
here when he tries to try to write on a
so you pretend you're back here okay yes
yes so this okay to commit time stamp
after ste ste gets 35 again then when
this guy does right just to read this
guy so this guy commits guess this guy
then reads yes question is in my less at
the Apple here this guy got a commit
time set by 35 but if now if I come back
and do this read but I have timestamp 30
what I see no because under snapshot
isolation I should only see things that
before I started in this case here
that's okay yes questions how do I make
sure if I need to go flip these so what
happen is if I go to a look up and I see
this things committed right the one says
I go figure out what what is actually
going on so if it's set them one I go
look my map and I would say oh it's
committed the real commit timestamp is
35 so I guess I was tough to do that in
my local view of this and then when you
do the update you go from all you go
from the newest to oldest because people
are going in the other direction
so you wouldn't have that that issue
okay
so let's jump now and talk about how
we're actually gonna the state map here
again so this is a global hash map
they're going to maintain throughout the
entire database system that just keeps
track of what's the state of every
single transaction running so active
transactions are just one transaction
shows up it's done a bunch of reads and
writes it has begin timestamp you can
still do more reads and writes we just
don't know the outcome just yet
validating is when the application says
I want to commit my transaction and now
we begin the process of figuring out
whether it is actually a lot of commit
right like we have to go check the
rewrite sets and see whether there's any
conflicts committed transaction is that
we pass the validating phase we have a
community who goes reads our data has
well know that it's actually been
committed but we just haven't gone back
yet and flipped those begin time stamps
and end time stamps to being our what
our commit time stamp is and then
terminated is when we updated all the
time stamps for our versions that we
created and then at some point what
we'll get will get pruned away will get
thrown away out of the out of the map so
let's go through now the lifetime more
details so it began transaction gets the
begin timestamp we said it said it in
the map to be active then we do our
normal processing again under OCC they
would call this the read phase for doing
reads and writes on on the datum but as
we run maratha me keep track of the read
set the scan set and the right set of a
transaction so for the read set in the
right set these are just going to
physical pointers to the versions that
we read and wrote right but they're
actually gonna be like in case a read
set it's going to be the version that's
produced to the access method of the
transaction I'm sorry of the query
executors I'll explain that in the next
slide and the scan set will be the
actual where clause that we use to do a
scan on on a table because we need that
for to do phantom checks for
serializability then we hit pre-commit
this is when the application tells us we
want to commit we now get our commit
commit time stamp we do a validation to
figure out whether we're actually there
any conflicts and then right and then
validation again we just check
everything to see whether whether we're
not violating serializable order but why
don't you think is here
this is when they're gonna write now the
new versions to the redhead log out on
disk so this is different than a
Discordian system in a Discordian system
remember you're just appending to the
right head log buffer and some point the
buffer gets full or there's a timeout
when you do in crew commit and then all
your log records get flushed to disk
even though that transaction may have
not committed yet in the case of Hecate
on they're gonna buffer all the log
rights in memory and only flush them out
when the transaction actually is
committed so that means that there's a
crash you come back you're not gonna see
any log records from transactions that
did come and they did not commit you'll
see everything you'll see all the
overall records also you see all of our
guests were all in only committed
transactions then we do the commit we
set our transaction state to committed
we go through now and update our version
time stamps to flip the begin time
stamps and end time stands to now be the
transactions commit time stamp then at
point we're done we set us off the
terminated and we'll get cleaned up
later on all right so let's talk about
this this is metadata for tracking here
because this is important to understand
how we actually maintain sterilized
ability so for the read set and the
right set these again these are me the
physical vert pointed to the physical
virgins in memory that I access or
created and for the access one it's
going to physical versions that I've
produced back to the access method that
that that I used to execute the query so
the thing of this is like say I have a
virgin chain and I have you know three
versions in it the access method does
the scan once the wants to get back a
tuple it's only going to get back one
version so my reset doesn't contain the
first two versions I looked at that
weren't visible to me I don't care about
those it's the one I then returned back
to the query executors now up in my
query plan that one version may get
pruned out like if it gets fed into a
joint operator and the join operator
says I don't need this to bone it throws
it away I still need to know about it
right I even though it's not produced
the final result of the tube or the
query because I gave it to my access
method I have I have to return it and
then the scan set is gonna be the thing
this is like it's the bare minimum the
information we need in order to re
execute a scan operation so things like
it's just the where clause of of a query
and what's going to happen is in our
validation we're going to
basically just re-execute the scan all
over again and see whether we get back
the same result because if we don't get
the same result then we know there was a
phantom somebody inserted or deleted
something since since you know since we
started and therefore we have the you
know giving back a different result and
therefore we have the border transaction
because that would violate serializable
orders now if we're running at a lower
isolation level we don't care about this
but first utilizability we do yes where
when and doing the validation pays right
so I'm checking the check my read set to
see whether I've access anything that is
from uncommitted transaction and you
know whether they commit or not and then
I run my scans again to figure out if
I'd run this a second time do I get the
same result if I don't then I know
there's a fan and I abort so you may
think this is kind of heavy-handed right
like if my scan reads a billion to polls
when I when I do validation I'm gonna
read a billion tuples again yes so this
is this is just the metadata this is the
metadata at the track in order to do
this so board would happen here or
actually here if I have a write write
conflict
I gotta bore myself right away if under
validation like if I scan again I get a
different result then I kill myself well
you sort of skip down and and well yeah
you just kept down and terminate and say
I'm not I'm I'm not gonna commit and
then the garbage cracker will come
through and clean up any versions
shouldn't shouldn't be okay to that yeah
probably no question or not
is the queer call sponsor yeah so the
where clause contains predicates a
predicate would be like a equals one and
B equals to each of those eight one
that's I call that a predicate it's just
the set of predicates okay all right and
then commit to and see what he was
asking here is like this is basically a
list of all the transactions are waiting
for my transaction to commit because
they read something that I wrote before
I committed so think of this is like a
pub/sub system like transaction reads my
uncommitted data they then subscribe to
my you know commit notification whether
I'm gonna finish or not and then if I
commit and I and I read something that
you wrote and you have committed yet but
I need to wait to see whether you commit
for I can commit yes yes the question is
would I use the commit timestamp to
react so you can yes you have to because
that's like that's when I'm installing
everything all right can you have a
circle in dependency in the commit
commit commit timestamps no because
because when you whenever in the first
time I can read a bunch of stuff
I mean I'm before you but I haven't
committed yet so you can't see any
myself yeah if your timestamp is greater
than mine then I won't then and you
write some table I won't read it yeah so
it's always one direction all right so
in the heck of time paper
they proposed actually and evaluate both
the optimistic and pessimistic version
of what I've just described so
optimistic is what we've already talked
about again the key thing is here in
order to ensure serialize ability I have
to check for phantoms by rerunning my
scans on commit and so when you download
sequel server and you run it and you you
run it in every table this is actually
what you get but they also implemented a
pessimistic version based on two-phase
locking and the the main thing this to
understand is that they don't have a
validation phase because they're going
to do index locks and and you know share
locks an exclusive locks
to avoid any phantoms and they have a
background thread to do deadlock
detection all right so this is the only
graph I want to show you from the paper
again the papers from 2012 so relative
to the other systems we're talking about
this is pretty old and the horror that
running on is a bit dated the main
takeaway from here is again as you scale
up the number of threads for this sort
of high contingent workload with only a
thousand tuples the the pessimistic
version it's worse than the optimistic
one and there's gap mate may not seem
like a lot but if you look at the
numbers here it's this the the
optimistic version is doing at most 1.5
million transactions a second and then
the pessimistic one is doing 1.2 million
so the difference is 300,000
transactions per second that's actually
a lot so like running this particular
workload I don't know the exact details
on the hardware but my sequin po stuff
can maybe do it most a hundred thousand
transactions a second I don't know what
you know if you disable logging maybe a
little faster but you know this is
pretty so this is a law even though
relatively between the two of them it
doesn't seem like much right no so this
paper basically said like Oh an
optimistic approach for an in-memory and
multi version system is the way to go
and not the pessimistic one okay all
right so where does someone takeaways we
can have from Hecate on so from a design
standpoint they talked about having this
this global map to keep track of the
state of everything they're gonna laughs
respective reads and of course
everyone's gonna do first writer wins
but some of the things that came out of
the paper that they discussed it says
like your design in memory system that
there were sort of tenants you should
follow the first is that they said that
you only want to use lock for your lat
tree data structures so that means no
latch instead of spin locks no critical
sections everything should always be
written and on a lock free approach and
this would be free indexes your
transaction map the memory allocator the
garbage collector so I just I agree with
everything except for this one here for
indexes so next week you guys will read
about the BW tree which is a lot free
index that they built and part of the
hackathon project we and them
implementing the same thing and it gets
it it's not crap like but it new
two indexes that still use sort of
traditional locking techniques right the
way Hecate inversion started was they
went all-in with skip list skip list as
a walk free data structure that sort of
looks at the Kabbalistic B+ stream that
you can make a lock free so in the
original versions the Hecate on they
were like skip list of the way to go
this is how they design the system then
they said actually skip list or crap you
actually want to use a BW tree but even
then the B Double Tree is gonna lose to
you know regular P plus tree this this
is what you end up guys building for the
second project so it's also interesting
about this the one database system
that's out there that is very big on
skip lists his mem sequel right and the
reason is because the one the
co-founders and then sequel was at
Microsoft at the time working on sequel
server when the hecatomb project was
going on and he saw about to these
internal talks from Paul Larsen and
Mike's willing the two guys leading the
hackathon project and the very beginning
of the project they were like skip list
of the way to go this is what you should
be using so the mem Siegel guys saw that
and then you know to borrow those ideas
when he went off and done em sequel but
he then he missed the second half of the
talk the basic said skip lists are crap
and that you want to use a BW but I
think still today like MEMC go still
very big on skip list but again the
research shows that that is garbage
so I would say like house is you almost
make with very rare exception you never
want to use a skip list like there are
some cases weren't like for in memory
stuff that small skip list might be okay
I just have some nice properties for
memory fragmentation but in general for
index will cover this you know all next
week
skip lists are a bad idea don't go don't
use that and don't use the P Double Tree
either even though we still use we still
use it all right
the other interesting thing they talk
about is that and I agree with this is
that you should only really you know you
want to minimize the number of
civilization' points or bottleneck
points in the system and the only place
you need to do that in the case of
hackathon is when you hand out the
beginning began to commit timestamps
because these always need to be
monotonically increasing and you can't
you can't give out to placate timestamps
so the way they do this is through a
compare and swap for atomic addition
right single instruction to add one to
the counter in the paper you guys let
read last class we showed that if this
approach can you know really high core
count can get max
maybe like you know hundred million time
tens for a second so you could try to
batch these things in our current system
we we we actually don't do this we do
what heck we hyper does and in that case
there is actually a spin lock around a
sort of a critical section so in case
the hackathon they don't have that issue
they just hand out these time stamps
array efficient okay all right so okay
Hecate on i spent you know the first
forty minutes about talking about it
because that's what about it's a
baseline to now understand all those
sort of modern implementations or
variants of a multi version control so
that we can make some observations and
now about what the Hecate on
architecture looks like and what are
some challenges are what some
bottlenecks they're going to face when
we look at other workloads other than
OTP so the first thing is going to be
what i talked already mentioned is that
the reset and thus can set validation is
going to be really expensive if our
transactions to access a lot of data so
typically under oil to be workloads
transactions you know update maybe a
couple dozen tuples or acts as a couple
delves into bowls so in that case
they're the scan side or the reset is
gonna be quite small so we can do that
validation very quickly but now if I'm
running on analytical query where I scan
the entire table my table has a billion
tuples now when I do that validation I
got to go read one building two polls
all over again
right and that's gonna take a long long
time the next issue is that the append
only version that they're that they're
using going oldest and newest is me bad
for OLAP scans because now as I'm
scanning along the version chain I'm
reading a bunch of stuff that I probably
don't need just to get to the version
that I actually want you know depending
on how fast I do garbage collection the
version change can get quite long and
all this pointer chaining chasing and
branching is going to be bad on a modern
CPU architecture because they're gonna
have these long instruction pipelines so
now if I miss predict on a branch
I gotta flush my pipeline and fetch
everything back in and I'll have long
stalls the last issue is going to be
with Hecate on that they were doing a
coarse-grained conflict detection and
determine whether you had a complex
routine to transactions so what I mean
by that is all they were doing to
determine whether there was a conflict
is just does the pointer exist you know
does did I reckon you know is there vert
another
after the version I'm trying to read so
let's say now though I have a table that
has a thousand tuples and my transaction
reads reads one of them I'm sorry my
transaction rights one of them your
transaction reads the other 999 of em
you don't read the one that I wrote but
now that's me consider it as a spec of
read because you read a version that I
created but you didn't actually read the
part that the data that I modified
so now if I abort you have to work too
because the database sim doesn't know
anything about what you read it just
knows that you read a version that was
created by this other transaction that
transaction aborted it so therefore you
have to work too so right so that's so
again and we're doing this visit we're
just the mere existence the pointer it's
enough to say that you read something
that I that I wrote but nothing
internally no nothing more fine-grain so
the hyper system again this is out of
the EU Munich right this is the Germans
anytime I refer to oh the Germans are
beating us that we have to work harder
cuz of the Germans it's these Germans
they're very good so hyper was the first
data submit they built its an in-memory
columnstore using Delta record
versioning going from newest to oldest
and what they're gonna do is that
they're gonna support more fine-grain
conflict detection then what Hecate on
can do and we'll see how we do that in a
second they're also going to do avoid
write write complex by saying the first
writer wins and then the others do you
think thing that we talked about the end
of last classes the way they're gonna
handle indexes in a multi version system
that anytime you have an update on a
tuple
if the attributes you're updating are
our index but you know in some some
index then you have to do a delete in
the index followed by the insert right
because otherwise you have to maintain
these different versioning information
inside the in the index to point to both
of these I and it becomes a big pain so
you treat it as a delete by answer and
that that solves that problem
so let's look an example here so again
they're doing deltal storage and it's a
column storm so they're inside of every
block of tuples they're going to
maintain a special column called the
Virgen vector and this version vector is
going to point to now a delta store
that's allocated per thread or per
transaction that we're gonna maintain
all the updates that we have for you
know for this particular tuple so if the
pointer is null that we know that this
is the the master version in the latest
version of this tuple
and there is no you know there is no
other version we need to check if the
pointer is not null then if we need to
go back and try to find an early version
we just follow along this pointer and we
look inside of our our transact red
space so sort of related to what Hector
tom was saying that you don't want any
global data structures you don't want
any global memory space the this Delta
storage is gonna be on a per thread
basis so when I allocate a bunch of
space for my thread and thread local
storage I don't worry about contending
on into the memory allocator for other
threads because that space is allocated
from me
although threads can read my memory
that's fine but nobody else can write
into it but me and that voice haven't
take any latches on any internal data
structures we have in here so now if I
have another transaction it comes along
that wants to do an update right so say
it wants to update the Tupac tuple so
the first thing we're gonna do is copy
out the the attribute that we're gonna
modify so we're gonna modify attribute
two so he put the old value over here
and then we update our pointer to now
point to what the the previous version
was and then we can go ahead and do
compare and swap install our version
vector and update our value right same
thing for the next guy right we update
this table there is no older version so
our pointer doesn't point to anything we
copied the old value here and it's
updated version pointer there so in our
current system we do it the same way all
right but we actually do this all in a
latch free manner which gets a little
tricky in order to make sure you get
things in the right version when you
have two leads we can ignore that for
now in Hecate on the way they actually
did it was have a latch on the entire
block of tuples they each block is going
it's like 1024 tuples so in that case
here I take I take the right latch and
the whole thing and I don't worry about
someone else coming along and reading
something while I'm an intermediate
state in our system because deletes are
tricky we do you know we do some extra
stuff to make this all be less free but
you don't worry about that for now
all right the thing that is really cool
about hyper is again how they're gonna
do validation to ensure serialize a
building so again first writer wins
that's easy right if I if I have two
transactions that try to update the same
thing whoever got there first succeeds
and the other guy aborts so the paper
that you guys are trying to read
describes how to handle this in
actuality which is not discussed in the
paper and it's not really public but
they don't really have write write
conflicts because they actually only
have one writer thread so only one
thread can update transaction or update
the Davis at a time there's much a
reader thread to do analytics but
there's no write write conflicts because
there's only one guy could be updating
the data at the time same same time but
the protocol you guys read about would
actually handle multiple threads so now
the way they're gonna do validation said
are you react seeding the scan set is
that they're gonna use a technique
called precision blocking so this is
really cool because this precision
locking paper came out before I was born
in 1980 and a time before these Germans
picked up picked it up it had like 40
citations so a 30 40 year old paper with
40 citations is essentially forgotten
right no-one's citing it no one's
reading it right and somehow the Germans
dug this thing out and what its gonna do
it's gonna be like an approximate
predicate locking so I don't remember
whether we discuss predicate locking in
the intro class but basically predicate
locking is a way to look at to where
clauses and queries and figure out
whether they intercept all right and for
simple cases like a egos 1 and B equals
2 like those don't intersect that's not
a problem but for more complex things it
becomes very very difficult I think it's
np-complete
so precision locking is like an
approximation of that where I only need
to look at just what I actually modified
whether the tuple that I modify it
overlap with what my queries are trying
to do and so rather than having execute
the scan you just sort of re execute the
query based on the the Delta records
that are generated by transactions it'll
make more sense the next slide but
basically when my transaction commits to
do validation I look at all the
transactions that have committed after I
started me
I did not see their updates when when I
ran because they not they did not commit
before I started so I'm going to see
whether they then created new versions
that I should have ran read when I ran
the first time all right so let's look
an example here so say this is the
transaction we want to validate it has
three queries and then there's three
transactions that have already committed
so they're in the past right they're
gone and we have their their their redo
records so these are the same video
records we would write out the disk
anyway so it's not like we're generating
these to do just this validation we have
to log them out to disk so we keep
around a memory to do our check and so
that so the idea is that we're gonna
look at the where clause for every
single query and check to see whether
there is an overlap with what we're
looking up here with what they actually
modified and if so then we know with it
we should have read what they wrote but
we didn't so therefore we have to abort
so the way you take about this easily is
that we look and see what attribute are
we accessing in our where clause for
each predicate and then we look at see
whether they modify that attribute in
any log record and then we just
substitute that value in here alright so
for this first one attribute ask me to
it's greater than 20 this guy modified
attribute to is 799 so he placed 99 here
so 99 is not greater than 30 or greater
than 20 and less than 30 so we know that
this thing would not evaluates it for
our query here we wouldn't have read
this yes no no they committed it after
we started no not necessarily
again snapshot isolation says I can only
read things I only see things that are
visible to me if they were created by a
transaction that committed before I
started so I've started and there's a
bunch of transactions that have already
started in there making some stuff and
the current transaction that started
after I started that wrote some stuff
then committed as well so in this case
here for both these predicates alright
for this transaction it evaluates to
false so we know again that this
transaction did not create anything that
I would have read if I was if it was
installed before you know when I
actually had to read the first time so I
didn't miss anything so there's no
phantom here I could
that same thing with an ex guy here
right after two is in ten twenty or
thirty this guy created ninety nine and
thirty three and so for both these
predicates evaluates to false three
threes not ten twenty or thirty
ninety-nine not ten twenty or thirty so
therefore and I didn't read any I didn't
miss anything so that's false so we we
can skip that in this case here I I'm
doing a lookup on attribute one this guy
only modified attribute to so there's
nothing that this guy would have modify
that it read so I'd replaced that with a
null null like any wild card what would
it actually evaluate to null so long as
it's not true then we're fine and I
didn't miss anything so I'm gonna do
this down the line for all these guys
alright one by one but now we get to
this guy here accurate one like ice wild
card ice wild card and in this case here
somebody installed the you know the
string Ice Cube so now in this case here
my predicate would evaluate to true so
therefore again that means that this
transaction did an update that was
committed after I started but because I
was looking at a previous snapshot I
missed it
right this is the right skew anomaly
because I missed it then I have to then
then you know I have to abort because
it's something that I should have read
but I didn't read and I would've violate
sterilizable ordering okay yes yes yes
question is this question is what if
like what if like here this evaluated
true and then say this is this is going
forward in time so transaction one zero
one is older than ones there's are three
so this evaluates to true but then this
evaluates to false what should happen in
that case
let's go question
right there's a brief period where it
was true but the am result would be
false I think the last writer would win
yeah I think the last writer would win
so you you could in theory and this guy
updated actually won on the same to poll
would you actually have that information
though I don't think you would you
wouldn't know that so this is again this
is an approximation of a phantom
checking so false positives are okay
because we abort when we didn't have two
false negatives are bad we don't want to
abort we don't we don't want to not
abort when we showed up so in that case
here I think the safe thing to do is
like even though there is a window where
like like we're like or after this guy
then everything will been okay because I
conflict it at least once
I'll play it save it and a board
immediately again it's not predicate
locking would be an exact measurement or
determination of whether there was a
conflict precision locking despite the
name is a little less precise and is
it's okay to have false negatives or
false positives okay
the other cool thing about hyper that
they do is these Virgin synopsis so
again the issue is that under Hecate on
is that we have these long version
chains and then as we're scanning along
we basically have to traverse them all
the time to figure out to find the right
version that we actually want so if
you're doing a TV queries where you're
doing lookups on single attributes
through an index and I land at the head
of verges a mattress that yeah who cares
because I I just follow a virgin chain I
find what I want but now if I'm doing
analytical queries when I basically want
to do entire table scans I don't want to
have to go check that virgin vector and
go follow some JSON pointer over there
because that's gonna ruin my cache
locality because I want to be able to
rip through these columns very
efficiently that's the whole point of
having a column store but having these
pointers causes them you have
indirection so what they're going to do
on a per block basis they're going to
maintain
Virgen synopsis and this is just gonna
keep track of what range of the of the
tuples here if they might block don't
have a virgin' vector don't have older
versions that I need to go check so in
this case here it's between two to five
inclusive exclusive so way think about
this these offsets are number from 0 0
to 6 so this is gonna say between 0 & 5
so zero inclusive five inclusive that I
don't need to look at anything else so
in this case here when I do my scan I
look at my virgin schnapps it would say
oh I'm at offset zero offset 1 that does
not intersect with my virgin synopsis so
I know I can ignore this thing entirely
but now for this range here I got to go
check sometimes there'd be no that's
fine but as I'm doing the scan I don't
have to even look at this for these
other parts here and now I can rip
through these columns as fast as
possible you could even do something
like because sequel or relational
algebra is unordered I could then maybe
do fast scan on these two guys and then
at the end then go check this one I
don't actually know how that's actually
implemented you probably don't want to
do that for a really large columns or
large blocks because this will be you
know within you'll have a stride you
know in in your cache and jump me to
another part could invalidate your cache
so it's better off to maybe just rip
through sequentially so this is sort of
like a zone map but for the physical
versions because zone map is a little
thing of the header of the block says
you know here's the values that are in
my block and use that to figure out
whether you actually need to read it
this is like a way to say like alright
here's the here's the versions that you
may here's the tuples that you know you
don't the check the versions all right
the idea is that as data gets cold over
time you can have progressively larger
and larger ranges when you don't have
older versions and that makes your scans
go faster right under hackaton it's just
you had no notion of this well it's also
a penalty but without any notion of this
do you have to scan through everything
yes Birju schnapps it was in a block so
this block has ten twenty four tuples
and this just saying like here's a range
where here's I actually don't know where
you can have more than one I suppose you
could but here's the range where you you
have to check the versions anything
that's not in this range you
don't yes question why not use the rain
versus the bitmap yeah
yeah I mean like yeah especially so
actually this would be a great project
for project three tribe maybe the bitmap
and try this one and see what's once is
faster and I imagine the larger the
blocks are the bitmap the more tuples
you have in a block the bitmap gets
larger but if doing 1024 that's not a
larger bitmap you know actually probably
what you do is just take this and
convert it to a bitmap and use that for
the scan and manage just keep it around
yeah this is something we should explore
about your you cool project okay all
right so another system we want to talk
about now that does that sort of NBCC
but with a focus on doing transactions
and analytics is si P Hannam so Hana was
a it's in every dating system that was
built by SI p that was meant to be you
know mostly designed to power their
their big you know enterprise resource
whether a RP application writes the
things that use to keep track like
payrolls and stuff like that to get off
Oracle but it is actually a standalone
data system subject you could use for
other applications so they're gonna be
doing time travel storage with newest to
oldest and like Hecate on their support
both optimistic and pessimistic i
actually don't know what you get by
default I don't know I assume Utley this
is tunable and so they're gonna have a
hybrid storage layout then have rows and
columns and so some versions are gonna
be in the row store and then some
versions are gonna be in the column
store and the idea is that you want to
have the latest version I'm sorry you
won't have the oldest version in the
column store because most your your
analytical queries can just rip through
that and then you have the roast or it
was where you append the new the new and
the track time travel space you can pen
them very quickly because there's
they're just gonna be sort of you know
deltas you're adding so they
shuri of hana is actually kind of
interesting it originally started off as
this Frankenstein Frankenstein system
where they bought a bunch of database
companies mash this thing together and
called it Hana so this P time was an
in-memory day system that came out of
out of South Korea the South Korean for
whatever reason there's a lot of Awesome
enemy databases in South Korea alta base
is another one so they bought these guys
they had this thing t-rex it was like a
like a search system and then a maxtv
was an embedded Rho star system they
mash these things all together they call
it Hana turns out that was a
and then they've since as of last year
sort of released a new version where
they've actually rewritten everything to
be a clean code base I don't know how
much Appy time is still there but like
it's it's much better now it's actually
pretty interesting
the name Hana doesn't they told me
doesn't mean anything for large
corporations name is a big deal like
they're paranoid of getting sued right
that's why all the the Intel CPUs the
Zeon's like KB Lake skylake those are
actually named at for real lakes and
they do that because no one can sue them
and say they stole their name because
it's like it's a geographical region
right so I'm making a name like Hana it
doesn't mean anything that avoids them
getting you know getting sued I've heard
that this mean has no planners new
architecture has no planner is the one
of the founders of sa P like he's the P
and s AP but I I don't think that's true
I think this someone added that
afterwards okay so let's talk White
House authority virgin stories so this
is kind of interesting
so the oldest virgin it's always giving
the main data table and that's gonna be
a column store and then the hub this
little flag this and say hey there's
actually there might be a newer version
in the time travel space that you need
to go check and see whether that's
actually the version that you're looking
for right and so for some queries like
for analytical queries
I don't maybe need to run and have the
exact latest version of of a tuple like
who cares if I'm trying to compute the
number of you know open orders that I
need to go check who cares if I'm 10
milliseconds behind right so I'll just
scan through the column store in in the
main Dave
tablespace it may not be the newest
version but that's good enough for my
query and so now when you land in the
time travel space they're gonna have a
hash table to like dual lookup
find the head of the Virgin chain for a
particular tuple yes what did I say it's
all done ooh yeah sorry yes here okay
all right so every tuple in the main
data table is gonna have a record ID
right that's a immutable identifier to
say that this is this represents a
logical tuple and then then there's our
version flag which could just be a
bitmap that says for each version
whether there's a newer version that we
need go check in the time travel space
right so so if I'm doing a lookup on a1
I would say all right well this thing
set to true so now I use my record ID a
land here and then now I can traverse my
virgin chain so yeah so it's oldest to
newest globally and then when you land
in this hash table here this is also
older or this is actually newest to
oldest that's what I was confused about
so globally its oldest to newest I'm
look at the oldest version here but then
if I want to find a newest version I
land here and then the head of the
virtual chain is newest please again if
I'm doing updates I care about mostly in
validating the latest one this is my
hash map if I need to go install a new
version I can do that very efficient all
right and again I think this
architecture bore out from the fact that
they were trying to match these
different systems together you know this
could be like the t-rex side and this
could be like the in memory P times side
all right so now unlike also in
hackathon and hyper where we're going to
keep track of the of the timestamps in
the in the in the header of every single
tuple they're actually gonna embed a
pointer for every tuple to some auxilary
metadata object and that's gonna have
all your timestamp information for every
single tuple and the idea here is that
we're doing this to reduce storage
because instead of having this repeated
timestamp over never again for every
single update I make to every single
version I create for a given transaction
that they all now have a 64-bit pointer
to some metadata object that has all the
information they need to know about that
that that tuple I cut down the amount of
meta head or space I'm storing for every
single tuple and now when I need to
update timestamps like we did in
hackathon I did go to that one location
update that one made metadata object and
that updates all my versions immediately
against sort of this trade-off between
the the the slower bees or as faster
updates or large you know for big
updates because I can go update a one
single thing in the updates everything
all at once right so it looks like this
so down here in I this transaction
metadata space and for every single
transaction I'm a maintain sir for a
group of tunes actually I'm going to
keep track of like here's all the things
that they've been modifying so now when
my transaction comes along once in an
updates guy write to C and D these guys
as I create these new versions now point
down to this this the single object for
my from my transaction that says here's
my current status so I don't have that
global map I don't really maintain all
the version information and every single
tuple I can go down here and figure out
what you know what am i you know what am
I actually looking at when I look at a
version and they have another layer of
indirection that then combines together
a bunch of these transaction con taxes
when it does group commit and adds them
together into this group of commit
contacts and then that flushes
everything out so now if the upper parts
of the system want to say hey did my
transaction at ID 3 did that actually
commit instead of maintaining that
information for every single transaction
I could look across all these in this
group contact and know yes everything
got flushed out to disk I think this is
a bit wonky I think this is a bit over
engineered but I do see why they do this
if you're doing a large updates which
I'm sure they're doing in their workload
or infer therefore their target
application this approach it wouldn't
make sense I think there is somebody say
about like I do like this sort idea that
you have this global thing to keep track
of everything so you can do quick
updates this one I think is I don't see
the real reason to have this ok hi so
let's finish up real quickly you talk
about circuito so let's not with some
limitations about the approaches we
talked about so far for the nbcc and
sort of optimistic and hurt retool and
then we'll see a system that
specifically designed to overcome these
so one is that we've talked about so far
is that there's this there's this all
this in direction for because of this
version chain to be they have to go look
up all the time to figure out what the
right version is for us in the case of
Hana we
saw right they have this global context
object hyper try to reduce this by
having the version synopsis to avoid
having check the version change but in
general we have to you know if we're
updating to post we have to maintain
these version pointers so we got to now
do garbage collection to go through and
try to clean things out so if we don't
run out of space and it produces the
size of the Virgin chain that reduces
the number of things to have to look at
when we do scans all the other purchase
most approaches we talked about so far
are also maintaining a bunch of stuff in
global memory right there's the global
map for hackaton for Hyper there's the
sort of a global space of the blocks of
tuples and so in this case here because
we're reading writing to enter any
address space in memory our threads
aren't entirely cognizant about where
the data they're reading is and what
that where the data is located that
they're reading writing to and how
that's gonna affect their cache locality
so we'll discuss Numa stuff in for the
detail in the semester but in modern
architecture if you have multiple CPU
sockets the the memory access speed for
you know one memory location mean on one
sock it may not be the same on another
socket so if I don't know where my
memory is actually located I may end up
reading on another socket and that could
be really slow and then for all these
approaches as well we also talked about
how there there's a single counter to
you time stamp allocation and that could
become a bottleneck and really high core
counts of thread counts so for OCC some
of the limitations that we talked about
and these aren't specific to multi
version this is this is certain general
for OCC protocols but if there's high
contention then we're gonna have a lot
of aborts and we saw that 1,000 core
paper when we show her everything
cratered at a thousand cores all the
time we were spending executing
transactions were basically just
aborting them because there was a
conflict immediately Brett and it had to
do a metric actually reads and writes if
we implement the private workspace for
OCC and this is additional copying in
memory and that that's that's gonna add
it's gonna slow us down because that
sector work and then now when we do
we'll talk about more this next class
but in some protocols the way to handle
updates to indexes before I actually
commit my transaction is I have to
install what are called virtual index
nodes
basically a placeholder to say like I'm
gonna start this key into this index I
don't know exactly what my commit
timestamp man is yeah because I haven't
committed yet but this is just a way to
prevent somebody else when trying to
start this the same key at the same time
it's another way to do first writer wins
but for indexes so Sakina was the engine
built here at CMU by healing tech limb
so he was a peachy student of Dave
Anderson stuck around at a postdoc and
dabbled in databases end up building
this system so there's a bunch of
optimizations that were interesting to
us that cicada proposed that I want to
sort of go through will do best effort
in lining
Lucey synchronized clock which is we're
not going to cover too much but
contention where validation index notes
so the first one in the second two are
things that weeks we could consider in
our own system this one I have not
thought through more carefully to see
whether this actually makes sense this
is actually borrowing techniques from a
distributed database world which makes
sense if you're saying if I have a lot
of cores have a lot of sockets it's
essentially like a distributed database
which is on a single machine but I want
to focus on the you know these three
because this make more sense before we
talk about so far so best effort in
lining the basic idea here is that
instead of having this version chain
that could just point to anywhere what
if I allocate some fixed amount of space
along with the version pointer and that
way when I want to do a lookup and say
what's the latest version well I can
maybe just go find the latest version
right here right and so the idea here is
that as of now I'm scanning along
instead of jumping followings pointer to
some other location you know there's a
small matter space right here that has
the latest data that I need and mirth of
the time that will be good enough for me
right so this one's okay I mean I think
the the paper shows that this actually
for sort of old healed workloads this
makes a big difference but I think this
is tricky to do when you have variable
length data because if these are strings
are different sizes then this is hard to
do and for analytical queries
I think the columnstore approach is
actually is obviously gonna be better
all right but let's talk about how we
can do fast validation right so again
the scan stat approach is well guarantee
sterilized ability under Hecate on the
precision locking approach would
guarantee sterilized body
Piper for this paper here I think he's
mostly retorting the the the scan setup
wrote that used in in hackathon he
didn't actually evaluate the precision
locking because I don't think he was
aware of the paper when he wrote it and
he wasn't sitting he took targeting MVCC
systems but it basically has three
approaches here to kind of speed things
up
alright to do validation the first is
that instead of treating every
transaction blindly or do validation
blindly you actually can maintain a
little information on what happened with
the last transaction you validated and
so if you can identify if there are
records that are highly contended like
everybody trying to update this one
tuple instead of having checking that
maybe at the end or at random I'll check
that at the very beginning of validation
and that way if I'm going to abort I
abort right away without having to check
everything else so all you basically do
is keep a counter for like the most
content of tuples that I keep a boarding
transactions on so now if I go see if
that when I do my validation if that
tuple ever I've read that tuple and that
that everyone keeps a boarding on all to
make sure I check that one first and
that'll boys doing wasted work another
technique we're gonna do is early
consistency check and this is actually
barred from a paper that we wrote after
the DB X 1000 approach we had another
protocol code tik-tok and what this one
is that again just like before if I keep
track of what things I'm contending on
in my validation phase if I can then
push that information up to now actually
why I'm running the transaction so now
if I transaction read something that I
could that I could conflict on instead
of waiting for validation to go do the
validation I'll check immediately after
I do the read or even before I do the
read to see whether if I read this now
what I abort and the idea here is
instead of waiting for the entire
lifetime of the transaction just to see
I'm gonna abort and not a bitl finish I
can do some early checks and avoid all
that the last one is through incremental
version search and the idea here is that
since they're doing newest to oldest if
I know that I keep reading some older
version then rather than having to
follow that very chain I could maintain
a little memory address in the
but the master version that says that
the version you're probably looking for
is here here's how to go jump into it
and if I land into a version that it's
exactly what I wanted I'm done if it's
not what I want then I just go repeat
the search as I normally would it's
taking a little extra memory space and
to avoid having to do the full version
change search so for these first two you
want to skip these if your transactions
are mostly committing successfully but
it's only when you have high contention
what these things actually make sense
and so it's sort of you sort of need to
be adaptive and have a way to determine
oh well I keep a boarding because I have
conflicts then you switch these things
on and maybe that can produce reduced
amount of work good because again OCC we
only do validation if there's a
transaction committed so if I'm doing a
thousand updates and it's the the first
one is what I'm gonna conflict on and
that's gonna cause me to abort if I
don't check to see whether there was an
abort
operation until I do the other 999
updates then that's all wasted work so a
technic technique like this kind of try
to avoid all this alright so the other
interesting thing about cicada that I
find extremely fascinating this is the
third year where I say this is something
we should we should look into and
hopefully I have a PhD student that's
gonna start looking to this is instead
of storing the index nodes for the B+
tree just in the heap they're actually
going to store it as tuples themselves
as blobs in a table and the idea here is
that instead of having to do the scan
checks instead of having to do with
precision locking if the if the index
nodes are just tuples themselves and I
can do validation to see whether I'm
allowed to read something or not doing
something then I potentially get
sterilized ability and phantom checks
for free if everything is a table so
again normally and you'll see this in
the the B+ tree you'll build or the BW
tree that we already have the nodes are
just sitting out in the heat right but
instead we're actually stored these now
as blobs inside of a table like this
we're just serializing the keys and
sterilizing the the pointers to the next
version so now when I do a scam from you
know to get down to G I'll do my lookup
an a I basically know how to interpret
these bytes and that's going to tell me
oh the thing I you know for the Kievan
key I'm looking for
I want to jump into two B or C and then
I know how to do then do a lookup and
find the the node that represents C of
course now the issue is that if I do an
update for a single key in my in my node
that's gonna invalidate the this entire
version because either create a new
version and that could be a excessive
copying so I think it's just trade-off
of like how much churn there is an index
to how much benefit you're gonna get to
this but again I think that the paper is
correct that this will give you
sterilized body checks for free but I
don't know this and then he claimed that
Segel light actually does this so as far
as I know no buzzes okay no real system
actually does this I checked with a
single light guy last night the the
creator and he told me they don't do
this for B plus trees but they do it for
like full table indexes like inverted
indexes because there's no notion of
those things at the first class object
or entity within the database system so
you store them as blobs and that could
shoot the stored for free right the B+
treats are stored separately as you know
separate pages in the heat again I think
this is super interesting and this is
something that if we want to get up we
want to actually get off the BW tree and
in our system we might want to pursue
this but we'll see all right so two
quick rafts for cicada so this is the
first workload we're gonna have low
contention right and they're gonna
compare against a bunch of different
systems so two-phase locking is sort of
standard approach silo is it is a system
out of Harvard that will talk a little
bit about later in the semester they
have a data structure called the mash
tree which what we'll cover
tick-tock is the the protocol that I
helped work on for OCC and then all
these other ones are sort of variants of
silos hermia is a better version of silo
foetus is a better version of silo and
they have cicada so under low contention
you see that a Hecate on is actually
doing the worst here and these sort of
variants of silo are all doing all about
the same but when you have high
contention because cicada has all that
extra stuff that I talked about like the
early kisses new check the the jumping
to the right version that I needed are
checking on validation to see whether
you know what's with what what tube or
my most likely to be oh I have to abort
on so I make sure I check that first
because of that that's why they're able
to do better than these other ones so
the overall architecture of cicada is
interesting but it's all those little
one-off optimizations I think that are
that are super interesting that are
worth pursuing as well so this might
also might be another project resuit so
in addition to the to the the cicada
style B+ tree we could also look at
adding into our own system all these
early validation checks because we're
doing the same thing okay I thought I've
rushed through that last part very
quickly but the main idea is that just
showing that like instead of treating
every transaction you know we're
learning from scratch whether I'm gonna
abort or not
we could maintain some information for
one transaction the next and make better
decisions when we do validation all
right so the the other main takeaway
once you get from this lecture is that
there's a bunch of other design
decisions we talked about that don't
follow exactly into the forward things
we talked about last month the last
class that can affect the performance of
the system depending on whether you're
targeting o2b workloads or OLAP
workloads so like if you're doing long
scans for OLAP queries then the global
hash map and the and the virgin chain
for pen only is probably a bad idea
under heck atomic
right but the hyper way is that might be
better and so there's this classic
trade-off again between having these
different interaction layers to maybe
store stuff off separately or have
redundant information stored in one
location to reduce our storage overhead
but then that could affect performance
and some systems like Hana they decided
to make that choice okay all right so
next class will be the last lecture we
do on garbage collection so yenna be
reading another paper from hyper this
came out in VO to be or just just came
out less last year on how they do
garbage collection and then we'll spend
time at the end doing a sort of demo how
to do run perf for project number one
okay any questions bank it in the side
park what is this
ain't dead here called the okay
cuz i mochi ice cube down with the testy
hi you look and it was go grab me a
forty just to get my buzz song cuz i
needed just a little more kick like a
fish just once if my lips and just say
nice and my hood won't be to say i've
nice to take a say to the prey