[Music]
[Applause]
as I said I can't be on campus this week
I'm still here in Europe right now I am
actually in Munich visiting Thomas
Norman at at T um and that's where they
invented hyper and the new database and
putting an umbrella so part of me going
down to visit Thomas is sort of to sort
of get a better understanding why the
Germans are so good at databases and so
as part of this they took me up here in
the Alps somewhere in the mountains I
don't know exactly where we are it's
freezing and the idea it's like this you
go in the woods and you think about your
thoughts for like an hour or something
somehow that's gonna magically make you
better understand databases so whatever
I'm just sitting here now it's freezing
cold there's some hunting dog running
around fighting things you may see that
in the background and I thought it'd be
a good time to get through and start
discussing the next lecture so let's see
how far we can get before it gets too
cold so the last class we discussed the
sort of a high-level history of database
systems and primarily what I focused on
was sort of thinking about the problem
in terms of like at a high level mostly
based on data models you know whether it
was the codasyl stuff or the the
hierarchal data model the relational
data model and so that was the sort of
main discussion of last class another
way to sort of think about it was an
overarching theme throughout the entire
history of databases is this constant
struggle of building database systems
that have to deal with the limitations
of the harbor at the time right it's the
same in the 1970s 1960s as it is now
we're you know we're always trying to
run databases on new hardware and get
the best performance we can out of it so
back in the 1970s though when they built
the first relational database systems
database systems the hardware it was a
lot different than what we
today but at a high level the the basic
idea is still the same and so the
problem though is like when we start to
talk about modern systems the although
the basic idea is still the same the
limitations that harbour is not exactly
the same so back then in the 1970s all
right you didn't have machines with a
lot of sockets a lot of about a cores
right you had a unit processor you had a
single single core CPU that could really
only execute one thread at a time the
rams also severely limited it was very
expensive so you were you were lucky to
get you know a machine had diarrea but
maybe like of like a megabyte sorry now
we can go into the terabyte so in a
single box and because bran was limited
we had a store the entire database on
disk and so the the whole architecture
the database system was predicated on
you know retrieving data from disk and
of course back then this were way slower
than they were now and certainly the
sequential access was was much faster
than random access so you try to design
algorithms and data structures that
could maximize going to access so now in
the modern era in you know 20 20 s now
we have machines that have enough DRAM
such that most databases can probably
fit entirely in main memory and there's
always going to be the outliers there's
always going to be you know the googles
and the Facebook's and Amazon's of the
world where their data but their
databases can be in the size of
petabytes but for probably 99% of the
applications their database maybe
measures in in gigabytes or a few
terabytes and so again with that with
that size you can certainly have a
database fit entirely in main memory
whether it's a distributed system or a
single node system so to understand why
databases you know aren't as maybe as
large as you think they actually are you
gotta understand that there's a sort of
difference between structured and
unstructured data or semi structured
data so structured data sets or be
things that we mean normal talked about
with you about databases so you have a
well-defined schema they have attributes
right and every record has to have those
attributes and so in those data
they're usually again these are
typically smaller unstructured data sets
would be things like video files sound
files or images right these are things
where the contents of every single
record in in that data set are is going
to be different or there's not even any
structure at all and you know you can't
run queries directly on on a video data
semi-structured would be things like log
files that are generated such that
they're they're meant to be human
readable but they're you know they're
not gonna have the exact same fields for
every single log record you can parse
them and extract those fields but you
know some love records might have other
fields other ones might have others so
again unstructured and semi-structured
data sets these are typically larger you
think of like YouTube YouTube yeah the
the my sequel database that that they
use in YouTube you know that's gonna be
a fraction of the size of the total
amount of video that they're storing and
the videos all the unstructured stuff
the my sequel forties database is the
structured database so for our purposes
here in this class we're primarily going
to focus on the structured data because
that's really only you know you can kind
of do the things that we're talking
about here but there's no magic way to
do vectorize query execution on video
data what do you have to do you have to
convert that video data into structured
data and then you can run your queries
on it so right so they so that's gonna
be the poker server for ourselves here
today the other thing we need to
understand also now is that how are we
and how we're gonna get the best
performance in a davis ism to run on the
structured data so you may think all
right well if my database can mostly
this is to fit on main memory can I take
a you know traditional disk or a
database system as as one as I described
last semester in the introduction class
can we just give that you know run that
on a machine with a large enough large
nut via Ram and set the buffer pool
cache size to be big enough such that
everything's gonna fit in a memory is
that going to be enough for us to get
the best performance and the spoiler is
gonna be no right and we need to
understand why so for today's lecture
see how far we can get before we get too
cold
is that we're gonna first discuss what a
dis cornea database system is so we can
understand you know when we started
talking on imitative systems how do they
avoid all the bottlenecks of the
slowdown issues of distorting system
then we're to talk about from this we
can go a little deeper into the current
role and see what are the bottlenecks
that we have to overcome to get these
control protocols to run in in memory
systems so the the definition that I
always like to use for a disc or any
database system is one where the the
architecture system of the system is
predicated on the assumption that the
primary search location the database
like all the contents of the database
there's records and indexes and material
that's used everything with the store is
going to be on some kind of non-volatile
storage but that's a spinning disk hard
drive or an SSD so that means that the
database is going to be designed based
on this assumption and therefore all the
algorithms the data structures and
everything that's on inside of it has to
be aware that you know at any time we
could have to go get something from disk
now the database itself will be
organized into a set of fixed length
pages or stuff that sometimes goes
blocks and then we're gonna use a Emery
buffering manager to store or cache the
pages in memory as we receive them from
disk again we're assuming a von Neumann
architecture and that means we can't you
know can't operate directly on on data
as it exists on disk you know that can
change in some modern hardware but for
our purposes here assume that's not the
case and therefore the preferable
manager is really all about how deciding
how to move this data back and forth
between disk and memory as needed and we
want to do this in such a way that we
minimize the amount of stalling or the
amount of times we have to go out the
disk so this buffer pool is sort of the
key thing that differentiates a disk or
nativism with the in-memory database
system from terms of like the
architecture so what's gonna happen is
we'll have a query that's going to
execute in our system and anytime that
asks to access a tuple we have to go
find the page that our tuple is located
in so the data says go check to see
whether that page that it needs for that
query is already in memory if it is then
we just hand back the pointer to where
slow
from our proper poll and the query can
execute if it's not then we start need
to do some extra stuff so first thing we
have to go we have to go do is well we
got to decide what frame we want to copy
our page into our buffer pool so a frame
is just a location in the allocated
memory of our profitable manager and we
use this term to differentiate it
between a page or a block because that's
the same frames gonna be used over and
over again for different pages so if
there's a free frame then our job is
easy we just say this is that frame that
we're gonna put our page in we go fetch
it from disk and copied in and we're
done but now there's no free frames then
we gotta find a page to exists from an
existing frame and that's when things
get complicated so if the page we want
to we want to evict if it's never
modified by a transaction I mean it's
not dirty then our job is easy we just
go write it out you know we just go drop
it and then reuse the frame but if it is
dirty then we got to go now evicted so
we've got to write about the disk and
flush it and once that's done now we can
use our frame so again you can see sort
of why this is complicated because you
know we're running essentially you know
LRU or clock or whatever exhibition
policy you want to use to decide how to
evict frames and we got to balance that
with you know what other queries or
transactions are running at the same
time what pages are dirty right this all
gets very complicated so now once the
page is in memory then you know we can
try to be smart and trying to translate
quickly any on disk or references to to
our page to now an or memory address so
that maybe we don't have to go through
this whole process of checking the
buffer pool manager every single time
but not every now in every system
actually does that so at a high level
what I just talked that looks like this
so for our purposes here say we're doing
a query that's going to look up an index
index it wants to find a record the
records inside a page and we got a go
fetch it from disk so to simplify our
discussion we'll say the index is not
not backed by buffer pool pages it's
just actually sitting in memory in most
systems that's actually not true right
the index pages themselves would be
backed by the powerful manager so we
have to go check to see whether those
pages are in memory as well
and do this entire process but we'll
just keep it simple and say it's
entirely memory so the first things to
be do is you look up on our index to
find our
and what the index will give us is back
give us back as a paid ID and a slot
number and then we can use that page ID
to look do a look of an a page table and
find the location of the page that we're
looking for so let's say that we're
looking for page 1 and then we would not
find the entry in our page table or we'd
see an entry that says oh it's not in
memories on disk and here's where to go
find it on disk so in order to bring it
to memory we have to go pick a existing
page to vicked so we have to latch this
page table to make sure that nobody else
is trying to bring it in the same time
we are and then we got to pick up one of
these pages to evict so let's say we
pick page two but page two is dirty so
now we gotta write it out to disk and
flush it and then once that's done then
we can now use the free frame to copy in
page one and at this point now we update
our page table to say hey if you look in
for page one here's the frame in the
before manage to go find it and then
once that done we can release our
latches and anybody can access it so
this is a sort of a gross simplification
of how this eviction process works right
because I'm not showing it well if there
was an entry for page two and then you
can update that now in the page table to
say it's not on not memory now it's on
disk but you know at a high level every
single database system that's you know
using a buffer pool is doing something
similar so what's the problem this well
if now we get we go back to our example
say let's give our database system a lot
of memory and now everything's gonna fit
memory well we still going through this
entire process to go look up the page
table on try to do a translation of like
the record ID to its memory location
every single time we access a tuple and
we have to take latches and protect
things because we don't want us to be
accessed in the page wall and then have
another threat try to evict that page
but like I said if if we have enough
memory then we're never gonna actually
write anything out the disk so pinning
these pages are and latching them is
actually not necessary at all so just
sort of wasted work and then running
that an eviction policy to updating all
internal metrics about how pages are
being accessed that's also a waste of
work too because again nothing's ever
going to be a victim so this sort of
answers my strawman question at the
beginning that well can't we just give
it some a lot of memory and you know
traditionally dissipated in a lot of
memory and what
that'd be enough for you know getting
the same performance as we would get an
in-memory system and the answer is no
because you're doing this all apps you
know doing these extra work just go
access the single page now this is gonna
have cascading to other issues as well
so like in concurrent rituals so the the
traditional disk based systems
destroying the system's their designs
such that at any time a transaction
could touch memory and it's not in disk
and therefore that transaction has get
stalled while the the disk manager go
fetches it and so while it stalled other
transactions are gonna be able to run on
other threads or the same thread so that
this system can keep making forward
progress even though you know one
transaction got stalled because it has
to get something from disk all right we
do this otherwise if we can only execute
one transaction at a time and we stall
anytime we have to get from something
I'm disk then the system's gonna look
unresponsive because it's gonna keep
stalling and you know every single time
you know we have a page miss so because
now we're allowing other transactions
are run at the same time we have to use
a concurrent protocol that could be
setting locks in our own records or
objects in the database to make sure we
provide the asset guarantees that you
want for transactions right because if
now a transaction modifies a page and
then that page gets written on the disk
before that transaction commits can
commit because some other transaction
evict that page then we got to make sure
that we keep track all the section
information and that if we crash and
come back that the uncommitted
transactions changes don't persist so in
a disk or any system if it's using
locking it's going to maintain this
locking information in separate data
structures right it's an in-memory hash
table in the lock manager to avoid those
the lock information getting swapped out
to disks that way I don't have to
determine whether I can even hold the
lock on a tuple to go got the disk and
figure out you know go fetch that lock
information everything is always going
to be in memory other problems would
have an in memory system is with logging
recovery so most database systems that
use a buffer file manager are going to
be using the steal no force but football
manager policies and this just basically
means that all the transactions that a
transaction mates all the modifications
that a transaction makes
have to get added to a right ahead log
and that those entries have to get
flushed to disk before transactions
allowed to commit and then any updates
to a dirty page the law of records
correspond to those updates has
rewritten a disk before the dirty page
can be written a disk these are things
that we covered in the introduction
class last semester so now an in-memory
system we don't have dirty pages anymore
so maybe we don't need to use the exact
same protocol and then maybe our log
entries don't need to store the exact
same information as we had in dis
oriented system right if no dirty pages
have to ever get rid of disk then it
maybe doesn't make sense to store the
before image or the redo information I'm
sorry the undo information of the
transactions modification because that
page will never the dirty page never
gets written so there's a lot extra
stuff we had to do in a tyranny system
that maybe doesn't make sense anymore in
an emery system like keeping track of
the logs sequence numbers again again
maintaining the the undo information
because again dirty pages don't get rid
of discs because everything fits in
memory all right so to get others a
better understanding of what this
overhead is actually gonna be there's a
study that was done at MIT it's actually
2008 over 10 years ago now where they
took a old TV database system and
they've instrumented so that they can
measure the number instructions that the
data system was spending in different
parts of the current query execution
while you're running TPCC and the idea
here is to break down the system into
different components as I talked about
and just measure again how much time
we're spending in each of them it's okay
this is for a database where everything
fits in memory there's no any no reason
writes in memory nothing gets flushed to
disk and that right ahead log this is
just what is the cost of going access
data that's in memory using the disk
oriented architecture so the first
overhead is in the palpable manager this
is about 34 percent of the CPU
instructions are spent doing updates or
lookups into the page table doing
updates you keep track of all the
metadata you have for the eviction
policy 14% of the time spent doing
latching by this could be for the
internal data structures such as the
page table with the lock manager ran
anytime that's you know
the low-level constructor we need
protect 16 percent of instructions were
spent on locking so this particular
system it was called sure and uses
two-phase locking so this is the
overhead of updating the lock
information for transactions while they
run for 12 percent of the instructions
were spent in the log manager so this is
not the cost of running out the disk
this is the cost of preparing the law of
records that we're going to write out
then 16 percent of the time is spent
doing a comparison of keys doing
traversals in the B+ tree but this is
sort of unavoidable this is just saying
you know if I'm trying to find the
record that I want through the D plus
tree this is the cost of comparing keys
so this is now going to leave us with a
paltry 7% of the CP instructions we're
actually doing what what they would call
real work like executing the the logic
for transactions getting back the data
and then performing you know perform the
commit operations and things like that
so this is again this is showing you
that if you take a disk learning system
and you give it all the memory that it
wants so that everything everything fits
in memory you're not going to get
potentially the best performance because
everything could still you know you
still have pain the penalty for all this
internal architecture that assumes the
data is not on disk and there's all the
protection mechanisms for that
assumption and that are actually not
necessary
so my battery on my tablet shut down
earlier today when I was recording this
outside it got too cold and everything
just the whole thing to shut down I was
like 20 degrees Fahrenheit which is like
negative 7 or so degrees Celsius so that
was kind of weird so back inside in this
weird German gold deprivation chamber
thing that they have here again and
since to come in here and think about
deep thoughts about databases and
somehow become a better programmer like
a German I don't know if that's gonna
work so let's just continue with the
lecture so where we left off just now
was we were talking about how the
Discordian systems have because they
make that assumption that the
prime-minister education the davis could
be on disk there's all this architecture
set up so that at any time you know when
you read something you you have to go
check to see whether it's on disk and if
not you can install that thread and do
other stuff so now we're gonna switch
over and talk about an in-memory
database system so this is one where
that where the system's gonna zoom that
the primary search location is going to
be above all the data base is always
going to be permanently in memory so
that means that any single time a
transaction or a query goes and reads a
tuple it can assume that that thing is
going to be in memory and therefore it
doesn't have to go through all that page
table and in the buffalo and check
anything goes goes and reads whatever it
wants or writes whatever it wants so
it's not to say that everything we're
gonna talk about this semester is going
to be only targeting in-memory databases
but we'll see how there's be certain
design decisions that we're gonna make
that'll make our life easier if we make
this assumption so this idea of an
in-memory database is not new
the first proposed systems go back and
into the 1980s but they're not really
you know viable option now maybe in the
last 10 years because it's gotten to the
point where dear on prices and
capacities are such that you know we can
store really large databases in memory
so the you know that there was initial
ideas proposed in 1980s we'll talk a
little bit about that as we go
but the first commercial America
databases diddly didn't come out until
like the 1990s the most famous three are
probably times ten which is really
originally called small base and then
they forked off from HP and became times
10 and then Oracle bought them probably
about 2006 or so data blitz was the
system at a Bell Labs 1880 in the 1990s
it was urgent called dolly it was sold
for like telecom switches and things
like that I don't think it's still
around today or if it is it's sort of
it's obviously in legacy mode and the
Alta base is that a South Korea it's one
of these early beginners he's early game
every day to business which actually is
still around today and actually within
the last two or three years they're open
sourced it is you can go and check that
out of github so even though and now
that the Davis is gonna be entirely
named memory we're still gonna organize
data into blocks and pages does not slot
at pages because we don't you know what
the word about indirection within a page
itself and so the system architecture
would be slightly different now because
now instead of doing these record IDs we
can deal with direct memory pointers the
way we're gonna handle fixed length
versus variable length data if we
slightly different than a than a disk
based system because again we don't have
slotted pages and although not many
systems have this because some do there
is a concern that now because
everything's in memory any thread can
read or so you can write anything in the
address space of the process so to make
sure that we don't have you know
error-prone software collaborating our
data and causing permit damage we can
use check sums throughout the system of
these blocks to keep track of you know
the status of a page and you know detect
errors with these ever problems now
underneath the covers the operating
system and the hardware is also going to
be organizing memory into pages as well
that's not really going to be our
concern for most most of this semester
we'll talk a little bit later on and a
few more lectures because we need to
understand how it's actually going to
layout data so that when we start laying
that data we can align to what the
underlying
page representation in the OS is or the
hardware
is Roberts's now we can ignore that so
again let's return back to our
high-level example here where we were
had a query one of that accesses a tuple
lets people go through an index to look
it up so now in our index instead of
returning back a record ID or page page
ID in an offset we're now gonna get a
block ID in an offset and this block ID
could either be the direct memory
address of a fixed length block or there
could be an additional mechanism that
allows us to look it up and see you've
convert that block ID to a memory
location so the primary search locations
database again is in memory or every
tuple is in memory but we're gonna
organize them in these fixed length
through records and so for this it
doesn't matter what we're assuming a
roast or a column store but the basic
idea is the same and that is we're gonna
have a set of blocks or restore the
fixed length data for a tuple so
anything like an int dates floats reals
things like that all that can be stored
is fixed length and fixed length block
and that means that the size of every
tuple here is going to be the same and
so that says now if we have as block ID
and we convert that back to a memory
address when we want to do a lookup to
find the tuple within the offset of that
block we just do some simple memory
arithmetic to take the size of the tuple
multiplied by our offset and then as
tell us where to be jump in memory that
blocked and regret it now to handle very
length data this is gonna be much
different than what we would do in a
disk based system so variable length
data were instead instead of actually
storing the data in line the fixed
length data block for the most the time
restore point err to some other memory
location in a very linked data pool
where that's a direct access to the data
that corresponds to the this attribute
within this tuple and again the idea
here is that we can guarantee that all
the tuples and the fixed length data
blocks are fixed length and then for
anything that's variable length we shove
that into the very length data block
again this is different than the slotted
page design you would see in a disk
coordinate system because in there we're
trying to reduce the number of disk
reads so therefore we try to pack in all
the variable length data
for a tuple within you know with the
tuple itself all the fixed length data
that doesn't always happen and if it the
spillover to another page we can do that
but most the time we try to make that
happen
and in this world in memory system were
actually want to store the variable
length data separately so that way we
can do that deterministic lookups to
find memory addresses for tuples all
right some other things that better
could be different then we kind of
talked about quickly within memory
databases right and again these are the
things we're talk about their entire
semester the first one is gonna be how
we're actually going to store indexes
sort of how with data structures we're
gonna use for indexes so when this first
in memory database systems were proposed
in the 1980s the harbor it was a lot
different than the hardware we know
about today or how the harbor is laid
out today so in particular back then the
cache and memory access beats were about
the same but now this is not the case at
all right CPU caches are way faster than
main memory access so back then people
were designing data structures were you
know reading from cache was the same as
reading memory to be so they would
organize a certain way but now in the
modern era we don't want to do that
so therefore we want to use indexes that
know that they're dealing with memory
and they're and they have caches and try
to minimize the cache misses when when
he access things so the spoiler is gonna
be that a B+ tree is gonna turn out to
be a the best data structure to use for
a name every day but it's even though
d-plus trees were originally designed
for disk based databases they're
actually still really good for in-memory
data as well so the other major think
difference between the difference we're
gonna have indexes is that in a disk
based system you would also write log
records and write out pages for the
index disk so that you can recover them
after the system restarts an in-memory
system we're actually not going to
record any low of record to not write
indexes out to disk for most systems
because the cost of rebuilding the index
after restart the system is is gonna be
super low rise to think about this when
the system and the rate is when I
restarted I gotta bring the database
entirely back in the main memory and so
the cost of reading that there's the
data from from disk is super expensive
whereas the cost of building
index at once the data is already in
memory is is it's cheap because it's
just CPU computations so for this reason
and and gain avoiding the having to log
records to the log updates to records to
the in debt updates to the index at
runtime or just slow us down
we just rebuild the index after after we
restart again we'll cover this and clean
it's more detail when we talk about
indexes for query processing again now
in the dissapointing system the disk i/o
was always the most expensive thing who
cares what kind of for the most part how
you computed the data or you know the
organize the access of data once it was
in memory so in a disk wedding system or
so an in-memory system we are gonna care
about now the overhead of doing function
calls and branches of the things like
that so you need more care for how we
organize the system and do query
processing sequential scans are also not
significantly faster in a in memory
system so maybe there's certain
algorithms and you know join join
methods for doing joins and other things
that we don't have to worry about making
your optimizing or maximizing that of
schedule access because random access it
will be good enough again we'll cover
this in more detail as we go along for
logging and recovery I sort of mentioned
this already before but now that
everything is in memory there are no
dirty pages you to flush out the disk we
can be more conservative or we can end
up recording less data than we need then
we normally would need a disk or new
system if we know that everything is in
the memory so standard techniques like
root camp we'll use the batch of logs
amortize FSN cause that's that's
applicable for a disk warning system too
but being able to use a more lightweight
logging scheme is a definite advantage
for a in memory system right because
again there's no dirty pages we don't
need to do undo anything we write to
disk as part of a checkpoint is going to
be a party from a committed transaction
for the most part all right so now if
the disk i/o is not the slowest resource
then we can change
and we change what sort of protocols and
methods and algorithms are using the
process queries and transaction in a
database system now we can be mindful
with the other bottlenecks that are now
going to come to the forefront because
disk i/o is no longer in the critical
path so this is essentially what the
entire semester is about how to deal
with these other issues when we design
database systems so locking latch and
Sorkin kernel methods and the lone
low-level primitives to protect those
data structures cache lionesses are big
deal cos can memory access versus cache
access is is much more expensive
chasing pointers doing jumps to random
locations in memory and it will cause
more cache misses that's problematic
evaluating predicates do you know taking
the where clause for every for a billion
tuples and evaluating it that's gonna be
expensive moving data or copying data so
data movement would be if I have to move
data from one sock CPU socket to another
that's expensive copying data would be
materializing the intermediate results
or copy data between sockets to pass
things around those are things we want
to avoid and of course networking is
always a big issue now there be
primarily between the application and
the database system and not between
different nodes of the same database
matters were a discordant system - but
again now the disk is gone this is this
is even more problematic and an
in-memory system so for the rest of this
lecture I want to discuss locking and
latching um so we're gonna focus on the
cartridge hole here and this is just
mostly to set us up to understand going
forward how you know to think about and
that's it to think about you know what
is it that makes a game system slow and
when we started scaling up more CPU
cores
what does mean these other bottlenecks
and problems that were going to have so
again as we covered it in the
introduction class concurrent your goal
is essentially the protocol that the
deities have used that allows it to
execute multiple transactions at the
same time and each these transactions
are going to sort of have this illusion
that they're executing on the system by
it's by their self so they don't don't
worry about reading or reading the
effects of other transactions from at
the same time I this is essentially what
you would want to achieve in your system
because that's it's the easiest way to
program your application of course now
this is not easy to do if start
interleaving interleaving operations
between different transactions you could
violate this ordering so the kikuchiyo
protocol of any database system is going
to provide the atomicity and isolation
guarantees within this SSN acronym so
for an mme database system there's this
key observation we have to make about
how we're going to acquire locks to
access to poles and that is the cost of
a transaction acquiring a lock is
essentially the same thing as just
accessing the data so what I mean by
that is in a disk loading system we said
that all the locks would be stored in
memory in some kind of data structure
and they would be and they were separate
from the actual tuples but now
everything's in memory then the cost of
going and accessing the lock table is
going to be the same as accessing the
tuple so ideally I want to be able to do
those at the same time so that I'm not
paying the penalty of doing two memory
reads and this is the core idea that
furniture try to install and when we do
in memory data system concurrent control
the other important thing to understand
too is is in a disk running system the
stalls are due to transactions trying to
access data that wasn't memory you have
to go get out to disk and get them but
now we're not gonna have those kind of
stalls anymore yeah yes I'll be memory
stalls but those are gonna be much much
less than you know just stole but what
you think we are gonna have or that the
earlier assistants don't have is a way
more cores and so now the contention is
going to be in the system of many
transactions trying to read and write to
the same objects at the same time and
they're not stalling because there's a
disk there stolen because they don't we
can't acquire the locks on certain
things so do you understand again how
we're actually going to be able to
maintain locking information along with
the tuple we understand of this sort of
basic compare-and-swap primitive we're
going to use to modify things so we're
not going to use mutexes protect tuples
because there would be too slow instead
we're gonna use these atomic operations
called compare-and-swap
so I think this is primarily covered it
in other classes and so I just want to
give you a quick overview what it is and
because this is gonna come up multiple
times throughout the semester and it's
good to sort of see at once we're not
really details of actually how this is
implemented Hardware just know that this
this concept but actually exists so
compare swap is an atomic instruction
that pretty much every modern CPU will
provide you it's not a new concept I
think it goes back to the 1970s probably
pretty much every Zeon arm architecture
or a PowerPC will give me this now and
the idea is that it's a single
instruction that's gonna do a lookup in
a memory location and it's gonna check
to see where that memory location has a
certain value that provided and then if
that value is equal so the meta is a
value that memory location is the equal
to the value you're checking with then
you're allowed to install a new value to
update it otherwise the operation fails
and so in this example here this
underscore underscore sink pool compared
swap this is a this is a C++ or Linux
Lib C or Lennox did you see both flaws
operation or intrinsic different
platforms have different things and I
think for the most part in modern
systems there's there's either
understand or the intrinsic functions
that can do the same thing Daddy here is
that we're giving up giving in a memory
address
we're giving it a compare value and a
new value so the current memory address
that M points to contains the value 20
so in a single instruction now we're
gonna see whether 20 equals 20 in the
memory location and if yes one stall
install the new value 30 so in this case
here in a single instruction and we look
up to see that M equals 20 and it does
so then we can stall 30 right otherwise
that this would have failed so in this
example here the the function here
returns true false and saying whether is
succeeded or not there's all different
types of compare and swap instruction
and sometimes they'll return by
the the new guy that I got installed or
the old one if it didn't get updated
some and then you can change the you
know the size of the memory dress that
you're looking at with 32 bits or 64
bits but again the basic idea is always
the same thing within a single
instruction we can do this check and
this is we incorporate them that were to
use all throughout the semester allows
do these kind of lock free or latch free
operations very efficiently so we want
to talk about quickly sort of the tutor
of categories or classes of comparable
protocols that we're gonna be working
with this semester and this again
there's sort of a refresher from what we
covered in the introduction class lesson
Osterman and so the first time you two
phase locking so these are pessimistic
schemes where the data systems going to
assume that transactions are going to
conflict and therefore they have
required locks on any objects before
that allowed to access them
timestamp ordering is an optimistic
scheme where you assume conflicts are
rare so you don't require transaction to
acquire locks on database objects and
all you do instead is that when the
transaction goes to commit you see
whether there there was a conflict and
then you correct them as needed so let's
go through each of these one by one
showing really high-level examples and
then we'll get into the paper discusses
how do you actually implement this on
modern systems so if there's a simple
example for two phase locking we have a
transaction t1 and it wants to do a read
on a followed by a right on P so again
one or two phase locking we have to
acquire the locks for any object that we
want to read and write so in this case
here we've got to get the read on the
lock on a follow up a lock on B so this
is a really simple example or simplified
example because I'm you know there's
only this a simple one type of lock on
on a and B but in a real system as we
covered last semester you know you would
have different lock modes you can have a
shared mode the multiple transactions
read the same object and exclusive mode
to say that only one transaction can
lock it could connect can write it at a
given time so in this case here because
two-phase locking the first part of the
transaction is called the growing phase
and this is where we're
acquiring locks that we need okay sorry
that we're need during during the
exertion in the transaction and then
soon as we release one block now we're
in the shrinking phase and we're not
allowed to acquire any new locks but we
can do operations on the only objects we
still have all the locks for so in a
real system like in it's based on sequel
you wouldn't actually have explicit lock
and unlock commands these are something
we've dated some dust where you
automatically underneath the covers so
typically you you don't release the
locks until the transaction actually
commits which is called rigorous new
phase locking but for a preferences here
in this example we're not doing that we
can unlock a and then file and then do
the write on B and that still follows
the original two phase locking protocol
all right so let's say now we have
another transaction t2 comes along and
it wants to do a write on the father I
don't name and so say these transactions
are running at the same time on
different threads and therefore they can
they can do these things in parallel
with each other so in t1 we first get
the lock on a on t2 and get a lock on B
this is fine assuming there's no other
transaction written at the same time so
both these transactions can acquire
those locks in the next step their
transaction t1 does the read on a which
is allowed to do because it holds the
lock on a transaction t2 does the right
on B which is a lot of do because it
holds a row the lock on beam but now we
get into trouble here because t1 wants
to do a lock on b t2 one's gonna lock on
a but each of these are held by the
other transaction so they have to stall
right and they've been there essentially
waiting for the other transaction to
give up the lock so I'm go ahead and can
make forward progress but of course we
have a deadlock here and so now we have
to do something to break this because
otherwise the system would be locked
forever so there's two ways to do
deadlock or handle deadlocks and if he's
locking the first to do deadlock
detection this is where you have a
separate background thread that's just
gonna occasionally or periodically wake
up check to see whether the transactions
are running and if it finds a deadlock
then uses some kind of heuristics to
decide how to kill them I could say you
know kill the transaction has
that has done the least amount of work
or is the oldest or holds the most locks
the various systems do various things
different systems do all have different
types of deadlock detection algorithms
deadlock prevention is instead of having
a separate thread you just have a way to
make sure that when transaction tries
acquire a lock they can't hold it then
it makes a decision about what it should
do other than just waiting so for
example if I if a transaction tries to
hold a lock acquire a lock but that lock
is being held by somebody else and you
can either kill itself or kill the other
transaction and steals locks right again
we do have to make sure we do the
operations in the right order so that
there's so that way there's you know
there's no cycle of dependencies all
right so the other type of protocol is
called timestamp ordering again this is
sort of category systems that are in use
time stamps than a lock to figure out
the right order that transactions should
be allowed to complete so the sort of
two basic protocols are basic time stamp
ordering which is sort of confusing
because it's usually referred to as the
time stamp boarding protocol which is in
the category of time stamp ordering
protocols but it's all call it basic tio
dis to differentiate it so the idea here
is that we're gonna check for conflicts
on every read and write and we're just
gonna and use time stamps determine
whether there is a conflict and then
we're gonna copy tuples into a private
workspace for each transaction as they
read them to ensure if they go back and
read the same cable they get the same
value because otherwise you could be
reading something that was written in
the future and that shouldn't have
happened
optimistic cartridge role is where in
addition to copying the things you read
into your prior work space okay you're
also gonna come make copies of any
tuples you modify and and all your
rights go into private workspace and
then when you go to commit then you do
the validation as checked as whether
there were the ramming conflicts and if
not then you can merge all your private
workspace changes back into the global
database so again we'll go through each
of these one by one so say for the basic
time stamp warning protocol we have a
transaction t1 wants to do a read on a
of write on B and there's been some kind
of stole
and wants to do it right on a so when a
transaction starts we have to assign the
timestamp because we're gonna use that
to determine the serial ordering of
transactions so there's different
schemes you could use I can use the
hardware clock I can use a logical
counter I use a hypo to the tune but for
simplicity let's just say we use a
logical counter and we just update that
counter every single time we start
transaction and we sign that new
timestamp to get to the to the to the to
the transaction so this transaction
starts and it's gonna give the timestamp
10000 1 now inside the database for
every single record we're storing we're
gonna maintain two additional fields so
we maintain the retime stamp in the
flight times 2 3 times same would be the
highest time stamp of the last
transaction that successfully read this
tuple and the write time stamp will be
the last times the time stamp of the
last time ii that road to this tuple the
idea is that these time stamps are
always going forward in time they can
never go backward because that would be
violating the time stamp ordering of
transactions all right so our
transaction starts does a read on egg so
the first thing needs to do is check the
write time stamp and see whether it's
time stamp is greater than hours meaning
we'd be trying to read something in the
future that we wouldn't read me allowed
to read in this case here the right time
stamp for record a is 10,000 hour time
stamp is 10,000 won so were we allowed
to read this so we need to update now
the re time stamp to check to see
whether it's time stamp is is less than
than hours and if it is then we want to
go ahead and update it so in this case
here we'll update it with 10,000 won now
this is telling other transactions that
may want to update this this tuple that
there's was a transaction at timestamp
10000 won that has read it so make sure
that we don't write something in the
past and this terms actually missed so
then now we do the right on beat same
thing we first check to see the right
time stamp
see if we have to see whether it's in
the future from when we're at and
therefore we would be overriding
future data with past data which is not
allowed and then we check the read time
stamp and make sure someone didn't read
this record in the future and if we did
write to it they would end up missing it
so in this case here our time stamp
checks out for both of these both the
reads and the rights so we go ahead and
update my time stamp field
then I'll say that our transaction has
some kind of stall like it's computing
the you know the 1 billion billionth
digit of pi or its accesses remote some
root system for whatever reason there's
a stall and during this time another
transaction comes along and modifies
record a and now updates at the right
time stamp with ten thousand five so now
we'll see that we have a real issue
because now when our transaction wakes
up and tries to then write to record a
that timestamp 10000 five is greater
than our timestamp 10000 one so we
shouldn't be allowed to do this because
this would be trying to overwrite a
logical record that was updated in the
future with a physical record of in the
past so in this case here this be
violating the time symbol ring and our
transaction has to get killed and aboard
it and we roll back any changes so most
systems that are out there don't do the
basic time stamp learning protocol the
more common approach is to do OCC
optimistic a cartridge whole again this
is confusing because time stamp ordering
protocols are by themselves or
optimistic schemes but there is a
protocol to this figure called the
Optima secure protocol scheme alright so
the basic idea here is that like touch
the border all right just late like time
see I'm ordering there we're gonna
maintain a private workspace we're gonna
copy all the read data into it so that
we go back and read same record you get
the same value we're also going to write
all our changes into that private
workspace as well so now when a
transaction commits we get the verify
that there's no conflicts and if not
then we can go ahead and install them to
the global database so OCC is an old old
protocol as you most most conclude your
protocols the basic ones are old this
one goes back to 1981 and actually was
invented here at Carnegie Mellon by
Professor HT Cohn HT Kong is no longer
here he's now at Harvard and he's not
even a Dana's professor he didn't know
networking but this is sort of like his
most famous work is actually a databases
paper so that's kind of cool this came
out of the computer
department here at CMU so here's the
simple transaction was to read on a on
write on read on a write on a and write
on B so in our database now we don't
need the read time stamp field for
records we only have to have the write
time stamp field and so now when our
transaction starts unlike in basic time
stamp boarding protocol we're not gonna
actually gonna assign it a time stamp
we're gonna do that later
so any time we're gonna read and write
stuff we're gonna make a copy of it in
into a private workspace and set it with
the types of infinity so OCC has three
phases so the first one unfortunately is
called the read phase so even though
we're gonna do rights and this this for
whatever reason the this they call this
the read phase of a transaction if I had
my choice app I would call this like the
run phase or in the execute phase I
think that makes more sense for whatever
reason it's called the read phase so
again we're gonna do a read on a here in
the B phase so we're gonna have to copy
that record and the global database into
our private work space so that again we
can always read this thing over and over
again at the same value so now when we
do on write on a write we're not gonna
modify the global database we're gonna
modify the one in a private workspace so
we don't have a write time stamp yet
because we haven't been assigned one so
we're just gonna set that to an infinity
in our workspace and then update the
value same thing on B here we're gonna
first copy it from the global database
into our private workspace and then
update it with our infinity timestamp
and the in our new value so now when our
transaction goes to commit it's not
actually gonna commit right away there's
not gonna be two additional phases the
validate phase in the write phase and so
the validate phase is basically where
we're gonna look at a private workspace
see what see what what records we
modified and go to see whether that
would by whether there's any there's
there's either transactions that are
still running but have read this data
and therefore they didn't see our
updates because there was in a private
workspace or there's transactions in the
past that I've already committed that
have modified this and therefore we
didn't actually see their changes
well and therefore we would have a
conflict so that's either you're doing
backwards validation a forward
validation again we covered that in the
introduction class it's not really
important right now but basic idea is
like you and you're making sure that
transactions are always committing sort
of in the right order so if we pass the
validate phase there's no conflicts then
we now enter the right phase where we
now are finally assigned a time stamp
and then we update the global database
with our changes that we've made from
our private workspace with out with our
new time stamp and then and then at this
point that transactions considered be
done and it goes and commits so the one
important thing to understand about this
is that when there's not really any
contention then the optimistic schemes
like OCC are actually performing better
than two-phase locking because since we
assume that the conflicts are rare we're
gonna spend less time checking for
complex right we spend less time looking
for for for conflicts that don't
actually exist it's sort of like in the
discordian system where if everything
fits in memory then we're gonna waste
time looking you know to see whether we
have to evict something to make space in
our buffer pool manager all right so
it's better off just to optimistically
assume everything fits and memory and
jump right to get and get what we need
but the issues can be now with high
contention I mean we have a lot of
transactions trying to tend to read and
write to the same records then all the
protocols that I've just talked about
are essentially going to degenerate down
to just being the serial execution of
transactions meaning only one
transaction can run at a time we're
gonna waste all this extra extra these
extra spend a lot of time in our
protocols doing work that's essentially
useless because we're transactions are
never gonna be able to commit so to
better understand this issue this is
what this the paper had you guys read is
about so this is a start the idea with a
former student of mine who is now a new
data to fester at the university
Wisconsin we did a few years ago where
we implemented a testbed system that
allows to evaluate different
aren't your protocols that rich green
levels of parallelism and so it's kind
of intrigue might this project is rather
than taking like post grass on my sequel
or whatever
Davison you want and trying to do a
bake-off between the two of them we
implemented a single system that had a
pluggable API that allows a plop in
different cultural protocols without
making major changes to the rest of the
system and the idea here is that we want
to strip it down to just being the bare
minimum you need to execute transactions
in a database system without all the
additional bells and whistles and
features that are yet that a
full-featured system like might see what
Prescott's would have we just focus on
what the overhead is of these
concurrency of protocols
so the idea also to was that we want to
run this you know this these systems in
a highly parallel environment so that it
would sort of really exposed as the in
what the main bottlenecks are in the
implementations of the different
protocols in the system in a way that
you couldn't get maybe running on a
machine like 32 cores or 64 cores which
is so the most you can get around this
time in 2014 when we wrote this paper so
the system we're gonna use for this
evaluation is called DB X 1000 so this
was again the system that the student
wrote for this paper and then it was
written from scratch just to have this
pluggable API allows you to plop that
drop in different implementations of
these concurrent your protocols so it's
a stripped-down system there's no
network access there's no logging at
least at the time that we were at this
paper and a dated support concurrent
indexes it really was just focusing on
how fast can you do convert your
protocols all the transactions are going
to execute with store procedures and so
that means all the server-side logic in
order to execute a transaction is
contained on on the data system itself
so you never talk about them over the
network and ask the application of the
client you know what should I do next
and so we're gonna run this now also in
a chip simulator developed by who at MIT
added my team called graphite and this
was modeling a single socket table based
CPU with a Nuka architecture so Nuka
stands for non-uniform cache acts
and we contrast that with the Neumann
architecture non-uniform memory access
that or mostly gonna be talking about
during the semester in like you know
Intel Xeon ships so Nuka basically means
that the cost of one core accessing the
cache of another core is not always
going to be the same because it's gonna
have this tile based architecture where
you have to communicate over this mesh
network in order do you know cache
invalidation and do reason writes
between different cores and so some
cores are closer to you on the network
and therefore your reading writing their
memory locations or their caches is much
faster than one that's mainland to clean
the other side of this network so I'm
not really an architecture person the
reason why we want with this or a tile
based approach is that when you talk to
people that are architecture experts
they said that when you start getting
them to like a thousand core count sort
of the conventional wisdom is that you'd
want to use a table based architecture
like this again the main takeaways we're
gonna get from the study are not gonna
be dependent on using a tile based
architecture and they're still
applicable to the xeon type system as we
talked about for the semester it's just
is what the harbor was that we had at
the time to model this so another
important thing to understand too is
that this cpu stimulator runs really
really slow all right it's it's ten
thousand X slower than the wall clock
time of a you know system running bare
metal so that means that there's a bunch
of optimizations the student had to do
indeed X 1000 that get to run at a
reasonable time in the simulator so if
you go look at the code on github you'll
find that there's a lot of them there's
a lot of assembly in the different parts
of the system because he had to do that
to get it to run run fast and her you
know get the experience to finish in
time all right so the target workload
we're gonna be using for this paper is
going to be y CS be W Yahoo Cloud
something benchmark so the it's
basically a key value store workload
that's sort of meant the model the sort
of ESS patterns of a web services or web
based applications so in the database
there'd be two million tuples and each
tuple is is one kilobyte so every
transaction that we're gonna model our
Iran in our system is gonna execute
queries they're gonna read and write
sixteen different tuples at a time and
we're gonna vary their access patterns
excu in the access pattern so sometimes
they'll be hotspots and sometimes
they'll be uniform access and all the
transactions are so going to run a store
procedure
store procedure is running the
serializable isolation level so the six
different schemes are going to compare
or based on the the different type of
protocols that I talked about before so
for two phase locking there's gonna be
deadlock detection and then deadlock
prevention with no wait and wait and die
and this is emblematic of sort of the
some of the biggest database systems
that are out there today now in the time
stamp ordering side there's a time stamp
ordering and there's FCC and there's a
multi version there's the original multi
version protocol present or described in
the 1979 paper that version described
MVCC that uses time stamp whirring next
class we'll see that you can have
different variants of multi versioning
that uses OCC or two phase locking but
for this one we just went with this sort
of in the original protocol for posed in
the 1970s and this is emblematic about
most of the newer systems today as well
as some sort of classic database systems
that use multi versioning alright so for
the first experiment here this is sort
of the sort of the baseline performance
of these different protocols and a
read-only workload so what you're seeing
is that along the x-axis as we scale the
number of cores we're adding work the
more concurrent transactions running at
the same time so every single time we
added a core that's going to have an
additional transaction running that's
you know run important executing part of
the workload so 200 cores there's 200
current transactions at the same time so
this is a read-only workload with
uniform memory access or tuple access so
and this is the best that these
different protocols can do because
there's there's zero contention so the
first thing we see is that the deadlock
detection and the no wait protocols
actually can almost scale linearly and
perform the best because these protocols
are so simple there's no
locks and therefore the overhead of
transactions and executing is mental
next thing you see is that there's me
here at eight hundred cars where wait
and die and MVCC start start to dip down
and this is due to the overhead of
allocating unique time stamps for
transactions as they're running right
when you're running with a million
transactions at the running the same
time or when you're running eight
million transactions a second for this
table based architecture at the time
stamp allocation and coordinating across
all the different threads becomes a
bottleneck and lastly you see that OCC
here actually does the worst and so this
is a combination of of having to copy
the private workspace for every single
transaction and copy that back into the
system that actually comes a big
bottleneck so next we see here is a
write intensive workload where you know
I have transactions actually updating
the database and this is on a medium
contingent workload where 60% of
transactions are going to try to access
a hot spot of 20% of the database so the
first thing you need to see is that
deadlock detection is actually now the
worst protocol used for this miss
environment you know in the last slide I
showed you to was actually the best but
now when you have high content to higher
mountain contention there's deadlocks
there's more dead locks in the system
and therefore it takes longer for the
deadlock detection thread to come around
and break these dead locks so you sent
you have threads stolen and waiting for
that deadlock detection threat to come
through and clean things up and that
hurts performance next you see that the
no wait and wait I actually do the best
all right and this is because these
protocols are so simple so what's
happening is that the you know yes
there's anytime there's a conflict and
there would be a deadlock these
protocols immediately just kill the
transaction to restart them so you don't
spend any wasted time trying to figure
out you know should I wait or you know
hoping the other transaction could give
up a slot you make some action right
away
no waits the simplest one writes
basically says I try to acquire my trans
block I couldn't get it immediately kill
myself and again because we're store by
seizures there's no overhead of
restarting transaction and in a memory
environment it's super fast
all right in the middle here you see the
three timestamp warning protocols basic
tio MVCC and OCC they're roughly all
doing about the same of CCS doing slower
again because there's extra overhead of
copying things into the work you know in
and out of the work space over and over
again but you know they're roughly about
the same so now we get to this final
graph here which is the most important
one of the paper and this is where we're
running a writing system workload where
90% of the transactions are updating 10%
of the database so now you see that all
the protocol is basically crashed down
to zero when we get up to a thousand
cores okay there's none of these
protocols were actually scaling sewing
and the reason is that this is all this
overhead of transactions having to check
for conflicts or copy things around and
there's so many conflicts that you just
can't make any for you know for progress
and get things completed so one
interesting thing is that you see no
wait is kind of going along doing okay
relative to the other protocols until
800 threads and then it crashes down to
zero so it's not doing that great
compared to the previous life think it's
only executing 200,000 transactions a
second where's the other slice I was
sharing you can do millions of
transactions a second but again it's
it's doing okay because it's it's
protocol is so simple that yes there's
no way when the system identifies that
there's going to be a deadlock it kills
the transaction immediately restarts it
where's the other ones and they cost of
doing that is super cheap relative the
other ones of course now at a thousand
cores doing that just you just go
boarding transactions so much that you
can't get any work done
the other interesting thing to point out
is that OCC is actually the worst over
here when you have a small number of
cores but on the other side is actually
doing the best and again this is what
because it's basically des generating
down to do user execution of
transactions so the way the protocol
works is that when you enter the
validation phase you can guarantee that
one transaction is in that validation
phase and therefore one always always be
allowed to actually commit so when
you're essentially running here at a
thousand thread
a thousand cores is through running same
thing is you're running on one course at
least one transaction is gonna always be
guaranteed to commit and that's why if
it gets rough at the same performance it
gets on the other side of the graph
right but the main takeaway again is
that over here at a thousand cores
everything's is doing bad and roughly
it's got a little bit better since 2014
we were at this paper but this is
roughly where we are actually today in
modern systems in terms of running me in
a single box there 64 32 or 64 cores so
we really haven't hit in the danger zone
in a modern system of of having high
contention and you know without really
large number core counts on a single box
we're just sort of not there yet but
just this graph basically shows you that
the existing methods that we use out
today aren't I'm gonna be scalable and
so real quickly where are we actually
spending our time so this is a breakdown
of the different protocols while the xu
transactions and you see that in the
case of no wait it's spending a large
percent of its time boarding
transactions because can soon as it
finds a conflict it says this this is
bad and just restarts it or is the other
protocols are spending time waiting to
try to acquire locks or try to acquire
time stands are waiting with a
delectation thread again that's all just
sort of wasted work all right so let's
quickly talk about some of the
bottlenecks we identified in this paper
and sort of some potential solutions we
can to get around them and the idea here
is sort of understand these issues at
high level so that again when we start
talking about FVCC more detail in the
next class in the back your mind should
be thinking about oh well this is how
they would handle this this is how this
could be a problem when we see hit
larger core accounts than what we
actually have today so lock thrashing
time some allocation memory allocations
will cause each of these one by one so
lock thrashing is a phenomenon that you
would have in a two phase locking system
where the if a transaction ends up
waiting longer required locks then this
causes other transactions waiting behind
it end up waiting longer to acquire the
locks at the first transactions holding
and therefore that causes other
behind that service second path of
transactions to wait even longer so is
this convoy effect we're cause one
transaction wait longer cause everybody
else wait longer and then that gets
exacerbated as you add more transactions
so one way we can actually measure this
in our system is by removing all the
overhead of doing any deadlock check
prevention or deadlock detection and
just having transactions just do nothing
but acquire locks and just wait and so
in this case here the way we can do this
is that we're gonna force transactions
required locks always in some kind of
primary key order just think of like
we're holding you know we have a lock
one two three four five six and we have
to acquire them in that sort of
lexicographical order so in this
environment deadlocks are possible so
we'll never have any stalls due to dead
locks it's just just the stalls waiting
to acquire these locks and so if you run
that experiment on the system you get a
graph like this so the fader variable
here is representing the amount of skew
in the workload or more transactions
trying to access a small number tuples
so the most extreme case is stated 0.8
and theta zero means there's there's no
contention so what you see is are these
nice curves these knee bends where the
lock freshman comes into play and now
transactions are end up waiting the
longer and longer to acquire locks when
there's more contention right and at
some you know this grabs keeps going
down these lines keep going down you
don't recover from this thrashing effect
when I really like what this experiment
is because is that it shows this graph
actually looks exactly like any sort of
textbook that shows you were describes
lock thrashing right like this is sort
of one example of a textbook but they
always had this sort of theoretical
diagram of like oh here's the effect of
lock thrashing but you know in this case
here our graph matches exactly what you
would expect to see according according
to according to the theorem which is
kind of nice I have a time stamp
allocation is it not necessarily gonna
be a big issue for us in our system
we're gonna get by with doing either
batch addition or atomic addition which
is another variant
swap but it's basically saying that in a
really large number core counts having a
transaction to opto acquired unique
timestamp so they actually could be a
big bottleneck so the mutex is always is
gonna be bad we don't boy that
impossible atomic add bash these are
just compare swap methods and then for
these particular cpus some cpus like
intel they can have a hardware clock or
you can get through some instruction but
this is not clear whether intel's
exigent going to keep this around and
that's not something we potentially
would want her lie on and then a harvard
calendar approach was something that was
something that the the student came up
with an added to the the graphite
simulation system this is not something
that we would have it you know that
exists today and so this graph is just
showing you that the one of these
bottlenecks come into play for running
these different time scheme allocation
schemes and again the batch atomic one
is probably gonna be good enough for
what we need right we're talking you
know trying to allocate a hundred
million time stamps for a second that's
more than we'll ever need all right the
memory allocation stuff
the main issue here is that since we
have to now copy things into private
workspaces for some some protocols or
you know copy tuples and make sure penal
reads in public spaces that copying can
be expensive and so if we use the
default Lipsy malloc that's gonna always
be super slow and we never want to use
it so we're not gonna discuss different
memory allocators too much this semester
other than say we don't want to use the
default malloc when we end up using GE
malloc or TC malloc or these other
malloc protocols their libraries that
are out there all right so again I
realized it's kind of weird for having
me give the rest of this lecture in this
this gold-plated chamber thing but I
just want to get this out there so that
we can start talking about MVC see more
detail on on Wednesday I want to come
back to come back to campus so the main
takeaway what you give in this lecture
is that the design of an in-memory data
system has be much different than a disk
writing system conceptually it's the
same right you
two queries their indexes will not
transactions but the implementation of
the protocol of these systems are gonna
be much different and the good news also
too is that a memory databases are not
considered to be super bizarre anymore
when I first started grad school maybe
over ten years ago now but like 2007
2006 they're considered sort of an
exotic system but nowadays especially
with systems like Redis they become more
common if people become more comfortable
with the idea of having in memory
systems the one thing that I will say is
that in recent years it seems like the
DRAM prices and capacities have stalled
compared to the games we've seen in SSDs
so whereas before I was pretty bullish
about oh well in memory databases are
gonna take over the world of court why
would you ever want to use dissapointing
system I I don't think that's actually
true and I think that it's worth looking
to see what we can do to bring back SSDs
in a database system without actually
having to slow it down and bringing all
the overhead of a disk oriented
architecture so we'll talk about little
bit at the end of the semester but
that's something in the back of my mind
I think it'll come up a couple of times
during the semester okay
all right so just to finish up this is
it for today I'll be flying back this
Friday and I'll be on campus on Tuesday
next week and we'll have the recitation
for discussing that the architecture of
the system and then on Wednesdays class
next week well we will start discussing
multi version commercial because again
this is the the dominant method or
protocol that everyone uses but it's
more than just compared to protocol it's
gonna sort of you accomplish all
different aspects of the data system so
we'll start understanding that a bit
more detail okay so that's it for today
I'm gonna go hang out with the Germans a
bit more and then I'll see everyone next
week in class all right take care see ya
what is this
say you're here I took a sip in hand to
spend tonight with Ned here called the
Hokey cuz I'm og Ice Cube down with the
testy you look and it was go grab me a
40 song cuz I needed just a little more
kick and my hunky to say I'm nice to
take a say I pray