[Music]
[Applause]
for today's class I've gone back and
forth three or four times and what I
want to call this lecture like it was
originally I think just old to be
indexes lat free data structures then I
switched it to be plus tree data
structures and then as of last night I
said let's call it whole key data
structures and then I'll make more set
more sense and a few more slides but the
main idea here is just like we're just
talking meant what kind of indexes or
data structures we could build or use
for doing for all GP workloads the other
thing that I forgot to mention when
Piazza because they were later and gave
me the information there actually is a
visitor today from snowflake coming to
give a talk at 4:30 on the query
optimizer in snowflake snowflake is a
one of the biggest sort of OLAP cloud
database vendors davis is a service i
competitor to be something like google's
bigquery or amazon's redshift and so
beau way is actually a former student of
mine here at CMU
he took 721 like you guys started
working in the query optimizer people
could not hire him fast enough so he's
been a snowflake for two years now and
he loves it so they'll give a talk today
about the kind of stuff they're doing in
the query optimizer at 4:30 so by all
means please come to this and I'll I'll
send a reminder on Piazza ok everyone's
invited
but wait I think there's a summer
recruiting event and campus this week
guy I forget why he's here what's
tomorrow with that ok so he's here for
that but like I said if you take this
class many ways the things that you'll
learn from this will help you get know
past the interviews various data to
companies and so boy I can tell you
whether that's true or not cuz he's been
it you know he's been uh something like
for a while ok all right so as I said at
the beginning I debated back and forth
what I want to call this lecture and
whole key is kind of not exactly true
but the main thing I want to try to
distinguish is the things we'll talk
about today versus what we're going to
talk about on on Wednesdays class
so this is also in quotes because this
is my term I don't think this is
actually what this is not standard
standard vernacular I don't know what
they say an information theory but this
is this is what I'm using just to
contrast the two by whole key I mean
that we're have a data structure where
it's gonna be ordered reserving so we
want to make sure we can keep track of
you know whether one key is less than
another key and that we're going to
store all the digits of that key
together in the various parts of its
representation inside of the the data
structure so what I mean that is if I
have a key ABC I could have in in my
leaf node I could have Kiki ABC together
and now if I want to do comparison see
where the my key is less than a greater
than or equal to that given key I I have
all the contents of the key right there
that's not entirely true when you start
doing some compression techniques but
for our purposes today we can assume
that's the case all right and then on on
Wednesdays class we'll talk about what
I'll call partial key data structures or
tries where you actually break up the
digits of a key and store them
separately inside the nodes inside the
data structure right so one way to think
about this is like with this approach so
with this approach you the partial key
like you may have to do less work to
find whether something that you matches
amantha store less data potentially as
well to represent all the keys in your
in your data structure but you may have
to still go out and look at the original
tuple or the original record to see what
was the original key that you're doing a
canoe and look up long because it may
not all be contained in the tree whereas
in the the whole key you know key ABC
exists in the tuple key ABC will exist
in in the data structure
okay so again this will make more sense
as we go along I think I contrasting it
with with with Wednesday's lecture but
for our purposes today we just assume
that we're dealing with B plus trees so
today I understand most of the time
talking about the BW tree because that
was the assigned reading and that's the
current data structure we use in our in
our database system today and part of
the reason I want to have you guys read
this is because it is exposure to how
you actually want to build a lat tree
data structure lacks flash
B+ tree right you may if you read on
Hacker News or we don't own the Internet
you may think people saying like oh
these lats read data structures relax
that tree algorithms are superior to one
that do use latches and you always want
to be using the latter II data structure
and I certainly thought that was the
case when we first started building our
own BW tree but the paper you guys read
basically shows that you don't so before
we get there though I want to provide
some historical background of what kind
of data structures people built
originally for in memory memory
databases and particularly the tea tree
and then we'll also then finish up how
to actually then take a regular P Plus
tree as we described in the introduction
class and maybe do something a bit
smarter and how we do latching right and
that's how when you read that paper when
you see the B+ tree beat the BW treaty
so everybody using this last last
technique here okay all right so back in
the day in 1970s before we were all born
they mentioned the B+ tree
and at the time since they were dealing
with discs going to databases and discs
was super slow the B+ tree turn out to
be a a well-designed data structure to
allow you to efficient access for long
strides of sequential sequential data so
I trust the tree died in log n time in I
land on my leaf node and I scan along
the leaf nodes until I find the key to
looking for all right so that's
fantastic right again if this is slow
scruncher weeds are faster than random
reads this this this approach was
perfect for it so then in the 1980s
there's some early work done on
designing the first Mme databases and in
that world you don't have a slow disk
you have fast random i/o in memory so
the idea what they were looking into was
can we build a it you know is there an
alternative data structure we want to
use instead of a B+ tree that would be
preferable and more efficient for a in
memory databases and so the the most
famous one that came out of this work
was called the Tea Tree so Tea Tree is
gonna look like an AVL tree basically
just means that instead of having you're
looking at B+ tree where the the keys
always exist on the leaf nodes and then
the inner nodes are just gone
posta to tell me to tell you whether
goes left to right in the inn and the
tea tree the keys gonna be scattered all
throughout the different notes with the
leaf nodes and the inter notes but the
big way the big difference between us
treating and the tea tree is that
instead of throwing the keys in all the
nodes like copies of the keys in all the
nodes there instead disgust reporters to
the original wreckers the two Plzen
cells and the idea here was back in the
1980s when memory was quite limited
instead of storing redundant copies of
the keys like in a whole key B plus tree
if we destroyed the pointers then that's
way more efficient in terms of memory so
yes we paid that penalty of doing that
lookup to say we know for this pointer
what's the actual key that corresponds
to that tuple but again that reduces the
amount of total size of the index so the
tea tree was originally posed in 1986 by
the universe University Wisconsin I was
Mike Carey in his group of doing a lot
of early work in memory databases of the
1980s and in the 1990s when people
started building the first in memory
databases the commercial ones like small
base out of HP which became times 10
that Oracle bought and it's still around
today you know these first early in
memory data businesses actually used the
T to design so one key aspect of why tea
trees actually worked back then was that
the difference in speed between CPU
caches and and and DRAM was not as
significant as it is now all right so
back then if I if I had at the cache
miss and had to go read something in
memory that you know in the teaching
role in the nineteen eighties that
wasn't that big of a deal so it was okay
to follow that pointer right because you
know it wasn't a big performance penalty
and you saved a lot of space in the in
the in the data structure itself right
so I've been teaching tea trees because
I think they're fascinating and there's
not a lot of there is a Wikipedia
article about them and as I said time
stands still uses them today but default
though like you get if you create a
table or index in times 10 you get a B+
tree you can pass a flag to force to get
a tea tree but there's very few
databases that still use tea tree
today's they're mostly for like embedded
devices running like extreme low memory
environments so there really isn't that
much information about them so I always
like to talk about them because I think
I think they're kind of fascinating and
it turns out the guy that actually
invented it sent me an e-mail at last
month and just say hey look I see you're
talking about tea trees and the mistake
I always made was I said oh it's called
a tea because the the note looks like a
tea but he tells me I'm wrong and so the
guy's name is Toby Lehman he got his PhD
at University Wisconsin I he named it
after himself so the tea and tea tree is
Toby which i think is awesome so now the
for a B+ tree right we always say oh the
B means balanced he says that it
actually just means it's named after
himself the Rudy Bey or the guy that did
the original work he just called it be
for himself I don't know whether that's
true but tea tea and tea tree means Toby
which is awesome and he points out some
other organizations that I'll talk about
in a second so again this is why I love
the Internet because I've never met this
guy I actually know who he is he just
found the YouTube video and he sent me
an email hey that you're wrong about
some things which is fantastic okay so
here's here's what the data truck looks
like again I always thought because it
was the the nose look like look like t's
and that's why they call my tea tree but
that's not the case so what does the
node actually look like so the nodes me
a combination of pointers and then just
two keys so the first thing we'd have
here these are the data pointers and
these are gonna point out now out to the
actual table and a correspond to the to
the tuples that they represent all right
so this is our data table these are the
keys so these are just pointers to two
different keys right or to the original
to post so these pointers will be sorted
in the order of the keys that are stored
in the data table right so now I keep
again I can do that binary search that I
would normally do in a B+ tree to jump
around to find the the entry that I'm
looking for but any single time I need
you to comparison like is my key equal
to this key or less than a greater than
I gotta follow the pointer to get to the
original tuple to figure out what the
original key was all right okay in a
modern system I our pointers are 64 bits
in the actuality they're 48 bits but but
you have to allocate a 64 bit 64-bit
pointers space back then you know these
things were I think probably 16 bits and
the values neighbor 16 bits so by not
having store the key plus the the
pointer back to the key right I can
reduce the size
of the amount of states had the story
nice knowed by half right the other
thing would have now is also these data
pointers so unlike in a B+ tree where
you normally only have the pointer to
either your child or any sibling if
you're a leaf node in a tea tree you
have to have pointer back to your parent
because the leaf nodes aren't going to
be the final location of keys we may
have to reverse backups we need have a
pointer to go back there and then we we
have pointers to the right and left
child then we have our node boundary
keys and this will just be the min and
Max value of the key that's represented
by this node and so anything that is
less than this key will be found on this
side of the tree anything that's great
in that key will be found on the other
side right so this is not like how does
his it's not like in a in a and a B plus
tree where the root node would have you
know the right and left boundary would
be sort of encompass most of the space
below you in the key space right this is
just a slice of the key space all rights
and then now let's look at it say about
actually want to look up so we have a
three node tea tree and we're trying to
find key k2 so again I started the root
right these are just pointers to the
original keys so my key space here for
this node here encompasses some Kum Kee
for two key six inclusive so here now I
have pointers that are that are sorted
in the key order over to what's being
stored in the data table so now then I
have my my pointers down here and that
allows me to do my traversal so the very
beginning i struttin the root I'm
looking for a key key to so I only need
to potentially do one comparison per key
to figure out a perm node to figure out
where I need to go so again I have a
copy of this key here because this way I
can do this efficiently without having
to go out to the original table but I
just do a quick comparison it's K 2 less
than k 4 and if yes then I know I want
to follow that pointer down here all
right so even though I said it's kind of
inefficient to have to do these pointer
lookups most the time you don't have to
do that it's only when you land on the
node to find what you're looking for
that you think the key should be in this
that you have to do follow this all
right so then we we land down here
and then now we check to see whether K 2
is greater than K 1 it is we also want
to check where the K 2 is less than K 3
it is so we know that our key will exist
because we know or it should it could
potentially exist because it's within
our boundaries here right
so now we just do now again this keep it
simple because we don't we only have
three keys per node but we used to a
linear scan and look at every single
record right follow the pointer and then
do our prepare some of the key over
there yes question is when would you go
back up I don't have a slide for this
but when you do a range scan like final
Keys greater than k2 I would come to
come down here scan along find
everything and then jump back up and
keep going
so basically in the initial search
you're trying to find the from your side
the leftmost starting point and then you
scan along and when you realize there's
nothing below me and I think there's
something up above I filed back home his
question is are there no sibling
pointers and that's why we have to go up
correct yes that's that's how AVL trees
work yes y3 in this example because it
fit in a slide so again like there's
there's nothing in the original
specification the key of the tea tree
that says you have to have three again
to make it fit I put three you could
have five get 20 in whatever it doesn't
matter
yes so her question is what
differentiates that this range in the
pin the route between are the parent
between the children so again so in a B+
tree all the keys are at the bottom
alright and in a ABL tree you can
actually regular B tree you could have
keys anywhere throughout or key and
value pointers to the actual tuples
anywhere in the data structure in the
tree right so in a B+ tree if I only
have keys in the leaf nodes
a couple keys and then the values to the
point is leaf nodes then I have up above
I'm wasting space because a now I'm
storing these guidepost keys so they're
trying to use get the maximum usage of
every single node and so they store the
key value pointers anyone including the
root node here in the parent node here
well the these are guideposts but if I'm
looking for for Keith's key five for
example and I'm here then I would say
key four key five is greater the key for
and key 5 is less than key six so I know
the thing I'm looking for is in here so
I don't need to look at leaf nodes right
again and a B+ tree they pushed
everything to the bottom because now if
I want to do that skin I don't backtrack
I just scan along leaf nodes
sequentially and I find what I want yeah
yes question is why does having a B+
tree design of pushing all the the
actual the keys and the values to the
leaf nodes how's that better for the
scoring there versus this being
scattered anywhere for a four in meri
system so again if I'm trying to find a
find a range of values right it's an
order preserving tree so if it is a B+
tree all the leaf nodes are stored in in
that order I just try to find the left
most node to start and then I
sequentially scan which is faster on a
disk Orion system least in the spinning
us even actually even today them SSDs
they're still faster but like I just now
do a sequential scan along the bottom
and find what I want I never to go back
up we're trying to avoid random i/o in
this world random i/o is not a big deal
because it's in memories who cares so I
can jump around and Traverse back up and
I don't pay a big penalty for that all
right am i sticking to her back to her
point by storing the the by using all
the upper notes or the inner nodes of
the data structure to actually store
keys and values that I care about I buy
a waste less space right cuz in a B+
tree I could I could delete a key right
in the leaf node and I can extend the in
the internet because that's my guidepost
okay
it's got here look at it okay so I think
I've said a lot of this already
again like part of the reason why I
teach tea trees is because it's just in
its a different way of thinking about
how to do a memory database and then the
indexes and you may come across some or
you may come across somebody who says oh
why are we using a B+ tree for in memory
database shouldn't we be using you know
in a more optimizing their data
structure like a tea tree the answer's
no because well I'll get to the
defenders in the next slide but just a
missus mostly just for your background
information so again we already said
this we store use less memory for index
because we don't store the copy keys in
every single node and then every single
key is also always being used for
storing key value pairs and not just
guideposts the other interesting thing
that the the inventor of the teacher you
pointed out which I think there's kind
of something I didn't think about is
that in a tea tree because now when you
do the evaluation of saying is my key
equal this key or does my search key
equal that the two plus key I'm falling
the pointer I'm looking at the whole
record so once you do that you're
already sort of paid the penalty of
falling the pointer and now looking in
the record instead of just comparing you
see whether that's the search key
matches that the indexed keys for that
tuple you might as well evaluate all the
other predicates that you have in your
where clause right if I have a where
clause where a equals one and B equals
two and my index is only on a and a B
plus tree I would just do traversal
because and only look at a because
that's the only thing I can see inside
my index then I have to go do the lookup
on the index or the tuple then evaluate
B but in a tea tree you could just do
that all at once right while I'm looking
at the tuple for a maza look at B so you
could potentially end up throwing away
or throwing out tuples that more quickly
than you would otherwise
yes david has been the key table what do
you like a key table
this is the whole yet so yeah this
column data this is like a bunch of
other attributes this is this is the
attribute I'm Keith I'm the next one
there's no separate key table that would
be waste of space why because I mean the
index itself is a key table to think of
it okay so for this one here there are
techniques in modern systems to sort of
get this benefit as well so you can do
like partial indexes where you you
define a where clause for what keys
could be in the index like build index
that only have students that are in
enrolled at fifteen seven 21 right and
so all the other students that aren't in
the class aren't inside the index and so
that way that's sort of like
pre-filtering the where clause ahead of
time without having a stores an extra
information or in other systems you can
have include columns so you can say I
want to be indexed on a but also by the
way store B in the in the leaf nodes so
that I don't have to go do the lookup
the index but look up the tube or to
figure out how to evaluate a predicate
on B right post-course can do this
sequel server can do this this is
actually a bit more common now today and
it's not as bad as actually have a store
B everywhere throughout the the index
you're only storing it and just let the
leaf nodes so the benefit you would get
from this I think is not as significant
as maybe it was back in the day when
they evaluated this all right so why
don't anybody use them well I didn't
talk about how to actually how to
maintain this thing and keep it balanced
if yellow trees are kind of tricky
because you don't really do split some
merges you have to do rotations I said
now I have to take more heavyweight
latches on my data structure in order to
make significant changes and that's sort
of late at this as well like it's hard
to make sure that I guarantee that all
my operations in a thread safe and then
as I said once the CPU cache has got
much faster the cost of going chasing
those pointers I'm looking at the tuple
that actually became quite significant
so it's better off actually just yes or
making a redundant copy of keys in your
data structure but that avoids this this
penalty here you're paying a little
extra storage overhead to get a quite a
significant performance efficiency game
so there's a paper done in like 1999 by
Ken Ross in Columbia that basically said
that teachers are a bad idea for M
indexes and actually a B+ tree or
aberrant that looks like a B+ tree is a
better way to go and so that's why I say
nobody nobody today actually actually
actually uses this other than like you
know embedded devices like because a
game is called extreme DB that's just a
run on like you know little IOT devices
and that world sure right that I think
that makes sense but for you know a
large you know Xeon server
teachers are probably not the right
choice yes this question is how can a
binary search actually work here well
again so this is linear search so say I
did binary search and I landed here so
what am I gonna go do I'm gonna go look
up the key in the data table I get the
key now and then I compare it with the
key I'm looking for if my key is greater
than that Keeney
then I know I want to go this way if
it's less than then I go to the other
way these are sorted on the key and the
key the values of the Kings the data
table can be sorted any way at once
right it's a relational database bag
algebra these are unsorted so all the
points I make is all the standard tricks
we would do in a B+ tree of doing like
linear search of binary search or
tribulation search we can still do all
those things it's just we have to pay
extra a penalty extra jump somewhere
there and see what the actual Milky is
one think we actually would be
interesting to do though now I think
about it I know it's too late to do this
for project two but so as I said before
like when you get a pointer in in on x86
like you have to allocate 64 bits right
but in the hardware they actually only
store 48 bits so you kind of have 16
bits there you can actually store
whatever you want and when you do it
when you do reference to that pointer
that dereference that memory address the
the the harbor just ignores the 16 bits
so you could do something where like
this is 64 bits I still have the 48 bit
pointer to take me back wherever I need
to go into the data table but I
store part of the key in here so some of
the times I have to go look up sometimes
I don't so yeah that potentially work
but the problem with this is one Intel
could take that away at any time and
start using the full 64 bits I I was at
a that it's our technical seminar but
with this Intel guy a few years ago they
said like they had an in-memory database
that was maxing out to to the 48 you
know minus one addresses and that
eventually Intel would be going to to
the 64 so don't store anything in those
extra 16 bits but that was like three
years ago and it hasn't happened yet huh
so I I don't know what I don't know I
don't think it's a good idea at least a
future-proof the system we will see this
technique used though for hash pass
joins from hyper they use chain hash
table because they store that some crab
net they sort bloom filter in that 16
bits which is kind of cool okay I won't
dwell on teacher he's too much like this
is again there's the beat up beat up
retreat in the B+ tree or or more modern
we should focus on that so any questions
for teaching story switchover okay
so part of the reason why it's difficult
to make the tea tree perform efficiently
or making it even make it latch free is
that we have pointers all over the place
we have you know every every parent
pointer has a pointer to the child and
that child has a pointer to the parent
so now if I need to move one of them I
changed one memory address I got to
change a bunch of memory just as to all
the children about pointing to that
parent and I can't do that with atomic
compare-and-swap instructions because
you can't update multiple memory
addresses it's like one 64-bit one
128-bit location I can't say atomically
update these two things so related this
week this is also reason why we can't
build a latch for you P plus tree you
know for the same reason we're gonna
have pointers to things in
multiplications that update them
atomically it's just not possible so to
sort of motivate the design of how we
may be potentially want to build a a lat
tree B plus tree the way to sort of
solve this multiple address problem is
that if we had an indirection layer or
some centralized data structure where we
could record
aren't these addresses and then multiple
multiple elements or notes in our data
structure could know how to do lookups
in that indirection layer that that
mapping table and then now I just need
to do a compare and swap in that mapping
table change one address and that
automatically propagates the change
through throughout the entire data
structure and then I can make a latch
ring so that's essentially what the BW
tree is well B Dimitri is a latch tree B
plus tree that came out of the hackathon
project as I said I think two classes
ago the the awesome people at Microsoft
they when they first art a building
hackathon they originally building it
with skip list cuz skip list or latch
tree then they realized skip lists are a
bad idea the graph will show showed that
it performs poorly ed then where they
came up with was was the BW tree I
should also comment to that they beat
every tree although it's sort of
described in our paper and there's most
of the papers that talk about at least
the original BW paper that talks about
from Microsoft talks about in the
context as an in-memory system in
hackathons at Emory system there's
another project they built called
Deuteronomy at a Microsoft that actually
stored things on flash and so the Delta
record approach in the VW tree you know
a pending changes to nodes those
actually worked really well for Flash
environments we just appending to a log
but for an in-memory database the p30 is
gonna be a bad idea so I'm jumping ahead
but before we get into details who here
read the paper and felt like they
understand the BW tree okay I asked this
every year very people raise their hand
look at the hard data structure right
hard to wrap your head around there's a
lot going on and this is not so much a
commentary about the complexity of the
BW tree it's just the complexity of any
lat tree data structure any laterally
algorithm is actually pretty gnarly
right and so a lot of times even though
you're using latches could potentially
be slower the engineering complexity of
the data structure or what you're trying
to do is we significantly less and
therefore you're you're less likely to
make mistakes and you it's easier for
other people to work on it so right now
for a BW in our system I think it's like
five thousand eight thousand lines of
code
very few people and our team can
actually touch it the one guy that wrote
it is like he's not like crazy but like
he's kind of eccentric right so he wrote
the beat every tree the rumor is he
wrote me to retreat for our team it took
him like a year and a half he wrote it a
lot of it in notepad um on a Windows
laptop there was Windows 10 but he
modified his Windows 10 to make it look
like Windows 95 and then he sets the
default font to Comic Sans and he wrote
like in one of the hardest data
structures he wrote in that environment
so like there's a lot going on um all
right so let me go through the actual
key ideas of the main ideas and then
we'll sort of increase the complexity of
what else this you know we need to do
our data structure actually support real
things yes question is why is called the
BWT let me take a guess it was in the
title of the paper buzz words so it was
I like it was all take all the buzz
words at the time when the paper was
written written like lat tree in memory
LSM long structure murmurs trees to take
all those buzzwords and they throw into
a single index and it's called the tree
your face is really disappointed its
neighbors really bizarre yeah all right
okay so two key ideas the deltas and the
mapping table so they are gonna argue
that you want to avoid cache
invalidation right again think of like a
multi socket system where you have a
bunch of Numa nodes and the CPUs are
trying to update the same data structure
to reduce invalidation of having to make
in place changes to the nodes they're
gonna do Delta records so you pend Delta
records to the node as you modify them
and that's some later point you'll
consolidate them now this is not
entirely true
because it won't work the way we
actually implement it because we're
actually stored the Delta records in the
notes themselves so you still have cache
invalidation but this is what they
claimed and we didn't see at this we
didn't see this this this benefit the
other thing was the mapping table and
again this was a central location that
your store all the the addresses of
physical nodes and then now if I need to
change the address of a logical needing
to change the physical address of a
logical node I just go to my mapping
table and update it okay so let's look
at really simple tables so here were a
three node BW tree so the first thing to
point out here is that again we have our
mapping table and every nodes going to
be assigned a page ID or our note I do
all right so page 101 1 2 - 104 and then
now in our mapping table we'll have
physical pointers that tell us the
address the starting address for each of
these nodes so I'll denote this in in in
in all these diagrams the the solid
black line will represent the physical
address and the dotted red lines will
represent the logical addresses so in
this case here we have the root node and
it has two pointers to its children so
the only thing we need to store now in
that node is just the page ID of the
children 102 and 104 so now if anytime I
need to go say alright I I'm traversing
my tree I'm at page 101 and now I need
to keep to page 102 all right this is
not a pointer I can actually follow I
have to do a lookup in my mapping table
and say oh I want page 102 tell me the
physical address of it and then now I
can land into this right you're gonna
have this indirection layer that allows
me to take any logical page ID and map
it to a physical address all right so
let's see now if when we do an update so
let's say I have a single page here by
page 102 and now every single time I'm
gonna do an update to a page like insert
a key delete a key we're not worried
about updating keys because that's but
it's just a delete followed by an insert
all right so it's leader insert so again
instead of making the change directly on
the page itself right so this is just
another this is just a node like in a B
plus tree
I have an array of keys an array of
values it's the same same same physical
layout but now instead of making an
update to those arrays I'm gonna create
a Delta record that says what the change
I want to make into the quines
that's represented in 102 so let's say
now I want to sort key key 0 so this
record will have a physical pointer to
the base page
so how do I get that while I do my look
up and my mapping table and I would say
I know what this physical dress is gonna
be 1 or 2 so then now at this point
nobody can see my change because if
anybody is looking for page 102 they
would look in the mapping table and see
this pointer and bypass my Delta record
entirely so what what I need to do now
is do to install it I'm gonna do a
compare and swap in the mapping table to
replace the the physical address that it
used to point to to now my physical
address now that anybody goes looks at
102 they're not gonna land here they're
gonna land here recognize they're
looking at a Delta record and evaluate
it accordingly so if I'm looking for a
key 0 I landed this Delta record here I
say Oh insert key 0 voila
I'm done I found exactly what I was
looking for if I'm not looking for a key
0 then I just follow along now down here
and then now I can look at me in the in
the base page the base node so this
clear this is like the sort of the core
idea what they're doing
yes
your question is I the question was like
if I'm storing this with this I fight
because I'm not storing with this it's
like this is always the latest version
and then if I want to say what was the
version before this then I picked
somehow and then this would be like what
would be the Versa insert k0 with like
you said this is like the reverse of the
change you made here so what's the
reverse insert KZ row it's not really
delete k0 cuz it didn't exist before and
then what would happen now and at least
in that case and for your example I've
modified this page to be in cache
invalidation to the other other suffice
to view sockets but then also it's
another cache invalidation because I
updated another region of memory at
least in this case I just and I create
this Delta record this day's unmodified
so the only sort of cache reference I
need to update would be this thing here
yeah they're packing together yes we do
that for efficiency reasons your cache
line though is what 64 the cache line is
64 bytes so long as you update something
less than it's something more than 64
bytes it'd be ok I had to think like
that but I think it's sort of weird
cuz like you're creating a personal
something it doesn't exist and you need
to know like even in your example you
need to know I'm looking for k0 I don't
I see it here I'm done but he have what
there's no reversal for that delete
maybe you could say alright I see
something here
I don't see something but did it used to
exist yeah I have to think would you
just would you say he's weird sorry
yeah so the question is like when would
I actually follow this pointer right so
at this point here I've been created the
I created this Delta record it has a
physical pointer to the page nobody else
could see it though because everyone
else is following the mapping table that
takes you to the base page
I do the compare-and-swap on this and
now anybody that's looking for page one
or two lands here doesn't matter where
you're looking for k0 or not if you're
looking for page one or two you land
here and then you have to evaluate
you're essentially replaying like a log
in memory to say well what's actually
being stored in one or two question is
the more records you have the longer it
takes actually fine the the key if you
had a look at the base page yes we'll
fix that in a second yes so this
question is what if there is a
concurrent delta update next slide will
handle that so again now if I do this
let's do another one if I do a delete
eight same thing compare-and-swap on
this right and now the points of this so
now anybody coming along for one or two
right they would have to evaluate delete
k0k date that's not what I want
delete key zero that's not what I want
and then do the search down here in the
base note yeah
so we've already covered this that this
is just doing search like a B+ tree
alright if the thing you're looking for
is found in the Delta chain you're done
otherwise again you just do a search of
the BOP I'm alright so let's handle his
problem so now we're back here we've
installed a delta record for inserting
key 0 and then now I have two threads
they're gonna try and stall to Delta
records at the exact same time so two
threads are inside inside the index and
they say oh I need to perform an
operation and this is the note I want to
pour this is the base page I want to
perform my operation on so the first guy
wants to leak 88 is second I want to
leak key 6 so what's gonna happen here
how do we install these updates
like yup it's actually only applied
whenever you update yeah correct so his
statement is the updates are only
applied and are only visible to everyone
else if you know when you update this
thing so these guys now are gonna do
compare and swap at the same time on
this memory location in the mapping
table but only one can succeed so you
know essentially what you're doing is
when you're back here you know what you
note that the physical address is to the
head of doesn't record a delta chain for
this node all right that's what these
guys that's how these guys got got these
these physical dresses so now when I do
a compare and swap you say if the
current value of this address here is
what I think it should be then go ahead
and swap it and install my new update
right so let's say the first guy is able
to do this right that's fine so now he
is at the head of the Delta vector Delta
chain and his his update got installed
the second guy with that compare and
swap operation would fail because we
would do the evaluation of the mapping
table see that the address is not what
it's thought it was gonna be pointing to
this does record here it's now pointing
to this one so it knows that somebody
else got in before he did and updated
this so my update will now fail and then
depending on implementation I can either
try to another compare and swap and try
to update this or I could just repeat
and do the whole operation Traverse down
and try again you're saying that if I
try to compare and swap now yes yes yes
so what I could do is I up take this
this visible just here now point to this
one out so they so if you're here the
compare-and-swap succeeds case comparing
saw it feels so now I could go back
inside wall just fail what's in there
now no number copy but like this thing
is always gonna point to whatever the
head of the Virgin chain that doesn't
record genius correct I just go look and
see this again you could do that way I
don't think we implemented that way
because for like safety reasons because
like you don't know now that this thing
might do a split and the thing you're
looking for may no longer be
encapsulated in this index or this note
here like this I might have done a split
and now we're k-6 should be should not
be page one or two H now mean another
page when yes yes so again we're only to
delete and inserts all right so there's
no if we handover updates right the
other thing too is like this is a inside
the data structure we don't have to
worry about higher-level consistency
issues of the transactions like I think
maybe we're possibly saying is like well
what if one transaction deletes k-8 and
I try to insert it or I'd I'm kind of
read it and it's been deleted all that's
handled up above in the and like either
doing this the rerunning the scans are
doing the validation stuff all that's
handled above us we just care about the
low levels linearize ability correctness
of the data structure and this thing
will handle that for us yes
you're currently accessing that case
would be different from you know every
study again I mean what like I don't
really see the point of why you worry
about it's pretty known that page 102
like we'd have to restart on the
beginning that how does that propagating
that could ensure that um when I say Inc
uses Cu it has to do with like it has to
do with like I'm trying to insert
something and in a trying to start a
logical key that is not that is not
represented or should not be stored at
this this this location here so if now
key six should not be in page one or two
should be page 103 if I try to
immediately come back and do equal
parents WAP here now I'm starting key
six into this page but anybody else that
looks for key six it's not gonna lay in
here they're gonna follow the guide
posts and lans mother node and they'll
have a false false negative
[Music]
how do I make sure I'm landing up here
where I should be right yeah because
that's just the weight I mean because
we're enforcing the the the the ordering
of the directions of where you go from
left to right from one node to the next
right with the keys and so we're
guaranteeing that we're propagating the
changes from the bottom to the top so
you're not in this weird state where
like something is pointing you to
something that shouldn't be or something
that being stored in the place that
shouldn't be but always restarting at
the top it's inefficient and that's sort
of that the the downside of a laterally
data structure but we guarantee the
correctness the kids Assistance II of
the data structure at a at a physical
level okay so now to his earlier
question and would like well can't this
Delta chain get kind of long yes it will
and so we want to do consolidation so
basically what's gonna happen is one
thread will recognize as it's going
along this Delta chain has gotten too
long alright this could be like a
threshold you say if the Delta chain is
as more has more than these number
records then I want to have a solid
ation so what you're going to do is
you're gonna make first a copy of the
base page
and then now you're going to apply the
the changes in reverse order of the
Delta chain we take us why were you
doing reverse order that is the order
right like this is like in physical time
the change to be made is like this is
the oldest change and this is going to
the newest change right so if I say if I
if I'm deleting k-8 here and I insert
k-8 here then does it make sense or try
to delete something if I'm going in this
direction so we always go in reverse
order so basically it's gonna be as I
scan through and I recognize this depth
of change it's gotten too long I have a
copy of all these things and now I can
replay them in reverse order one by one
alright so now after I replay all my
changes now this new copy of the node
represents all the same things that are
represented by this base page and it's
in his dental records so how do I
install it now command swap easy right
all I needed to go back now is compare
and swap to this this for the record
here the entry here for 102 and now
anybody else that comes along can see me
if I fail then I wasted work I've done
my consolidation and somebody else
changed something like if someone else
appends a new Delta record before I get
my before I do my compare and swap well
then that solves the problem of not
seeing that you know potentially missing
a doesn't record update because now this
thing would have pointed to a new Delta
record that I didn't see and therefore I
throw away my work and start up yes
[Music]
it calls this a virtual moon yeah it's
just in the heat it's just like an ode
that nobody else can see yet it's in the
like only my thread is doing the
consolidation can can see it yeah this
question is why don't I just instead of
doing this and comparing solving this
why don't I take all these things and
apply to this you think you questions
why didn't have these Delta records
wanted to apply this change here again
they're they're arguing that in order to
make it latch free if I fat from
allowing anybody to make any change down
here you still need latches right
because that these things that have to
be sorted and you have to deploy latches
to try to like you know enforce the
ordering on them so they're trying to be
entirely Larry yes this question is is
the comparison in your latch we will
cover this next class could you
implement latches with clear and swap no
like still a it'd be like I hold I'm
holding a latch on some critical section
and I do a bunch of stuff so this is
like here's a single update I apply now
you're right well if it's a spin latch
what do you do you spin so I could we
don't yes
no you make it latch free yes if you
don't wanna make a latch free then like
you take a latch do the update yes then
you have a B+ tree
yes so like if you whenever you try to
recompute this like consolidated note
yes pray and like let's see go back to
compare and swap that you fail right I
don't necessarily think you actually
that throw it all that work because you
could essentially read all this new
chain and then see where like your
change in this last word and then
updating compares about that one point I
ready to swap yourself like if you're
right if this is just an insert you
could say alright I missed it just put
it in and then try it again I don't
think we do that I think we play it safe
because again if you have a split or
merge that's why that's what that's when
things get bad yeah all right so one or
two is new one or two is installed this
guy's sitting around what do we need to
do with it you wouldn't we obviously
want to clean it up at some point right
so these things can be marked as garbage
and at some point we need to clean them
up what does this look like this is
starting to look like MVCC right once we
recognize that something's no longer
visible to bunch of threads or
transactions in MVCC world then we want
to go ahead and clean this up and reuse
the memory so this now looks a little
bit different though then slightly
different than what we've talked about
before but the high/low idea is going to
be the same all right so what for
garbage collection for these in memory
data structures what do we what's what's
the issue well we don't want to throw
away something that somebody could be
reading a jump into because then they'll
have a seg fault because a reading you
know unallocated memory so like say I
want to delete k2 here and this is a
simple single Direction linked list
right my thread is here it's at the key
one it sees the physical pointer now to
the next key then the garbage capture
comes in cleans up this thing but now I
follow this pointer just some random
invalid you know and your member dress
that doesn't mean anything anymore and
you know worst case scenario I said fall
actually worth chasing they're also like
I could read garbage and think it's
something real right so we want to avoid
this so the two approaches we'll talk
about our reference counting an epoch
based reclamation there's a bunch of
other techniques to use hazard pointers
what's the other one I forget to forget
what they're called it does matter like
there's other things these are two ones
that the the most prominent most common
in in memory databases so reference
counting is essentially what you get
with the shared pointer on the Unruh
Steven
Plus on a standard template library so
all it is now is that inside of every
node in a data structure or in a
SharePoint inside the points the the
pointer data structure itself we're just
gonna maintain a counter that keeps
track of the number of threads that
could be accessing a that memory
location I inserted before I go access
it I increment the counter that's at an
atomic add right that's that part's
efficient but then when I'm done doing
you know accessing it then I decrement
that counter to by one
so the garbage collector would know that
it's safe to reality to deallocate some
region of memory when we know that our
counter is zero because we know no
thread could be looking at it so long as
everyone updates that Conn before they
jump to the next location right we won't
have it have an issue turns out though
this is actually really bad for
performance because now I'm probably
every single time I jump to a new
location I'm incrementing this counter
and that's a global counter that
everybody needs to be able to read and
write so if I have a lot of course a lot
of sockets that's a cache invalidation
message to everyone just to go read
something yes especially this is this
invalidation also apply when updating
the map in general yes but but I can
read the mapping table without having
updated this turns every read into a
write this is bad right so again this is
what you get and share pointers and this
you know this is obviously gonna be slow
so one obvious thing to point out though
is we don't actually care what that
counter actually the value actually is
all we really care is whether it's
nonzero right so whether it's 1 2 4
whatever who cares we know somebody's
reading it we can't garb something it's
only when it's 0 do we do we actually
care so maybe instead of storing this
fine-grain counter per per node in our
data structure we could just try to keep
track of a higher level contract more
coarse-grained counter and just know
that when nothing can be visible to by
anybody within some some time range just
like an MVC see then it's safe for us to
go ahead and promote
things so this is what EPA epoch base
grabber selection is and we briefly
mentioned this last class and I said I
was going to spend more time than on it
today but again the high-level idea of
what we did msec for epoch base copper
collection is the same one here so
there's me this global counter that's me
periodically updated like you can have a
thread do this or cooperatively
cooperatively every 10 milliseconds and
the only thing we need to keep track of
now in our in our index is that what
threads exist at a given a POC I went
what time did they show up what you pop
do they show up and then when did they
leave and I don't care what you pocket
that they left in all i care is that
like that they did leave so I could show
up an epoch one then I leave epoch -
that's fine but I'm still only
considered to be an epoch one and then
now what'll happen is when we do our
consolidation we'll say what's the
current epoch of my of this node or so
what's the current epoch of the B but B
EE
I mark that garbage with that epoch and
then once I know that there's no threat
could we possibly see that node because
they're not in that epoch anymore then
it's safe for me to go ahead and delete
it remove it so in Linux this is called
our Cu recopy update this is used in
various different data structures
internally inside of the kernel to go
read systems papers they'll refer to
this as our Cu in database papers we've
heard of this epoch based garbage
collection all right so now to do this
again and this is just repeating what I
said but every tree again we tagged
everything we're gonna do any search
insert or delete is tagged with my
current epoch is we register with the
garbage collector when a thread shows up
say you know I'm showing up and then do
something I'm in this epoch and then
when you leave you D register and then
the garbage collection can say I know
that nobody else is in this epoch here's
a bunch of garbage for that epoch let me
go ahead and remove it so let's look at
this example here so this is the same
one we had before we get our cut we're
gonna do a consolidation on on 102 so
CPU 1 thread 1 is gonna do this
consolidation so it when it showed up in
the very beginning it just registered
with this epoch table said the garbage
collector
all right and now there's some other
thread thread - all right that's gonna
be scanning this at the same time so we
registered with the epoch table so now
we do now the compare-and-swap
to update 102 and now nobody else that
comes in after this point will ever see
this original thing but this thread here
is still hanging out we actually don't
know where it is it could be anywhere
inside the data structure looking any
node but it could potentially be in here
so instead of tracking exactly you know
what no damn I'm looking at or what
Delta rather looking at every single
time we just say hey there's somebody
around that you know within this time so
now we registered this garbage with it
and but then epoch this first epoch this
guy goes away and we D register this
guy's scans down and then when he finds
whatever he's looking for in page 102
right and then when he's done it's safe
for us to go ahead and delete this right
so instead of actually giving every node
a timestamp or every Delta record on
timestamp like an MVC see we just have
this chorus granny box yes the epoch
gave us means the entire instance of the
data structure all it is it's just it's
just a it's a pointer to the physical
address of this node here so this says
like alright if I've register this
garbage here I'm not actually making a
copy of this we're storing the pointer
to the head of it there's out the record
chain so then I know that anything any
doubt the record and the base table base
page itself can be garbage collected
again nobody else can can never jump to
this because we did a compare and swap
here and we're able to you know and now
point to the new page yes your question
is is what is the data structure of
edging the threads yeah it's just a cue
array like it could be array pointing to
a cue because you could cycle through
the epochs yes it could be a bottleneck
but traversing the index itself is more
expensive than that yes
so we're back here we're here so what if
somebody else creates a new Delta record
here while we're doing compaction what
would happen when I do the compare and
swap I would fail because it's now
pointing to now some dealt with record
above this that I didn't see and that's
what I was saying to him like you could
be smart saying oh well this is just
another insert let me reapply it and
then do the compare and swap for that
one you basically do add if you're
trying to figure out well what did I
have and what did I miss
so it's just one maybe it's not a big
big of a deal but it's a bunch of them
you might just be better off just
restarting but again the compare and
swap because this mapping table
guarantees that this thing is always
gonna be like the ground truth of what
the correct what the correct pointer
should be so it's not what we think it
is somebody else got in before before we
did okay so far so good right let's make
it hard let's do splits emerges right
though this book will just focus on
splits merges essentially the same thing
in reverse order so now we're gonna
introduce two new types of archetypes
the split delta record and the separator
so the split is going to be a delta
record that says that the node paid the
base page below us in our and that in
our delta chain has been split and
here's where to go find the two new
boundaries of keys so we'll have a
physical pointer down to the the next
delta record and then a logical pointer
to the page they got we got split off
from and then a separator Delta record
it's not required for correctness but
it's just a it's a shortcut up above in
in the higher part students to tree to
say oh by the way below you there was a
split here's where to go find the things
you're looking for so let's look at
example here so now you have four pages
and we're gonna want to do is and then
the keys are sort organized like this
and we want to do a split on one 103 so
say we want to insert actually let's do
a split we don't insert anything so the
first thing I'm gonna do is do a split
in you know
from my thread what you know with a
virtual note here the thick nobody could
actually see yet and then he's just now
pointing to the next sibling 104 so now
I'm gonna do a compare and swap here
nobody else could get in it before I did
so that's not a big deal but I want to
update now the the Delta record of Delta
chain from 103 with this new split
record here right and the way what the
split burgers gonna store is that
there's the physical pointer to the base
page and that just says key three key
three keys keep three to five are here
and then five this key seven or over
here and this is just a logical pointer
so now I do my compare and swap to now
update 103 to be now pointing at my mind
you split record so now anybody that
comes along is looking for key five for
example will come down follow this the
Virgin chain here
okay these all get updated to
automatically again because I have the
mapping table all right these guys have
logical pointers it turns like up there
that everyone automatically now points
with a split record so anybody coming
along either from from the bottling
pointer or from the top let's see the
split record and recognize oh well if
I'm looking for key five I want to
follow a logical pointer here otherwise
follow the physical pointer down here
now this point here we actually ever
done two copies of key five and key 6
right they're still stored in in 103
because we can't do in place updates so
you so when you're now traversing like
down here and saying I'm trying to find
keys greater than four for example I
would have to remember that I saw a
split record up above that said alright
this note here if you looking for
anything greater than C five or greater
should not be short on one or three even
though you may see it in this one or
this one or three you know you need to
go find it down down here and 105
alright so then now I need to sort of
propagate this key space up above or key
or split up above so at this point here
the root table has the still the
original splits or demarcations for
what's below me and so if i from a
correctness standpoint if I follow it in
here and I'm looking for something key
five I would say key threes keep I was
in case
and k7 and still follow that logical
pointer down to the split one and then I
would recognize I really need to go down
to this other side now this other side
but to avoid having to you know do that
as necessary look up I could insert a
separator record that just says all
right well key 5k7 are now at this new
here's a logic component to this new
node here right
same thing compare and swap on this gal
that gets installed and anybody else
comes along with but see this okay and
you don't need to separate it for
correctness it's it's just for
efficiency reasons and then when I do
consolidation obviously compact it and
update this correctly any questions the
logic point is what what is a lot of a
pointer what are we actually storing
yeah hey ready so if I'm scanning along
like final Keys greater than greater
than equal okay k2
I would land here I say all right well I
see k2 but I want to keep going so I'm
looking for he's greater than k2 oh I
need to follow my sibling pointer my
sibling pointer is page 103 right that's
what you know that's sort of this thing
is but I'm just only storing you know
the ID one two three here it's in order
to get to there I go look my mapping
table and wallah now my physical dress
points to here and then and I can either
scan down find when I mean you split the
one side to the other as needed yes
question is when I did the split here
would 105 1 3 show the same doesn't
change
now the split is the Delta chain of 103
because that's what we're back here
right so again I just copied out the
keys I need for 105 now I have a split
record here and I want to have anybody
that ghost of 103 should know that I
split right so my compare-and-swap needs
to be on this guy's delta chain this guy
has his own doesn't
and again if I now start making changes
to page 105
well that's gonna have its own Delta
Delta chain but the logical pointer to
it will still get knee to the head of
that double chain if anything goes to
103 there should be going to 104 you
like the separator so now the separator
just allows you to avoid having to do
like an extra actually lookups going
down in say so you're saving as
something that should be in 105 can
never end up at 1 or 3 yeah because we
can't because like I've displayed record
say well if I want to insert say a key
5.5 this should be in between 5 5 & 5 &
6 I would get here 5.5 is greater than
or equal to 5 so therefore it has to go
here I can't I can never get there why
wouldn't you if you're here yes when
you're up here no yes so like if there's
a lot of lines here so confusing sorry
so the root note still thinks that if
I'm looking for key range k3 to k7 I
should be looking at a logical pointer
103 right so this arrow should really be
here but physically when I do the lookup
I'm gonna land this split so I'm looking
for key 5 I do my I think it should be
in page 1 2 3 I landed a delta record
that that's a split and I would
recognize Oh split therefore I need to
look at the boundaries in the split and
then that'll take me left or right here
so this is the separator key is
basically updating this information yeah
so once this thing's installed and I'm
looking for key 5 I could potentially go
now down here again this is like say I
could store four things in this node and
I don't need to split it instead of
having to do in place update to add a
fourth entry or a guidepost
in this thing this the separator thing
does that for me yeah yes
so I'm going back to the previous
questions where if you do convince water
fails you would essentially see that's
pretty low right so if the comparative
Vic parents ops fails where whatever
like when you're trying to update like
so here
yeah so in the implementation and you
guys did that you have to go star upon
the news because you might not be going
to the same page correct
1:03 of like a shaved you go dude 105
yes so but I but the one that fails that
we were actually see this prenup cat so
if that's Ryan right now it could just
actually follow the logical 0.02 to 105
and it doesn't happen if it fails where
when at 103 like they say insert k72 103
keep 5.5 I'm trying to sir Kay 5.5 and
yes so in seats you're here this has
been updated and you will see the
correct there I think there are some
optimizations I don't know whether we do
them all we're like five compare swap
fails and I recognize oh well if I come
back and read what am I seeing
I could then use that as a way to jump
to what I'm looking for I think we are
very conservative and we don't always do
that in the implementation yes sir
question is when I'm creating if I'm
creating 105 how do i what I apply
changes yes and I would know again you
know what you're splitting on so if it's
like delete k4 I ignore it because I'm
not not that's not in mine but it's like
insert k 5.5 that should be in mine then
I apply it
yes question is are the split and
separator at atomically again I can only
do one thing atomically I can only
update one address in the mapping table
atomically it's because the latch it
Slattery
we'd have to read them tear down forever
to find this place
Ford this page here right yes there
could be stuff up above like there could
be like okay it could be like delete it
could be insert Cape if there's insert
five point five I think we're insert you
always have to go to the debates page so
then you would always see this split
actually think for everything you always
have to go to the base page yeah for
delete and insert yeah so I it's not
like I would blindly append this thing
all right weren't shorten time um I'm
rushing this a bit much but I can answer
questions afterwards so I would quickly
to start talk about the our optimization
so again the paper how do you guys read
this was our attempt to write the sort
of the the the missing guide on how to
build opw tree
so the original be double tree paper
from Microsoft doesn't explain a lot of
the core things you actually need
actually build a real real P Double Tree
there's a bunch of these other papers
they wrote after the original paper that
sort of sprinkle in some of the the
things that are in our paper and asked
our papers meant to be consolidated
guide on here's how to build a real BW
tree and so when I first started at CMU
I said alright we're gonna build a new
database system and have a super
enamored with the BW teams like well we
ever build a new system we're gonna use
a BW tree the first time I taught this
class the second project was implemented
BW tree which was a nightmare right but
the like I said the one student the
peaches student that was super awesome
we took his beat-up tree he kept on
working for two years and that's that's
what the paper was but his paper was not
meant to be like oh look how crappy bbw
tree was it was like you know we were
actually one of the benchmark and see
how I'd actually cook perform and it
turns out it was terrible um so that's
why it's sort of the split brain like
half the paper says here's how to build
it and then the second half paper says
why it's bad right because the RISM
wasn't supposed to be like that alright
so almonds quickly talk about some
optimizations that we did in our version
so as is called to open beta every tree
ours is is to the best my knowledge it's
the best open source implementation
of the beat every tree there's a couple
other ones that are out there but they
don't do all the things that we do
there's one system out of Germany called
sled it's like an embedded system that's
written in rust they're supposedly
using a beat-up retreat I don't know
whether they go to the extreme extent
that houses the be dimitri shows up in
other systems that Microsoft so cosmos
DP or used to be document DBS their
version of MongoDB or their cloud
database they use it the beat every tree
in certain cases but ours is the best
open sort one
alright so I even talk about what these
two help we're actually storing these
Delta records like you know the original
the original discussion of in Microsoft
they said oh there's room they don't
really say where they are so you could
just allocate a bunch of little it up
duck doesn't records on the heap but
that's a bad idea because you'll have
fragmentation and memory so what we do
is when we allocate a base page we have
a little extra space in the header of
the base page that we can use for
storing Delta records so now all I need
to do now is if I'm gonna update the so
I'm going to add a new Delta record I
just do a compare and swap on this thing
here get a new offset and now I can
insert my Delta record here and then I
go back here and do the the compare and
swap to have it point in my head of the
Delta record right so again I don't need
to take a latches to acquire the space
and then when this thing gets full then
I do the consolidation the other thing
that would that was too important was I
have really described what the mapping
table is in the original version of the
b/w paper it seems to be a hash table an
application it's just an array and so
you want to allocate an array that could
store any possible and you know noted
you up to something some limit and so
the problem though is that if you
allocate the full array in the very
beginning for every single possible no
data you could ever have
then you end up wasting a lot of space
because you're allocating memory that
you probably don't need and so I think
in the in the in the current version of
the bead every tree that we have in our
system the mapping table the max size is
1 million so I can have 1 million node
IDs in my system and so if we're storing
128 keys per node I can have up to 128
potentially hundred 180 keys total it's
less than that because we're only
starting things in them
I'll eat in the leaf notes but roughly
that's what it is so to allocate an
array with 64-bit pointers
with 1 1 main entries is 8 megabytes so
it doesn't seem like a lot but if you
like load the TVC database if every
table has two or three indexes so for
every table I'm creating three indexes 8
megabytes starts to add up a lot from
naturally not storing anything so in the
rolled version of peloton when you first
load a TPCC the database would grow to
be like 256 Meg's with no data in it
right so the way we got around this was
we just use we allocate virtual memory
and this is not using anything special
just using the constructs you have from
the OS we allocate a chunk of memory and
make sure we only use the upper portion
of the mapping table when our index is
small so it doesn't actually get backed
by physical memory so although the
virtual size can get large the resident
set size is quite quite small right
because it's only when you touch a page
in memory does the OS actually back it
with physical memory all right quickly
to finish up so this is the this is the
the the these are the results that were
in the original bead of retreat paper
that Microsoft published with Justin and
the other people there and this is when
I saw this I'm like oh this is awesome
we totally want to build a luxury index
here at CMU so what are they comparing
yes it's their version to beat every
tree against the Skip list and then the
B+ tree but this B+ tree is actually
from Berkeley DB Berkeley DB came out of
UC Berkeley it was its an embedded
database it has you know basically like
level DB a Roxie B but like one of the
first ones to do this an Oracle bought
it and like 2006 so they extracted out
the source code for the d-bus tree from
from Berkeley DB and they modify it so
it didn't actually store anything on
disk so this this shows that the bit of
tree crushes everything right so when I
saw this like this is amazing we should
totally do this but then when you
actually implement it so these are our
results this is the best our best
version of the open BW tree this is
actually the state-of-the-art
implementation of the Skip list right
it's out of and from alan techies group
in australia instead of using towers it
uses wheels which it's some minor change
whatever and then this is a B+ tree
written by one of the authors from hyper
who came and visited us for a couple
months and this is like his this is one
of the data structures they you
in hyper for their comparisons so as you
can see the deep uh streak rushes except
for this one here this won't make me
wrong I get the mitosis but V Plus V
pretty much crushes everything alright
so then when you look at all the data
structures we'll talk about next class
alright then you see the open media
which we gets gets gets gets wiped away
so I'm now gonna bring in the mash tree
and art index art index is what you read
on Wednesday's class it's a radix tree
or tri from piper and then the mash tree
is at Harvard this is a tree of trys
which we'll cover next class so again in
this environment the beatable tree just
loses to everything so this is why we
need to get rid of it but we just have
we haven't started it yet okay okay that
was like super rushed at the end I
apologize
any questions all right so next class
I'll spend more time talking about
latches for B put B plus trees then
we'll talk about the radix tree stuff
and then we'll talk a little bit about
what you can do for project one okay hi
guys see ya what is this
[Music]
Mia 40 just to get my buzz song cuz I
needed just a little more kick look like
a fish after just one slip-up put it to
my lips and rip the top off eight ball
just drop them to say nice
won't be the same I've diced you take a
sake to the player