[Music]
[Applause]
today we're gonna talk about parallel
sort merge-join algorithms just again me
here in my home office although I did my
I did up my lighting game quite a bit
and I have the terior down here who's
gonna be asking questions as we go along
so let's get right into this so before
we get into the material for today we
want to talk about some logistics about
what's expected for you for the going
forward starting next week so next week
we're gonna be doing the project 3
status updates so did the same setup we
did last time we'll do it over zoom and
then everybody will go for 5 minutes
just to sort of give it update to the
class of where they're at with their
project prior to that though I want
every group to reach out to me and
schedule a time later this week to meet
one-on-one to discuss the current
progress of your your project to see
where you're having trouble is when you
need help with and give you a sense of
get a sense of what you'll present to
the class on on next week so those those
in class project presentations will be
on Wednesday April 8th so in addition to
doing the presentation they're also
going to provide a design document that
discusses you know a bit more detail of
what your implementation is gonna look
like you're also going to need to submit
the your what you've written so far for
your project I'll submit it as a pull
request to us on github so that we can
do the first round of code reviews how
can I explain what's expected in a code
review next week but the idea is that
you will be assigned another group to
look at their project and they'll look
at your project and you'll go through
and you know try to understand whether
what their implementation is trying to
do and then give them feedback on the
quality and and sort of ideas that
they're pursuing so again that'll be
sort of part of the participation grade
for this project every team member is
expected to participate and when we do
the second round of code reviews you'll
be looking at the same groups code again
so that way you're not starting over
from scratch like you've looked at it
the code
and now you're looking at it the second
time as they're getting ready to submit
the final the final implementation to
get a grade and so again you'll provide
them an additional feedback on on what
what things they can do to fix them well
what could they can do to fix up their
code okay so I'll post those on Piazza
about reaching out and setting up
meeting time I will pull or sign up for
slots on the administration move
spreadsheet for the class and then we'll
go in reverse order next Wednesday or
next week we'll go in the reverse order
that we did in the first time when we
when we did the project proposals so if
you went first last time you get to go
last next time okay so this lecture and
the previous lecture have been about
payload joint algorithms and so last
class again we focused on hash joins
because I said that was the most
commonly used joint algorithm in OLAP
system and that's the one we're gonna
try to get the get the best performance
benefit by paralyzing or vectorizing it
because again in most developed systems
those the times to be executing hashed
ones the other major approach to do
joins is the sort merge join and that
sort of focus of will be on today and so
we'll first start off with a little
background information about what a sort
merge one looks like again this would
just be a refresher from what we
discussed in the introduction class then
we'll talk about different sorting
algorithms you can use or - the one in
particular approach will focus on from
Intel which would be how to vectorize
and paralyze the sorting algorithm which
is possible then we'll talk about how to
combine it together to do a parallel
sort version and then we'll finish up
with the evaluation that was provided
that was in the assigned reading from
ETH okay so the the sorbets join
basically has two phases it's the same
thing as the as the hash drawing right
you prepare that the data in the first
phase in such a way that in the second
phase when you want to go try to find
matches the data is laid out or indexed
in the case of the hash join and laid
out in such a way that you can easily
find matches without having to do that
brute force sequential scan that you
would have to do in a nested loop join
so again in the first phase we're just
going to sort the tuples on the r NS
based on the join key or the join keys
if it's multiple keys and then in the
merge phase we'll just scan through the
two tables in the sorted order in with
these two iterators that are sort of
going in lockstep and doing comparisons
between them and the idea here is
because we sort of things ahead of time
as the iterators are walking through we
we would know that we don't have to ever
backtrack to look for a matching tuple
or sorry it was scanning down farther
than we actually need to if we come
across a tuple or a key that is
different than the last key we saw then
we know that you know that that key
can't exist any results it's again the
idea is that we are by sorting this it's
just avoiding having to do a boot for
search to find the matching key we know
that as the iterative boost down we have
everything that we need
so the at a high level conceptually
looks like this again so the table our
table s first phase is I'm gonna sort
them by the join key I'm not gonna
describe what that sorting algorithm is
just now but this is what we'll cover
today and then now once we things are
sorted will now do the merge phase well
we'll have again these two iterators
will go down and scan through the the
tables usually once but depending on
whether there's it's an equijoin what
kind of joint you're doing you may think
it's cancer multiple times we can ignore
that for now just every single time it
will come one tuple when I'm done with
it I'd be one to the next tuple and then
I just left before in the hash join if I
have matching tuples on the inner and
the outer table combine them they're
combined their attributes together and
write it into my output buffer now the
confusing thing that we're going to hit
today is that we're gonna be doing a
sort merge join and the algorithm we're
gonna do to do the sort will be a merge
sort so I'll try to get careful when I
use the term marriage to make sure that
I'm telling you whether it is the
the merge phase of the merge sort or the
merge phase of the sort merge-join
it's a lot of taken out as we go along
to try to make it clear what what kind
of merger we're talking about but a high
level of essentially doing the same
thing so this would have you know in the
introduction class we talk discuss how
to do this in a you know sort of basic
high-level approach and we don't worry
about workers we don't worry about
threads or newman's but now in in a
modern system we need to be aware of
these things so we need to talk about
how we're actually gonna speed things up
by paralyzing everything so of course
we're gonna want to paralyze the sorting
because that's going to be the most
expensive part and again just like we
saw in when we talk about factorization
we can paralyze the this step of the
algorithm both in terms of having it
execute on multiple threads at the same
time but then on each thread try to use
vectorized operations so that you know
we're operating on multiple keys or
multiple elements of data in parallel
with a single instruction or single set
of instructions so the there's some
basic rules that we're gonna try to
apply in our algorithm to try to get the
best performance as much as possible and
again this is also relevant to the hash
join but I just want to bring this up
here again so we obviously want to use
as many CPU cores as possible that our
database system is allotted to us for
this execution some systems only execute
one query at a time so you'll get all
the cores that are available on your
machine as you're doing the join and
then when your queries done it then
switches over to the next query in other
systems they'll want to try to run
multiple queries at the same time so you
just want to be the system's scheduler
has to be aware of how many threads that
are allowed to a lot to do a sort and
make sure that it only runs on those
cores obviously also we need to be
mindful of the Numa boundaries because
again we don't want to pay this big
penalty you have reads and writes go
across new regions because that's been
much more expensive than reading data
that's local to our threads so we'll see
in the case of hyper they're actually
gonna go against this second goal here
and they're gonna argue that because
they're doing sequential needs when
you're doing the merge phase of the of
the join that hardware is actually gonna
help hide these latencies of going
across Neiman's but when we look at the
results from the edge paper we'll see
that it's actually not the case and then
the last one again we said before I want
to be we're trying to use in the simian
structures as much as possible so that
the amount of data were processing per
instruction a per cycle is is maximized
all right I'm going to try to do it
you'll compare this with assisting
instructions where you know can only
operate on one one key at a time so the
parallel sort merge-join
is like the parallel hash joint where
hand you have now three phases because
now the first phase is this partitioning
step where you're gonna divide the data
up across it across the workers or cores
but unlike in the in the hash one case
where you you would partition both sides
in this case here we could just
partition one side and some algorithms
will partition both some items well
partition one and then for this one
again we'll stay in a second but you can
do the same kind of partitioning you saw
last time the next one will be the the
sorting sorting phase and again this is
now where we take both the inner table
and the outer table and we just sort
them on our join key then in the last
phase we do the merge where we just scan
through the sort of relations and
compare the tuples and if we have a
match let me write them into our output
buffer so for today we're gonna spend
most of our time on these two okay
there's not much more else we can say
about this but we'll see how it's gonna
what choice we can make in here with the
pen on what kind of merge we want to do
later on so I didn't talk about
partitioning at a conceptual level last
class but what I'll say here is also
still relevant for hash joins so there's
this notion of sort implicit and
explicit partitioning when we want to do
a join so implicit partitioning would be
how the data is already partitioned when
it got loaded into the database and then
if we know that the data was partitioned
on our join key for the
query we're trying to run right now then
we don't actually need to do an extra
step of partitioning because the data is
already partition on our join team and
we're good to go so this would be like
if I load the table and I do as I load
the table or create the table I can
declare in the in the DDL that I want a
partition like my table over some set of
attributes or some kind of join key it
might be like in the case of teh PCC
like the where else ID or in in in TP CH
could be like country or whatever the
longer you have in the light on potato
so this is something that the the the
the application or the database
administrator has to do for us they have
to be have to be told the database
doesn't has to be told here's how I want
to partition things and in our catalogs
we can keep track of what that
partitioning key was because since since
we had to write the data out through
different new merchants and so now the
query optimizer can say oh where I see
that you're trying to do a join on the
key that I've already partitioned my my
table one so therefore I don't need to
do the an extra step to partition things
because it's already partition but this
always won't always work for us in a an
OLAP environment because people want I'm
going to want to join their tables on
all sorts of columns and attributes
where it may not be may not know that
ahead of time and you may not actually
be able to declare what the me the right
partition key for a particular query
because it may change from one crate to
the next you don't see this so much in
OLAP queries because our sorry OTP and
workloads because typically the the
partitioning key is sort of the
partitioning scheme of the table follows
a sort of hierarchy you say you know
here's the customer and for a given
customer ID here's all the order so that
customer ID and here's a order items for
that customer that order ID so you have
this nice hierarchy where you can take
sort of the slice of the data across
tables and put them on a single
partition and most of the times you're
joining across those you know foreign
key dependencies and oh that queries
like I said people join on all sorts of
crazy things so it's hard to actually
get this right you know to cover all
possible queries it's actually
impossible so what we're talking about
instead when we say the partitioning
phase of a join algorithm would be
explicit partitioning
where we're going to divide the the
relations based on the join key and then
redistributed them across the post open
course right so you could use the radix
partitioning that we talked about last
class in practice though for the sort
join for the merge sort the sort merge
join algorithm that's not going to be a
good idea because typically you want to
do range partitioning because you know
how to divide up the data and you know
what the boundaries are of that data
from one partition to the next and then
carefully you know that there's no key
with the same the same partition sorry
there's no key with the same with a
different value could be in a different
partition than you aren't that you don't
expect all right so that's again the
partitioning phase we can do rate a
partitioning range partitioning it
doesn't really matter it's the same
stuff that we talked about last time
there's nothing really different that we
would be doing then because we're doing
a you know sort merge joined versus a
hashed one all right so now we get into
the sort phase again this is this is the
gonna be the most expensive part for us
so the key thing to understand about
sorting here is in the introduction
class when we talked about sorting the
the main bottleneck the main thing we
had to deal with was writing pages in
and out from disk and so we would want
to use a an algorithm like external
merge sort that was designed to do as
much sequential access to special reads
and writes to to disk as possible and it
made sure that when it brought a page or
chunk of data from disk into memory we
did all the operations we needed to do
on that that chunk of data before we
moved on to the next chunk so we didn't
have to go read or write it back
multiple times but the key thing though
is that when we brought the block of
memory block it you know from from disk
into memory and then maybe he needed to
sort that that that that data that was
in memory we said that you know
something like quicksort was good enough
for what we needed to do begins we
weren't going to little details
learning about cache cache locality and
parallelization for those algorithms in
the induction class it was all about
minimizing disk i/o but now in this
semester when we're talking about a
memory databases and now our database is
already in memory now we need a sorting
algorithm that is aware of where the day
is located and what our hardware looks
like meaning it needs nowhere you know
if it's reading writing to a certain
memory location is that memory location
in the same Numa region as where my
thread is running so it also means that
we need to be aware of what the size the
data that we're dealing with and what
our Karma looks like in terms of the
cache sizes so we may end up choosing a
different algorithm for chunks of data
of a certain size right if things can
fit in my l1 cache I maybe want to do
one thing differently than if I'm
spilling out 2d Ram because again that's
an order magnitude slower going from the
cache to derail so I would be very clear
that like what we're talk about today is
a better way in some cases the doing to
do sorting for a join if your data looks
a certain way in particular if your data
is gonna fit into 64 bit 64 bit values
or quicksort is still very very good it
can be paralyzed it can be implemented
to avoid branch mispredictions which is
one of the things we're gonna try to
overcome today it like I said it's
almost like the pickup truck of sort
algorithms it's can almost handle
everything pretty good and certainly you
can do better and so what we'll talk
about today is is a way to actually do
better over over over a quicksort so the
thing we need to understand though going
forward is this notion of essentially
doing gonna do divide and conquer
similar to quicksort where we're gonna
split the data up into smaller smaller
chunks called runs which is sort of a
disjoint segment of the total table that
have some number of elements that will
then now sort and then over time what
will happen is as we accumulate
or more these sort of runs will start
combining them together into larger
shorter runs and then combine other you
know larger sort of runs with others
larger shorter runs till we get
progressively larger and at some point
now we have the entire table or retired
key space for our join completely sorted
so this is sort of the the the atomic
unit we're dealing with when these
notion of runs but these runs are gonna
grow in size as we get you know as we
get further along in our execution of
the sorting so the approach we're gonna
focus on is this cache caution sorting
from Intel so remember last class I
talked about there was these six papers
going back from 2009 discussing the so
the various progressions on doing modern
sorting on today's hardware and the
first paper was this collaboration
between Intel and Oracle on doing hash
joins or swimmer's joins with Cyndi so
that's where this technique that comes
from and so the reason why it's called
cache conscious is because the algorithm
is aware of how big the runs are as is
going along and then it's going to use a
different algorithm to sort those runs
that's been the target the fastest
storage level that's available that can
store the run in its entirety so then
when they when a run gets too big then
we move to the next level in our storage
hierarchy by going from registers to
caches to to memory and you know well
how there you have a different
algorithms designed or optimized for
that that that approach so the the at
the first level we're gonna do in
register sorting because again CPU
registers are the fastest memory you can
have but of course there's very limited
in size so we're gonna deal with runs
that can fit into our CB registers sort
the entire table space into these small
chunks and then now we'll then spill
into in cache sorting at the next level
where we're taking all the runs we
generate from the first one and have it
fit into and sort them into runs that
fit into our CPU caches in this case
here we're going to target the last
level cache like l3 and therefore we
need to make sure that the
the we're gonna keep using this approach
level two until our rungs are half the
size of our l3 cache because again you
for this for this particular algorithm
you to store you know the the input data
and then an output buffer the same size
that contains the sorted run so for this
one also too as I said we're targeting
l3 cache which is you know roughly on
mono Zeon's
maybe up to forty megabytes we're not
gonna be worried about China's target l1
versus l2 l3 we'll let the harbor take
care of that for us we'll just say long
as we don't spill into DRAM and we're
still hanging out l3 then we're good to
go once we go we go go beyond l3 then
we'll use at a cache sorting where now
we're going to do a completely parallel
execution of the sorting where we're
gonna be aware of what's in cache which
is what's not in cache and we're gonna
have our threads actually be able to
jump around and operate on different
parts of the run or the tablespace
depending on you know what what what's
in what's in cache monopoly I mean we'll
go through the each of these one by one
we also say too that there's an idea of
level one level two level three this is
not actually in the original Intel paper
I think Intel calls them phases or
stages and that obviously conflicts with
the term I'm using to describe or join
our relevant phases so I'm using this
term level here so again let's look at a
higher high level what it looks at what
happens so here's our unsorted key space
and then in level one we're gonna do
we're gonna sort these now into four
element runs then once that exceeds our
CP register sizes then we switch into l2
we're now going to combine together
multiple sort of runs or at least two
sort of runs at a time and they combine
them the larger sort of runs until we
have ones that don't fit in our CPU
caches
and which point we enter l3 where now we
want to start using a different sorting
approach do you combine them together
until we get to some point where we have
our complete key space in sorted order
nice again high level heroes will go
we're going to focus on these two the
level three is a it's a bit more of a
architectural approach to doing sorting
across multiple cores rather than an
actual sorting algorithm itself and so
again like I said we'll go through these
one by one all right so the the in the
first level and what we're gonna do here
is we're going to combine together or
we're going to sort together runs
containing four elements here and we're
to use what is called a sorting Network
so a sorting network is an old idea it
goes back to the 1940s but some of the
first computers but back then when they
describe sorting networks they use the
term wires that carry values they
literally meant like physical wires like
actually you know in the copper wires in
Hardware in our case we're obviously not
doing that everything's all transistors
so this is just this is a conceptual
model and described this approach but
the hilum ideas the same thing just
we're just doing this in software now so
what's gonna happen is we'd have our
input sequence of four keys and then the
output buffer for sorry they for each
key element there's a they'll be this
wire coming out of it that's gonna carry
the value of whatever came before it
across until we get to an output buffer
or one of these compare rate or
operations so in this case here we have
nine five three six so in the first step
right well again we're all just gonna
carry the value going forward so in this
first compare Raider here we're gonna
it's we're gonna see which value is the
min which values the max it will write
the min value on the top wire and then
the max value will go on the bottom wire
so in this case here 5 is less than nine
so we're gonna swap swap the location so
now five will be carried on this wire
and nine is carry to own on the wire
below it same thing down from here for
three and six three is less than six so
this three will be carried out from this
wire and six will be carried along on
this water so now we repeat this down
but now we're gonna do comparisons
across different sets of wires so now
we're gonna do a comparison between five
and three 3 is less than 5 so 3 comes
out here
five comes out here and now in the case
of this wire here there's no other
comparator we have to do so we can write
out three to our output buffer in the
case of the next competitor is nine and
six same thing six and nine nine has no
other compare a generic comparators we
need to do so we read that to the output
buffer then we compare with five to six
and we produce our output here so we
were able to mount again through the
sorting Network we're able to take an
arbitrarily ordered set of keys and then
produce a sorted output buffer right so
what's really interesting and cool about
this is that no matter what our input
sequence looks like what keys there are
what went in what sort of sort of order
they they start off with we're always
gonna do the same set of compare
comparisons in the same order every
single time because again it's this
sorting Network a set up to do work this
way so if you now take this sort of
conceptual model and actually write up
code I've got a really simple
implementation like I said like you're
gonna do the exact same steps no matter
what our input sequence actually is
right so you know here's the first set
of comparisons right and the second and
the third like that so what does this
mean this means that it's super fast to
do because there's no branches there's
no if clauses like you have to do in
quicksort we have conditionals to decide
where the pivot point is you just are
you always going to execute this in the
exact same order every single time all
right so you sort of think of this as
like loop unrolling right instead of
having you know instead of looking at
one iteration from one level to the next
I just unroll it he has the exact
instructions I want to execute so why
does this matter well now this means
that we can actually vectorize this
because as I said before the vectorized
instructions assembly instructions don't
support conditional branches and so
here's a simple here's some you know a
sequence of code we can execute that
that doesn't require a conditional
branches it's gonna always require to
execute the same instructions and in the
exact same order every single time just
for just removing values around so we
can easily vectorize this
so this is how we did that so now what's
gonna happen is instead of sorting one
you know one Cindy register of four keys
we're going to sort four registers
containing four keys in parallel and so
for this one we're going to assume that
we have 512 bits in d registers we're
going to have 128-bit lanes
so every Lane is hundred eight bits so
if you store four keys in one 512 bit
register and so in this example here
right I'm only showing the key hi and
that's our that's our joined key
attribute but implicitly also there's
also gonna be a 64 64 bit pointer back
to the tuple that this key corresponds
to so you have to store the join key
when you do this sorting in Cindy
because if I now store these keys and
come up with a different order I have no
way to have the key map back to the
tuple that it belongs to so again for
illustration purposes I'm not showing
the tuple pointer here but assume that
it's actually both and then the join key
is in the higher level bits because now
when a new comparison of whether five is
is less than or equal to one there's a
greater wood between 501 what's the min
was the max I essentially ignore this
part of the key and I'm all and looking
this other upper part here so this is
also another reason why as I said last
class the Intel paper talked about how
you know you can implement a Cindy or
vectorized sort merge joint algorithm
that I'm talking about here but they
couldn't do it for real at the time
because you needed 512 bit registers or
Cindy red chairs which we actually have
now since 2017 in the case of the
Columbia paper that came out in 2015
AVX 512 wasn't around at the time so
they only operated on 32-bit keys and
32-bit pointers which in a real system
actually wouldn't work but now in
today's hardware we can actually do this
all right so now the way we're gonna do
this
sorting just we want again we want to
come up with we want to produce 4 for
element or for key sorted runs so our
sort of runs contains 4 outline
and we won't but we want to soar sort
for runs simultaneously at the same time
so now the first thing we need to do is
do load the data into our semi registers
so assuming this data is contiguous in
memory we can execute that with four
loading instructions into the registers
but now the way we're going to sort this
is that we're gonna sort this in a
columnar fashion right and so what that
means is I can't sort within a single
register because the symbian structures
that are available to us don't work that
way but I can sort across the registers
at the same time all right so I'm gonna
sort in a columnar fashion so in this
case here nine eight six seven I'm not
gonna sort that I'm gonna sort instead
this column with 21 eight 14 and 11 so
now I can just do that same minimax that
we did and I showed in the last last
slide but now I'm just doing this with
Cindy so in this case here I need to do
10 min and max instructions that are
vectorized to produce output that gives
me now in a columnar fashion the sort of
order again think of each of these
elements or lanes within a register as
one of those wires going into my sorting
Network and I just invoke the min Max
instructions compare these two and these
two and then these two and so forth
right depending the same way they did in
the last slot so again that only
requires ten minimax instructions but
now the problem is again I want to
produce in memory a sort of run of four
elements so I need to do a little magic
now to get this column now in a row
fashion because if I write out this into
memory it's not it's not a sort of run
right five four is less than than eleven
but lemon comes first so I want to do a
transpose now to take this column and
convert it into a row
okay so there's transpose operations to
do this in Cindy and then now I end up
with my my four sort it runs all right
so now again what cross cross one
register it's sorted so it takes me now
eight shuffle instructions to do that
transpose and then now for store
instructions to write out the registers
healthy manner so in in quicksort the
the number instructions we'd have to
execute to do this would be be way more
than what we're doing here so this is
only 26 instructions right assuming the
load operation only took four four four
instructions we take 26 instructions to
end up sorting 16 keys right or have
four for element sort of runs and we can
do this because it's deterministic so
this is actually this is pretty
phenomenal right this is this is a big
win to definitely do this but now what
do we have right now we have a bunch of
for held that sort of runs across
Ontario keys which could be a billion
keys and now we need start to start
putting these things together so at this
point now once we once we sort every
single key in our in the table then we
enter now level two where we want to
start combining these together into
larger sorted runs so to do it this at
level two we're going to use what's
called a victaulic merge Network and at
a high level it's gonna look like a
sorting Network but now we're just gonna
be able to sort larger runs together
into a locally sort of runs into a
globally sort of run that's a little bit
larger and again we keep doing this and
expanding the network which just means
more spaces more more more more sort of
steps and shuffling in min/max
instructions until we hit the half the
size of our last level cache because
then we fall down into into level three
and again on a 2020 easy on the l3 cache
size is around 36 to 40 megabytes I
think I think AMD would be less than
that so this technique won't talk about
here is also from Intel it comes came
out in 2008 it was one year before the
the hash join paper for Intel came out
and I the reason why I'd like this paper
and I like this technique is because
this is actually a big deal because they
were able to show that by using Cindy
instructions in the baton of certain
baton immers networks you can get almost
up to a 3.5 X improvement over a sisty
or
so sick non vectorized implementation
and so 3.5 x is for an algorithm that
for an old algorithm because all you're
really doing is now getting a constant
factor speed-up because we're using
harvard correctly that's actually a big
deal I mean you think of like quick sort
of quick search something in the 1970s
there's no magic wand we can do to make
that sort of fundamental core algorithm
we use all the time in computer science
to go faster through theory it's just by
making sure we use the harbor correctly
do we get the the better and proven that
we're looking for
so a I'll say also to you know this
paper was published in vldb one major
Davis conferences Intel is obviously not
a database company so they're not in the
business sign database their business of
selling hardware and so the way the
Intel stays competitive no I do not want
to restart thanks whatever Windows um
you would like so Intel is not in the
business of selling database they're
selling harbor and so the way they stay
competitive is they add new features
like Cindy instructions or the
non-volatile memory stuff I will talk
about later in the semester the add
additional things in the hardware that
you as the application programmer or the
Davis system developer can take
advantage of and get actually knowing
sort of justify buying new Intel
hardware and so the issue is that if
these things are super complicated
nobody's have knows how to use them then
Intel's not gonna sell more chip so they
actually put out it's been a good amount
of time and actually do good research on
putting out papers that are easy to
follow easy to read showing you how you
can apply you know the latest
enhancements and intel's hardware or to
two databases so the papers are always
always a good read and look look forward
to them so again at a high level the big
tonic merged network is just gonna look
like the sort merge are sorry of the the
sort of sorting network
it's just now review multiple steps
because we're dealing with large restore
it runs so say this is now on our input
size side and we're going to take two
for element sort of runs from level one
and we're going to combine them together
into a eight element output buffer so to
take two to sort of run so the first one
will be in the
same order that was generated in level 1
ii though we're gonna put in reverse
order so in that case here the smallest
element for this sort of run is the last
element and for this one the largest
element is the last element and the
reason is do this and just when you
start doing the evaluations it works out
the better what it works it's correct to
do it in this in this way so now what
would have it a bunch of these min and
Max the same that we had before we can
vectorize and then now we're just doing
more shuffles to do comparisons between
them until we produce our final output
and a completely sorted run right and
the key thing about this is that this
shuffle in particular can keep
everything in CB registers for as long
as possible without having to bring it
back into into the CPU cache because
that's gonna be that's gonna slip slows
down heist and then now once we once we
run out of cash base we're gonna fall
back into earth fall down into level
three but again this is gonna use the
same step the same procedures we did
before
it's just now there's gonna be this
high-level orchestration of keeping
track of what data is available on our
CPU caches and having operate on that
data first before we go jump to another
region of memory and so we let that get
fetched in torcida caches and before we
go ahead and start executing and the
idea here is that we're going to be
doing some extra bookkeeping to keep
track of where what's in memory what's
or say what's in what's in the CPU
caches and where we left off in our
pipeline and all those extra
instructions could potentially slow us
down the cost of doing that extra work
is much less it's gonna do it's me much
less than having to have stalls in our
threads while we go wait to fetch things
from from memory all right so we're not
burning every thread when it runs always
has stuff into CPU caches and it can
actually very efficiently so we're not
ping pong in our thread from going going
from being CPU bound to to memory
bandwidth bound right it's this always
says everything every time the thread
runs
there's always data in CPU cache and
it's running as fast as possible by the
instructions per cycle will be much high
in that case here so again we're gonna
run this in parallel while in multiple
cores keep track with all the different
cores are doing what threads are doing
and within the pipeline as data is
coming it's coming from level two or
moving along through progressing through
our sorting Network here we can have
outside jump around and work in
different parts and just keep track of
where this halt it's so there's no
synchronization between threads every
thread knows what needs to operate on
and we don't need to do any sort of
global there's no global coordination
every thread can figure out on its own
what it needs to do so this is actually
very difficult very convoluted and
complicated and to the best of my
knowledge no database system actually
implements this because it makes this
big assumption that all the all the
threads all the you know all the cores
are only being used for for sorting
meaning there's no other queries running
there's no other sort of background
tasks running like networking a garbage
collection or indexing they're things
like that and so I think the reason
because if you now could have different
cores doing different things that aren't
involved in sorting it's hard to have
that sort of precision that you would
need to recognize the data that I need
is in my CPU cache or not not my CPU
cache I think all that becomes like I
said more complicated when there's
things that are outside of the sorting
process so conceptually just looks like
this these are all the sort of runs
we've produced from level two and then
we want to start merging them and what
will happen is as a as a thread starts
executing say in this case here it does
the merge starts running out data into
this queue and before we can now start
doing the next merge we have to wait for
this all this data to be be done instead
of having a thread here just sort of
spin thread can pick up and jump to
another part of this multi waiting
Network and process the data that's
there and then when this data is finally
all available in our caches then the
thread can come back and and pick up
left off right so basically there's this
flag at every single stage that we set
to say there's there's nothing to do and
a thread
check for it for work and then when the
thread is when it's actually available
it's sort of like a pub/sub notification
that tell somebody hey come and get
start processing the data that's in my
queue that's available and again this
seems like this would be bad for CPU
caches because now we have our thread
jumping around different parts of the
program so to speak over the network so
to speak and processing different things
but again the the penalty of having to
wait for things that sit in the cache or
to be available in the CPU cache before
I start running on them is gonna be much
less in terms of you know the amount of
work the amount of cycles you're having
to spend again this is assumes that I
think it makes a big assumption that you
have complete control over all the
sockets and all the threads on each
socket and I think in a real system that
it's not not the case okay so as I said
no as far as I know far as I know nobody
does this I also think that the the
various in-memory database vendors that
are out there everybody's doing
something slightly different for the
disk based vendors oftentimes you'll see
a fancy version of quicksort if
everything's in memory otherwise they do
extra merge sort when you have to spill
a disk but I briefly want to talk about
what we do in our system and it's some
point we should go look to see what are
the other in memory Ben Davis vendors
were actually doing so we use something
called an in-place superscalar sample
support this was a paper that came out
in 2017 by these other Germans in
Karlsruhe and the main thing i want to
talk about is that it's an open source
good have library that we just linked in
into our system so it's not like we're
empty and free implemented this using
their implementation but the the basic
way to think about this is that it's
using sample sort which is a
generalization of quicksort the
quicksort only has like to you know has
one pivot point divides it up to two
parts in each step in sample sort you
sample some keys and make a decision
about how many partitions or any buckets
you want to generate
right and you serve occur Sulli do that
but the key thing about this one that
makes it work really well is that it's
doing this all in place meaning it's not
truly in place but it just means that
the the amount of extra storage space
you would need to as you start moving it
around is is caught the constant factor
to the total infant size and so what
will happen is as you start splitting
the data up when you in writing in the
particulars and you are writing into
your output buffer when that upper
output buffer gets full rather than
allocating a new upper buffer you then
try to write it back into your key space
over a - over write another part of the
the key space that's already been
partitioned so that you're not wasting
wasting space are you're not allocating
more memory that and then then you
actually need it's also gonna be
optimized for superscalar architectures
which means that they're an avoid
conditional branches in the same way
that we talked about before and the way
do this is by comparing keys usually
conditionally execute instructions
Christa copilot can generate for us so
again we use this in our implementation
and the research results at least from
this paper shows that it you know
clearly outperforms some of the more
optimized versions of quick so all right
so that's the sorting phase again we
we've we've taken our relations and we
sorted them on the join key but now we
want to have our iterators walk through
the two tables and compare compare two
poles from the outer and the inner and
if there's a match then we make a copy
and put it into output buffer so in our
well we'll talk about here today we're
not going too soon we have to backtrack
but if you have to recognize that the if
I have it if I have multiple keys we
sorted multiple tuples to the same key I
may need a backtrack on the inner table
but we can ignore that for now at a high
level all the algorithms we'll talk
about here today I work all the same way
so just like in the sorting phase when
we want to split this up and run those
multiple threads we want to do the same
thing here we want to have multiple
threads scan through the outer inner
table in parallel so that we
do this more quickly and of course that
also means now we wanted to we want to
have them not require any
synchronization during this process so
that they basically can run at almost
bare-metal speeds so there's no sort of
global creation decide you know who's
reading what peach that piece of data
right so we can do this if we if we're
having everything that right to separate
output buffers if you have to write to
the same output buffer and then you have
to do like compare and swap take take
out you know a slot do you want to write
into and so far as I know everyone's
always does does this in parallel so
what also say to is if you just want to
do an order by in your query so not a
join just an order by or sorting for an
aggregation or distinct yet you stopped
at the sort phase that we just talked
about you don't have to do this merge
step there's merge step is only to do
the soltner join so I want to talk about
now three different approaches to do do
assert merge all right so did do this
merge phase and put it all together so
the first two are from the ETH paper
that you guys read right from the guys
the guys in Switzerland and then the
last one here is from the hyper guys it
was the paper that they wrote in 2012
that said this is the best way to do
joins this is even better than hashed
joins and then the next year they
abandon that and switch over be entirely
in to do hash joins and so the paper you
guys read basically shows that this
approach for as much as the the the
hyper Germans touted it was it was
amazing it's gonna get crushed by by by
the first one here the Malta wave sort
merge so when you go through each of
these one by one
see what how they set things up and see
how they're different and then we'll do
an evaluation and look at the
performance numbers with that
the terrier asks whether leap the hyper
Germans are the same ones as the
in-place superscalar merge sorting out
them these are different Germans the
hyper Germans and Munich the the sorting
algorithm Germans are in arrancars well
different people different Germans okay
so the first one is gonna be this
multi-way search and so the multivator
sort merge so the idea here is that for
the outer table we're going to have all
the course sort the data in parallel
using the level one level two approach
that we talked about before
then they're gonna redistribute the data
across their cores in business doing
another round I like a range
partitioning and do the multi wage merge
sort or they'll ultimately merge from
the level three that we talked about
before we'll do the same thing now in
the our table so that means now we have
at the end of the sorting phase we have
at every core we have a chunk of we have
a partition of data where we know that
for any tuple in the outer table it has
to either exist or not exist in the
corresponding partition from the inner
table and that tuple cannot exist in any
other partition all right so again it's
like the grace hash joint by breaking up
into buckets or partitions I know that
the data I'm looking for has to be in
this other partition and it's not there
and then doesn't exist and I know I know
I don't need to check anything else so
this is actually gonna turn out to be
the best approach the important thing I
also say about too is that in this case
here you know I said that the multi way
merge is complicated and no real system
actually implements this so for this
paper here this is a testbed system
similar to the Columbia paper as far as
I know it only does the join so they're
not worried about interference from
other threads in the system running at
the same time right it's just doing the
join so let's see what it looks like at
a high level so say this is our outer
table here so at the very beginning
we're just gonna have that local Numa
partitioning the same way we talked
about in hyper for morsels I
are just chunks of data of the table
that's unsorted that is local to each
each of our pours each each of our
threads so now each threads going to
take its its local local partition and
it's gonna do the local sort so that's
gonna be the the level-1 level-2 sort
that way that we talked about before
then now in the next step we want to do
the multi way merge where we're going to
combine together the values within a
given range at each core and move them
to be on a single core so for this first
sort of chunk here say this first sort
of range which we know the ranges are
because we've already scans to the data
once all the data that corresponds in
that same range will be then getting
written to to this core here which then
does now the the multi way or the level
three merging that we talked about for
where we have we're sort of jumping
around to different parts parts of the
of the sort of execution flow based on
what's what's in our CPU caches all
right
so we do the same thing now for all the
other for all the other data this would
happen in parallel it's not we're doing
these one at a time but every core is
gonna get all the data they need from
the other other cores and do that multi
way sir multimers here then now what do
we have now we have for our outer table
we have a globally sorted global sorted
table so now on the on the inner table
we're doing the exact same thing as the
outer table for the sake of space
because the screens all look so big I'm
just gonna say that there's this little
sort box but that's doing the same
multiwave merge sort and multi merge
that we saw here so now what do we have
we have that every single every single
core again we have a partition range
partitioning chunk of data where we know
that a key either exists in this
partition or it doesn't exist at all
because you know key five should should
be mapped in here we're not gonna find
it at any other position when we try to
do the join so now we do this local
merge point where we have each thread
just rip through the data that's local
to it having two iterators run at the
same time do comparisons and
every thread writes out a matching tuple
to to its own output buffer me alright
so a way to think about this algorithm
is happening here is that we're paying a
penalty in the beginning to do remote
writes when we do this this so there's
merging across different course right
but that means now when we do the merge
of the sort merge phase or the merge
phase of the sort merge phase in fact
the merge phase of the certain merge
join here we don't have to do any remote
reads across from the new Marie Jeanette
slept local to us and that's gonna be
super fast the next one from ETH is the
multi pass sort merge join so the outer
table will do the same thing that we did
in the last one at level one for level
one level two will sort our data locally
but now instead of redistributing the
the data across different cores with
that multi way merge we're just gonna do
comparison across the entire table on
the inner side to see whether we have a
match and that may require us to do
multiple passes hence the name multi
pass over the the table for every single
to go to find the data that we're
looking for right so in this case here
the merge phase is just looking for
matching pairs of chunks to the outer
table in the inner table and that maybe
could be across different Numa regions
so conceptually it looks like this same
thing before we have that same local
Numa partitioning we use that same local
local sorting and every partition using
l1 l1 l2 methods then now we'll do a
global merge join where for every single
thread or every single chunk of data on
the outer table we got to scan through
every single chunk of data on the on the
inner table and again all the threads
are going to do this doing this at
parallel at the same time so you have
sort of anyway connections going around
and everybody's reading data from
everyone else right so we'll see now and
if you next slide the hyper guys are
gonna claim that this is not gonna be an
big deal because the harpy fetcher will
will help us but doesn't turn out to be
the case at all
all right the last one again is from the
hyper guys so this is massively parallel
sort merge so we're gonna range
partition the outer table redistribute
it across the cores and then now each
core is gonna sort that their their
local local data in the partition in
parallel the inner table we're not going
to redistribute at all we're just gonna
sort it locally for whatever data that
they have then now when we do a merge
phase the scan across the different
threads we stop the stand across
different threads for every single
thread on the outer table every single
partition on the outer table but since
we know our data is is sorted we know
what boundary on the inner table we
actually need a deal with them and we
don't have to scan the entire partition
of the inner table every single time we
want to do a lookup so looks like this
same same cost name a partitioning I
sorry different before it so now the
every threads gonna write out the data
that it belongs to data within a range
to a different partition so you much a
remote writes in the beginning and then
now locally you're gonna sort these high
and these will be globally sorted the
the outer table will just sorry the
inner table will just sort locally and
then now when I do my join I have to go
across partitions so I'm gonna scan here
scan now for every single tuple in the
inner table but only scan a portion
sorry every scan through the entire
partition on the outer table but only
scan now a portion of the partition on
the inner table but I gotta do that for
every single partition to find all the
data I'm looking for and of course again
I can do this in parallel across all my
threads at the same time but everybody
everybody's gonna have to do the exact
same thing right
so what hyper hyper guy is gonna argue
is that in in all these cases you're
doing sequential reads and so we haven't
really talked about hubber prefetching
but we talked about software prefetching
when we talked about the relaxed
operator fusion where that's where we
have special instructions that tell the
CPU hey I'm gonna need this data pretty
soon and go bring in my CPU caches at
the same time the harbor itself was
trying to figure out
what's your access patterns look like
and if it recognizes that you're doing
sequential scans over some stride of
memory or region of memory it's gonna
start trying to prefetch that data for
you because it thinks you're gonna keep
scanning scanning it along so the hyper
guys argue that in and in and this step
here when you start doing remote reads
different new Murray jhin's the harbor
is moving to recognize that I'm doing
special scans over these remote regions
and start prefetching it over the
interconnect and bringing it to your
local local CPU cache and your Numa
region so that this is gonna hide any
penalty to you you would have from doing
these around reads truth is though this
this doesn't actually work out to be the
case and the and the in the Swiss guys
will show this in the result one
additional thing I think that came out
of the hyper paper which i think is
interesting is that they sort of laid
out some rules that you should try to
follow when you if you want to implement
an efficient sort merge algorithm the
joint algorithm that is aware of the
hardware and then that can be paralyzed
well so the first thing they're gonna
argue is that you don't have any random
writes to non-local memory right
contrast this with the multi pass
certain merge when you did those random
writes and then instead what you want to
do is used to break things up and then
reach trigger to them and have each core
operate on the local data the second
rule is that you want to try to perform
it and come you got to read data that's
not local to your thread always do a
central scan so the harbor fetcher can
bring things into CPU caches I had the
penalty doesn't work I always break out
of the case and for these these joins
and then the last one was related to the
fee like in the multi way merge in level
three it just and in general this is
always good advice for parallel systems
anyway you don't want to have any core
have to wait for another thread to do
something right that means you want to
avoid it's fine rain latches or
synchronization barriers and just have
every thread be able to operate on data
immediately without is as much as
possible that haven't according with
anybody else all right so for the to
finish up with results we're gonna
discuss the from the paper you guys are
signed to read from ETH where they're
actually going to compare
the three different sort of complete
joint algorithms that I've talked about
just now on a pretty beefy machine at
the time that had four sockets with a
half a terabyte of DRAM so again
everything's gonna fit in memory and so
they're gonna compare against the the
three games of three sort merge joins so
the two that they developed and then the
one from hyper and then they'll also
compare against the the radix partition
hash join that we talked about last
class I think in this paper they
referred to it as a radix join just
means that it's a radix partition hashed
run so the the first thing they want to
compare against is or evaluate is how
the sim D sorting algorithm that we
talked about before from Intel how that
sort of compares against a sort of non
vectorize or non Cindy implementation
when you're running on a single thread
so they're gonna pair against the SCBA
plus STL's standard sword which is a
hybrid sword that's using quicksort in
the beginning and then they switch over
to heap sort as you get further along
and they this is just showing you along
the x-axis as you increase the number of
tuples you want to sort you can show
that the the throughput you can get and
how it varies so this is actually a
great result because this is actually
corroborating the 2009 Intel paper that
did the same comparison so this is sort
of like you know further justification
or evidence that the cindy sort is
preferable over to you know sisty
sorting implementation and this one's
like matches exactly with the speed-up
that Intel reported which was about you
know about 3x faster so you know this is
good science this is this is really cool
that they were able to do this so then
now you want to do that you compare this
one and the sort so for this one if
they're gonna have the outer table be
1.6 billion two bullets and the inner
table is 128 million tuples and they're
going to be just sorting 8 8 by tuples
so the way this is divided up is that we
have the multi way the multi pass and
the nasty parallel from hyper and then
it's broken up into the amount of time
or amount of cycles that you're spending
for tuple for the different phases so
the partition phase across all of them
is about the same but the big difference
you now see is for the sorting and the
merge so this is the sort phase of the
actual sorting algorithm and then this
is the merge phase of the merge
algorithm and then this is the merge
phase of the joint algorithm but it's a
you know this is obviously confusing
we're doing merge twice but this is
where the sorting and this is for the
join so the main takeaway here is that
the multi-way actually performs the best
partitioning is the same the sorting is
a little bit slower than the multi pass
but then the the merge pass is is you
know there's nothing and then the the
merged itself or the join is super fast
because that's always gonna be in that
operating on on data that's local to you
my numeral region swaggin so the number
of cycles I'm spending to do that
comparison is super short where in the
case of hyper they're spending a lot
more time more cycles accessing remote
memory and they pay big penalties so
this is showing you that the harbor
prefetcher that hyper claims is going to
help them here and doesn't another way
you can plot this is include the
throughput graph so in this case here
when you're doing cycles for output
obviously lower cycles per two pool
output lower is better in the case of
the throughput line higher is better
because you're pussing more data quickly
and so as expected if you guys see fewer
instructions to compute the join the
throughput will be higher right so again
this is this is a great result that's
just showing you that the you know that
breaks down at what phase of the joint
itself are you spending all your time
and if you're aware of if you're if
you're designing your album would be
aware and conscious of the cache sizes
and my new Murray jhin's I'm able to get
the better performance by minimizing
them out of the remote reads I have to
do I should the baby penalty do move
right to the beginning but then the
remote reads is is you don't have any at
the end alright so the next one would
cap error is now just a little more
detail of scaling now the number of
threads for the foot for the multi way
and the hyper join so in this case here
I think this one was
this was all the threads on a machine
but this is now scaling up that I'm the
number of threads so when you're down on
one thread it's not not that not that
there's no big difference between two of
them although the multi way is still
faster but as you now you scale up in
order threads you see of the larger gap
in performance and so this is showing
you now though in in well to scale log
to scale like you're doubling the number
of threads as we go along the x axis and
so if you're able to achieve linear
scalability which is the gold standard
which you want in a parallel system and
if I double the number of threads and
double internal cords I double the
amount of throughput or double my amount
of work to accomplish so in case the
multi way merge sort all right wet at 16
threads I'm doing 130 million tuples per
second and then if I double the number
threads to 32 I'm doing 259 so it's
slightly less than 260 but it's almost
exactly double when of course once you
have hyper threading there aren't you
know they're not real true cores you
have to program counters that you're
you're switching in between to name in
between on the core and so if your CPU
bound doesn't really help in this case
here we're probably memory bound so you
still able to get a little bit
improvement but it's not gonna scale
linearly in the case of the hyper
approach right they're not able to scale
linear law so going from 54 to 290 like
this should be this should be 108 but
we're only at 90 so even though we're
adding more more threads we're getting
worse performance and then when we go
into hyper threading then it just all
falls apart all right so the main
takeaway here is that the extra
instructions we're gonna spend for the
multi-page sort merge in level 3 turns
out to pay off for us because we don't
have to you know we're not doing remote
reads when we do the merge phase of our
joint album all right and if the
overhead of reading across new Marines
is what's hurting the the high
performance right in this case here
what's happening is for Hyper the reason
why it's falling off and getting the
worst performance because if I now split
my data up across multiple threads more
and more threads
then the likelihood that a when a thread
goes and tries to access a tuple the
likelihood that that thread is is not
that the - they like to hug to my throat
is trying to access is not in my
numeration increases as I add more
threads because now the data is split
across multiple threads so therefore I'm
doing one or more remote remote reads so
for this for this graph this graph is
comparing the the multi way merge sort
sort merge join with the radix hash join
and what I'm showing you here is that
you're varying different sizes of the
inner table in the outer table and what
it shows here is that the for smaller
table sizes the the performance gap
between the two of them is quite larger
then as you increase the larger and
larger and larger tables the the
partition gets more and more expensive
for the hashing and that sort of negates
some of the difference you would get
before it's better if you get over the
sort of merge join out with them but
it's still still going to beat it here
right and so for this the I'm combining
together the the building probe phase
and just doing a single number but it
shows you that the cost of building a
hash table and then probing it to find a
match in some cases can be less than the
cost of sorting the outer table in the
inner table and the merge drawing
because then I still have to go do the
the join I try to merge after the
sorting and then do the merge to join
like the cost of doing the sorting phase
and sometimes is is greater than just to
build a hash table so this is sort of
showing you why the you know a using
efficient hash table implementation
parallelizing across multiple threads
even though we can't Simbi all of that
you know all that that process to in
that in the hash join it still may be
much faster than sorting where sort
merge we actually would beat the hash
join is if if I might the output of my
query has my query as an order by Clause
that's the same that needs to sort the
data on the same key that I'm joining on
then if I do a sort merge
I can just use the output of the join
which is already sort of that in the
same way that need for my order by and I
don't have to do an extra sorting so in
this case here so say I have to do the
sorting for for this I use this clear
ball say I've do this an order by for
this query if the order by is the same
as the same as the joint key I'm using
my servers don't I got one then I don't
need to do anything extra effort I do
the joint in this case here if I need to
sort it F my hash table then I got to
add that same chunk of time up here
it'll be a bit less depending on the
output of the join but it's still an
extra step I have to do and this is
something I need a count for in my query
optimizer so this graph is just
explaining the last graph last slide of
how you vary the the size of the tables
when you're trying to join what if the
how does the performance gap between the
two approaches close down and again this
is just showing you that with radix hash
join when you have larger tables you
have to do more passes to do the to do
the partitioning and the performance
benefit you get is reduced but still in
the end it's going to be it's gonna it's
gonna be preferable over the sort merge
join and I don't forget why this +
plateaus um I think at some point you're
just paying the penalty everybody things
in and out of memory in the same way you
would do in a disk based system ok so so
one of the main main thoughts about this
as I said the in a modern commercial or
enterprise or high-end
oh that database system that wants be
competitive you're going to need both
the hash join and the cert merge-join
algorithms
I think they implement both and the
optimizer will figure out which one you
actually want to use and so but if
you're building a new system scratch it
unless you're targeting old GP workloads
if you're trying to target OLAP or pose
the first join implementation you're
gonna want to build is the hash join
because it's just the research so is
that it's ideally you know clearly
preferable and faster than the sort of
merged one the and as I sort of said at
the end here we also do not consider
the impact of having the data already
sorted on the join key as as you may
need by the order by clause and in that
case they're like you know you wouldn't
have to pay that extra sorting stuff and
that the sort MERS joint actually may
end up being better than B then the hash
join but again this is something the
query optimizer can figure out for you
so that's it for today for Wednesday's
class now we'll get into actually the
part of database systems that I
admittedly know the least about and but
it's something that I find the most
fascinating and so we'll do a we have
expanded lecture series this this
semester we're going to have additional
lecture on Cori optimizers and the idea
here is that just try to understand how
we can take a sequel query and convert
it into the best query plan we would
want to execute on our system so we can
use all the various techniques that
we've talked about so far the joint
islands the vectorize execution the
scheduling methods all the indexes all
these different things now we think we
can consider when we do our and when we
try to build our query plan and so the
paper that's the sign for Wednesday
reading is just an overview of the
various problems you have to deal with
in query optimizer and then on next week
when and well then talk about actual
implementations and the main difference
will be this sort of dynamic programming
approach from IDM versus the Cascade
approach from the volcano guy okay all
right that's it for now and a post on
Piazza about getting set up for getting
prepared for for next week's project
presentations blanketing the side park
what is this some fool heyyo
[Music]
this design with that here called
the whole kit cuz I'm og ice you down
with the testy hi you look and it was go
grab me a 40 just to get my buzz song
cuz I needed just a little more kick to
just slipped up my lips and just say
nice and my hood won't be the same I'm
nice to take a seat I pray