[Music]
[Applause]
last lectures it's been a trying
semester but we finally got through it
so for this last discussion we're gonna
talk about databases running on sort of
new emerging hardware or sort of
non-traditional hardware that's slightly
different than everything we talked
about so far before we get into that
material I've quickly want to go over
what's remaining for you guys in you
know from now until the end the semester
of final grades so on Wednesday this
week we'll have a guest speaker from
Amazon come give a talk about the things
he's been working on that redshift so
this will be live this will be on zoom
is unfortunately it's only available for
senior students so I'll post the details
in Piazza on May 4th next week you'll
have your the second round of code
review submissions May 5th go do your
final presentation also unzoom also only
available to CMU students to discuss you
know the butcher group has worked on the
final exam that I gave out last week
will be due on Wednesday May 13th and
then what's missing here is in the code
drop that's posted on the website as
well so when you get those you know
submit all your information to me to say
you're actually done after incorporating
the the second second round of code
review comments and then on May 16th on
Saturday we will have our extra credit
hackathon again this is optional this is
available to those that want to
participate it's actually also going to
be open and potentially for for non CMU
students and so we'll figure out how to
cordate that again the idea is that
you're not gonna work on you know just
keep working on what you worked on for
project number three it would be
something new or sort of adding a new
sequel function or new feature to expand
support of our sequel system for this
okay again I'll post details about this
on on Piazza
one additional thing is I need everyone
also fill out the course evaluations at
this URL here so this is super useful
for me because they I realize that the
last you know last class have half of
the class semester has been online only
so just in general comments about the
projects the reading assignments the
general cadence or the pace of the class
those things are actually very very
useful I actually read them and I
actually take in the consideration of
tweaking the class from one semester to
the next the the University and the
department actually read these things so
this is don't take this lightly and
don't be like most master students often
are where they just click five five oh
five for everything like actually you
know if you want to spend time and give
me sincere feedback please do it's
entirely on anonymous so to give you a
kind of idea a feedback that I often can
get we got this once a year where people
rightly pointed out that I had a body
odor problem this has been since
resolved in subsequent years with sort
of special shampoo so hopefully no one
has been too offended by any odors of my
body emits but again this is super
useful I didn't really know that I had a
body odor issue until this person
pointed it out and then I went to the
doctor and he's like oh yeah this you
have this problem this this medical
condition here's this special shampoo
you should use so this is why I want you
to be candid and open about all your
comments for the course I I do take them
in consideration okay
the as I said the thing where you want
to talk about today is running databases
on you know sort of new hardware
hardware that's not just you know CPU
and SSDs and spinning disk drives and so
this has been a ongoing theme in in
databases for since almost the very
beginning where people have always been
looking to use a specialized hardware or
new hardware to make data systems go
faster
in the in the early days in the 1980s
late 1970s there was this movement
called called database machines where
the idea was you would buy like an
appliance
a specialized server that had custom
hardware Asics
to do splitting of the database
operations so this common one was that
you could buy a database machine that
had specialized hardware to do hash
joins very efficiently so this movement
fizzled out in the 1980s because because
of Moore's law that you know Intel and
Motorola and and Dec we're putting out
new CPUs all the time and so by the time
if you were a databases machine vendor
by the time you went and you know design
and fab and sold your specialized data
as Hardware Intel put out the new
version of x86 that got even faster so
it was you would get diminishing returns
on the amount of effort you had to do to
build these things so in the 1990s for
the most part everybody was running on
commodity hardware and certainly when
the cloud came along in the 2000s this
is even more so in the 2000s though
there was some early attempts to build
FP FPGA databases where the idea was you
would have DJ sit between the CPU and
the disk controller and you just you
push down predicates on that so the
teaser was a famous system that did this
IBM bought them
I think they've sunset of them or killed
them off about a year ago but they you
know they were they were the first FBI
database system and again there was now
also a bunch of appliance databases
where unlike a database machine where it
had specialized hardware just for the
database system the idea of an appliance
was it was commodity hardware but the
system in the operating system the
database system were tuned explicitly
for the for the Harvard that was running
on so you can just buy this one rack
unit that had my sequel running on it
but my sequel was already tuned for that
exact hardware so we sort of achieving
them to the best performance but again
because of the cloud this sort of
fizzled out because everyone just said
it's just cheaper to buy you know
commodity stuff on it from Amazon in
2010 there was a the vinegar the FPGA
czar sort of always been there I think
in recent years they've become
more prevalent but the baking we saw in
the 2010 in the last decade was the rise
of GQ databases and this is where
because of the the big interest in using
GPU computing for machine learning
people correctly identify that oh I can
actually do some database stuff on the
GPUs and take advantage of all the
advancements that the machine learning
guys are are getting and so we'll talk
about a little bit just a little bit at
the end of this lecture there's what
these GPU databases are and what they
look like so now in the current decade
that we're dealing with I'm actually
very excited because I think that I
think it's gonna be the Wild West again
in terms of everybody's gonna be trying
everything I think there's a lot of
interesting things coming out in
hardware that may not be explicitly
designed for database systems but sort
of data intensive applications if you
want to call it that which includes
machine learning or data science things
but databases are a key component in
that kind of stack and I think that
there'll be some things that we can
start incorporating in database systems
and still have that be considered
commodity hardware so the main thing
that we're going to talk about today is
persistent memory and just to be how you
can design a data center to handle this
I think this is gonna be a major change
in this decade FPGA and GPUs are still
be around I think that there's still be
niche players I don't see I don't see
them being like every database systems
gonna have to have a GPU or an FPGA sort
of accelerator component for it its
majority the databases are gonna run on
Davis isms are gonna run on it you know
Intel CPUs going beyond FPGA is are
these things called configurable spatial
accelerators think of this is like an
FPGA there's a programmable hardware
that instead of doing the sort of a
logic that the FPGA is do it's more of a
dataflow thing and again like when I say
more I mean it's hard particulate else
is gonna come out i fabbing costs should
be going down
especially for sort of maybe like 70
nanometers like sort of larger size
transistors so people can start
fattening stuff much more cheaply than
they'd been able to do before
so the economies of scale is good sort
of helped us so again we're gonna focus
on this today we'll talk a little bit
about GPUs but I think in the next 10
years I think a bunch of more things are
gonna come out which I'll be pretty cool
all right so as I said we wanted to spin
us at a talking about persistent memory
we'll talk a little about how to
accelerate things with GPUs and then
we'll finish up talking about Harvard
transactional memory because this one
also often comes up with students asking
about oh you know is this something I
could be using instead of how to do all
the kernel or latching stuff that we
talked about the semester and the answer
is going to be no we still need to do
everything that we've talked about so
far and this may help in in small cases
okay
so persistent memory the persistent
memory the way to think about this is
that you know when we talk about in the
intro class this this dichotomy between
the volatile and the non-volatile
storage and how we had a design or a
disk oriented database system to account
for those differences and certainly
lesson last class when we talked about
larger the memory databases we need to
be aware that our database could have
been writing out to a it's reading data
to a non-volatile block-based storage
device that's much slower so we have to
you know design our algorithms and our
hierarchy to account for that
with non-volatile memory or as
persistent memory the idea is that we're
gonna get almost the speed of DRAM and
have an access interface that is
addressable byte address bold like DRAM
but the hard ler will be able to retain
all our reads and writes even after the
power is lost my sense why it's called
persistent memory so I'm gonna slip up
multiple times during this during this
lecture and keep calling it non-volatile
memory because that's what we were
calling it when we first started doing
this research back in 2013 the industry
standardized on calling this persistent
memory which I actually agree with is a
better term sometimes you also see this
called
storage class memory but they're all
they all essentially mean the same thing
so the first persistent memory devices
that were available which is sort of
confusing because they were like PCI
Express cards that were block
addressable even though the storage
medium inside of it was the same thing
that's gonna be in the precision memory
or talked about here it just provided it
through a you know PCI interface but the
new ones that are actually available now
from Intel are gonna be byte addressable
so it's gonna look and smell exactly
like DRAM to your application but
there's some extra stuff going to need
the covers and make sure that
everything's persistent I have to let
the terrier in so let's talk about the
that's why we got where we are not
because camellias backstory is actually
very interesting and sort of part of the
reason I got you know I spent a few
years researching persistent memory in
databases with with my first PC student
so the if you take if your electrical
engineer and you take off you know
fundamental course on on circuits
they'll describe three types of circuits
right we'll talk about a capacitor which
is invented back in 1745 but this is the
ability to store some charge like a
battery then later on the resistor was
invented to modify the voltage that's
coming in over your circuit and then if
years later they developed the the
inductor which is just a way to convert
the voltage into into heat so after 1831
it was just assumed that these were the
three fundamental circuits there
couldn't be anything else like you the
way to think about this is you can't
build any of these other types of
circuits using other sorry any of these
elements using another element and that
sort of thing there to look at an atomic
element of the circuitry so then in 1971
there was a professor Leon Chua at at
Berkeley who was working through some
equations
and he he did and discovered that there
seems to be that there should be a
fourth type of element because the way
the math worked out is was that there
was like this missing Kapena component
of the equations that you had to have
this other fourth element in order for
the math actually worked out correctly
right and so he hypothesized that there
was a two terminal device where the
resistance of that device depends on the
voltage that's applied to it so it's
like a resistor right but the difference
is that you can actually changed its its
resistance depending what voltage you
give it right and then when you turn off
that voltage it permantly retains
remembers its last resistive state
forever
and so what he hypothesized was that
there was this fourth element called the
mem risker so he wrote a paper about
this in 1971 it was sort of lost to time
because it had a lot of citations it was
very mathematical nobody understood it
and it was essentially forgotten flash
forward now to the early 2000s and there
was this team at HP Labs that was trying
to build sort of self self-configuring
nano devices and what they were finding
in their experiments is that these nano
devices would have certain properties
that they did they couldn't understand
why they were why they were doing
certain things and in particular would
be like when you give them a voltage
they would change the the they would
change the resistance you were seeing in
the in the in the circuit they were
trying to build and so they looked and
they couldn't figure out what it was and
they they've kept looking in the
literature and then they just happened
to stumble upon the the 1971 paper from
Chua that says that oh you know there's
this other fourth have a circuit that
you need actually could exist we just
don't know how to build it yet and then
they determined that it was actually
they they that there that HP Labs
actually and love accidentally building
a memristor or two super interesting and
part of the reason why they figured out
that what they had built was
same thing as what what you hypothesize
is that there's this graph of like the
circuit that shows this sort of
hysteresis loop and what they were
measuring exactly match what he proposed
or in his conjecture that this is what
it should look like so then they went
back and for this for this paper they
wrote how we found the missing memristor
they went back and looked at the last
like 100 years of Electrical Engineering
scientific publications and they found a
bunch of other people reporting the same
hysteresis loop in their in their
experiments but no one could explain
what it was going on so people had been
stumbling upon the memristor for years
and years and years but nobody actually
knew what they were actually building so
HP made this big announcement that they
had they have discovered that mr. that
this is something that they were
reliably able to reproduce in the lab
and that they think they can actually go
ahead and next manufacture it and that
this was gonna be a major game change in
the field of computing so so much so
that like in 2008 they had this big
presentation like I said there whatever
yearly conference that talked about
their their work on memristors and you
can see here that I think this came out
in 2007 so they discovered it in 2006
proved that actually was real 2007 there
at this conference 2008 their claim that
the memristors will be development ready
and then in the near future they were
gonna claim that memristors were going
to replace all DRAM and hard drives and
SSDs and transistors and everything
we're gonna be running off memristors so
this was over 10 years ago deep hims not
gone SSDs aren't gone being his hard
drives aren't gone so what happened well
HP as far as I know has still not
produced a or shipped a memristor
product HP then eventually also split
off between like the consumer side and
the enterprise side they had this ya
have this moonshot project called the
machine that was gonna run entirely off
of memristors as far as I know
that has was was canceled in it and at
this point I don't know whether team
members are going to come out least from
HP so let's talk about other types of
persistent memory or let's not
understand now a little bit about what
we're gonna be talk about today for
Intel's device what the memristor is
what it could have been and what some
future technologies are actually going
to look like so well safety was also
like I drank the kool-aid from HP
although I had no affiliation with them
I thought memristors were a big deal and
I was really excited and I sort of why I
went down this path are doing persistent
memory research here at Carnegie Mellon
and I was always under the impression
that the memristors were always two
years later to our two years away right
so like every time you HP had a press
conference every time HP each system and
publicly
avilés like it's two years later it's
two years two years later and then you
get to the next two years and then come
out say the same thing as two years
later or two years away that it and it
never happened um but Intel actually
shipped shipped shipped a device which
is the first one here at phase-change
memory which is pretty exciting so let's
go through each of these one by one
again this is not specific the databases
is just sort of you get an idea about
what what's going on underneath the
covers with this technology so
phase-change memory the idea is that you
have this storage cell that has two
metal electrodes going into it and what
happens is that you put a charge into
into that this phase change material
that's calcination ID and that
essentially bakes or cooks the material
to be able to change the resistance of
the circuit right so if you give it a
short pulse then that changes the cell
to a zero because that gives you a
different resistance if we changed it to
a long gradual pulse then that'll change
it to a one and again I'm showing this
heater here it's not actually you know
it's not a little match underneath it
but underneath the covers you're giving
it either a short charge or a faster
charge and that changes to be 1 1 0 1 so
the
the idea of a phase change memory has
been around for a while people have
known about them and says nobody's been
able to manufacture them at scale and
the Intel opting DC memory that we'll
talk about is to the best my knowledge
is actually phase change memory it's not
they haven't said it publicly at least I
don't think they have but when the
devices first came out some guy in South
Korea took it out and cut it you know
but busted open the device and looked at
it under electron microscope and saw
that it actually was high during phase
change memory so there's some downsides
of this now because you're actually
having to put a charge in here obviously
this will generate some heat so that
prevents you from potentially storing on
on the on the the CPU itself and I you
know you can only write to it so many
times before it wears out so you know
ehh memory is here it's fast it exists
and you can buy it at large capacities
but you know compared to memory stores I
think I thought this was an inferior
technology but of course this exists you
can buy this today you can't buy memory
stirs
all right so memory stores are a this is
sort of confusing that there's the
memristor to the circuit fundamental the
fundamental circuit element and then and
that actually includes facial memory of
the spintronics but then there's like
the HP marketing what they would call
whatever they were selling the memristor
but these are the these sort of
scientific definition of what they had
built was called resistive Ram and the
way this works is that you have two
layers of titanium dioxide above you
have two titanium dioxide above two
layers of
in between two others are platinum and
the Platinum is gonna carry the charge
and what will happen is if you if you
run the charge in one direction you'll
change the resistive state if you change
around the charge in the other direction
you change you change the resistance
date so the idea is like the
there's floating electrons in between
these two different layers and that's
how you said it'd be a 0 or a 1 so the
cool thing about memristors again why I
was excited about them is like titanium
dioxide is a very common element it's
the same stuff that's in white house
paint or sunscreen that you put on your
face so it's not like some you know some
obscure material that you had to
manufacture the Platinum is obviously
not not super common but but for tiny
dioxide there's you know there's a ton
of it so it was gonna be super cheap and
actually super high density you know
petabytes per square centimeter because
the you know there's the current you're
sending through this is much less than
then the phase change remember to change
the state the other interesting thing
that's really wild about the memory
stirs or was resistive Ram is that HP
was talking about how you could use the
storage fabric or the storage medium for
executable logic so they talked about
how you can actually change the like it
like an FPGA you load a program onto the
onto the memory and have the as data
comes out of the memory it would flow
through your logic gates and do whatever
additional processing that you wanted on
them all right so you think of like I
can do like in memory computing I can do
a scan on a column and have some
executor logic gates to apply the filter
and then the cost of changing that
executed logic on the fly was super
cheap compared to a an FPGA so you like
loaded per query and so there was all
this talk about how they could build
neuro networks and memristors they could
model the brain with memristors that was
about 10 years ago and I haven't heard
anything about it since then
the other thing about the ask you the
logic for members is that it wouldn't
use the traditional NAND based logic
that we use in our CPUs that we have now
it would actually use something called
material implication which was invented
the great philosopher Bertrand Russell
back in like the 1910s so it was a
completely different way of thinking
about computing if you ran on the
memristor of course you know it never
happened yet to happen all right so the
way to think about the three mediums
were talking light also here as well as
like there is a there's the phase change
memory exists now the memristors might
be in the near future and then a little
bit farther out will be this magnetic
resistant RAM or spintronics and for
this one instead of actually storing
instead of actually storing or changing
the the storage medium to record to
record a charge we're going to change
the we're going to move electrons using
magnets okay so the idea is that this
oxide layer is going to move electrons
between them and that's how you're going
to set them to be do you know set the
bit B 0 1 and then supposedly this not
only uses less energy it just has a
smaller scale factor so you can you can
store this at like you can have these be
stored at 10 nanometers per bit and the
speed is almost equivalent to your CPU
caches and like using static Ram SRAM so
you could now replace all your your l1
l2 l3 caches with spintronics have that
be super large because it's a higher
capacity much cheaper to manufacture
sitting on the cpu and you're you know
you basically have persistent l4 it's
like latency is less than D Ram so this
is super amazing right if this exists
this would be a big game-changer
I think for all of these actually Mel
sure what the memory serves I first
spintronics and first patient in your
memory prior to them manufacturing like
your DRAM dam replacements you can buy
them are like small scale factors for
like for like cellphones things like
that so you can get I think now you can
get spintronics DRAM or spintronics Ram
in like 16 mega byte capacities
certainly not enough for what we need
and a database system but like you know
it does actually exist just not at a
large scale
so why is this for real
so four three so three reasons why you
know persistent memory is actually a
thing now we need to consider in our
database system the Stars have sort of
lined such that we need to be cognizant
about about this technology and actually
consider it when we design a new system
so the first of that the industry has
agreed upon a standard technology
nomenclature and form factor for these
devices so there's this thing called j
deck is basically the consortium between
a bunch of manufacturers they said okay
if we're making non-volatile memory
here's what the form factors have to be
right
I sort of like DRAM right you know
there's there's you know there's DRM two
three and four like that's a consortium
that has decided this is what the form
factor is the spec is and then all the
manufacturers can go off go off and make
the same you know sin make devices that
that followed that specification the
next thing that happened in 2018 2017
was that both Microsoft and Linux have
added support for persistent memory in
their kernels and this is something
called Dax is a direct access extensions
this is allows us to write programs that
are that are able to use an API where it
knows it's talking to you persistent
memory right I could space easy sis
calls that we can access this and we and
we had the right instructions we would
need to actually make sure things are
flush which is the next one here so in
2018 2017 Intel refreshed the
instruction set for Zeon's and add
explicit instructions to do cache line
flushes to persistent memory again think
about how you write programs now I when
I do an update to a piece of memory
underneath the covers that's doing a
store operation or stored instruction to
update that that memory but I'm that the
my right is gonna land in my CPU cache
unless I'm doing streaming rights but
you know ignoring that my right lands in
the CP
- but if I if if that CPU cache has now
been backed by persistent memory like
instead of DRAM its persistent memory
but a program needs a way to know that
the things that I wrote that are sitting
in CPU caches have made it out - has
made it actually made it out to - to
persistent memory and therefore I know
that my right is durable when you think
of again a disk based system I'd call F
sink right and that'll move it out of so
whatever buffers that it has and
actually persist it on disk and I don't
get a return call to my application
until I know the disk controller says
that right was successful so we need the
same thing for our cache lines and
that's what these instructions give us
so this is sort of was the state of the
world up until 2019 2018 but then last
year is when this stuff actually became
available so this is what Intel's
shipping now it's called opt Ain DC
persistent memory and as you can see it
looks like DRAM it has a DRM form factor
meaning you can fit right on where demon
exists in the motherboard but instead of
being volatile it's non-volatile storage
now this actually works is a bit
complicated but like there's it's almost
like an SSD where there's there's a
price there's an ASIC on the device
that's doing load balancing or we're
leveling and garbage collection and
encryption and a bunch of other things
so this is this is more than just like
hey I'm just writing just from all bits
this is intercepting the writes and
actually doing something so you as far
as you know you can't go to Amazon
because I tried today you just can't buy
this this is something you have to get
through like a manufacturer so it's nil
still not widely prevalent but it
they're out they are shipping this you
can get access to this today if you have
the money
price wise mean I I'd have to go look I
yeah actually
publicly I don't think I discuss the
prices um I think it's three or four
four times the price of DRM we should
just look that up but but it it exists
which is awesome right so so obviously
over time it ever get cheaper then maybe
other manufacturers of this technology
so this to me this is a big deal
alright so how are we actually going to
use this so from from a databases
perspective there's really two ways and
as far as I know well yeah from a data's
effective there's two ways there's a
there's an additional way to to
configure the the configure that the
device the the opting device to do
writes a certain way but we can ignore
this is what we care about in a database
system so the first is that you just
have DRAM being used as as a Harvard
manage cash so what does that mean so
this is our persistent memory whatever
the size of this is that's what the
operating system thinks it has for for
the total amount of memory that's
available to the database system so now
as I start doing writes for my database
system it'll go through the VM subsystem
the right will first land in DRAM
because that'll be fast and then I can
return back to my application say yeah
we got your got your right in memory and
then eventually this will get pushed out
to do the persistent memory or if I do a
flush then I make sure that that's
actually retained down there but the
idea is that since DRAM is faster than
persistent memory at least as they exist
today I can have them all my ripes
writes absorb this and I don't I don't
experience the slowdown necessarily of
the slower Layton sees for persistent
memory so in for Intel they call this
memory mode where again it's just we're
just using it as if it was D Ram and
there's actually nothing we're doing in
here in our database system for this set
up that is aware that we're writing to
persistent memory and this thinks that
it's just DRAM
it's a larger cheaper potentially DRAM
and so that means that we start the
write a law we said to do much but a
bunch of extra stuff to account for this
because again we think that we're just
writing to to DRM the other approach is
that we would have the the DRAM adjacent
to persistent memory and now our
database system is aware that were right
- persistent memory and that has the
durability properties we didn't want and
so to do this again if I have a right I
can I can declare I want to write it to
some region a memory my address space
that is backed by DRAM or gonna have a
right go to some region of memory that's
backed by persistent memory and I know
that if I do that right the process of
memory and I do my flushes then like my
changes are durable so intel calls this
application mode and the idea here is
that the application meaning our
database system is aware where the
boundaries are or then we've allocated
some memory into our address space
that's in persistent memory versus DRAM
and that we can do flushes as needed so
the as I said beginning these devices
first were arrived on PCI Express cards
and they were block addressable so from
from a database systems perspective
that's not interesting because that's
just we just take our disscourn and
design choices we made from last
semester and build a system to use that
it just looks like a faster faster SSD
and I should when we did benchmarking
against some high-end Samsung devices we
really did see a major difference in
performance for the PCI Express version
you just you saw way more stable
agencies though like if there was less
oscillation and performance the one the
the this set up but we do care about is
the the second one I showed in the last
slide the application mode where I know
I'm ready to the RAM and I know I'm
writing to persistent memory and my dad
listen can manage that right so because
because now we have to go and design our
system to account for that that now I
can actually do byte addressable updates
to some location and memory some data
structure or some table heap that will
be guaranteed to be be durable and then
Intel's device handles the you know
handles of the case where even if I
restore my application I restore my
system I come back and I get access to
my memory that I had it for it's not
gonna restart the program counters for
you so it's not like you can manually
pull the plug and come back and
everything's exactly the way it was
before we still have to do some
potentially some recovery work because
we're processor gonna is gonna start up
all over again
so this is a conjecture of mine I still
think it's true we'll see how it plays
out in the marketplace in the next
couple years but I believe that when
persistent memory come becomes more
widely available and that basically
means like Amazon will give you access
to it
when Itoh ec2 the in-memory database
systems that we've been talking about
this semester they will be in a better
position to accommodate the byte
addressable persistent memory because
they've already written an entire
architecture to assume they can do
random access very quickly to to storage
the image this morning to do systems
what will will probably end up starting
with the second approach I showed before
where you just have the DRAM sit in
front and a Pasiphae is a cheaper more
efficient memory pool or larger capacity
you know memory address space so you
don't the rewrite and your application
you just you're just using more D Ram
but then if you start want to be taking
want to take advantage of persistent
properties of DRAM a persistent memory
then you have to go and reor connect
your system to potentially use a byte
addressable API essentially all the
things that we talked about this entire
semester all right so I want to first
talk about some storage recovery methods
for persistent memory and this is sort
of just get you to think about what what
can change if you design your system to
account for to be aware that you're
writing to byte address well persistent
memory so this is the paper that my PC
soon
joy realized and I wrote a few years ago
on skin can think looking at all the
basic designs you have of a database
system storage architecture and what can
change with with persistent memory so
the back in 2015 we actually did not
have the device the only what we were
using at the time was a harbor emulator
that Intel provided us in Hillsboro
Oregon where they've modified the
the the motherboard for these devices
for the system to introduce some
additional microcode in like debug hooks
for the Zeon so that anytime I did a
load in the store it was basically this
this sophisticated busy loop that would
figure out the timings for how to slow
down the there's loads in store
operations to mimic behavior of
persistent memory when it actually when
it finally came along so this work was
all done in a prototype data system we
were building called n store this is the
first one of the first days system we
were building at Carnegie Mellon when I
started this is actually what the
peloton project came out of so we
started building in store for this paper
the project kind of got bigger and
bigger we renamed it to peloton and then
we eventually killed all peloton and
that became the materia database system
that you guys are working on today we
threw away all the peloton code and
started over so this is you know from n
store to peloton material that's how we
ended up with this but there's nothing
in our current system that uses any of
the code we use we generate and store
because of this a lot of it was was
specific to the Intel emulator device
and it was also before Intel put up put
out a bunch of libraries to do memory
allocation other things you would need
it to write persistent memory programs
nowadays all that stuff exists with the
PMD K from Intel like they provide you
with all the the important constructs
that we had to roll our own backpack
that all right so let's understand how
we reduce synchronization with
persistent memory so again the way we
write programs now when you you allocate
malloc a bunch of memory you do a bunch
of rice to it you assume that it's
volatile and you also assume that's
gonna lend in your CPU caches if the
program crashes you lose everything but
now since we since we want to be able to
write data adorably and have it backed
by persistent memory we need to know how
that actually works at a high level so
again say our pipeline looks like this
this is our process that's running on
the CPU they do a store operation
to update some location in memory but
that store operation is always gonna
land again in our CPU cache all right
guys that's that's the fastest storage
medium and that's available to the CPU
but then now if I want to make sure that
my data my change makes it out to to
persistent memory I could just wait and
hope that eventually it makes it out
because again when my what will happen
is if my cache gets full the the CPU
would then write it back right to change
you actually made out to alton memory
right and then you then fetch in the
next piece that actually needs into the
CPU cache to make space but I I but I
can't I need you know exactly when that
occurs but there's no callback method
for this and when it happens but that
would be too slow so I want to tell it
did I won't tell the CPU hey write this
alpha me so we can use a cache line
right back instruction that then pushes
the the change to a memory controller
and this is sitting on the motherboard
that has the small capacitor to keep it
especially he's battery backed so the
capacitors size such that I lose power
there's enough energy in here to make
sure that everything actually makes it
out to to my persistent memory and then
at this point I'll return control back
to the program because my right made it
out to the memory controller and it's
responsible for making sure it makes it
on the other side and then this thing
does what's called an asynchronous data
refresh
it's a special instructions I'd said it
for Intel that prop assist that changes
to the to the non-volatile memory or
that the TM device so from our database
systems perspective we just need to be
aware of what cache lines or said what
memory locations we modified that we
then want to make durable and we use a
cache line flostor cache line right back
instruction to make sure that happens
the next thing we have to deal with is
if our database system restarts and we
come back online we have a bunch of
pointers now to tuples or other
in-memory data structures that we have
but how do we actually make sure that
those pointers are still valid the
second time to come around because I
can't guarantee that and when I start
caning memory that the first time been
allocated the secretary my program
starts I'm gonna get the same virtual
memory addresses that that I had before
time so the issue is this I have an
index it has a bunch of pointers to some
tuples and then let's say if I'm doing a
pen only I'm doing multi version control
so I have multiple versions of the tuple
and this in like in my version chain I
have a pointer to another tuple here but
now this my system crashes this gets
blown away right and my index gets blown
away all the pointers are now invalid
what I want to be able to do is come
back online and have all my pointers
still be valid so that so if I'm using
you know virtual memory addresses
there's no guarantee to do that so what
you said you need is a memory allocator
that is aware of of these two issues
that you need to be able to synchronize
your data out the disk or try out the
persistent memory when you call the
right instructions and then when I come
back the second time that all my
addresses steal point to that the
correct correct memory check locations
in virtual memory so the first one again
you're just doing the the cache line
flush but then you have an S fence
debate to wait until essentially a
barrier and junction pipeline to make
sure that those changes get flushed
before we start executing the next
instructions like this is sort of the
same thing as s ink going to the OS and
not returning until the the disk
controller confirms that the flush for
naming the idea is that the memory
allocator can you can declare
specialized pointers that come through
the memory allocator that are backed by
persistent memory and that you know that
anytime you have a pointer to that
memory location for your application
when you come back around the second
time when you restart the program those
pointers will still be valid for your
application and so you don't want to
write all the stuff yourself you want to
use PMD K from intelligent and they
provide you the low level primitives to
do this all right so let's see now how
we can use these these primitives to
build a database system so again for
this paper what we did was we
looked at the three basic design
architectures you can have for storage
manager in a database system and we
identified where are the bottlenecks or
what are the issues for when you're
running on persistent memory and how can
we do redesign them to be aware that I
can now write changes that are durable
so for this one we're gonna assume that
for simplicity that there's no DRAM that
everything's in persistent memory and
therefore if I do the flushes then then
I can guarantee that my changes are
durable so this way think about this
this is like you know maybe fifteen
years twenty years in the future where
DRAM goes away and does everything is
just durable so the first choice to do
in place update so this is where you
have a table heat plus a redhead log
snapshots and this for our example we're
gonna base base our design on on a volte
beam the next approach to do
copy-on-write
updates and this is just like shadow
copying or shadow paging where every
single time I'm gonna update a page I
make a copy of it and a side side
location and then when my transaction
commits I just flip a pointer to say
here's here's the here's the here's the
latest version of the database so for
this one you're making extra copies of
the table but it doesn't require you to
have a right ahead log for for
durability and so our design here would
be representative of something like LM
DB which uses this approach the last one
is a log structured system where you
don't have a table heap the log is the
database and we just keep appending to
the log to do fast writes so this would
be something like level DB or rocks dB
so we're gonna go through the each of
these designs one by one and again the
idea is that take the textbook
implementation of these architectures
run it on persistent memory identify
where the bottlenecks are or where the
word that redundant updates are and then
redesign the architecture to to account
for persistent memory so again for the
first one if we have an in-place engine
the way we do writes is that we follow
an index that lands to this tuple here
and then we go ahead and update it
to make sure when a transaction commits
that everything's durable we're going to
write out a Delta record of the change
that was made to to write a head log and
then apply our change here and then some
some later point we when we take a
snapshot then we make sure that our
change our change gets persisted there
so for this one we're an update the
tuple sort of logically once it's like
one update query we're applying for this
one tuple but we end up writing it out
three times because we have to write out
the tuple Delta get there right up there
yeah so two point in the heap and then
we'll write it out to any additional
snapshots that we take so again oh this
is running in persistent memory so
everything here is considered durable
and so we have a bunch of duplicate data
here because again for the same update
we've read it three times this is also
gonna have slow latency now because I
have to do traditional Ares in my my my
database system where I load the last
successful snapshot or checkpoint and
then replay the log with with the you
know analyze redo and undo phases but
again everything is persistent
everything is already durable anyway so
it may not necessarily need to need to
do all of that so we can see how we
actually want to design a system to
account for the fact that we have
persistent memory and use the fact that
we have just pointers that we have
pointers that can be guaranteed to be
correct the second time you run our
system to now only record what was
changed rather than how it got changed
so to do this we're going to have to
maintain a transient undo log in case
our transaction aborts while while the
system is online and we have to roll
things back and we just make sure that
any changes we make from a we have the
confidence because there's any change
that we can't we can't guarantee that
the CPU will flush out any dirty changes
to tuples that are sitting in the CPU
cache out to to memory because that's
something beyond the control we can't
tell the CPU not to do that it was
does it on its own so we need to account
for that but we know that once our data
is durable in our tuple then we don't
need to maintain that we do long for
that so the two buildings durable out on
debt or out in the table heap in in a
persistent memory we don't need to redo
anything does looking like this so are
we follow the index everything's in
persistent memory we get to this tuple
here we apply the before we apply the
update we can now put a an entry in our
log that says here's the pointers to the
tuples that got modified but that's all
you need you need to know about it and
then I can actually now apply my change
and then if I now you know flush this
then I know that the change for this
transaction is durable right this is
just sort of helping me to say oh by the
way here's what actually got changed in
case I need to follow pointers and undo
things but once this change is flushed
along with any other changes for it have
flushed my transaction is considered
durable alright so let's see how we do a
copy and write engine for this again so
this is a hierarchal version of shadow
paging I'm just using a plus stream and
the way to think about is that we still
have the master record that points to
the master copy of the shadow copy we do
compare-and-swap to flip that but our
our pages are just laid out in a
hierarchy in a tree so let's say I want
to update this tuple here so I would
first make a copy of the of that page
and then the the the entry and the tree
on the side here then update my
directory to now point two for the
second page your still point to the
original one for the new page over here
I point to the new one so that's another
write to do my to my entry to my
structure then I do a third right now to
flip the master record to the to the
dirty record so the first issue with
this is that these copies are expensive
because
again we're taking this entire page even
though we only update you know one tuple
inside of it we have to make an entire
copy we have to update the leaf
information update the dirt directory
just to retain this and say what we can
do because persistent memory is can be
treated like DRAM instead of having a
page oriented architecture you can be a
byte addressable architecture like we
have now where we just have pointers to
tuples and then now when I do an update
I only have to copy pointers over here
as well as applying the change and then
I update the dirty directory and and and
the the master record so the key
difference here is that the the
granularity of the change we're making
because we can read and write two byte
addressable locations in memory is is
much smaller all right the last one is a
log structure Artic architecture and the
idea here is that sort of classic
architecture would have is you have an
in-memory mem table with right ahead log
and a skip list or some kind of small
data structure to keep track of what a
log entries are in memory and then you
have on on disk you have a bunch of SS
tables that always have a bloom footer
in front of it and then index that
points to locations in the log so when I
want to update I first apply it into my
Delta of the change I made to the right
head log and then at some later point
I'll I'll flush that out the disk and as
I'm doing compaction now I'm gonna keep
I have right amplification where I'm
keep applying changes or combining log
records over and over again if they have
to be retained so the issue with this is
that we have to pluck data and because
if we're using a level architecture
we're going to have expensive
compactions so if you want to switch to
this to persistent memory then we can
get rid of the the ESS table entirely
because now all of this is persistent
and therefore we can just have the right
ahead log and our data for that and we
don't need to do any any of this we
still have to do compactions though that
I think that doesn't go away but
we don't have to have this you know this
concept of a mem table and SS table
which are different different sort of
layouts of the data in all the examples
we just looked at as I said those were
assuming that the computer we were
running one only had persistent memory
and there was no DRAM but I guess that's
not really gonna be realistic for a
while so let's think about how we acted
we design a system today using what is
available from Intel now
so let's target a way to speed up
performance and take advantage of
persistent memory by focusing on the on
how to sort of take a standard table
heat plus write a hello implementation
and speed that up so what is the right
ahead log doing for us well in a gather
for a in memory system or dis coordinate
system the idea is that we're trying to
avoid random writes disk by replacing
them with sequential log writes for an
enemy database we only do special log
writes because we're writing to the
table heap in memory for a disk
coordinate system we do our write
sequentially to the log and then
invention in the background will flush
out dirty pages so that's one advantage
we'll get the other ones that will also
get transaction capabilities because now
if there are changes that are hanging
out in one disk from a transaction that
hasn't that did not commit before there
was a crash before the system shut down
we can use the log as a way to roll them
back and reverse any other changes so
again this design number right ahead log
of some writing to the tuple first then
writing to to the started writing to the
log first before we write to the tuple
makes sense because again the the log
right it's gonna be scheduling in a
persistent memory world though we're
gonna have fast random writes alright
we've invited dress will implies that we
can jump to any location in the
procession of memory space and that will
have the access speed that's almost
equivalent to doing scones access so
they're huge dichotomy or the
the difference in performance we had in
a sequential light versus a random light
in a spring this hard drive or even SSD
this will be much less in a in a
persistent memory system so you wanted
to find now a logging protocol
potentially that can take advantage of
this and the way we're going to do this
is that the weight the way we're gonna
do this is maintain a multi version
database and do copy on writes or make
sure we don't overwrite existing
versions and then we'll have in our log
just the metadata about what was
committed rather than the actual copies
of the changes that were made so this is
the technique that my PhD student
developed here at Carnegie Mellon called
right behind logging and the idea here
is that it's a logging protocol that's
designed specifically for persistent
memory but in a world that still has
DRAM for the table and the idea is that
we can get instant recovery of the
database after a crash with minimal
amount of redundant information being
stored in the log and so the way we're
gonna do this is that we only have the
that we have a copy of the the database
in persistent memory we make sure that
we flush changes to that database and
now our log is only going to change
contain pointers to the records that got
changed and then now after a crash or
anything we need to do is just look in
the log to figure out what transactions
are running at the time of the crash of
the order or the the shutdown and we
would have pointers to the tuples that
they modified and we keep track of the
fact that the the updates that these
transactions made did not commit and
therefore we know the pointers to those
tuples and therefore we want to want to
reverse them if anybody tries to access
them so another way to think what this
is like we unlike an already have log we
don't need any redo information because
the changes that our transactions made
are made durable to persistent memory
right away and we never have to worry
about reapplying them from from the log
so the now in the context of persistent
memory this protocol is new
there was one other system that we're
aware of that did something sort of
similar to this and this was brought to
my attention by the great Phil Bernstein
sort of the Godfather of sort of modern
concurrent retool and he told us of a
database for a I think it was a it was a
Puerto Rican telephone company back in
the 1970s so at the time Puerto Rico had
bad power infrastructure and they would
lose power several times during the day
so they had to have a database that
could run that could come back
instantaneously at any time there was a
power loss because if you're shutting
him to me the book shutdowns multiple
times during the day and if you're if
you're a recovery time is super long
then you know by the time it took you to
go over cover the database the power
might get shut off again and you're just
never able to keep up so they had a
database that sort of did something like
this obviously it wasn't with persistent
monitor system memory but it was making
copies of the database they're paying
the penalty of doing random random
writes to disk in exchange for is faster
recovery times the most modern systems
don't don't make that choice and in our
case here with right behind logging
we'll be able to get good good
performance at run time and good
recovery time so again because test
reactor setup is like this we have a
table heap so you want to run this query
there's an update a tuple so the table
heap will hang out in memory and DRAM
and then there'll be a second copy on
persistent memory and then we'll have
our logon persisting memory as well so
now when we do an update table we first
update the tuple in table heap then
write the change to start in memory then
we write the change to to nvm but then
we also Nautilus write some metadata to
the log to say oh by the way here's the
pointer to the tuple in persistent
memory that change so that we know if we
crash before transaction commits we can
use this to figure out where do we need
to go and make sure that those changes
aren't persisted and when the system
restarts so how this is all going to
work is that we're going to rely on
multi versioning and we're gonna assign
transactions timestamps there's as we
normally would and when we go to flush
out
changes for transactions the we're gonna
figure out what is the range of
transactions in flight transactions that
are running right now and is record that
in our editor log wears a red behind log
along with pointers to the two posts
that they're modifying and that tells us
what what are the potential range of
tuples rent range of transactions that
should not be persisted after a crash so
now when after a crash would come back
again we use this fail group commit rain
to identify what tuples are not valid so
we don't have to look at individual
timestamps we just look at does the is
the tuple I'm looking at have a
timestamp that falls in this range and
therefore I know comes from a failed
transaction and I can ignore it and so
what you're essentially getting is like
the you're getting the undo operation
sort of free as you're normally doing
the visibility checks for a multi
version concurrent role so it made more
sense more sense in Excel slides so when
I recover I only have an analyze phase
the analyze phase looks through the
right behind log and says here's all the
here's are the timestamps of the
transactions that that could that didn't
commit successfully then I Amelie start
processing transactions but now I've
computed this global range that says
here's the here's the range of
transactions that if you come across a
tuple that was modified or created by
BAM our version that was created by them
you know we should we should ignore it
and then reclaim the space so you're
sort of doing like cooperative garbage
collection as you're going along and
identifying tuples that that shouldn't
exist so let's look at an example so say
here that this is our timeline of going
forward in time ever to keep track of as
transactions get started and and let me
commit so t1 starts here so for the
current range of active transactions we
know it's between t1 and t2 all right
and there's no failed transactions
because hey this is the first time we
turn it on the system so let's say now
here before t1 commits we crash then
well when we come back T say the next
transaction that starts t2 so the only
thing that we needed to do after the
crash is when we scan the log we would
find an entry here to say wheat the last
range that we knew about from the last
group commit was between t1 and t2 so
now
range factors actions this to t2 to t3
so now as T 2 runs and access to the
database if it comes across anything
that was created by t1 it knows that it
should be garbage collect and cleaned up
so it it go has to start cleaning them
removing those things say t2 commits but
then t3 starts same thing our active
transaction is t3 t4 and since we know
the pointers of the tuples that t1
modified we would know whether we've
clean up everything that t1 has touched
yet and let's say in this case here we
don't have a transaction that touch is
what do you want to t2 t it does so we
could run the background vacuum in a
separate thread just to scan through and
find all those things to reverse them so
that way we're not stuck with with
versions that nobody wrecks essing in
its wasting space right and then t4
starts and at this point here we know
that we've gotten everything that t1 t1
modified so we can then remove it from
our list of failed ranges so I'm going
to show you now the performance of what
red behind logging can do but I'm gonna
do it the opposite of what we normally
just got how we nearly discuss things
with transactions I'm gonna show you the
recovery time first I have no many you
show performance first before recovery
so this one it's running replaying right
behind log right behind log and right
ahead log of 1 million TPCC transactions
and this is running on that Intel
emulator that I mentioned where you
could to the the latency of persistent
memory relative to 2d Ram so in this
care we keep this case here we're making
the the speed 2x the latency so and also
to the the the latency here was
symmetrical so the read and write costs
were the same and the sequential and
random writes were this sequential the
sequential and random access these were
the same cost and then they reads in the
right cost were the same as well
but a real Hardware the reads gonna be
faster than than the writes so we're
gonna pair the time it takes to restart
the system and recover the log put the
debisch back to a correct state for a
spankers hard drive a solid-state flash
drive and the persistent memory emulator
so what you see is that with right ahead
log
the performance of the different
approaches are roughly the same right
because this can be the cost of or these
also unlock scale but it's a couple you
know it's the cost of accessing disk and
then replaying the log the combination
the two of them are about the same the
difference though now with ripe ahead
longing the recovery time is a thousand
X faster because all you do when you
turn the system on is you just check to
see that right the the the failed time
stamps from the right behind log and
that's all you need to do to say I'm now
my databases has been fully recovered at
least at a logical level so what this
just shown you is that the performance
benefit are right behind logging for
persistent memory as well as the older
storage devices is about the same it's
about a thousand necks so now you look
at this and say well sure right behind
logging is faster than write ahead
logging but why do I have to do this in
persistent memory because I'm getting
amazing performance sorry amazing
recovery time for these other storage
devices as well well now if we go look
at the runtime performance now you see a
big difference so for the runtime
performance of the right ahead log you
see that of course as you add as you
have a faster storage device you're
gonna get a better performance so
persistent memory is faster than the
solid-state drive with a spinning hard
drive right and that's the bottleneck of
when you commit transactions obviously
in this case here for TPCC
so that's why persistent there the
persistent memory gets the best
performance for right ahead logging but
now if you do right behind logging now
you see why you need persistent memory
because in the case of the spinning disk
hard drive in the solid-state drive you
get a temperate 10x reduction in the
runtime performance when you use right
behind log but only if you use
persistent memory
you're gonna get a one point 2x speed-up
in performance and this is because in
with the persistent right behind logging
with persistent memory because you have
flat fast random writes to the table
heap on persistent memory you know
that's random i/o which is gonna be
terrible on these these tablets slower
devices so this is the combination of
right behind logging and persistent
memory is the is the right
combination is to get the best
performance in this scenario here okay
so just to summarize what we talked
about um we talked about how to if you
if you know you have persistent memory
that's byte addressable you can
reorganize your storage architecture to
take advantage of that and reduce the
amount of data duplication and redundant
copies of data during update
transactions and then we saw in the case
of right behind ball game is the
technique allowed you get better
recovery time because you're taking
advantage of the fact that you know that
you have a protocol that's writing to
persistent memory and therefore you can
set yourself up the system up so that
upon recovery you have to do minimal
amount of work to put the database back
into the correct state so as I said I
think for precision memory this hardware
is available now and I you know once
becomes more prevalent and more
commoditized you gonna see a lot of
database systems coming out to take you
to take advantages in the very beginning
they're all just gonna use it as larger
cheaper memory that's a little bit
slower and some symptoms of what systems
will be more sensitive than that but if
the you know but the prognostications
about the limitations of scaling DRAM
you know those turn out to be true then
the everyone could be switching over to
something that looks like an opt-in
obtained in okay so now I want to finish
up talking about some some computational
acceleration we can do in our databases
and explicitly I want to talk about GPUs
as I said for FPGAs
they're used in they're becoming a
little bit more common now sorted
because you can get them on Amazon high
you can get ec2 instances with them but
it as far as I know there's more GPU
databases around today than there are
FPGA databases and I think partly is
that because the overhead or the sort of
engineering cost of writing FPGA
code versus writing GPU code or just
using a GPU and library like the stuff
that NVIDIA provides like that's much
the bar entry to get advantage of a new
hardware or sort of non-traditional
hardware and your database system is
lower GPUs than at PJ's ok so if you
want to use a GPU or in our database
what do we need to know about well we
need to know about what what GPUs are
good for well GPUs are gonna contain
thousands of cores and but the the type
of computation or the programs that
those cores can can execute our going
have to be less sophisticated and less
complex than which we'd normally run on
a full-fledged xeon core this is because
these cores are designed to do
relatively simple operations can
relative to xeon can support on that are
repetitive on large amounts of data data
streams right so you like you want to be
able to say like the best-case scenario
would be like doing this to furniture
scan on a bunch of columns or single
column broken up to different chunks and
you can blast that out across all the
cores and all the cores are doing the
same thing and there's no there's no
indirection
there's no conditional branches it just
says I'm gonna from beginning and I'm
gonna apply the same filter and over and
over again so again this basically what
I was saying but like the kind things we
want to push down to the GPU or anything
that don't require a additional input to
make decision about what to do next or
require you to the the program to do
branches like if causes and things like
that so what's really good for it
sequential scans what's really bad for B
plus trees right because that's like
looking at the the contents of a people
astray node and make a decision or where
to go now there are proposals in the
research literature to build like B plus
trees or other tree based data
structures that you can run on GPUs to
best my knowledge nobody's actually
using them yet
and again this is not my area of
research and I don't know the
limitations of them are but for the most
part people aren't doing transactions on
people aren't doing transactions on GPUs
they're primarily being used for for
OLAP workloads the other point thing we
need to be mindful about is that
although GPUs are gonna have a lot of
memory now it's not gonna be cache
coherent with the CPU so that means that
if you want to do if you if your
databases can be updated and it exists
up in DRAM or even an SSD you either
need to copy the whole thing down to the
GPU with all the updates or do like a
merge operation to apply those changes
incrementally but it's not like if I
have you know I have my data's in DRAM
and I do an update there the GPU is not
gonna magically see that change we have
to explicitly send a message down and
say here's the new data so again the
idea is here is that we want to figure
out what computation we can offload to
to the GPU and it's gonna be mostly
central scans there are there are
implementations for pretty much I think
all relational algebra operators we
would want to execute in na and you know
to run queries but sequential scans are
the sweet spot like those hatrocks
implementations they're sorting
algorithms obviously that are designed
to avoid these conditionals and
branching so the high-level architecture
will look like this so say that this is
this is what we would talk about the
entire semester so far that then we have
a CPU or all multi socket system and
then we have our database hanging out in
DRAM and we can be aware of the Numa
regions to recognize what you know what
what dims are closer closer to a given
core and so over here now in the PCI
Express bus is going to be our GPUs and
we need to sort of think of them as just
another another socket that has way more
cores that look a lot different and they
have their own they own D Ram as well
and they're not gonna be in sync all
right so I think like for for GPUs and
2020 I think you get once only up to 100
gigs of DRAM
I probably on the high end ones whereas
like on the CPU we can get
and he up to 48 terabytes of DRAM if we
have a lot of money so the other thing
we be mindful to is the the bandwidth
between our compute and storage so to go
between DRAM and and CPU core with ddr4
we can do about 40 gigabytes per second
over the pci-x PCIe bus the best I think
we can do now is is 16 gigabytes per
second so it's it's not that far off
it's not like an order of magnitude but
it's still significantly slower than
what we can do over here so that means
that that's the one of the challenges
we're gonna face is that you have to run
a query we have to send a bunch of data
down here and then be able to crunch on
and get it back and that's gonna be it
made it be faster just to run it up up
here I with the with the CPU I'm not
gonna have as many cores but this
bandwidth is gonna be our bottleneck for
us
so now NVIDIA has this thing called MV
link that gives you 25 gigabytes per
second in between in between two
different GPUs you could you know you
message passing in between them you can
also get MV link to go from the DRAM
memory up into the CPUs memory at 25
gigabytes per second that though is this
MV link technology as far as I know is
only available on PowerPC machines I
don't think it's only x86 so you have to
run on IBM power and in order to get
advantage of this
I think Intel has its own fabric but I I
forget what it's call are a and B might
have something as well okay so how well
do you organize our system so there's
three different approaches we can take
to how we want to use a GPU in our
database system so the first is that the
easiest way is just take our entire
database and plop it down or copy it
down to the PCIe bus put it on the GPU
and now all the queries own if this has
data that's down on the GPU this
obviously is limited to the amount of
VRAM that's available in the GPU if your
database exceeds that size then this
work maybe you could daisy chain a bunch
of GPUs together and have the sepia
coordinated about what who has what data
and combine the results up in the cpu
across the different GPUs but it's best
my knowledge that I don't think any of
the major vendors do this anymore so
this is actually what calm nice I used
to do when it was called map D and
they've sensibly architected it to do a
the third one here so the second
approach is that you recognize that you
for some queries or some some databases
you don't maybe don't need all the
columns for a table down in the GPU so
you only copy down the parts of them I
can now your query planner can recognize
alright for this part of the query I can
run on the GPU because those columns are
down down to the GPU but then I'll get
back some offsets and I'll you know copy
the to the the the tuples a bit cover
the batteries that are needed for those
two blows based on those offsets for the
other columns that open my memory and
then I just made two of those results
and return them back to the application
so for this one where I've seen this
done as usually requires the
administrator to identify that these
should be the GPU resident columns and
these should be up in the CPU and you
know that has limitations because people
may not always know how to pick what the
right approach is there may be some
other systems that can configure that
out before you automatically know the
best approach though is to do support
streaming algorithms where I can have
the data to stand on the fly move data
from the CPU memory down to the GPU
memory and process it incrementally
while I'm continuing to send out more
than you know why send them send down
the first batch of data the GPU fires
off starts crunching on it and then the
background I now start streaming down
the sort of the next wave of data that
I'm gonna need and so by the time that
they finish the GP finishes processing
the first batch the second batch is
ready to go and it just keeps on going
so like the GPUs all be always being
fully utilized and there's hash join
there's sort merge-join there's there
budget of albums that that can their
implementations of albums that that can
can do that for you so hard work seller
databases were something that I was very
interested in a few years ago we end up
having a seminar series at CMU on on
this very topic so I invited most of
these vendors over here the ah-ha meet I
went to club map Deacon add a couple is
in DB scream bright light airy tea bees
from uber that was that came out after
we had the seminar series but the point
I'm trying to make is if you're really
interested in this topic and want to
learn more you can go to this URL here
and I have a whole I think there's eight
different eight or seven or eight
different lectures or talks from all
these major database vendors that are
building GPU databases and they'll tell
you you know what makes them interesting
and how they work but the last thing I
want to talk about is Harvard transact
on memory so every year I debate whether
I want to bring this up because it keeps
getting turned off by Intel because of
security leaks so the waiting went over
transactional memory is that things like
you have a critical section in your code
and now I can have a heart our
transaction managed by the CPU that
keeps track of the loads and store
operations into memory for my
transaction and then if I now if it
determines that there's a that there was
another thread that running also a
transaction that may be read or modified
the same things I I touched
then it'll can go ahead and abort me and
restart be so the way it works is
basically operates like OCC and it will
maintain a read rights in a private
workspace for your transaction and then
when you go to go ahead and commit they
check to see whether they do a
validation to see whether anybody else
has modified the same location as that I
read or wrote and it's kind of cool
because the way basically works is that
they just piggyback off of the the cache
coherency protocol it's using any way to
keep track of to heat the Corazon Singh
and they're using that to figure out
when there's conflicts routine
transactions running at different cores
so the so for this is this was exactly
invented by Maurice Herlihy
who
the guy invented linearise ability he
used to be a professor here at CMU but
now he's a professor at Brown he amended
this I think in the early 1990s and
actually Intel put it in their hardware
I think starting in they now stood in
2012 and then it came out in 2013 but
then they found a bug in it in 2014 so
then they disabled it and then I think
I'm like 2017 they're like alright
here's the new CPU as the bug is fixed
go ahead and rename bêlit and then 20
million teen I think there's another I
think it's called vom b-bomb or
something like rabbits so then another
bug that can have security leaks when
you use this so this what I'm saying so
like I hope you kind of wanted to teach
us and show this and have you guys use
this but like I it's unclear whether
that you know this is actually like you
could you actually use it today safely
on on in a modern modern intel cpus i I
don't know if AMD has has similar issues
so everything I already said like the
the way it works is that you keep track
of every writes that oh the readwrite
set has to fit in your l1 cache so you
can't use this for you hug me buddy uses
for like you know to replace the
transactional stuff that we talked about
for concurrent ritual right because a
lot of times your transaction and
rewrite set when we large with an l1 and
certainly if you have multiple threads
running at the same time you'd be
thrashing out one and you would have
problems to this so the reason why we
might want to use this also too is like
the this is not just for performance
this is also useful from a software
engineering standpoint because now
instead of doing all the latching and
crabbing stuff that we talked before you
could use this as an alternative and
maybe getting the same performance of
having software manage latches or
software manage transactions with lower
engineering overhead that's purely
conjecture I don't know what the fact
that's actually true but that's sort of
been what the proponents of this of this
technique have argued so let's see how
you would actually want to use this so
with how transactional memory there's
two programming models that you can use
the first is called hover lock elysian
and the way this works is that start my
transaction and anytime I do a write
during my transaction I don't actually
do it I just you know sort of like to do
a Jedi mind trick I sort of tricked
myself thinking the night that I did do
it and what happen is like so too if I
write to a memory location it's hanging
out my private workspace if I the
threads try to read leave that memory
location they won't see my right and
then when I go to do a commit the the
harbor will check to see whether there's
a conflict with other transactions or
other threads if there wasn't then I can
go ahead and apply my changes from the
private workspace into sort of a global
memory if there was a conflict then the
the harbor will roll back roll me back
to the starting point of my transaction
almost like a strawberry teacher you
roll back to its beginning and then re
execute it but now when the exit of the
second time I'm actually gonna take
explicit locks to protect the memory
regions that I'm writing to them and so
that way I mean you know I'm guaranteed
that I can run with that without
conflicts so it's like again it's
optimistic first and then if I get it if
if my if I conflict with somebody else
then it gets restarted with pessimistic
locking the other more complicated
approach is use rtmp restricted
transaction memory and with this one
it's like the hardware lock elysian
where I'm gonna run the first time
without taking locks but then if there's
a conflict instead of going back and
running the transaction again with the
taking explicit locks you can you
provide it with a pointer to another
location in the code to jump to that
will do something different than this
the regular code so you still abort the
transaction and you roll it back but you
don't jump back to the starting point of
the transaction and run it again you
jump to some other memory location for
the program that can do something
slightly different so this requires more
engineering effort on their own outside
as the data system developer to be
mindful that we're jumping to another
location and you know and have sort of a
an alternative implementation of the
critical section that we're trying to
protect
so let's look an example how we could
use it so say that we want to do we have
a B plus tree and we learn when you want
to insert into key twenty five so if
we're just doing the latch crabbing that
we talked about before the optimistic
latch crabbing I would take real a ch's
until I get down to here and recognize
that this is the thing I want to modify
so I take a right latch or a that's an X
for exclusive which should be it right
and then when I have that and go ahead
and plan my change but now if I'm doing
this with Howard transactional memory my
program would look like this I would
have the boundary from where my
transaction starts and when I when I
commit and for this critical section
here this is just the crabbing portion
where I'm traversing down into the
traversing down into the tree till I get
to this F node and then you take the
exclusive latch only on me or the right
latch on F so from the outside it looks
like that I've magically made it through
down here transactionally and this would
automatically detect whether if somebody
else took a latch at the same time I
would and so from the outside it looks
like that I magically warp down here I
took the correct latches all the way so
I'm guaranteeing the the integrity of
the data structure in terms of what were
their pointers the the pointers are
pointing to but I didn't have that I
didn't have to have to you know actually
apply these rights to you know to in
memory all that got alighted and I get
jump down here and get it and do and get
exactly what I want okay so to finish up
the as I said we spend most the time
talking today talk about persistent
memory because it is my opinion that is
out now and that when it becomes more
widespread that this is going to be a
major change and how we build software
and especially database systems like I
could foresee that if persistent memory
takes off as much as I think it should
and will then it may be the case that we
don't you know in the introduction Davis
class we don't spend time talking about
things like buffer pools and
you know how to do right in logging with
with scrunch why you know maximizing
cement rely on kids like that think you
know now memory is just persistent and I
got right to it I make sure I flush it I
have to order my rights a little bit but
like I don't have to do all that page
latching and all the crap we did in the
introduction class so it's my conjecture
also as I said earlier that I think the
in-memory databases are in a better
position to take advantage of persistent
memory because they're already written
to assume that they're they can talk to
byte addressable memory and and not deal
with pages so I think that the
conversion from a dram or in memory
system to a persistent memory system
will be lower for in-memory databases I
also think that the you know GPU has
been around for a while FPGA has been
around for a while but you know like I
said there's not most databases are not
database systems are not being written
assuming you have that hardware it's
still in my opinion it's a niche you
know niche market the what could happen
though is that beyond GPUs and FPGAs you
may start seeing additional
computational devices like configure our
special accelerators something that
looks like a TPU or you know some kind
of custom ASIC that could make a bit you
know big difference in the performance
of databases the only thing that would
have to have to overlap pretty heavily
with the potential machine learning or
data science the applications more than
just you know doing sequential scans
which data science machine learning do
do a lot of but there's a way for data
set to take advantage of them I think
that would be interesting as a sort of
also another side to eye
I think matrix databases will have could
potentially become more important in the
next decade and in that case you know
the some of the accelerators that out
there that are doing computational or
machine learning on matrices you know
those databases get to easily take
advantage of those things but the core
that the point thing that was like the
core ideas of the things that we talked
about this semester and certainly many
of the algorithms would still be the
same
quanto scans the sequential scan
right evaluating a predicate you know
coding that or you know traversing the
tree that is all pretty much still gonna
be the same and so we do see how to
think about how we taking the knowledge
we know about how to bit a bit did his
some way to be talked about in this
class and apply it to this new hardware
and so I think you have the background
to do this now ok so this is the last
lecture on Wednesday we're having again
the guest speaker from Amazon but that
we closed off to only CMU students so if
you're watching this from outside of CMU
I hope you're safe I hope everything is
doing okay and you know hope you're
watching this
well after we passed the the pandemic if
you made it through the entire semester
watching the YouTube videos that
congrats so what what should you be able
to do now well after going through 25 26
lectures you should now be able to
understand and comprehend and reason
about the major topics that we talked
about and on how to build a modern
single node database panel system and
I'm qualifying when I'm saying my single
node because going distributed brings up
a whole other bunch of issues with
networking and distributed transactions
that we haven't talked about but at a
high level there there are many of the
same issues that we talked about here
where we care about placement we care
about partitioning we care about drawing
algorithms we care about transactions
all in that environment it's just the
the communication is slower and more
unreliable so we have to we have to
account for that I also hope that you
now have the reason about the ability of
a foundation to know reason about the
claims that people make about their
database management systems
and you'll be able to figure out what
those claims are real or whether they're
actually implausible or whether it's
just a bunch of marketing hype because
databases the Davis market is a lot of
money there's a lot of startups there's
a lot of big companies who want to make
money and sometimes they'll say things
that you know unless you're sort of
paying attention go that seems kind of
cool but if you now using the the the
knowledge of game right is going to this
course now should be able to like look
at this
is this real or not right so I don't
mean to pick on these guys but let me
give one example that came out last week
so there's this new startup called
terminus DB and they posted on Hacker
News hey we've come out we're around you
know this is what we do so it's a graph
database and so they're comparing
themselves against a bunch of other
other systems in the same space and they
had this little blip here though what
that talks about their features that
they do they do AI cogeneration and
rightfully so you see this and like what
does that mean and sure enough somebody
posted on Hacker News saying hey look AI
cogeneration what's that what are you
actually claiming and then these are
some of their some of the developers
like oh yeah this is this is incorrect
this is marketing gone wrong so if
you're just a casual person looking this
and go okay I cogeneration well that
sounds kind of cool what could that be
but for you guys who have lost at this
course you know what cogeneration is you
know there's no AI aspect really to it
because you're taking a query plan that
the optimizer spits out that you know
it's only we're gonna have one way to
execute it in terms of how you're gonna
generate the code for it and so there's
nothing AI to this so again this is sort
of something I'm hoping you guys can now
do on your own see things that people
are saying and use your background you
gotten from this course to decide
whether whether they're saying things
that are plausible okay so again next
class we'll have a guest speaker from
Amazon and then for everyone else
take care Bank it in the side park what
is this some fools say yo
[Music]
especially when they're called the Hokey
cuz I'm og Ice Cube down with the testy
hi you look and it was go grab me a 40
just to get my buzz song cuz I needed
just a little more kick like a fish
after just one slipped up to my lips and
just say nice and my hood won't be to
say I've diced you take a say I said a
prayer