[Music]
[Applause]
we're starting all right today we're
starting with networking protocols so
we're at the point in the semester where
I now want to do like a high-level
overview of what we've talked about and
what we plan on talking about it's kind
of difficult to show this at the very
beginning because the topics we talked
about we're a bit scattered let's
Kearney tall with indexes it's it's some
storage stuff but this is sort of
conceptual illustration of what the
system that were sort of envisioning in
our mind that we're talking about
discussing the various topics that how
to build what it looks like so this is
our application they send a sequel query
this is gonna land in our networking
layer and this what we're going to talk
about today then we hit the query
optimizer or the planner so the reports
the sequel bind to the catalog objects
do any rewriting we want to do and then
run it through our query optimizer to
generate a physical plan then we're
gonna pass now this through a compiler
which won't make sense now but we'll
talk about this in a few weeks basically
we're gonna take of that physical plan
and convert it into machine code instead
of actually interpreting it then we have
our execution engine where actually
we'll execute the query in threads and
then we have a storage meander down
below so this one we've already talked
about a bunch of stuff already this one
we already talked a bunch of stuff
already so these are the sort of the
parts we've already covered we've
covered how to do convergent role
indexes Gorge models and logging
checkpoints so now again today we're
going back to the top and then going
forward we'll sort of jump around and
start here and then work our way back up
this part though like for opera
execution we'll cover this all basically
throughout the rest of the semester like
we'll talk about how to do parallel or
vectorize hash joins vectorize sorting
and the nvcc stuff sort of covers all of
this like at least up to the planner
like in the back of your mind to think
about oh I'm working on multi Verte on
multi version database what are the
implications of that as I design my
system alright so this is sort of out
for the rest of the semester and then at
the very end the last two lectures would
be like the potpourri things we have a
new hardware or doing applying machine
learning method
to the stack okay so as I said today
we're gonna talk about the networking
protocol and this is either the data
coming into the database from the client
or how we send data out to our replicas
for high availability but the paper how
do you guys read was all about ingesting
Gator and taking queries in and getting
data out so let's talk about basically
how you would write in your application
the different methods for accessing the
database and running queries then we'll
talk about what the actual never wider
protocol looks like that you're sending
back responses over the network
then we'll briefly talk about the
different replication protocols that are
out there what are the sort of setup you
can have and then we'll finish up with
sort of a two different techniques to
bypass the operating system as much as
possible called kernel bypass methods so
for all these consumer going over the TC
IP stack and for simplicity we're just
assume we're going through the OS this
is a way to work around that and then
we'll finish off briefly talking about
what's expected for a project - okay all
right
so up until now all the demos that I've
given in class about you know using
Postgres or interruption class we showed
my sequel we showed Oracle all of those
were opening up the terminal over SSH
me typing in some queries hitting Enter
and then getting back a text response so
in a real application that's not how it
actually works because what I'm getting
back is showing the terminal is is like
is text it's it's characters and so if I
was writing an application where I would
go through the terminal like that I
basically have to now parse the text
field extract out what the values I'm
looking for and convert them to the
right type of my avocation and that
would be super slow and nobody would
actually ever do that right so what
we're really gonna do in a real program
is that we're gonna have a an API that a
programming interface that we can then
write queries against on our database
and then what we're exposed to in our
application is is binary values for the
most part if it's you for getting back
JSON then not always but like in real
applications or if you really cut out
performance then you want to get binary
dated back to application
then you don't have to do any of that
conversion yourself in your application
like oh I know I'm looking at an integer
but I have a string representation of
that integer let me now convert it to to
an end
so all these the API is the way to get
best performances to go through certain
standard programming interfaces so well
first talk about direct access these are
going to be a papaya type api's or
libraries that each database vendor
could provide and then we'll talk about
ways to actually now have a more generic
or generalized access methods or api's
that potentially would not have the
requires to rewrite our application to
use if we switch woman one day to this
vendor to another we may have to change
the sequel query dialect but if we
program against these things then this
will be standardized okay where was I
started right again the idea of these
guys is that if I read my application
using either ODBC or JDBC then if I'm
using my sequel today that I side to
give IBM money and I'll switch to my
application over at db2 I don't have to
rewrite any my application code because
these things are the API for that you
would use for my sequel and and and db2
would be standardized on these things I
can sequel my head change but like the
actual code itself won't change so the
actually just go back real quickly this
one we're not gonna talk about too much
there's nothing for there to say about
this other than like okay like everybody
has their own thing and ideally should
not programming us these api's right you
should always have either like a some
kind of one of these things in front of
it so that so that you make your thing
more portable and some applications like
if you know you're gonna be running on a
phone you're only gonna be you know
executing a sequel light you could
program it that way but even then like
Apple or Android or provide you with a
database wrapper or API that hides the
fact that you actually using sequel Lite
all right so the first sort of
standardized API for dat sesemann was
called ODBC and this wasn't actually
it's it's not the first exit II that was
implemented like Sybase actually tried
this back in the late 1980s where they
got together with some other database
vendors and some
application programming frameworks and
they took this Sybase api stripped out
all the side basis if ik logic in it and
tried to propose this as a standard API
called DB library that ever can use for
whatever reason that never took off
Microsoft then hooked up with this other
company called Simo technologies and
then they proposed in the early 1990s
this thing called ODBC and pretty much
today
every major database vendor actually
whether your relation or non-relational
is chances out there they're gonna have
a toady BC library like MongoDB has won
even though Hmong enemy doesn't support
sequel it's just you give them longer to
be you know queries and you write mommy
to be queries in their syntax but it
still supports their API so the way it
basically works is OTP they're gonna
follow what's called a device driver
model and the idea is that in the on the
client side the ODBC driver is this is
something that the vendor provides and
underneath the covers they'll have all
the logic that you need to communicate
with the database server over the
proprietary protocol look if I sent a
query request here this request is going
to be specific to my database system and
then when I get back to result it's up
to this driver now to then convert it
into the format that the ODBC API
specifies alright so the parlance we're
going to use with this class is that I'm
going to refer to this part here this is
the part that we care about this is the
wire protocol and again every database
system is going to do something
different
unless you're following what you know
copying with my Segel and Postgres tier
which is very common but this is not
gonna have anything like this doesn't
know anything about ODBC it just knows
that
here are some Seco queries and here's a
result now the ODBC API does have
additional things or it has certain
features that not every database system
is going to be a little support but you
can essentially emulate that through on
the client side in the driver so for
example if your database system doesn't
support cursors so cursor is like if I
run a sequel query instead of getting
back all the results on once I can get a
handle a cursor handle to that result
like an iterator and I'm called get next
get next get next and that'll send a
message over the network to get back the
next query you would do this it's like
if your if your result is huge and you
don't want to ship everything all at
once
so not every database systems supports
cursors so you can fake that through DC
library so you can still call through to
be seen your application and hey give me
a cursor underneath the covers they'll
send the sequel query to get back all
the results but then expose to you like
the iterator API to walk through the
cursor that's sort of nice that you
could you can hide all that complexity
if you don't support everything you need
for ODBC in the driver itself all right
so the other important thing to
understand too is that the the ODBC
standard specifies what the you know a
fixed specifies what the data types are
that you're gonna get when you say like
give me an integer from this you know
from this from this result set and so
it's up for the driver to make sure that
whatever the the ODBC driver API
specifies as a data type that it has to
give that to you in your application so
that way you don't have an unexpected
result and it makes it more portable so
for example if we store every integer as
64 bits for whatever reason and then the
ODBC API says give me a 32-bit integer
when I get back to 64 energy from the
server again that to convert that to 32
bits because that's what the API
specifies
so again that's all trying to hide the
the specifics or the nuances of every
single database system right bite
through this this client or driver model
all right so the other more common one
too is JDBC and the way to think about
this is like ODBC it's not specific to
Windows anymore but it sort of came out
of the environment and so that's sort of
designed for C or C++ applications JDBC
is designed for Java based applications
for applications that are designed to
run on the JVM so this was developed by
sun in 1997 when a few years after they
released the the Java Runtime in the
java language and again the idea was
that they recognized that they wanted
java applications to run in the
enterprise those things enterprise
applications need to talk to relational
databases or sequel databases so you
JDBC was their attempt to standardize an
API for this and again like I said like
you think it'll be C is for C and JDBC
is obviously for Java and so we
to be slightly different though in in
JDBC is that because they're running the
Java Runtime they're not always going to
have a driver written in Java it's more
common now but back in the day not so
much right for for ODBC yes if you
released your driver
if you driver it spot it's going to be
in C right and that would be universal
not so sort of as a way to bridge people
to be able to use JDBC before there were
enough drivers written in Java then they
have a bunch of different levels or
connectivity methods you can use to
communicate with the database system so
the first one is exactly as I was saying
so instead of having the the JDBC driver
communicate directly with the database
system you have a little bridge
middleware sitting in front of it that
converts JDBC commands into ODBC
commands and then ODBC then communicates
to the database system over its
proprietary wire protocol so this is
actually not supported anymore as of
like I think JDK 1.8 but and this is
actually was a pain in the ass to set up
I had to do this four times ten when we
do some testing here it's a nightmare
it was really finicky but like again
this was a stopgap solution in case GBC
didn't have exactly what you wanted for
your particular database system the next
approach is to have the JDBC calls just
invoke the proprietary native API of the
database system right again so sequel
Lite would be the best way to think
about this because Seco lights in a
better database system so it's gonna be
running inside your same process as your
application so you could have the JDBC
driver invoke through J and I to the C
commands to execute queries or open up
cursors or tables on the database system
but I don't think this would work if
you're going over the network this is
only for the bit embedded embedded
databases running on in the same process
the next approach is to have a the JDBC
driver communicate with some other
middleware system that then knows how to
then speak the wire protocol of the of
the database system so it's sort of like
the first one but the idea here is that
the the commands coming out of the of
JDBC are shouldn't generic
for JDBC but then when they land on
those middleware that the dated
assistant would have to provide it then
know how to convert and convert that
into the wire protocol that you expected
right whereas this thing is is sort of
the JDBC is invoking ODBC commands the
last one which I my opinion is the best
one is where the database so that the
the JDBC implementation itself can
invoke or send the packets that you need
for the wire protocol or the database
system so this is not wasn't that common
so much in the early days but it's more
common now like you can download a
Postgres implementation or Postgres JDBC
driver purely written in Java and you
don't need to worry about any of the the
C stuff and this will run the fastest
cuz again you just go natively in Java
over the network to get the packets and
get everything back right so this one
this one I think not actually this one
you sort of see in in other languages
like if you want to have like if you
have some obscure programming like rust
or go aren't secure or obscure but like
in the early days there weren't a lot of
drivers written for for different
databases and go and rust and whatever
language you want to use so you a
stopgap solution would be this thing
would wrap around like ODBC you would
have a go wrapper around the ODBC driver
which is written in C and but that means
again you have to then go out of the
could go runtime into the C program to
send these commands whereas if you have
a native go implementation yeah that's
me way faster because it's less copying
a packets or less copy my buffers so
this this was always gonna be better way
to do this so as I said all of the
database systems are going to implement
their own proprietary wire protocol and
these are as far as I know I don't know
of any other system that doesn't do this
everything is going to go over tcp/ip I
don't know of any database system that
goes over UDP and we tough to do if you
want to support transactions because you
don't know whether your packers are
actually gonna show up and you need to
send back aknowledge mints so for that
reason everyone's going over tcp/ip now
above that they could have additional
confirmation messages in back
but you know to say look did you get
this packet yes I got this packet like
at the application level but of course
TCP is gonna do that for you on the
covers as well so the typically way the
way the clients gonna interact with our
database server is that they're going to
connect to the database system they'll
go through some kind of authentication
process like username passwords Kerberos
can use things like that if most systems
also now support SSL by default so you
go through that process to encrypt the
the the channel then you send over a
query the database has executed that
query sterilizes the results it sends
that back over the wire protocol to the
client and the client can then hand that
off to to the application code so what
we're gonna focus on today and the paper
you had you guys read was focusing on
this problem here how do you actually
sterilize the data and get out of it
because this is actually where the
opportunity for optimization is actually
available or there are things that we
can improve right there's not much we
can do for this there's not much there's
not really much optimization we can do
for this because most sequel queries are
gonna be short rather there's strings we
send over you can then maybe say I run
these as prepared statements or stored
procedures but that's just really
reducing the size of the message most
queries aren't that big there's some
applications I've seen or heard from
people in the wild where like the sequel
query could be like 10 megabytes you see
this like big big corporations where
they have like this eaten internal
dashboards to do like reporting and you
click a bunch of options to like you
know just get all the people from a zip
code or some you know some geographical
region and then you you sort of you
click all the options you want for the
query you click go and then that
converts whatever you clicked on the
dashboard into a sequel query and
sometimes you can have these really long
in clauses like where zip code in and
then you know list of every single zip
code and in that case the sequel where
it can get really big but the only
optimization you really can do for that
it's just you compress it with like
snappy or gzip whatever you want to use
all right so there's not really any
techniques we can do in a database
system to make this go faster so we're
gonna be focus on this one here right so
I say all major Davis systems implement
their own proprietary waterfall protocol
that's not entirely true question good
question so the question is are there
are there any database systems where the
client can actually be somewhat
intelligent and maybe I mean do
compression maybe do some query
rewriting before it sends it to you I
was also gonna think you know she made
me do client-side query caching as well
not really for a couple reasons
the so the example you gave is like can
I do query rewriting I don't know if
anybody does that in the client driver
because like convert you know one equals
want you know two equals one plus one
can I convert that just to be true
because you basically would need to
implement that logic to parse the sequel
statement understand the semantics of
what the where clause is actually doing
on the client side then now you also
need to if you're supporting a bunch of
different programming languages and
you're using having a native drivers for
those things now you got to rewrite all
that in every single language for that
reason nobody I don't think anybody does
that I there is there was a system
called foundation DB which is a
distributed key-value store that Apple
bought it is now open-source snowflake
uses it internal for the metadata but
they only use it as a key value store
when put for pound eight before Apple
bought foundation BB BB what they would
do is they added a sequel glare and all
that would do was in the client they
would convert your sequel statement into
individual get get queries get command
to is send for the key value store so
that's one that's the only tip I can
think of offhand they do this kind of
stuff other things like caching query
results well if you don't know what's in
the database server on the client side
how do you know that like you have the
latest version so you so for this routes
and everyone always goes always go to
the network there I have thought about
this
we haven't pursued it yet but like I
there was some research done up in
Waterloo where like you could provide
hints about like hey I'm sending you
this query but oh by the way I'm gonna
actually these other queries pretty soon
as well but I don't think any that makes
it any commercialism the client drivers
are usually pretty brain-dead there's
like give me this query here's a result
yes what would be an existing protocol
then what's a like a me to use an
existing protocol what do you mean like
like I want like tcp/ip so I think we're
you saying are you when you say existing
protocols do you mean it like at the
lower level in the stack like at tcp/ip
level or do you mean like at the
application level right so - what with
an existing protocol that's tcpip but
that's that's a layer below we're above
and we're in the data server so 221 of
those existing protocols so some eight
my question is what's an existing one
it's a leading question because it's the
next slide okay so right so as I was
saying like all the major database
vendors like Postgres the my sequel the
other big three Oracle db2 sequel server
pretty much everyone implements their
own wire protocol from scratch but where
I thought you were gonna go is that most
of the newer systems however don't do
this and they need to be implemented in
an existing one in particular Postgres
on my sequel right and the benefit of
doing this is that and we do the same
thing in our system of building here is
that now I don't have to worry about
supporting a bunch of different
programming languages for my drivers
right for JDBC and ODBC
I guess if I speak the post s wire
protocol then anybody that comes along
with a you know the the Postgres driver
in rust they can just use that first
ghost driver and communicate in my
database system now these aren't going
to be the best protocols and we can talk
offline to the troubles we've been
having with the Postgres one but if you
think about it if your database startup
or your like your your research project
like AWS do you want to be spending your
time on writing client drivers for every
single programming language in order
people to user your database or can use
piggyback of what's already been done
and a large ecosystem and happy will
just you know use what's already there
so that's why this is actually very very
common so but I will say though
sometimes you'll see in the
documentation that oh we are Postgres
compatible you see in this application
of these different database systems or
Postgres compatible or my sequel
compatible but just because they speak
the wire protocol it doesn't mean
actually truly compatible but they're
not always gonna be an exact drop-in
replacement because there's a bunch of
other stuff that are specific to that
you know Postgres of my sequel that you
may not actually be emulating in your
server or in your new system and
therefore it's not going to work you
know your application code using GBC
ODBC may start sending sequel queries in
a dialect that your server doesn't
support and it's not gonna work
right so this will get you that sort of
it by following their protocol you'll
get the transport to go from the client
to the server correct but then this
query shows up and now what do you do
right it's not going exactly the same
other times - they'll be queries that
like if you don't support the same
catalog structure as post customize
sequel a lot of these like visualization
tools the first thing you do when they
turn them on is that go look in the
catalog sit and figure out what tables
you have what Commons you have but you
don't speak that if you're not formatted
the same way that post goes my sequel
are then that's going to break then
there's other things too were like the
tools may go at the the database server
in sort of a physical level like looking
at files on disk look there's a lot of
extensions and tools or Postgres that
can manipulate the actual files of the
database without actually having to go
through the the database system itself
no no that's going to work because
underneath the coverage your system is
going to be completely different
yes the drivers especially this just
like write a string of sequel into some
function that magically like writes that
over a network into like I saw it and
then like get some result back in some
form in so this question is what are
these drivers actually look like is it
at the bare bones are they just like
here's a sequel string you say go run
this for me and then that goes it gets
converted into the the packets to send
to the Davis system you get a result and
you get back data on some binary form in
the most simplest form yes but he start
doing like prepared statements or
cursors like you can specify like here's
the query template I want to use and
then the first values in second that is
a double like there's the API is
actually kind of big and all that won't
be you know passing everything just
through a sequel string there are ways
to construct queries programmatically
through the API that isn't just hey
here's the sequel string and then the
again the API specifies says you know
when you get back a result and you call
next row the you know when you say you
know for this current row give me the
the third tuple or give me the third
field as an integer it needs to know
that I'm gonna get back a third you
Pittenger not some other thing that your
your your davis administering internally
so like sequel light stores everything
that's varchars to meet the covers and
it's only when it gets exposed outside
the database system then it gets
converted to the correct binary form so
the driver have to handle that yes front
row yes sequel or sequel server sure all
right so that's that's the
implementation yes
what does the different client-side
caching and server-side caching question
is is I made a comment about the
client-side caching versus server-side
caching server side query result caching
would be I I sent a sequel query it does
some some complex calculation I send
back the result to the client but then I
also remember that I actually that VAT
sequel query with the result
so now someone comes along execute the
same sequel query I don't have to
recompute it I just get back the same
result so an alternative could be that
the client could do this so the client
says I exited the same sequel query you
know a few seconds ago here's a result
just reuse that the pom is if you if you
care about having the data be fresh and
up-to-date on the client-side I don't
know if somebody else came in and
modified the tables and therefore
invalidated my cache result so you'd
have to think about how do you actually
implement this you could then say like
the client could go to the database
server say hey has the state of this of
this has this cache result been
invalidated yes or no
then if yes then you react security if
no then you just reuse what you've done
I don't think anybody actually does that
though because it's sort of 1x turn it
round trip oh it's a huge quarter can
make a difference absolutely if my query
takes an albacore run and I can cache it
fantastic right so we're not gonna talk
about it this semester it's also another
area that I fully understand myself you
can kind of get this on the database
service side so queries alt caching
isn't always good because it's like core
spring it's like you have their cache
result for the entire sequel query so
like if I say you know if the giant
select query has has a predicate or say
where name equals Andy my cache that
then your query shows up with your name
I can't reuse any things that I computed
even though maybe one piece has change
so a very common thing to do is what's
called materialized views where you can
actually materialize pieces of that
query and so like maybe you Prima
sterilize some expensive join and then
the predicate this comes in and is how
to do a filter on that materialized
query and the high-end servers like
sequel server in particular can know how
to like reuse materialized views across
different queries right but again for
your table you would need an explicit
cache invalidation message and I don't
think anybody actually does that right
alright so yeah so a question is why
would I ever want to have a cursor where
I return one tuple at a time versus like
descending everything all the ones so I
think cursors I think I don't know the
exact details like I think they vary per
system they don't mean it's not just one
quick it'll be one be one packet one
message to get one result they sent a
batch with the question is do I send you
know five million results I sent all 1
million or do I send 10,000 at a time
correct same is if your davis ism
doesn't support support cursors you have
to send one my results yes and then
think about like think about like think
about what a database server would look
like versus what an application server
would look like a database server is
usually going to be running on high-end
software now distributed database the
world is different but like fingers like
you know a big heavy expensive machine
it's kind of a lot of memory fastest the
application servers can be these you
know off-brand ec2 instances they're not
gonna have as much memory so maybe I
don't want to blast it with all 1
million tuples that's sort of a thinking
of it right I don't know I I don't know
what difference it I actually don't know
what difference how different it is to
do two different things right cuz also
to like you could imagine the the way
you implement cursors could be different
too cuz like it could be I execute the
query
I now buffer the result and you call get
next on the cursor I'm miss feeding
through that or I could have it be set
up where I have a pipeline breaker where
I say here's the final result of a query
and called get next get next inside the
execution engine get a bunch of tuples
but one time you've reached my cursor
limit then I hand that back to the
client because maybe they're not gonna
come back and ask for more if they do
come ask for more then I'll just now s
cute the rest of the query could stage
it that way
I think everyone buffers it and then
gives you a handle to the cursor of the
buffer but you could implement it the
other way I think that's how it was
originally envisioned back but this like
the 1980s in the pipeline not the
pipeline model but like the the volcano
model wait is the pipeline it's about
you volcano iterator pipeline model yes
same thing okay so this is just a table
showing what you know what other systems
are actually using the Mexico's wire
protocol I thought they're actually more
system using hive but the only one I
could find that speaks the high wire
protocol is spark so my sequel is very
common a bunch of these though are
hacked up versions of my sequel like mem
sequel in the very beginning actually
wasn't a it was not a full-fledged
database system it was a storage engine
like in ODB or rocks DB that sat
underneath my sequel so they got to my
sequel you know compatibility and wire
protocol for free eventually with all
that out and they wrote everything
themselves because they otherwise you'd
violate the GPL and their proprietary
but so they basically speak the my
sequel protocol now so they are my
secret peddled cluster is based on my
sequel but it had sort of a layer above
that that was distributed so there's a
there's a framework called my sequel
proxy that gives you like a gives you
like a middleware front-end
implementation of the my sequel wire
protocol and a bunch of these other ones
are sort of again speaking the wire
protocol Amazon Aurora is slightly
different
I'll talk about in a second here's a
bunch of these ones that are basement
Postgres so a couple of these are
written from scratch like hyper copy HDD
our old system Umbra these are systems
where like we look the specification of
the purpose wire protocol and read
implemented it just in our system things
like redshift greenplum Vertica
and I think maybe you could bite these
are they the original code they started
with Postgres and they ripped out the
parts they didn't want and then rewrote
it for to do whatever they wanted to do
so they kept that front end piece of
code the networking layer for for
Postgres so the reason why Aurora is
different is because because Amazon
controls the whole stack of like if
you're running in in in in their cloud
center they collude to control the
networking layer excuse you layer and
the storage layer so what they do is
actually super interesting at least from
my sequel I don't know if they do this
for Postgres they actually take out some
of the networking logic for the wire
protocol for my sequel and shove it up
into the Amazon like load balancing
networking layer right so now when you
hit like when your application speaks to
your database instance and running an
Aurora you may not actually be hitting
up the actual Aurora system itself
you're running up and there's networking
there's never a cool there's never pink
layer up above that doesn't load
balancing for you which is really
fascinating and what they can do is they
can switch over sort of transparently
from one instance to another like if say
I'm running on a small machine I'm gonna
upgrade Amazon to a my Aurora instance
or a bigger machine in the networking
layer because it's now decoupled from
the actual database server they can copy
over your session variables from from
you know form all your clients from one
server to the other then it's had the
networking layer switch over to the the
new instance and it looks like you
magically just got more more more you
know more RAM more CPUs without actually
you know closing any of your connections
so that's crazy
I think only Amazon can do that because
it's Amazon right so we take this
offline implementing this has been a
huge pain taxes been awful you talk to
Matt about it this is our third attempt
trying to read them the post goes wire
protocol and it's it's really ugly
because they have two different modes
which is a mess okay all right so let's
talk about the paper you guys read today
for this class so as I said the where we
can have opportunity to get better
performance in it and improve the wire
protocol is when we serialize the data
back to the
client right we can ignore the cursor
stuffed assume that they ran a query and
they want to they want a bunch of
results and the papery how do you guys
read came from the same authors that are
building dub DB or bridge of people are
also working on Monet DB at a CWI and
what they were focused on was doing
these large data exports so not so much
running complex queries and getting back
up
you know aggregated results but I have
my Python or data science application
running some results and I have all my
database my data in my sequel database
how quickly can I get that data out and
put it into my machine learning pipeline
so a lot of things were talked about
today look like all the stores stuff we
talked about before right how to do
compression how to do the row versus
calm stuff because that's essentially
what it is right we have some giant
chunk and data what's the optimal way
that we should organize it to send it
over the wire and it's basically the
same thing we want to store a bunch of
data on disk or in memory what's the
optimal way to do that right so the
other thing I'll say to you also is that
everything we're to talk about here
whatever however we organize the data on
the server side and then send it over to
the client the client has to be able to
interpret that and reverse it so that's
gonna somewhat limit what we can
actually do because we don't want to
burden the client with actually doing a
ton of work now again they're focusing
on doing these bulk exports of the data
but a lot of times the same client
driver you would use in other systems
like the same client driver you would
use for your Android application would
be the same client driver you would use
for whatever your applications are
running on a you know giant xeon box so
now no one's downloading a terabyte of
data to their cell phone that's stupid
right but like it just means that we
need a little support whatever the
optimizations we have apply here for the
data we have to ever be able to reverse
them and to interpret them so that that
means that we can't be too heavy weight
and because we don't want have to
duplicate that that that logic in a
bunch of locations right like again if i
want to support all the different
programming languages and i have native
drivers for each of these program
languages whatever i need to do to
decompress data in one language I got to
do for another one right so sort of like
the lowest common denominator which
which is somewhat limiting but it is
what it is all right so the first thing
is going to be talked about is the row
versus column so the odbc jdbc are
inherently row oriented api's we we're
gonna the servers are always gonna
package up the tuples and results one
tuple at a time and sort of package that
as a single message that sends it gets
sent over the network
now with these stream a bunch of
messages all at once but the way these
these the servers are mostly written is
that it assumes that I'm gonna iterate
on the server side over one tuple at a
time I'll construct a message that says
here's what's actually in this tuple and
I put as many of those messages up I
guess I can to my packet ship that over
and then the client has to reverse that
so back in the 1990s when they first
started building to be seen JDBC this
made sense because it was you you were
either running all three applications
where the result sets are small like go
get Andes account record go get all the
orders that Annie bought from Amazon
that that's not a lot of data and it's
not not a lot of tuples if you're doing
analytics oftentimes would just be you
know computing the the the sales totals
of you know on a quarterly basis and
then you do something aggregations on
that so like the query the query is a
bit more complex and a little to be
decided but the amount of the end you're
getting back is not it's not a lot but
again as I said the duck TB guys are
focused on exposing the database
contents to these modern machine
learning software and in this world we
want things as as columns or matrices so
this row oriented approach is is as
limiting so what they propose to do is
that instead of sending over in a row or
engine format we could actually send it
over as vectors and in particular the
way they're gonna do this is they're
gonna organize a bunch of tuples
together and within a block and then it
within that block they'll be organized
as columns so it's not like I'm gonna
stream over one column at a time in a
bunch of messages and then when I'm done
with that column switch over to the next
next column and do that they're gonna
say here's a bunch of tuples convert it
as a as a
I'm store within that block and then
ship that block over and then for the
next batch of tuples on the server side
you do the same thing so we didn't talk
about this exactly when we we talk about
stores layouts but this is called the
packs model
I was actually invented not here at CMU
but by a professor who used to be here
at CMU and now she's at EPFL and this is
actually what we do in our day to be
system now we organize our data as one
megabyte blocks and then within that
block we have all the attributes or
fields for a single tuple but each of
those fields will be organized as a
column store because we follow what we
follow the arrow does and this is used
in park' agent or yes the question is is
is sorry is is this approach to
effective or ODBC so again he doesn't
know about any of us he doesn't know
that I got a batch of two blows back and
their own as as columns it just because
they now the programming interface is
that is definitely row oriented right I
get a cursor a call get next and then I
do whatever need to do on that on that
single column or that single tuple I
can't tell it would we see gave me the
vector of a to give me the vector of
column vector of values for a single
column across all tuples so I think what
the proposing here is that you could
you'd have to rewrite or have your own
API at the application server level
application side API to support getting
these vectors I actually don't know
whether I don't know whether it would be
C as a way to say give me my results
that and just dump it out all at once I
all the code I've written using G a B C
or D C has always been like you know a
while can't get next okay so the benefit
we're gonna get from this is that if we
have everything as as a column store
then we apply all the techniques that we
talked about last week of compressing
our data because we know all the values
are going to be within the same domain
and we're gonna get a better compression
ratio so it's the same thing that we
talked about before right we can do the
naive compression approach where we just
take take
our bites that we have in our block that
we're sending over and we just run gzip
on it or snappy send that over to the
why the wire and the climb didn't just
just calls the same you know using the
same correction algorithm to decompress
it the other approach to do the column
not specific encoding like our le or the
dictionary encoding or the Delta
encoding as far as I know no system
actually does this this does show up in
in some systems like my secret weapon
use gzip of all things took a press data
so as they talked about in the paper
this is obviously you're gonna get a
better compression ratio if you have the
more data you have and what's also nice
about too for larger blocks this is
actually gonna work even better
and they say that this is the better way
to do this because the the approach is
agnostic to what the actual data is so
there's no logic on the client server
side to say oh I'm looking at this
column and it's dealt on coding so I
need to now basically replay the Delta
to give me back the original values if
I'm just using snappy I just take my
byte stream or byte array and just run
it through that and I get everything out
but I want the other thing they tell us
to talk about in the paper is that if
the network is slow then a more
heavyweight algorithm like gzip will be
preferable over something like snappy
because you're paying you know you're
paying a higher CPU overhead cost to get
to get a better compression ratio and
that's usually going to be a good
trade-off again this what is it sound
like it sounds like a disc right it's
which it is it's essentially a slow
piece of hardware that we need to get
data through like a straw from one side
to the other so again if we know it's
gonna be slow we're gonna have low
bandwidth then we want to do as much
work we can on the on the on the the
ingestion and reading of the data to
minimize that overhead so for this
reason they claimed that this is better
and like I said nobody I don't know of
any system that does this now we get in
the question of how we're actually going
to represent the data or how are you
going to serialize it so the first
approach is to do binary encoding where
again it's just like as we talked about
when we took like alignment and and
layout we would represent the data in
its binary form and that's typically
native to whatever like C or super ball
so what the hard it gives us if we're
following the the I Triple E 754
standard so what will happen is the
client-side I'll be responsible for
handing any ns because the server
doesn't know what you actually want so
the server will send it out in you know
in one in DNS and the client says oh
well I was told I you know the servers
running x86 and therefore he gave me
little endian but at mine running on my
cell phone I need big-endian to the
clients responsible for reversing that
but that's not too expensive
other than this happen having to copy
data the other thing that's be important
too is that if we can have whatever the
format is that the data system uses to
store data right in the actual columns
itself where the rows themselves if our
wire protocol can match this what we're
actually storing then it's gonna be
super cheap or have low overhead for us
to go take data out from a result of a
query and then put that into a packet so
send that over the wire so what I mean
that if using my our old system as an
example and our old system we built our
execution engine and Storage Manager
separately and then we sort of grafted
it onto Postgres and then when we
actually want to go put the the results
of queries into a packet and send it
over the process wire protocol how it
represented strings was different than
how we represented strings so we would
then have to convert it right and
basically it means copying the data you
know into our original format and copied
it into into and converted to post
business format so that extra copying
starts to add up because if you're doing
this for every single query and every
single tuple and every and every single
result then that you're spending all
your time to do in copying and
serializing deserializing
sucks right I mean with peloton we had
another mistake like we had like three
copies of updated just to get over the
wire protocol two of them you needed one
of them was was was was superfluous but
it probably reason why we killed that
system the other thing you can do too is
instead of implementing your own you
know binary format for sending over the
messages that you represent in getting
messages you actually can rely on these
serial serialization open source
stabilization formats that are out there
two most famous ones are Google's
protocol buffers or Facebook thrift
right think about this as you define in
a DSL what a packet looks like what the
types are and so forth and then they
have a way to then to compile and
generate you code that you can then use
to build struck sand fill out these
these buffers and then they'll sterilize
it for you so that you can send over the
network I don't know of any system that
actually does uses protocol buffers or
flatbuffers is the new version of
protocol buffers I think it's zero
copying so it's faster hed uses thrift
thrift brings you a bunch of other stuff
like RPC you know and like other
networking communication protocol stuff
which is more than maybe you actually
want but faith hive is the only one that
know that uses this so I would not
recommend these things because these are
actually gonna be a bit verbose right
like they would have to record all this
extra metadata to tell you what the type
actually of the data actually storing in
our networking protocol if we if we if
we do it ourselves
maybe just in the header of the packets
we send over to say hey we're about to
send you a bunch of tuples that have
these types here they are rather than
these things I think they have to they
make multiple copies of that metadata
right for every single message so for
this reason I I don't recommend that
this you want to you want to roll your
own all right the image so in addition
your the metadata about what my types
are we got to keep track of like how do
we actually represent nulls the sizes
are our data right all that gets gets
expensive and some systems do it better
than others the alternate is that the
server just sends over all your data as
plain text right and so the advantage of
this is that you don't have to worry
about in these Indian Asst it's up to
now the clients responsibility to figure
out how to actually interpret what what
it is it you're actually looking at
right so yeah think of it this way so
say I have my server side I my my query
result has one was as one two boy has
one attribute the number of one two
three four five six so there's a 32-bit
integer I can represent in four bytes so
if I send this over in binary form
just say hey I have a four byte integer
on alternative could be I could convert
one two three four five six into the
string of characters one two three four
five six and send that over now in that
case assuming I'm asking in coded I need
one byte for every single character I
have six numbers so I need six bytes for
those but then depending on how I'm
representing either the length or say
help you know how long the thing
actually is I would need an extra byte
potentially to say here's a null
terminator or here's the length of the
string and then now on the client side
is called a 2 I if you're using C to
convert this string into the correct
form that we can then hand off to ODBC
or JDBC so this seems kind of crazy why
would actually one ever want to do this
you see it as in systems that support
essentially JSON types or JSON result
sets as like the output of a query Monay
DB we're seeing a second actually
supports this as well I forget why I
think it's just for historical reasons
they did this but as we'll see in the
results you know storing in the binary
format is the better way to do this
always okay all right all right the last
time you got talked about is how we
actually handle strings and I sort of
mentioned this just now so the three
approaches again the same thing but
actually we want to do in our database
system do we just do the standard C way
and have a null byte at the end of the
string to denote the end of the string
so now if I'm parsing the packet that
I'm getting over the network
as soon as I see this is no Terminator
character I know that that this is the
end of the string and then the manage of
this is I use all my clients I can use
all the sturby standard C API
strings string functions because they
know how to operate on strings with
multimeters the other approach is in how
we do this
natively in our database system where we
just add the length of the string to the
beginning of the pipes of the string so
we know the client knows how far needs
to jump ahead to find everything you
need the last one would be like a char
field instead of a varchar' where you
just use you have a fixed size the bytes
that you use just represent every every
string for every tuple well for every
attribute of a tuple you have a fixed
size
and then you just Pat out whatever the
value is for each individual to pool to
fill out the rest of the the rest of
that size the rest of that that that
allocated space so this seems kind of
also wasteful as well but like if most
of my strings are say you know assessed
by my chart field to be 16 16 characters
and most my strings are eight characters
or nine characters I'm a bunch of zeros
and if I'm using gzip or snappy that's a
good opportunity for get good
compression because you can see repeated
byte sequences over and over again I
think though in the in the paper they
discussed that this only really makes
sense think it's the best performance if
like all your streams are like one
character right and then the paper also
talks about how sometimes this is faster
or sometimes this is faster right it
just depends on what your strengths look
like and as far as they know no system
is actually gonna implement both you
just pick one and stick with it
because it'd be too much engineering
overhead both on the server side and the
client side to have missed support both
of these right the other thing to point
point out too as well is that the
performance are gonna get depending on
how you represent strings is not going
to be it's not in a you know independent
of just what the approach you're using
if I'm doing compression then sometimes
this would be really good and the other
ones could be bad so again there's a
multiplicative effect of based on how
we're designing all and what compression
scheme we're going to use and what the
put the we're doing Road services
counselor all these things combined will
you know affect what the performance is
gonna be all right so let's just show
two quick quick graphs so they did two
experiments on the paper the first one
is we're gonna go measure the time it
takes to send one tuple and time it
takes to send a million tuples and so
they're gonna compare against my sequel
both width without gzip and enabled own
a DVD Oracle MongoDB db2 and hive so
again although MongoDB doesn't support
sequel
they still support an OTP ODBC driver so
this works so what you see is going
across is that hive is actually can do
the worst here followed by db2 but then
these other ones here are roughly all
about the same
what's in the
though is that Moni to be is the only
one of these ones doing text encoding
where everything else is doing binary
encoding and it still outperforms the
other ones that doing binary encoding
has a case of of dB - I don't know why
this is slow we'll see in the next slide
it's more pronounced but at least his
oracle and db2 they have their own
confirmation message that the client
sends to the server and say hey i got
what you just sent me send me more and
think that's sort of redundant over top
of TCP tcp but you know maybes from a
day where you in one of that kind of
extra extra security right extra safe
teenis and then hive I said just sending
way more data so for this one again
this is only one tuple at a time so the
way to avoid all the overhead of like
parsing the sequel statement and and
running him the optimizer and running
the query they're gonna run the query
multiple times and then had the
babysittin cache at least the query plan
not that was all belief the query plan
so this is just saying what's the
overhead of constructing the packet that
we sent over the wire protocol in the
next experiment they're gonna then send
back a million tuples and so the first
two results to point out though is with
my sequel so this is my so this is when
the the along the x-axis we're gonna
vary the latency of these Network
messages so when your network is really
fast up into this point here the regular
my sequel protocol without any
compression is is gonna be better but
once obviously the network gets slower
then you know doing that extra CPU work
to compress the data actually pays off
in this case here my secret with
compression it always gets the same
performance because the dominant cost
here is it's calling gzip for all the
other ones in the the curves look all
about the same right obviously when
they're faster when the network is
faster they do better but it hasn't
network gets slower they do worse which
engine you point out though over here is
that Oracle is is the second fastest one
after my sequel here when the network is
fast but then up here it actually ends
up being one of the slowest ones I don't
remember what the paper said that why
this was the case I mean db2 here is an
order magnitude off of like propose
graphs right the db2 is like doing like
five
is that 500 up there and Oracle or so
postcards right below it is around 1050
seconds so that's just an example of
like how that confirmation message that
they're sending over is super
inefficient with a network of slow they
can't send the next batch of tuples to
the client until you get that second
round trip and say hey send me warm
alright so any questions about this yes
sorry this like this one here why is
this faster than this because I'm
standing back a million two bullets and
I'm gonna think exact size of that but
like when the networks really fast I
don't want to pay the penalty to
compress it I just want to shove it over
the wire as fast as possible and this
one here the dominant cost is the CPU
overhead of compressing and
decompressing so that's why again it's
basically flatline so no matter how slow
they never get gets the benefit you're
getting from sending less data over a
slower Network is negated by the
computational cost miss now they could
have used snappy and that might that
might change the curves a bit but it
basically this is basically saying and
why I highlighted this one first is that
when the network is fast you don't want
to do any compression these ones shove
data out fast as possible but as they
never get slower you do want to do this
soon a say alright well in what case
would the network get be the hunter
milliseconds well if I'm running in
different data centers the application
servers running one data center the data
servers running another one then you
know I can get up to hundred millisecond
latency yes
your statement is should they be
shouldn't they be varying the bandwidth
and not the latency because I'm gonna
related it to each other but I think
like the like in the case of like db2
like sending those confirmation messages
that's not a bandwidth issue that's a
week yeah you statement is that let's
take this offline but good cuz I don't
know exactly like I remember the exact
setup was in terms of like I think the
the client has to get the result and
immediately throw it away but in this
case here the client so that the cost of
decompressing on the client side is
being measured in this as well
so I think that's why the leave the you
can't hide it I think that's why the
latency matters wait a min bandwidth but
that one offline okay we have 20 minutes
um I'm actually gonna skip replication
protocols I think we covered this in the
we basically covered this in the intro
class already the only got to say too is
like that the sort of relating to what
we talked about last class with like
logging and recovery sometimes you do
logical logging sometimes you do
physical logging right and that's an
internal protocol that the data system
uses that's can be separate than the
client protocol you would use to
communicate with it to be seen a JDBC
and some of the optimizations you can do
again for doing compression and other
things or how you batch up the the log
records depends on what the consistency
guarantees you want for your your your
your systems so that one will
there's not much more to say other than
other than that but when you tell me
that offline if you want as well all
right so just to finish up real quick
because this is something I think I do
won't expose you guys to um
the in the experiments with with with
from the the duck TV guys paper like as
it was showing like their merit their
varying the network latency but that's
not the only bottleneck you're gonna
have their network layer itself is not
the only bottom like you're gonna have
in your in your app and your database
server to communicate with the client
oftentimes the the OS is gonna cause
problems especially if you're doing oak
tree applications where you're sending a
lot of small packets instead of you know
giant giant buffers of things the reason
why it could be expensive is because
communicating with the OS is always
gonna be a nightmare for us as the data
system right it's our frenemy we need it
to survive but it always gets in our way
so if we were gonna lie on the OS TCP
excuse me tcp/ip stack then we have to
have context switches handle through
inner area through interrupts in order
to get you know to be notified that we
have now a packet that we want to get
copying data out from our buffers and
the database server down into the tcp/ip
buffers that we send into the kernel
that's to me expensive and of course the
OS is gonna maintain its own latches to
protect its internal data structures and
those are gonna get in our way if we
have a lot of threads trying to write to
date at the same time so one way to
avoid all this is to what's called it
kernel bypass methods the idea here is
that we're gonna have the database
system we're gonna implement it so that
we're gonna be able to write data
directly to the NIC to the actual you
know the harbor the network device by
going around the OS right and so the
idea is that we can now have a buffer of
data that we can fill in with with the
results of a query or the packets we
want to send over using our wire
protocol but that buffer actually now
lives down in the NIC so we don't have
to do any copying to tan it off to the
hardware the harbor can get fill up a
buffer and we say all right we're done
with it and then now we can meet Lee go
over the wire and send over our messages
so the OS doesn't get in the way at all
so there's two ways to do this there's
the the data plane development kit and
the DP DK and then there's through
through our DMA or remote direct memory
access so they're not exactly it's not
true apples to apples can
Harrison because like the DB DK is a
library you can download originally from
Intel that provides this kernel bypass
method our DMA is sort of a category of
hardware and software libraries that you
can get for your system so there's a
bunch of because there's a specific
thing you can download called the DB DK
but that is a library there's no like
single library called already may you
can download it's a broader contact ok
so with the DVD K the idea here is that
it's it's just live where the Intel
originally developed in order to help
them sell their Intel's hardware but
they eventually donated the software to
the Linux Foundation and the idea here
is that it's a bunch of libraries that
are API calls that allows us to access
the NIC directly we can say give us a
buffer that's on the NIC we can then
fill it up and then we can then tell the
the NIC to go ahead and write write our
data to this location so ron was
treating like the the nick is like a
bare metal device yes this question
where's the buffer actually live I
actually don't know I mean the NIC has
its own memory buffer I I think you can
I think when you say give me a 2d PK
when you get a buffer for it I mean when
you Josh - you're right I think it lives
in the CPU cache because it has to
because that's when you write everything
but then when it gets flushed it does
get flushed 2d Ram it gets flushed to
the neck I think that's how it works
like does the NIC nice question oh yeah
so if i if i'm if my process is writing
to this the cache lines that are backed
by the NIC if I get a context which does
that then get flushed I think so yes
like the OS the OS doesn't control any
of this data movement it's it's the
harbor's actually providing this
functionality for us right and Intel and
they're in their world they're trying to
sell hardware so that they're making it
easier for you to write to their
hardware I for the DVD K I don't mean
until you know it came out of Intel but
now it's opposed to be this there's this
broader thing that other vendors can
implement I don't know whether you can
get this with other anything else that's
not our Intel Nick
so again there's no data copying because
we can write them into the buffers that
are on the neck and there's no system
calls to send any messages we're
basically going directly from our
database over to the harbor and saying
send our messages to this location OS
doesn't get involved at all it's awesome
so for as amazing as this sounds there's
only one database system that I'm aware
of that actually uses this and it's
called Scalia D beam so they implemented
this framework called C star which is a
networking framework that uses the DB D
K and then Scalia DB is built on top of
it
Scalia DB is a steep applause free
implementation of Cassandra Cassandra is
really visually written in Java this is
really now written in C++ and using DB
DK to get faster messages right so
amazing as it sounds as I said this is
not that common if you you can get
instances on ec2 that do support the DB
DK but it's not like you know the the
cheapo ones that we were running on this
class they don't support this the other
tricky thing too is like this sounds
amazing and it's constitutive but
someone tweeted at me once about the by
using SPD k is the storage one this is
the data one like this comment I think
it's fantastic like it seems like it's
gonna be a really good idea but then
when you really start pushing it then
it's all these nuances of it that trip
you up all right it's not something you
can just like pop in like link in a
library and you automatically get it you
have to rewrite your database server
application or database server to use
this right and that could be a major
change change in case of Scalia TB
they're built top of C star so all the
employee the complexities of the DVD K
are hidden under covers so for this
reason as I said like because your
server
I don't not many David subsection use
this the other one is the RDMA and the
idea here is that the if I have multiple
machines I can have the I can have the
client or the server write and read and
write the memory location of that remote
machine so the way you think about this
is like if my application server if my
client driver for my database server
room
new of the memory layout of the of the
data and on the database server then
instead of sending now siegel query to
go have that be parsed executed and and
then presented results that I could if I
know how the data's laid out I could
just read directly into memory and get
the date get the result I want back
that's actually super hard right because
now if I start moving them around and
everything everything is gonna get
messed up so the only two systems that
I'm aware of that actually use our DMA
the most famous one is Oracle RAC right
or it's basically you know a
multi-million dollar cabinet of high-end
servers that use already May just to
talk to each other within the rack right
in that case all okhla has designed this
system specifically do to do shared
memory buffers using our DMA farm is a
distributed transactional system at a
Microsoft Research I don't think it's
actually running production but the
tricky thing about our DMA is like you
don't know whether someone's accessing
your memory or you know or writing your
memory right because it's all handled
through the hardware it's all hidden
from you it from the OS so it's not like
I get interrupt to say oh someone wrote
to memory at this location I don't know
so in order to do transactions correctly
and farm when you have we know one
server running into a memory or another
server they basically have to do four
phase commit over our DMA which is
faster but it's four phase commit to be
it'll say all right I've made these
changes are you okay with that right so
again for this reason you won't think
you would you only use our DMA
internally to communicate between
servers of the same database instance I
don't know no I
there's been no work as far as I know of
about doing our DMA from the client to
the through the server because if memory
gets moved around it then then you're
screwed so I want you one quick raffled
s so this is an experiment that a former
student of mine did on the honor system
where we just want to see how how fast
we can get seven gigabytes of tuples out
of our TPC from TPC see the
the protocol is that the client is
actually reading into memory it knows
where the layout starting and starting
and stopping justice for all the blocks
of data that it wants to read it's sort
of how fast can we get everything out so
that's a low end you have if you have
post graphs where you actually iterating
and going through the post plus quite a
protocol if you then do what the duck DB
guy supposed in the paper you read about
vectorizing the Polacks you send back
you can do a little bit better aero
flight is a G RPC implementation or RPC
implementation of getting roll plots of
data out from the Aero guys but the RTA
is like the bare-bones like if I know
exactly the memory address that I want
and I can jump to that location on the
row machine and get all the data back I
need so this shows you again your your
you can get about an order magnitude
performance improvement if you don't
worry about going through any of that
sort of any other davis server software
okay
alright so this is a bit rushed at the
end but and I've covered most of this
already right so that the network
protocol is is something that we sort of
take advantage of but I think there's a
lot of opportunity for performance
improvements and this is what the duck
TB guys showed the problem is though you
have all these drivers out in the wild
and in some ways now the protocol is
sort of set in stone maybe a major
change to go back and and have everyone
linking new libraries that's never gonna
happen but now if you want to be to
update your protocol and support more
some of these optimizations you you
essentially need to support both because
you never know when a client's going to
show up and connect with the old
protocol the some external breaker told
me that when they were building vertical
one of the things that big things they
spent a lot of time alone because they
want to be Postgres compatible is that
they basically found every single jar
file they could of the Postgres wire
protocol that was out there and just ran
every single test over and over again
and like because there's so many just a
one-off variances although them they
spend a lot of time making it just be
post cut JDBC compatible because it's
super hard and the kernel bypassed
methods we saw again these are the
optimizations to avoid the OS avoid
having go through the front end layer
but it's more it's usually more work
than it's actually worth okay all right
so quickly project two so the plan for
project two is that everyone's going to
implement and the team
your own B+ tree in memory B+ tree it
has to be thread safe the means you have
to support splits and merges and have
multiple threads accessing the index at
the same time so the basic API you're at
the implement is insert get delete ring
and range scans you also have two
conditional inserts in a way that works
is I call insert with the key but I also
pass you a lambda function that says
that you need to evaluate on the key and
if that land up function evaluates to
true then you're allowed to insert
otherwise you can't write that's
basically how you do like I don't think
a parent swap I'd like to to replace a
value at a replace a key value pair
without having to do multiple traversals
or lock the whole thing you need to
support forward reverse range scans that
means you need sibling pointers and you
guys support unique and non unique keys
so that's all we're going to tell you
you have to do delete will be some some
some stuff api's or sub files class
files will give you how you actually
want to implement this is love up to
left up entirely to you right you can't
do something stupid like go take STL map
put a latch in front of it and just have
that you know be your tree it has to be
a real B+ tree but all whatever
optimizations you want to do for like
compression if you want to do make a
latch free or not latch free or how you
actually implement the traversal itself
and and do the search within the node
that's up to entirely to you yes the key
type will be we already pro that provide
that for you
so it's templatized alright so there'll
be there's two types is compacting ski
and generic a generic key is just say a
byte array so you don't the writing the
code to do the evaluation of keys we
handled all that for you and the key
type is you'll know the size of it so
you just you just pack that in to how
you want to sorting each node I thought
what's all that staying car and you're
basically just building the data
structure okay is it already what I said
so we'll provide you with the header
file and the API you have to build and
then all this other crap will do for you
so you don't to worry about how to
sterilize the keys or gonna mount
actually comparisons all that is handled
so as I said there's a bunch of design
decisions you're going to make and
there's no right answer sometimes
they'll be wrong answers like if I know
should I write everything the dev know
no that's wrong but like you don't need
to come and ask us like can I do this
can I do this at every single step it's
up for you guys to decide how you
actually want implement this and I can
point you to you know a couple there's a
book on B plus trees it's not specific
to in Mary P Plus trees but there's a
books and some papers I could show you
like here's some other things you can do
to potentially make this go faster okay
so we'll provide you with a basic C plus
unit test for implementation it's
basically the same unit test we have for
the BW tree and we just did a search in
replace and replace it with P plus tree
right but it's not gonna be that
exhaustive it's certainly not going to
test the internal data structure
correctness or integrity that that you
wanted want to have right it's done at a
logical level like if I insert this key
do I get that key back but how do I know
that my you know that I don't have any
empty nose hanging around right well
trouble check for memory leaks and
things like that but like I you're gonna
want to write your own test that
actually tests at the low level data
structure right because we don't know
how your thing is implemented so we
can't provide you with things we will
also do a will do a leaderboard to see
who has the fastest one it's gonna run
on grey scope which is not ideal because
it's single-threaded but at least we see
how how fast you are compared to that
and then we'll give extra bonus points
for the top three implementations the
other thing you have to do is also write
documentation about what your code is
actually doing and explain what you did
in all the different parts of the system
so for this there is a basic check in
doxygen we use the opportunity to make
sure that you actually have like
comments for every single function but
obviously doxygen you can't read the
comments and see what what you're saying
is actually correct so Matt and I would
go through and inspect all of these
manually so again we will plan is to run
some additional stress tests for for
your your your implementation beyond
what we're gonna give you already and
then it will give you extra points for
whoever is the fastest and didn't make
sure again all your code has to follow
the the formatter and linter stuff one
of the things we did actually do in and
another student actually made the linter
go faster so now you don't think you
know take all the course your machine
and look at every single file the Lynch
are only looks at what to put files you
change so that should run faster as well
okay
I posted this on Piazza last night
everyone it's a group project so be with
35 students there to be three groups or
there are 12 groups or three people and
then one two-person group project
don't assume you will be that two-person
project but we only have one so so
please start finding a form a group and
then on the on the sign up there's that
list for free agents if you don't have a
group to be in add yourself there and
then you know teams can reach out to you
and try to get you to join them okay so
the websites not up yet we'll take care
of that today
I think Matt push the stub files to to
github so you can pull down the latest
version of our new project branch and
then this will be due on on March 15 the
goal is obviously have great scoop up as
soon as possible so you know it's not
like a week or two before the deadline
okay any questions about this alright
this might be fun right it's for you
guys to be a creative and do whatever
you want to do and see who see who has
the fastest one okay alright so next
week we'll start talking about actually
now I start executing queries and this
is where I actually spend a lot of our
time for the rest of the semester we'll
talk a little bit how we're gonna
organize and schedule threads and then
our processing models for queries then
we'll talk about coding compilation but
at this point it's really we're focusing
on now we know that how to index things
and stored things and send things over
the network how do we actually execute
query so that's the whole point of a
database system you want to get sequel
queries and maybe I'll run them in
produce answers okay all right guys
enjoy your weekend see ya Bank it in the
side park
what is this some fools
[Music]
especially with that here called the Oh
it cuz I mochi ice you down with the
testy my you look and it was go grab me
a forty just to get my buzz Oh cuz I
needed just a little more kick to my
lips and blow the truck the same as hot
and my heart wants me to say I've nice
you take a saint I said of pray