Oh guys is restarting
welcome again sorry for being away last
week but I mean in town now so real
quick we'll pause around for my our DJ
DJ drop tables so I don't think people
know how bad you are right so once you
show the people a little bit someone
what you what you can do write letter it
[Laughter]
this is real yes we do have a course DJ
right I've always won one now I have one
how was your summer
good would you out there doing your
thing okay awesome yeah all right what
else is new yeah yeah there's that yeah
I mean so we're still been a database
system here at Carnegie Mellon so we're
still grinding on that that's just
taking all my time right you know it is
yes that is true
I did get somebody pregnant okay so
let's let's go through this real quickly
all right so I only care about two
things in my life I say this every
semester number one is my wife number
two is databases I don't give up
anything else right my family vote for
Trump I don't talk to them I you know I
have the dog that's fine but like I
don't have any other hobbies
it's just databases right and again so
people think I say crazy stuff and
so if I start talking fast I want you to
please interrupt me to slow down right
and just tell me repeat myself
I say you're sounding stupid you're
going too fast slow down
you can also interrupt me when you don't
understand what I'm talking about
and I actually encourage you and I want
you to do this because I know this like
I don't know if you guys knew it so
please stop me if you don't understand
what I'm talk about already have a
server database related question what
you can't stop me about or stupid things
like you have a question up blockchain
like in previous years I don't care
about ball chains okay
this course is not about block planes
that's not we're talked about here if
you also have a weird rash on your body
don't share it with the class in front
of the middle of lecture this happened
the first year it's weird don't do that
okay so all right what does this mean so
this means that I want you to interrupt
me as much as possible right don't be
embarrassed there's no stupid questions
so if you have a question though about
the lecture don't calm up in front of me
at the end end of the class be like Oh
what about slide three what did you mean
all this I will not answer these
questions because if you have a question
while I'm talking then somebody else
probably is a question and I rather just
discuss in front of everyone rather than
a line of people saying what about slide
forward what about slide six over never
again okay so again I will not be
offended I don't care just interrupt me
if you have questions okay so with that
any questions okay so I also post on
Piazza that homework one is out it'll be
due on the on the 11th next week and
then we'll also be releasing project one
on github next week as well just sort of
keep in mind of this this is this is
only your schedule with coming up who
here has finished the first homework I
think somebody already did and got a
perfect score
and they're not here awesome even better
okay so again it's we're giving you a
sequel byte file we're making you write
some simple queries it's sort of to
force you to do some of the things we
talked about in the second lecture and
this will actually be the only time you
were right sequel query for the rest of
the semester all the projects you will
be doing and it will be in C++ and all
the homeworks will be pencil and paper
okay so this I want at least have you
take a database course at least you know
write some sequel once in your life okay
all right so let's jump right into this
so last class at least the last two
classes we spent time talking about what
a database looks like at a
the logical level what is the
application programmers see they see
relational tables they see sequel and so
now what we want to talk about is how
are we actually gonna build the software
that's gonna manage this database system
alright this is essentially what the
course is about right how do we actually
going to store database and and and
allow queries to execute and you've
dried new data from it
so the overall outline for the course
again we've already covered the logical
part at the top it'll age from databases
and now we're starting to be going
through different parts of a database
and some one-by-one as if they're like
as if different layers so we'll start
talking about storage query execution
Kurchatov recovery and then we'll get to
like distributed databases and other
topics at the at the end and the way to
think about this this is a gross
approximation of what a database is
looks like it's just a bunch of layers
built on top of each other right so
we're gonna focus on this lecture and
the next lecture on the on the disk
manager how do we actually store data
you know on files on disk and then above
that once we know what API we're gonna
expose to the upper levels in the system
we start adding those extra levels to it
till at the end we have a full-featured
database management system so that's the
way to think about we're talking at this
point so we're no more sequel stuff no
more relational model stuff aspects of
it are gonna be important for how we
make different design decisions in our
system but can we you know we have to
figure out how do we actually gonna run
sequel queries but it's not like we're
gonna worry about how to write you know
you know complex sequel queries because
we've already done that ok it's again
we're focusing on different levels in
the system different layers one by one
and then you know sort of going up the
stack so as I said the first lecture as
well this course is about building disk
oriented database management systems so
just just to reiterate what I mean by
that if Discordian database system is
one where the software makes the
assumption that the primary search
location of the database is on disk and
so that means that any single time we
have to execute a query it may actually
want to run you know to want to access
data that's not in memory and we got to
go out in the disk and get it and
there's a bunch of components in sand
how we design our software that are
going to be based on this assumption to
protect ourselves from losing data
having you know invalid or incorrect
data
right so this is something's gonna
permeate all throughout the entire
system and we need to be aware of at any
given time something we're trying to
read is not in memory so to understand
this a bit further we want to make the
distinction between volatile and
non-volatile storage so essentially what
we're trying to do is we're trying to
have the data system manage the movement
of data from non-volatile storage into
volatile storage so what I mean by that
the way you think about the storage
hierarchy of computers is as such right
you sort of start at the very bottom or
start at the very top you're gonna have
things that are be very fast very
expensive they're very small so the way
to think of this is like a spectrum at
the top you have things that like CPU
registers or CPU caches l1 l2 l3 these
things are very fast right but they're
doing very small capacity because
they're like literally sitting on the
CPU itself then we're gonna have DRAM
and then below that we'll have SSDs
spinning these hard drives in network
storage again at the bottom they're very
large but they're much slower and
they're cheaper so again the dichotomy
that we care about is this division line
here so anything above this line is
volatile what does that mean yes yeah
she says it's not it's not persisted
when you lose power absolutely so all
these storage devices require constant
energy right like electricity to
maintain whatever they're storing right
you pull the power from your computer
everything in DRAM gets wiped everything
on your CPU caches get wiped everything
below this is non-volatile meaning it
doesn't require constant power in order
to persist whatever was stored in it so
that's the minute at a high level that's
the major thing that we care about do we
have to move data from here up into here
there's other aspect events though that
are going to put that are going to
affect how we design our software and
that has to do how're actually can
access this data so if it's in volatile
storage it's gonna support fast random
access maybe we can jump to any sort of
address location in the storage device
very quickly and we're gonna get roughly
the same performance no matter what
order we access the access things I mean
if I jump to this location this location
and maybe back to another location I'm
gonna get approximately the same latency
the same speed
sorry non-volatile storage they're gonna
have instead of having byte addressable
access to and how block addressable
access so in byte addressable access
that means I want to read 64 bits at
this stores location I can just go read
just that 64 bits and get exactly what I
want I'm oversimplifying but that's
essentially how from the programmers
perspective of us as the database system
developer that's what we we see in a
non-volatile storage we can't go get
exactly just a 64 bits that we want we
have to go get the block or the page
that has that data that we want and we
have to get everything that's along with
that page so I only want to read 64 bits
and that that you know and it's a
non-volatile storage I have to go get
the four kilobyte page that it's stored
in and then go pick out the just the
piece that I want another aspect that is
that the these systems also particularly
usually have faster sequential access
meaning 5v a bunch of contiguous blocks
in the storage device I can do that very
more efficiently than just reading
random locations the easiest way to
visualize this is just think about like
spinning this hard drive right most
laptops or every laptop pretty much
doesn't come with a spinning disk hard
drive but at a hot you know basically
the way it works is that you have this
arm that's physically moving on the
platter like like a turntable and
combined already single time you got to
jump to new location you have to pick
the arm up and move it to another
location and that's a physical movement
and it's very expensive and slow SSDs
don't have this problem because it's
solid-state but there's other issues so
in these storage devices we want to try
to maximize the amount of data that we
can read that's sequential right and
these ones we in the volatile storage we
don't care as much so for the purposes
of this course we're just going to say
that anything that's in DRAM we're just
gonna call this memory like that that's
what we mostly care about how we
actually put things into memory and then
anything below this this line here we're
just gonna say this is disk and for all
most of the algorithms and most of the
methods were going to talk about in this
course we don't care whether it's it's
you know which one of these it is it's
not entirely true when we talk about
joins sequential access matters a lot
but we'll come to that later and so I
don't think the textbook talks about
network storage they usually they always
when you see these kind of hierarchies
always have tape drives at the bottom
but nobody runs databases on those
anymore there's a relief like disaster
recovery
network storage would be like EBS or s3
on on Amazon so the reason why we're not
gonna talk about these things at the top
is that where you focus on these things
in the Advanced Course in the spring and
for our purposes in this class this this
course in the semester this is so slow
anyway that who cares how fast we can be
putting things in CP registers in the
advanced class we assume the database is
always here in DRAM and therefore these
things actually matter but for this
entire semester we won't really talk
about worrying about things sitting in
CPU caches because it doesn't matter cuz
going to disk so slow now I always talk
about this every year this is actually a
new class of storage devices that sort
of straddles the line called
non-volatile memory who here has heard
of this before who here has heard Intel
obtained memory one two three all right
yeah so that's so Intel is actually the
first manufacturer the hash tag put
released this everybody's been working
on this for like 15 20 years Intel
actually put the first one is put out
the first devices so it's like DRAM
where it sits in the dim slot and yet
it's byte addressable but it's like an
SSD meaning if you pull the power on the
machine it persists all your data
alright so this is super cool this is
like the future of what computer is
gonna be look like and eventually we'll
have to rewrite this class to take this
an account but we're not there yet it's
not widely available now again this is
something I've been working on it for a
while so this is a book that I wrote
with my first PC student we it was
basically his dissertation they put into
book form but I think this is the future
we're just not there yet it's not widely
available but you can't get on Amazon
yet but eventually a lot of talk about
what could go away if you have
non-volatile memory all right so let's
talk about how slow these things are so
there's again there's different tables
on the internet that have different
numbers but these approximately the same
you know roughly in the same ballpark
the thing that matters most is the
orders of magnitude that that's
different between these storage devices
so let's say I need to read a 64 bits
from from different storage device if
I'm in l1 cache then it's like half a
nanosecond if it's in l2 l2 it's seven
and a seconds and so forth to get to
really long just long delays so again
this is why we spent all this time in
this class worrying
how how we can try to minimize the
impact of reading data from disk right
because there's a pretty big difference
between 100 nanoseconds and 150,000
nanoseconds and so for every single
query if we always have to go out the
disk then we're screwed right the thing
is gonna be essentially grind to a halt
and we're not gonna get any work done
and I realized putting this in terms of
nanoseconds is hard for us to as humans
to wrap our heads around so if you just
replace nanosecond with seconds then you
start to realize how long these numbers
actually are right so the way to think
about this is like in another metaphor
you like to use from Jim Jim Gray a
famous database researcher is that say
that I want to read a book I want to
read a page in a book so if it's in l1
then it's just like reading the book
right in front of me on this table if
it's in l2 then maybe it's going across
the room to read it if it's an F it's in
DRAM that I got to walk to the library
and then now you start to these you know
larger and larger orders of magnitude
and if you have to read from a tape
drive it's like flying the Pluto to read
a page in a book it just takes forever
so again this is why people don't want
to store data on this but note is that
they had to all right so the goal of
what we're trying to do in our DNA
system is that we want to provide the
illusion to the application that we have
enough memory to store their entire data
base in memory essentially like you know
there's a fine amount of memory on our
machine and we want to say we want to
store a database that exceeds the amount
of memory that's available to us but
without having to you know grind to a
halt every single time we read something
or write something right so again that's
what focus in this course is and and the
next three lectures is really about how
can we be careful on any single time
we've got to read something from disk or
run a query that we minimize that impact
and we're gonna do a bunch of different
tricks to to mitigate this problem by
allowing different threads or different
queries are run at the same time by
caching things by pre computing some
data there's a whole bunch of slew of
tricks that we're gonna have in our
database system that we have in
essentially around avoiding this long
long long problem so let's look at a
high level diagram of what a disscourn a
database system looks like from the
perspective that we carry out care about
at this point in the semester and then
we'll see how
the rest of lecture how actually to fill
in and and and design these things so
again at the lowest layer we have the
disk and we have our database file or
files it doesn't matter and then we're
going to represent these through
different blocks or pages right a page
is the canonical term you use to
describe this sometimes slip and say
block but at a high little bit mean the
same thing so now a memory we're gonna
have what was called a buffer pool and
this will focus on this and the lecture
next week and this is what you'll be
implementing in the in the first
assignment the first project so there's
some higher-level layer in the system
and execution engine a query engine we
don't care what it is but it's gonna
make requests to our buffer pool and say
hey I want to read page 2 page 2 is not
in memory so we got to go look in the
page directory on disk and say here's
the list of the pages that I have here's
where to find them so I'd now I can go
find where page 2 is I bring it into
memory and now I hand off to my to my
excuse me engine here's the pointer to
page 2 in memory and then it can
interpret it do whatever at once we
don't care alright so this is what we're
focusing on here as for the next three
lectures that was how we actually build
this part here all right so today and
next week we'll we'll do discuss what
the data is files on disk next week will
be the buffer pool and then later and so
forth we'll talk about how we actually
represent the directory ok so what does
this look like
you take an operating system course what
does it sound like I'm trying to make it
appear that I have more memory than I
actually do virtual memory exactly so
now I may be thinking all right I've
taken OS course here why why do I want
to have my databases manage memory like
this it seems like a big waste of time
and they OS can already do this right
well it it's not a good idea here's what
so in an operating system parlance we
would call this memory map files or
there's a syscall called em map in POSIX
and essentially what this does is it
takes a file on disk and you tell the
operating system map the files pages
into the address space for my process
and now I can read and write to those
there's those memory locations and it's
not memory the OS brings it in I can I
can write to it and then eventually if I
can tell it'll Esther to write it out
for me I can do an N Sync and write it
up back out the disk so we're
essentially giving up control of the
movement of memory back and forth of
data back and forth we disk of memory
and letting the operating system manage
this for us right so again at a high
level it looks like this we have we have
a bunch of pages on disk file and then
in memory the OS has its virtual memory
page table and we have physical memory
so what happens is the application says
hey I want to read page 1 it looks in
the virtual memory we get it we get a
page vault and say this thing's not
backed by physical memory it's not it's
still out on disk we go fetch it back it
into a physical memory page and then
update our page table to now point to
that memory location so if I come along
and I want to read page 3 I go through
the same process I fetch it into memory
and then the application can do whatever
once but now let's say that I read page
2 what's the problem
there's no there's no free physical
memory page to put the particulars put
this page in so I need to make a
decision of which of these pages to
remove and while I'm doing this
eventually have to stall the database
system install my thread that requested
this page because now the the the disk
the you know the the disk scheduler for
the operating system is gonna go out to
pay the disk fetch it and bring into
memory so you there's tricks there's
ways to figure out from the application
perspective and might have to read
something that's not in memory so maybe
I could hand it off to another thread so
it stalls and not me because I always
want to try to keep doing useful work
because I want to mitigate the stalls
when I have to go out the disk right but
essentially the operation doesn't know
exactly what what the hell we're doing
doesn't know anything about what the
data system is doing it just sees a
bunch of reads and writes two pages it
doesn't understand any of the high-level
semantics or what a query is what deta
wants to read right so we wanted we want
to by going with virtual memory by going
with memory mapped files we're giving up
controls or giving up knowledge that we
have inside our database system over to
the u.s. that that's blind and doesn't
know anything right so if we're only
reading data there's a bunch of syscalls
we can to mitigate some of these
problems but if we start writing things
then it becomes problematic because now
the OS doesn't know that certain pages
have to be flushed out the disk before
other pages do again what we'll cover
this later when we talk about logging
and concurrency control but the OSS sees
yeah I need to I need to write some data
out means go ahead and write it out it
doesn't know whether that was an okay
thing to do or not so you get around
this by by giving it hints like using em
advised to tell it how you're gonna
access certain pages whether it's read
sequential and random how to prevent
pages from beginning paged out although
you can lock doesn't prevent it from
getting written out which again could to
still be a problem and this is when you
tell it to flush so I would say that
memory map files of virtual memory
sounds like a seductive thing we want to
use in our database system and every
year some student says why why are we
doing all this buffer pool thing why
can't we just let the oh let's do this
for us and trust me you don't want to do
this because it can be you have
performance bottlenecks and you'll have
correctness problems so there's not very
many systems out there that actually use
em
the most famous two are probably Monet
DB and LM DB level DB you ever heard of
that from Google is another one elastic
search is a search engine or the
document store then Raving BB is a JSON
database at Israel so all these guys use
and map but there's a bunch of extra
stuff you have to do to prevent the OS
from doing things that are incorrect or
there's certain limitations or
assumptions you have to make about what
the u.s. is allowed to do there's not
right so this is like I mean there's a
few more but there's not very many so
what's missing here we're missing all
the major database systems perhaps my
sequel Oracle db2 sequel server none of
those guys use em map cuz it's a bad
idea because you're giving up control
and the data student can always do
better then what the operating system
could try to figure out so there's some
systems that still use MF in very
limited cases this is actually out of
date MIT I mean I talked to the guys
last week mem Siegel got rid of MF
entirely sequel Dwight has a special
engine you have to tell I want to use M
map for some you know embedded devices
that's that's what actually what you
want to use but default you don't get
this influx DB only uses this for like
read-only caches but the example I
always like to give it talk about is
MongoDB everyone here has heard of
MongoDB for right that's a famous JSON
database system so when they first
started their their default storage
engine or storage manager was using M
map and there's a bunch of crap they had
to do to make that thing actually work
but it was a it was a super button pimp
was a big bottleneck for them and then
they raised put of money and then the
first thing they did was got rid of em
map and got it you know bought this
thing called wire tire which was a non
mm storage engine so if a map was a good
idea these guys had all the money in the
world had some top engineers they could
have figured it out but it was just it
became untenable so if I die in this
class and you want to have a memorial
something just say Andy hated M map you
can you can even publicly say these
things okay
we're actually working a paper at paper
and they let this year and actually
proving that is a bad idea
all right so the main takeaway I want
you to get from this is that the
database system is oh it can always do
better it always knows exactly what's
what the queries are trying to do it
knows what the workload looks like and
therefore it can make the best decision
the operating system doesn't know any
it just sees a bunch of again reads and
writes read and write calls so some of
the things that we'll talk about maybe
late in the semester that we can do if
we're not using a map is like
prefetching better replacement policies
better scheduling again the OS is sort
of general purpose pickup truck whereas
we can tune our system look like a
Porsche or Ferrari to be exactly what we
want to do for application so another
main takeaway is that the operating
system is not your friend we don't want
to rely on up we want try to avoid it as
much as possible because it's gonna make
decisions that could be hurtful to our
Davis system so it's like a frenemy you
need it to survive but ideally you don't
want to talk to it all right all right
so for database storage this is we're
gonna focus on today so there's two main
problems we have to take care of the
first is hat how we're gonna represent
the data on files on disk and the second
is that how we actually manage the Muta
memory back and forth right between the
disk files and the buffer pool so for
this lecture today we're gonna focus on
this problem next class well stuff up in
this problem and then starting when we
talk about buffer pools on Wednesday
next week we'll focus on the second
problem okay all right so today's
lecture again we're gonna go to that
first question how are we actually gonna
represent the the database on files on
disk so we're first talk about how would
organize the database across a sequence
of pages now let's talk about how we're
actually gonna store the pages inside
those files and then let's talk about
what's actually the what are the tuples
look like inside those pages alright so
we're gonna go sort of at a macro level
and deep you know step down to you know
inside the data that we're actually
storing all right so at the end of the
day the database is just a bunch of
files on disk some system stored the
database has one file like sequel light
does that for the first homework you
download that DB file that's the entire
database and capsulated it in that
single file most other systems however
store things in across multiple files so
here a look at like the the data
directory from I see bone Postgres
you'll see a bunch of different
directories mature files right you do
this because you know databases could be
very large like petabytes and you don't
want to you know you don't want to hit
up the faucet and limitation of a file
into the size of a file so again the OS
doesn't know anything about what's in
these files it's just there's a bunch of
binary data to the operating system
they're not special but
the format for these data files are
typically proprietary or specific to the
database measurement system
so meaning you can't take a sequel Lite
file plop it down inside a directory for
my sequel and I think my sequel is gonna
be able to read it right they're always
they're always specialized to whatever
the software is so these files were
these follows it pretty davis we're
typically just gonna store them on top
of the regular file system that the OS
provides us ext3 ext4 whatever windows
net has now I forget right these are
just and the OS who sees a bunch of
files and we rely on the file system to
provide us with basic readwrite api's in
the 1980's people did try to build
database systems that use custom file
systems on raw storage devices
so like say you plop down a new hard
drive instead of formatting it and you
know setting it up for NTFS or when FS
or xtxt for you say screw all that is
give me the roll storage device and I'll
grant I'll manage what's actually being
stored in it myself some of the
enterprise systems like that like
enterprise meaning like high-end ones
like Oracle db2 and sequel server will
still do this but most of the new
database startups are anything you gave
him that's come out in the last ten
years or 15 years doesn't do this right
because it's the engineering effort to
make your own custom file system for
your database system is not worth it
you get maybe like a 10% improvement but
now you you know you're managing your
own faucet which is a big chaos and it
makes your thing less portable cuz now
you can't easily run it on when Amazon
and other other Harvard vendors so what
we're building essentially is now again
what is called a Storage Manager
sometimes also called the storage engine
and then this is the piece of the
software at the component in our
database system that is responsible for
maintaining our database files on on
disk now we could do reads and writes
and let the OS schedule things some of
the more high-end database systems will
actually have a shim layer right right
above the file system that does allows
the the davison to do some disk
scheduling you do this set like I know I
have a bunch of threads writing to
blocks that are close to each other
I can maybe combine them together and do
a single write request write the OS can
kind of do these things but again it
doesn't know exactly what's above this
doesn't know what the semantics of the
above it motor systems don't do this and
then for the project we'll be working on
here we don't do this it's typically for
the higher ones yes yes a question is I
said that most databases and split up
the file the database files into
multiple files because you don't hit the
the file size limit of the operating
system is there any optimization for
putting things in memory yes just a file
Oh Russians just the file have a limit
for the amount of the size it can be in
memory with virtual memory no when we
talk to us to whatever the the swap size
is what the OS could let you store but
if it's it's essentially limited the
physical memory that's available to you
her question is would be better to have
a single file because then you get the
over you get rid of the overhead of
having multiple files wouldn't you like
the overhead like the inode that you're
that you have to find it go open a file
or what okay so you're talking like the
metadata there save it is if I have one
file then I have one file name and I
have one inode in my file system that
points to it if I have multiple files
that I have multiple inode entries or
and each one has their own file name
much a meditator
you know referencing it but like that's
what maybe a kilobyte of metadata it's
nothing right if your database is one
petabyte who cares that you have a bunch
of file names right I think really large
scales it doesn't make a difference
right I I think now for like for modern
file systems it's not really an issue
anymore like you can have like exabyte
you know single files are exabytes but
thinking like in the 90s or early 2000s
when like you were running like fat32
you can only have a 4 gigabyte file
right
that's back in the days it mattered more
not so much now but even then the
metadata doesn't matter
yes his statement is doesn't this limit
the number of files that you can have
open is usually open file handles on
them are things you can create and
therefore you have to have permissions
to do this that's really yes and so if
you go look at like the tuning guides or
setup guides for a bunch of different
data systems they'll talk about like
tune this kernel parameter delight you
have a bunch of you know this number I
notes or file handles over absolutely
yes okay awesome all right again so
we're trying to build a storage manager
and the storage manager is responsible
for maintaining these files on disk and
whether it's one file or multiple files
it doesn't matter so now within these
files we're going to organize them as a
collection of pages and so our Storage
Manager is going to keep track of all
the reads and writes we're gonna do to
these pages as if you track a wood
available space what space is available
to us to store new data in our pages so
a page is essentially just a fixed size
chunk or block of data that were just
we're going to organize our file and you
know into these chunks so a page can
contain anything right it contained the
actual tuples the data database itself
contain metadata indexes log records
from the storage management perspective
it doesn't really matter right but we
always have to store things within a
single page so now some database systems
will require you that to have the the
page be self-contained and what I mean
by that is all the information you need
to know how to interpret and comprehend
the contents of a page have to be stored
within the page itself so let me give an
example let's say that I have a table
and I have the table has 10 columns they
have different types but I call create
table and I create the table of
different attributes so I could have the
metadata about what's in that table
stored in one page and then all the
tuples or that pay for that that table
stored in another page so the problem is
now if I have a disk failure like my my
data center catches on fire my disks
melt and I lose that one page that tells
me what what the layout of the the
schema is
now I don't know how to easily interpret
what the contents are of my of my tubule
pages and so some systems like Oracle
for example require all the metadata
about how to say here's what's in that
page has to be within the page itself so
that way if you lose any other page it
doesn't affect you know you lose one
page it doesn't affect any other pages
you think it's a bit overhead to this
that seems crazy well they do it for
disaster recovery again so now again the
machine catches on fire and you lose a
bunch of pages you can you you literally
open up a hex editor and try to
reconstruct what the database was by
looking at pat one page at a time and
all the metadata you need about what's
in that page is stored within itself
alright so all the things that's
important understand is that we're not
going to mix different types types of
data within a page there's some research
systems that do this we could have you
know one page have tuple data and log
record data for our purposes here and
most systems they don't do this it's
like here's a page and only source
tuples here's a page that only stores
index information so now each page is
going to be given a unique internal
identifier that the database system is
gonna generate for us a page ID right
and we're gonna have then now have an
indirection layer and this is would be a
reoccurring theme when we talk about
storage we have an indirection layer
that's gonna allow us to map a page ID
to some location in a file at some all
set right and we want to do this because
now underneath the covers we can start
moving pages around you know if we start
compacting the disk or or set it but
another disk and it doesn't change our
page ID cuz we have this this page
directory say you want page 1 2 3 here's
where to go find it so there's a bunch
of page page concepts we need to talk
about to put it in the context of how
real computers work so at the lowest
level we have what's called a hardware
page this is this is the page API or
page access level you get from the
actual storage device itself I just know
what the SSD or spinning disk hard drive
exposes this is typically four kilobytes
then above that you have an operating
system page and again that's as you as
you take things out of the storage
device and put it into memory right they
represent that as an internal page as
well and that's typically usually four
kilobytes by default in Linux and
Windows there's things like huge pages
where you turn it you can take a one Gil
one gigabyte page to be broken up to
maunsell four kilobyte horror pages but
for our purposes we don't care about the
thing we care about at the database page
here right and this is gonna bury
between different systems so at the low
end at 512 bytes that's like something
like Seigle light like an embedded
system but then at the high end you'll
have like 16 ele bytes that could be
like my sequel so different database
systems do different things and there's
different trade-offs for all of these
all right the main thing we're going to
care about though is that the harbor
page is is the sort of the lowest level
that we do atomic writes to the storage
device and typically 4 kilobytes so what
I mean my bad is say I need to modify a
bunch of data the harbor can only
guarantee that if I do a write and flush
to the disk if it can only guarantee
that at 4 kilobyte of time it's gonna be
atomic so I'm excited I mean my bad so
like if I say I need to write 16
kilobytes I could try to write the I say
I tell the disk hey write 16 kilobytes
for me it might crash before you know it
writes the first 8 kilobytes then it
crashes before writing the next 8
kilobytes and then you come back and now
you have a torn right you only see the
first half and up the second half
because the harbor can only guarantee 4
kilobytes at a time all right this will
come up this we'll talk about this more
later when we talk about logging and
commercial but this is something we need
we need need to be mindful of and again
there's different systems do different
things the high end systems like an
Oracle sequel server and db2 you can
actually tune it so you say I want to
start things there's 4 kilobytes 8
kilobytes or 16 kilobytes II you can
even vary say 4 index pages store much
larger page sizes and then data page is
sort of smaller you can go crazy and do
much different things all right so now
we want to talk about how we're gonna
represent the the page storage
architecture so again there's different
ways to do this there's different
trade-offs for this the most common one
it's going to be the heap file
organization so we'll focus on that but
the thing to understand is that at this
point at this lowest level in the
storage manager we don't care about
what's actually in our pages we don't
care whether this indexes data or tuple
data we don't care USS for a page we'll
get
that page right or yes delete a page
will delete it so database heap file is
a unordered collection of pages where
the tuples of the data can be stored in
random order so again the relational
model doesn't have any orderings if I
insert tuples one by one
I'm not guaranteed that they're gonna be
stored that way on disk because it
doesn't matter because I write sequel
queries and that have no notion of
ordering so the API we need to have
again is be able to read and write and
access pages at a time as well as being
able to iterate over every single page
that we have in case we need to do a
sequential scan across the entire table
we'll have some additional metadata to
keep track of what pages we have which
ones have free space so that if we need
to insert new data we know where to find
a page to go ahead and do that right and
internally we can represent this heat
ball in a bunch of different ways again
at the lowest lowest level we can
organize these and pages and then within
these pages we can represent them with
different data structures so let's first
talk about doing linked lists because
that's sort of the dumb way to do this
or nobody actually does this but it
exists and then we'll see the page
directory way which is a better approach
so the way we're gonna do this again the
goal is we what we're trying to do here
is we're trying to figure out within my
file I have a bunch of pages what pages
you know what where those pages exist
and what kind of you know whether they
have data or not all the way they have
free space for me to store stuff so in
the header of this this heap father said
that for this linked list we're just
gonna have two pointers we have one
pointer that says here's the list of the
free pages that I have in my file and
here's a list of the the pages that
actually have completely for occupied
right and then again this is just a
linked list so it doesn't matter where
these pages are stored doesn't matter
whether contiguous or not I just
I now have just pointers and say hey
here's you know here's the data that you
know here's here's the first page my
linked list that where they're occupied
and here's a pointer to the next one so
vanayya if I want to say find me a page
a free page like a store stuff I can
follow the free page list look in here
and you know in traverse long until I
find something that has enough space for
what I want to store
and because we need to go possibly an
iterate in reverse order we need
pointers on the way back as well yes the
question is why is the heap file
unordered thinking at a high level like
the the the data we're storing does not
need to be ordered as we insert it right
so if I insert like three tuples I could
insert I could in my page layout the
actual inside the pages I could have
tuple three tuple two two and one I'm
not required to put them in order that
are given right so this question if you
had to look for a particular page with
these link list things I have to reverse
potentially entire link list if I might
one absolutely yes this sucks this is a
bad idea and saintly yes his question is
if it's ordered you can always search
faster right so there's different rate
offs so I have no metadata to say where
I have free pages so I need to insert
something now where am I going to insert
it now I've been since you have to do a
sequential scan and look at every single
page until I find one that has free
space or in this approach here I'm not
saying this I'm not saying this right
I'm not saying at a hile this is the
right way to do it I'm saying this is
how this works if I need if I have this
one here then I get this go follow this
pointer to find the first free page and
see whether it has enough space for what
I want to store it's a trade-off right I
can either go do you know almost binary
search to find exactly the page that I
want or I can just do I can do this
linked list statements you can maintain
ordered sets of it free pages and and
and fill pages look he's ever usually
linked lists use a treat a linked list
can still be ordered right so you could
say all right say I delete all the
tuples from this page and it's been its
page two and this is page one this is
page three so I could insert it in
between these two guys sure
order like we make two different or one
on the page ideally but again I think
your your the page ID is just like it
all set in it right it's not there's no
sort of a logical thing built in top of
the heap file look let's link to wheat
acres offline if you understand it this
question over here or okay let's keep
going if you have questions we talked
about it further I mean the main Taylor
this is a bad idea
nobody does this this is so I don't want
to dwell on it too much what people
typically do is having a page directory
and for this one it's a we have a page
now again in the header of our file
that's gonna maintain the a mapping from
page IDs to they're all set and then we
can also maintain some additional
metadata in this directory to say hey
here's the amount of free space that's
available to me in a particular page so
now when I want to go say I want to
insert some data I don't have to go you
know scan the that list I can just look
my page directory and find everything
that I need right so if my pages are
just ordered sequentially like this and
then this is just a mapping to Widow
they're located right so the important
thing about this going back to what we
talked about about the the atomic rights
for the for Hardware so now I have much
a metadata that's that's a summarization
of what's in my actual pages themselves
and I have to keep it in sync but I
actually can't guarantee that because
the the the harbor can't guarantee that
I can write two pages of exactly the
same time so let's say that I delete a
bunch of data here and my page and then
I update I want to update my page
rectory and say oh I have this amount of
free space I made a bunch of data write
that out and then before I can update my
page directory and write that out I
crash so now I come back online and say
oh this I think this page is full and
therefore I can't read any data to it
but I know it's actually not right in
reality it's not so you could say all
right well when I boot back up I'll just
scan through all my pages and figure out
what's actually really there but now
again think think think in the extreme
if I have one gig
by the data then that's gonna take
forever or aside one petabyte of data
that's gonna take forever to actually do
this so the bunch of mechanisms will
talk about later on or how we can
maintain a log and initial metadata in
in sort of special special files so that
if we crash to come back we know how to
reconstruct what's inside all these
things I think it is just a hash table
to say I want page 1 2 3 here's where to
go find it and I just can get it yes yes
each page has the same size yes what do
you mean sorry
these questions what is the size of a
page in this world right so this goes
back through this diagram here they do
different different systems do different
things right
if failsafe is like you know we can
write four kilobytes and because the
hardware guarantee that's atomic but now
I need to write you know say say my
pages themselves are four kilobytes but
I need to update one page they clean up
clear out a bunch of data update the
page directory and say all right that
that page you've been cleared out I
can't guarantee the right both of those
pages atomically I can write one crash
before before I write the second one
okay all right so again this is what the
pages are gonna look like inside the yet
certain files so he says why do some
pages you why do some data systems used
larger pages there's trade-offs so
internally inside my database system I
have to have this page directory in
memory mapping pages to some some
location either memory or on disk but
now if I can represent a larger amount
of data with one page ID then that size
of that table goes down think of this is
like in the the TLB the translation
lookaside buffer inside on the CPU if I
am trying to match all a bunch of pages
but it's my page tables get really large
and now I'm gonna have cache misses so
by you can represent more data in you
know with with few number of page IDs
furthermore going back to talk about the
difference being random and central
access
so now if I can write out contiguously
you say say four four kilobyte pages to
represent a 16 kilobyte database page
when I do a read I just read all that
sequentially and bring it in now I'm
getting potentially more useful data
that I need but again it makes more it
makes doing writes more expensive look
at that now at this stage a bunch of
crap ahead of time to prevent myself
from getting torn writes so there's
there's pros and cons for both of them
and this is why again the commercial
systems allow you to tune them in
different ways
based on what your application wants to
do let's go question yes so so his
question is for for self-contained pages
would that solve this particular issue
here no you still meet so self-contained
pages would mean like the contents of
that side the page I have all the
metadata that I need for it I still have
to have a page director to tell me where
to find that page if I want page 1 2 3
or 4 5 6 so it's not entirely
self-contained at the higher levels in
the system it's unavoidable at the
bottom level so what we're at here might
weaken we have any talk about what's
actually inside this the page but within
the page directory we can't guarantee
that self-contained okay it doesn't make
sense right yes yeah so this question is
is there any way to guarantee that the
if a crash happens when you come back
you can identify that the crash happened
yes
so you knew checksums right so say that
I my database page is d3 pages here in
the header of the first page I'll put a
checksum and say all right the next from
my starting point here the next three
pages the the checksum should be like a
CRC or md5 should be this this amount so
I come back online and I after a crash I
would look and say oh the last page when
I went to commute the checksum doesn't
match because this thing didn't get
written out so therefore I would do I
have an error right
and then we'll talk about logging and no
in a second but like you can log the
operations you do to modify the pages
and that's essentially what the database
hasn't worries about mostly alright cool
so that's all I'll talk about what that
actually looks like inside these pages
again every page is gonna have a header
and it's sort of what he asked about
we're gonna have information what's the
size of the page the checksum what
database version or the version of the
software wrote this data out right you
what could happen is people can you know
data is companies put out new releases
Postgres puts out new releases every
single time you know the page layout may
change so when you when you want to
upgrade you want to know am i looking at
pages that are created by the new
software the old software and I can have
different code paths to interpret them
if you're doing compression like the
dictionary compression or like lz4 gzip
you can store information about that we
all talked about this at this point in
the semester but it's also information
about you know what transactions or what
queries modify this data and whether
other queries allowed to see it again
and then we've already talked about the
issue of a maybe self-contained right so
now within a page we can represent data
in in two different ways so we can do
this as a sort of a tuple oriented
approach and I'll explain what that
means the next slide or we can do a log
structured approach so again it's within
a page now assuming of a page directory
to tell us how we need to get to that
page if we want you know a particular
page of one two three now we're talking
about what does it look like when you
look inside the page what do you
actually the data set I'm actually going
to see so for this one let's just assume
that we're storing tuples and let's say
a really simple case here a really
similar strong main idea is that in our
page all we're gonna do is just insert
tuples one after another right start
from the beginning we have a little
header space and say here's the number
of tuples that we have so we know what
else that we want to jump to if we want
to insert a new one but it's super
simple we just insert one at a time
right so say a third start three tuples
assuming they're all fixed length every
single time an insert one I just jump to
the next off free offset looking and
then update the counter
so this is a bad idea why perfect so he
says yeah if you delete a tuple you have
to move everything well not necessarily
right I could just do this all right
free the space table he says the
external fragmentation well why why
can't I just insert in there with that
right so I made the assumption that
their fixed length size but he's
absolutely right so this works great it
fixed if it everything's fixed Lane
could I just shove it the new one where
the old one was but it's not fixed
length then this slot may actually you
know this location may not be big enough
for what I would insert and now I got to
try to put it down in here right so so
that's one issue I mean the other issue
too is like every single time I need to
go say I delete this thing I either mean
to mean maintain metadata at the top and
tell me hey here's the here's a here's a
location in this page or you can write
some data or I got a sequentially scan
and look at every single tuple to figure
out where I can go right so this sucks
nobody does this instead what you do is
what it cause slotted pages so this is
the most common scheme that every disk
or in a data system will use the exact
details of how they're going to
represent these pages are we slightly
different but at a high level this is
this is what everyone does so the way
things could work we're always gonna
have our header the header it can store
that basic metadata about checksum or
you know access times and things like
that and then we're gonna have to sort
of regions of data we want to store at
the top would have what's called a slot
array and the bottom we're actually
going to have the actual the data we
want to store these in again we're
assuming we're doing tuples here so then
this one can be fixed length of variable
length tuples it doesn't matter so what
the slaughter rate basically is is a
mapping layer from a particular slot to
some offset in the page where that's the
starting location of the particular
tuple that you want right and the reason
why we want to have this indirection
layers because now we can start moving
these within a page we can move these
tuples around any way that we want again
the upper levels of the system don't
care
right they can always you know the
record i t's gonna the page ID and the
slot number and all i need to do is move
these things around and just update the
slaughter rate and say here's what
here's where you're actually pointing to
and the way we're gonna fill up the page
is that the slot array is gonna grow
from the beginning to the end and the
data is gonna grow from the end to the
beginning and at some point we'll reach
in the middle where we can't store any
any new information and then that's what
we say that our page is full
so yeah this means that there could be a
small little gap in the middle where we
can't store anything but that's you know
because we wanted to support very length
tuples we have to we have to do this all
right we could do what's called a vacuum
or compaction we could just scan through
and reorganize defragmentation and in
old file systems we could do that in the
background the days we can do it but for
our purposes right this is this what we
end up with yes good point so his
question is are we assuming here that
that the within a page we could have
tuples from different tables in practice
nobody does that
because you would have to maintain some
metadata say this is from tuple want a
table one this is from table two we'll
see at the end that there is a way to
there's some systems that do do this but
in general nobody does this like if you
open up sequel later postgrads or
whatever you call create table it'll
create pages and only tuples from those
tables will go in those pages it's good
question what will come to that in a
second so these are tuple oriented pages
and the other day we're trying to store
tuples inside these pages and so you
know when I do an insert I do an update
I want to find you know I take the
contents that tuple and just write it
out in its entirety in this page here
we'll see in next class we'll talk about
for really large data like if you have a
tree that's like you want a store like a
you know a video file in the database
don't do that what's fine why later but
like for that case here you couldn't
store this because it won't fit in a
single page so you some you have some
extra metadata some pointers to say
here's the pages that have the rest of
the data that you're looking for but in
general we want us pack in the entire
tuple in a single page because now when
we go access that you need to access to
the tuple it's one page read to go get
it
and not a bunch of different ones again
we'll break that assumption next class
but for our purposes here it's fine so
another way to store data and pages is
it's our question so his question is say
I remember the third tuple here right
what happens well it depends
I'll give it a minute in the class some
systems will actually compact it before
it writes out the disk some systems will
just leave a gap here and then if it
gets full and you say oh I have some
free space maybe I try to do compaction
yes yes this question is the the slot is
pointing to the starting position of the
tuple the question is what does a point
since question is what is the what is
the ordering of the storage address
within the slots not sure what you mean
like I have say this is 4 kilobytes I I
want to store a 1 kilobyte tuple for
Cuba 1 so from starting from the offset
I jump to the 1 kilobyte and then my
slot right points of that right yes the
question is if I delete one tuple in the
middle again I see people 3 what do i
what do I do it up above nothing missile
on array yes so again the header could
dimmer systems do different things the
header could could have a bit mat and
say you know here's the here's the slots
that are empty that you could point
something in or I just switch the scan
and read it right it doesn't matter the
key thing though I think is that the the
other parts of the system don't know and
don't care that where I'm actually
physically stored like it first so for
tuple 1 right this comes out of the slot
here
right so in the upper part of the system
it would say Oh tuple one you can find
it if you have page one two three
at slot zero slot one depending on what
your starting offset is so now no matter
how I reorganize my page and move to but
one around I know that I always want to
go to the first slot to find where it's
actually located and now if I reorganize
I don't have to update my indexes on to
update anything and this is sort of what
the page directory is trying to do as
well so no matter where I move the pages
on on the file either on disk or
different look you know on the network
other parts of the system don't care
where it actually got moved to because I
have a page once you know I have the
page ID I can only use the page
directory to find where it's actually
main stored right these indirection
layers avoid having to have updates
propagate through all the parts of the
system yes those question is how do I
know that tuple one is stored in in slot
one
so if I had too much but we'll go ahead
and do that so this is always in the
last slide but let's talk about it now
so the way we identify tuples is through
these record IDs or tuple IDs and it's
essentially a unique identifier to say
here's the logical location or a logical
address of a of a tuple it's a blend of
logical and physical but usually the
page ID and like the offset or the slot
so all the parts of the system that we
want to address tuple one right they
don't know what - Bolin is they just
know I have a page ID and I'm a slot
number and so I go to the page directory
and say I want page 1 2 3 the page
directory says oh it's in this file and
this all set jump to that then I get get
to that page now I say oh I want slot 1
I look at my slot array and that tells
me where in that page you can find the
data that I want so other parts of the
system like the indexes log records and
other things they're going to address
tuples through these record IDs
a morning that's separate from the page
like as well yes me it like I'll give a
demo hope let's make myself like say I
want to find find that the salary find
the the student record or the professor
record the name Andy I look in the index
on the name and something to say oh
there's a professor named Andy and he's
he has a record ID of page one two three
all set
slot one that's what that UNIX gives me
so then I say it go to the page
directory okay
Gav where do I find page one two three
you go get it for me it goes and gets it
now I have the pointer to the page and
say oh I want slot one I look at my slot
array and that tells me what all set the
jump to that page to find that need
right and so different data systems do
different things the most common
approach is the page ID and the slot
number the offset and again they Vantage
of this is that if I start moving data
around either moving the page around or
moving did within the page itself the
index and all the other crap doesn't
have to get updated because they're
still looking at page one two three all
set one so okay now let me I'll give a
demo explain some more detail so in
different systems do different things
like in Postgres it'll be 4 bytes or
equals 10 bytes there's a bunch of extra
metadata that they store and sequel Lite
is 8 bytes so let's give a demo because
that's always fun because I hate typing
on the surface and use my other laptop
and I can see it better
alright so I'm gonna give an example
again a what of how we can actually see
what these pages look like because again
the data system that stores this
internally you're not supposed to see it
but there's different commands to do to
actually to get at it
I can't were in the back see that or is
it too dark or too light how's that
better ok alright so we're going to make
a
we're gonna make a simple table that has
two columns ID and value and we're gonna
insert some tables in it all right so
this is Postgres right so you see ID in
value so Postgres has this thing called
the CT ID that is represents the
physical location of the data of the
data so I can add this like virtual
column here a CT ID and I get it in my
output so this now is a tuple there
that's gonna have the page ID and the
offset so again here's the data I
started three tuples so now it's saying
that at page zero slot one is the first
tuple page zero slot 2 is the second
tuple pay zero slot 3 is the third tuple
right so this again so that's not
actually storing this data it's just it
can derive this when it runs the query
because it says oh I look at my page I
see the slots here's the tuple that
actually are actually found all right so
let's go ahead and delete one of these
tuples let's say say I delete the the
second one so I go back and look at my
tuple alright look at my data and you
can see that it deleted the the second
tuple but it didn't realize the page
right the the third tuple is still it
you know page 0 offset 3 or slot 3
alright so let's say now I go and start
a new tuple in what do you think is
gonna do
with that what so again I had a deleted
a second tuple now I have us a tublat
slot one it slot three I started a new
tuple is it gonna be slot two or slot 4
raise your hand it's a slot two half
flat three are starting slot 4 less flat
four right it's not wrong right because
for our purposes the relational models
that doesn't say anything about the
order of how we insert tuples Postgres
it's way to implement I decided to put
it at the end so Postgres has this thing
called the vacuum think of this again as
like the garbage collector for my for
the database so it's gonna go through
and reorganize all the pages and
actually may take a while so I'll come
back to that but when it does this it's
gonna then say oh well I know that I
have a I have a free space in - so I'm
gonna compact the pages and write them
out sequentially all right it's gonna
take a while let's look at other ones so
we can do sequel server same thing I
have I have three tuples let me drop the
table start over
so now I have three two bowls select
star from our right one two three so
Postgres does start sequel server
doesn't have the CT ID it has this like
other built-in function like this and it
tells you here's the file ID here's the
page number and here's the slot zero one
two okay so let's do the same thing
let's delete a tuple insert a new one oh
yeah we can look at the old one query
and it didn't it didn't come back it
still says you know uh zero one actually
no I didn't come back it sorry take that
back let's start this over again
I missed that sorry I always remember
which one doesn't correctly or not or
not not again it's not correct which one
does it that way so we insert three
tuples do a right 0 1 2 now I
delete the the second tuple do the same
select oh did 0 R 0 - I didn't come back
yet sorry let's insert another one again
0 1 2 so so so this so this was the the
the second tube this was 2 now it's 1 it
made this - because what it did it says
when it updated page says oh I have a
free space let me compact it and write
it out right again from the high-level
part of the system we don't know we
don't care internally can do whatever it
wanted so going back to Postgres was it
one Postgres when we inserted the new
tuple I put it at the end but then I run
the vacuum and that does basically
compaction right now if we organized a
zero one three one two one two three
where that was one three four right so
the last one I want to show is Oracle
and although Oracle sponsor in the class
I will just say this their terminals
you could like you can't hit up there's
no way to go back and drop table arm
let's create a table and you can't you
can't so this is the nice shortcut like
everyday to symbolize you do inserts
like one insert query and then once two
commas to separate it sort them all once
Oracle doesn't let you do that so I have
to go do one by one so Oracle has
something called a row ID again so this
is an internal thing that Oracle's
maintaining you normally run queries you
don't see this but if you just add the
row ID column is that like a you know
internal virtual column it exposes this
information so this is some ten byte
gibberish I mean we don't have interpret
this so there is a command there's a
bunch of functions you can run again I
found this in Internet I didn't write
this
the basically deciphered this and now
you get like here's the file number the
block number and the row slot the same
way we saw for before for sequel server
okay let's do that let's let's delete
the second guy and go back can't do that
so it was 0 1 2 for the slots and out
still at 0 2 let's go insert our new
tuple alright so who says it's gonna be
at slot 1 2 okay who says it's gonna be
slot 4 or slot 3 even less nobody knows
ok
slot three right so again the main to
seacoast over compacted the page with
weren't wrote it back out Oracle and
Postgres does elite leave the empty slot
there okay again it doesn't matter to
the other parts of the system this is
just something how the system is
internally organizing tuples or slots
within the pages okay so let's go back
alright
so did I answer your question I realize
that was a long okay yeah so let's talk
about now are we doing time yes this
question is why do exposed to safety API
to the user so database systems are very
complex pieces of software people get
paid as money to maintain them and so by
exposing all the metadata you can to the
end user like administrator it just
potentially hyper help them to cipher
why it's doing certain things that's
what I would say but it you don't want
to write your application using any of
this it's not reliable right um let's
use Postgres cuz i know how to do
Postgres so going back to this so
Postgres again we've already done the
compaction with the vacuum but Postgres
will actually let you do this you can
say where CT ID let me put it up sorry
where c tige equals and then 0 1 right
so I can access the tool exactly based
on its like stores location I don't want
to do this in my application because
again at any time the data systems
allowed to reorganize it I could end up
with a different CIT ID so it's unique
like you know I can uniquely identify a
tuple but I don't want to do that
because it'll I get it screwed up again
I think the answers in is just exposing
the internals of the system to allow
administrators to understand what's
going on
yes boom
his question is what happens if you have
a if you try to name a column with that
I might trying to name a table with that
let's see that so drop table xxx create
table
xxx ID and CT ID int look who says it'll
be allowed to do this yes or no
raise your hand yes where you hand no
yes you can't do that
let's try Oracle great table
xxx heidi and row ID int nope in like it
so yes it's a reserved name there's a
bunch of other things you can't like I
can't name actually like I can name a
column this is C code like sorry
sequel server press rest okay so let's
try a create table like you can't name a
column int I don't think no you can
[Music]
never systems do different things yeah
okay don't do that that's a bad idea
all right uh have you drawn time so so
we're short in time so let me quickly
talk about tuba layouts
and then that'll set up set it up what
we're talking about for for next class
so a tuple in our world it's just just a
sequence of bytes all right if we just
we get a slot all set we just write a
bunch of sequence of bytes and we're
done and so it's the job of the data to
be able to interpret what those bytes
actually mean again and that's where
this schema comes in so the scheme is
gonna say I have an int it's 32 bits
I've been to 64 bits so when I look at
my 60 might might might my sequence of
bytes I know how to jump to different
offsets to find the columns that I want
all right so again it just looks like
this and our tuple again this is like
the starting location within an all set
within our page we'll have a header keep
track of different things like what
whether you know what what transactional
query modify this and then we'll have
the actual you know the metadata about
things like when we have null values and
then are actually tuples so do we
typically don't need to store the
metadata about the tuple with in the
tuple itself right so when we store two
but we don't say hey I have four columns
and there are this type we store that
and a higher-level metadata information
either within the page or within the
catalog pages themselves you have to do
this in in like JSON databases or
schemas databases like MongoDB because
every single tuple every single record
could be different every document to be
different so you have to store what the
metadata about what it's actually inside
of it so the inside the tuple data
itself you typically store them in the
order that you created the table so if I
say you know create table ABCDE I'll
just usually most systems distort in the
order that they happened right then that
we got created you don't have to
national model says you don't have to do
this but typically most systems do this
if you get talked about sort of you know
in memory systems that are trying to be
cache efficient
or you can reorder this so that your
word aligned for cash lines but for our
purposes we don't care right
so the last thing we talked about was
his question before about storing data
from different tables inside the same
page and I said most systems don't do
this and the the reason it the reason
why you don't wanna do this is because
again if you want the things to be
self-contained you don't want a bunch of
extra metadata about these different
tables where it does show up is when you
de normalize tables or pre join tables
so we're not talking about normal forms
or functional dependencies in this class
you don't know yet but you'll thank me
when you're older because they're
terrible
people cry every single time you try to
teach them most database classes to
teach them I don't think they're
important I
nobody does this in reality in the
practice maybe some DBAs do but but
almost nobody does so for that reason
when I first taught this class we did
two whole lectures on normal forms
we don't need to do that you just need
to know what they exist that they that
it exists and what it means so that
that's what this one slide is so we're
gonna Katz like two lectures in one
slide
okay so normalization is basically how
would we split up our database across
different tables and this sort of
naturally happens when you have foreign
keys like I have artists and albums I
could have you know foreign keys sort of
break them up and so we do this sort of
ins naturally as we design our
application now there's some cases where
we actually want to embed one table
inside another right if we want to avoid
the overhead it may be doing a join we
can say here's all the albums that
artists put out which is inline them in
in its own tuple and in that case within
a single page we could have data from
two different tables packed in the sign
beside the same page so let's look
really simple example I have two tables
foo and bar bar has a foreign key
dependency reference to the food table
so normally I would store my tuples like
this I would store them it's completely
separate all the data for the bar tables
stored in its page and all the data for
the food table is stored in this page
but if most of the time I'm trying to
join these two tables together for every
query I want to join these two tables
right get me all the foods for give me
all the bars for a given foo then maybe
what I want to do is just embed the bar
tuples directly inside of the food table
so now if you go back here like I had I
was replicating the the the the a
attribute for every single bar tuple but
now if I pack it inside of it I don't
need to repeat it I just have the
columns that are unique for the other
table right so this is called
denormalization another I think about
it's like pre joining I'm packing two
bowls inside of each other I can either
do this logically by rewriting my
application and creating tables that way
or I can do this physically which is
what we care about here and underneath
the covers we're storing our pages like
this the application can still tell us
hey I have two separate tables but
underneath the covers and our pages will
actually combine them attacking them
together right so this is the only time
I think that systems actually try to
store data from two different tables
inside the same tuples okay this is not
a new idea it's super old goes back to
the 1970s IBM first invented this when
they invented the first database system
system or the first relational database
system at IBM but it turned out to be a
huge pick to maintain in the software
and then they abandon it when they went
off and made db2 so system R was the
first relation one of the first
relational databases that are out there
but they never commercialized it never
sold it but they took up some of the
code in the 1980s and created db2 which
is still around today and so it actually
is showing up in more modern systems
today so if you get cloud spanner from
Google right if you have it when you
defined a proto protobufs
API you can actually pack in it'll pack
in the two different tables together in
the same tuple there was a start up a
long time ago ten years ago called a
Caban that basically sold a storage
engine for my sequel that did this kind
of denormalization automatically they
got bought by foundation BB even a
foundation DB got bought by Apple
so a coupon doesn't exist anymore and
then a bunch of these document databases
or JSON databases are essentially doing
the same thing right when you define
your JSON document you can pre join a
PAC in related attributes within the
JSON document itself and that's
essentially doing the same thing
okay that again that's the only time
people actually store tuples from
different tables inside the same pages
okay so we covered this and we're done
all right so again what do we talk about
today databases are organized in pages
they're different ways to track the
pages that are in our files and then
within this pages we can store them
different ways and store our tuples
inside the pages differently so for the
first assignment first programming
project we will already take care of the
page layout for you all right so well
and we already written the disk manager
for you it's when we get into the second
project you're actually gonna have to
define what the page layout is for your
your for your index that you're gonna
build okay it's next class we'll talk
about how you actually represent values
inside the tuples so we'll go eat now
inside of the bike sequences for two
bowls you talk about what the axial
average look like and then we'll talk
about storage models how are we actually
gonna represent how we organize two
posts within a within a table itself all
right any questions yes
[Music]
her question is which is a awesome
question what is test-driven development
look like for databases how do I know
I'm running queries correctly huge topic
let's talk about afterwards that's I'm
extremely interested in that I'm
actually trying to hire someone to do
that for us yesterday okay guys see you
on Monday ricochet jelly hit the deli
food usually rap is like don't drink it
you can't and if the sake don't know
your phone can of paint