[Music]
all right a lot talked about today and
joined she's in very important topic
extremely low turnout today I can only
assume because it's what 85 degrees in
in October which is crazy I remember
there being this this it's hot of you
know yeah I my parents don't believe in
global warming which is crazy they think
it's because the planets are aligning a
certain way cuz it's all big hoax which
is alright alright so we saw what joins
again joins are super important
it's probably the this is where we spend
a lot most of our time in an illiberal
Davis we're processing queries so we
it's very important for us to get it
right so the first question is why do we
even need to join right so it's it's
sort of a byproduct of having being our
relational database system and
normalizing our tables because we're
splitting them up to reduce the amount
of repetition or redundant information
so we want to break them up into
different tables like again foreign keys
or a natural way of doing this all right
you know you have andis orders and sorry
the table both the orders and every
single order can have multi t'me have a
separate table for the order items so
now if you want to run a query and say
give me all the order items for andis
order then you want to join those two
tables together and get I'll get all the
related data together so the way we're
gonna do this is through a joint
operator now the join operator is a
allows going to reconstruct the original
tuples without any information ball so
we want to do do this as efficiently as
possible
because because again for for analytical
queries the tables are gonna be quite
large so you know this could take you
know minutes hours even days depending
on what algorithm we choose so the for
this lecture we're going to focus on
joining just two tables at a time and
we're gonna always focus on doing in our
joints so two tables is probably them
two table joins us by the most
enjoying the album that's implemented in
database systems today right this is
what pretty much every single every
single major open source system and
commercial system does because it's sort
of a natural way to think about how to
break up a query into join operations
there are algorithms to do multi way joy
joins or MLA joins like take three or
more tables and join them exactly at the
same time that mostly exists in the
theoretical world although there are
some high-end systems that do support
this we can cover that in the advanced
class but for our purpose here today
we're just we want to understand the
basics of joining two tables together
and they're also going to focus on NO
equi-join so an equijoin means that
we're taking a tuple from one table and
we want to check to see whether there's
an equality match and for another tuple
in the other table
right we're not worried about less than
greater than we're not worried about
ante joins like not equals to so the
algorithms we'll talk about today can be
tweaked to support those other types of
joins it's not a major change but for a
preference we're going to focus on
equi-join just because that's the most
common one we're also focusing on inner
joins because that again in addition to
that being the most common one to do
outer join support or the algorithms we
talked about today is not a not a major
major operation a major change so in
general going forward for all the
algorithms we're going to talk about
today the thing in the back of our mind
that's that we should understand how
we're gonna organize the join operation
is that we're gonna always almost always
want to put the smaller table as the as
the left table in the joint operation
alright so think of like the query plan
tree you know you have the left side and
the right side the child's inputting
into the operator so we'll say the left
child is the one that we want to be the
smaller one when we talk about in this
and loop joins also refer to this as the
outer table right so even though some
algorithms don't have nested loops and
therefore they don't have an outer table
we'll always say outer table to mean the
left side all right so before we get to
now discussing what the algorithms are
yeah there's some other design decisions
we have to make in our database system
to talk about how all these join
operators are gonna work so again the
way to understand what a query plan is
think of this we're taking the
relational algebra of the sequel query
and we're converting it into a directed
graph or a tree structure and so at the
leaf nodes we have our access we're
accessing the tables and they're feeding
tuples up as
input into our child operators or
started parent operators so this is what
I was saying here so this would be the
joint operator so this would be the left
side and this would be the right side so
this is and this would be the outer
table and this would be the inner table
so the students nine stages we have to
figure out error what is the output of
our joint operator like what is the
actual mole little bits we're sending up
into our parent and then how we can
decide whether one algorithm one joint
algorithm algorithm implementation is
better than another so for the first one
it's going to depend on what our
database is actually implemented and and
other factors of its environment so in
general what we're trying to do is
they're trying to say for every tuple a
lowercase R in the relation big
uppercase R and any tuple that matches
in in the the other table s we want to
then produce some output because that's
you know that they satisfy the joint
predicate and we're sending that up to
the next operator in the tree and so at
a high level when we understood this
through a relational algebra we when we
first just talked about joins we just
said it was a concatenation of the two
tables of the tuples of the two table so
you take all the attributes in R and
take all the experts and s and you mash
them together and then that's the output
going up but that may not always be what
you want to do in a real system
theoretically that's okay but in a real
system we have to worry about disk read
with the worry worried about you know
how much memory we're using so we can be
a bit more careful about what we're
sending along so what we're actually
gonna use as the output of this operator
and sending it up to this next operator
can depend on our implementation of our
query processing model again that we'll
cover on Monday next week but just know
that's know it's not always the case
where I'm sending one tuple at a time I
could be sending multiple tuples at a
time could be also depend on my storage
model whether I'm a robe a system or a
column based system and then the pay
also depends on what the query is
depending on what's above me in my query
plan in my tree I may not want to send
all the attributes for the both tables I
wanna maybe send a subset enough so the
first approach we could do is actually
just send data right so we're in a copy
the values of the attributes for the
tuples that match
join predicate and then we're gonna
produce a new output to pool that we
shove up to the next guy right so say
our table looks like this R and s when
we do a join in them again we just
concatenated the attributes of our and
appending them the answers s to them and
then that's the new SP result of this
joint operator so in our query plan tree
the output is operator would be this
entire thing right so the benefit of
this approach is that up above in the
tree we never have to go back and ask
for more data from our underlying tables
because everything we you know that came
out of our and s that's produced in our
joint output so that's fantastic because
again we're not going back and reading
more stuff after the fact but it's bad
because now we're essentially
materializing this in giant tuple in my
example here I only have five attributes
so you know maybe not that big of a deal
but if I have a thousand attributes in R
and a thousand detrás in s and now I
just have this mm - pupil that gets to
be pretty wide and now I'm copying that
as my output going up above and that can
get expensive so the again the benefit
of this is that you never have to go
back and get more data you can be a bit
smarter and recognize that in this case
here for this particular query I for the
case of table are I only need the r ID
for the rest of the query plan so maybe
instead of actually sending up the art r
ID and plus plus the the name field
maybe i just send up our ID so i could
do a projection down here to start
stripping out things that i don't know
that i know I'm not going to need up
above then likewise when I as part of
the output of this joint operator I can
embed or inline a projection operator
and recognize that well after I do the
join on s ID
I don't need value and I don't need s ID
the only thing I need is the creation
date the C date field so as my output I
can do a projection and strip out that
so that only you know then essentially I
don't have to do the projection above
because it's already done for me as I
produce the output of the of the tuple
in the join alright the other approach
is what we talked about before when we
talk about column stores is that we only
now pass along the bare minimum
information we need for the for the join
keys and
then we also include the record idea
where the where we had to go find the
the rest of the data in our table so say
we do our join like this I
we're only joining on our IDE and s IDE
so the output result of the the join
operator will be just the RIT and s ID
that match and then the record ID or the
tuple ID which is in to the page number
and the offset or wherever you go find
the rest of the data and in our in our
database and then we just passed that up
into our tree and then up here when we
say oh we also need this creation date
because we have this field here we know
how to go back to s and get the rest of
the data that you need right so again
this is ideal for column stores because
it's very expensive for me to go stitch
together the tuple from all the
different columns to put it back into
sort of row base form as I shove it up
into the query plan so if I can delay as
much as possible having to do that
materialization putting all the tuple
back together into its original form
then I'm not passing along a bunch of
data up above and furthermore let's say
that I'm feeding up maybe a billion
tuples from R and s but only one or two
tuples match after the join then up
above when I go fetch that the creation
date the see date field it's you know
I'm only going and grabbing maybe two
pages it's again does this call that
this technique is called late
materialization this is what this is was
in vogue in about 1215 years ago when
the first column store database systems
came out things like Vertica and and
sort of seems like this be a huge win
Vertica told me that two or three years
ago they actually got rid of this
optimization because it turns out it
doesn't actually help you because the
cost I'm going getting this data out is
so expensive to you in the beginning you
might as well get everything you need
from the get-go and not worry about
going back getting it later because this
could be only like you know the data
you're getting could become own another
machine and now you're going over the
network to go get that data not just
like reading local disk so though and
the first column stores systems that
came out to thousands all promoted this
technique I don't know how many actually
still use it today yeah I know Vertica
does not which was very surprising when
they told me this
all right so again so this is this is
how we're gonna solve what we're gonna
shove up into the operator tree and
depends on what our environment looks
like what is what the query wants to do
the other thing we have to now consider
is how we're going to determine whether
one joint algorithm is better than
another and so the way we're gonna do
this is by basing on the cost metric of
how many iOS we're gonna have to do to
compute the joint so for the rest of
this lecture we're going to use this
nomenclature here so we'll say but that
we have on table are it's gonna have M
pages with a total of little m to Bowles
throughout the entire table and table s
will have n pages with a total of
lowercase n for tuples in NS so when you
use these these variables to determine
what the IO cost is for the various
algorithms that we'll look at today and
so the important thing to point out is
that we're only considering the the cost
is actually to compute the join and not
the cost to actually produce the final
output result because that's gonna be
constant throughout all the different
algorithms right if I do a sort
merge-join versus a nested loop join on
tables R and s right there it's they're
always gonna produce the exact same
result and therefore that cost is the
same across both of them and furthermore
for the stuff we talked about today we
don't know the number of tuples they're
gonna output because we know nothing
about what the data actually looks like
when we talk about query optimization of
query planning we do have to start
making those estimations because now we
need to start considering where to move
the joints in the query plan but for now
we were just focusing on take one joint
operator what's the best algorithm for
that and we're gonna base that entirely
on the number iOS to compute the cost
okay all right so real quickly the last
thing to talk about is the joint versus
cross-product again we're focusing on
inner echo joins today because that's
the most common thing we're not if
you're gonna bother talking about cross
products or cross joins or Cartesian
products because these are almost super
rare and you never actually really you
know need to worry about them right and
there's nothing really you can do to
make these run the cross product run
faster because it's just two for loops
just iterating one after the other and
everything matches so it's like a nested
loop join without a predicate to check
on matches the other thing also say too
is that there are B
a bunch of techniques we can apply to
our joint algorithms as we go long today
that can make things run faster but in
general there's not gonna be this one
optimization we can always do that will
work for every every single possible
scenario every single possible data set
every single possible query so certainly
again I'm gonna teach you guys the basic
of these algorithms I'll see four hash
showing one optimization we can do
because I think it's a really useful one
but for our purpose here today we're
kind of going to be sort of blind about
what the data looks like and not try to
do any sort of one-off ad hoc
optimizations okay all right so in
general there's three categories in
three classes of joint algorithms
there's the nested loop join which is
the most basic one and every single
database system that says you know
they're supporting joints at the very
very least they're gonna support
something that looks like a nested loop
join and then we'll talk about doing
sort merge join which will build on the
sorting stuff we talked about last class
and then we'll talk about hash join
which is the most important algorithm
cuz this is and that this is almost
always gonna be the fastest one that
we're gonna want to use okay all right
so let's start the beginning nested loop
join it's exactly as it sounds it's a
nest it's a four loop nest inside of
another four loop right so all you're
doing is for every single tuple in the
outer table or and you're gonna iterate
for every single tuple in the inner
table and then you just check the
predicate sin your where clause your
join clause in your sequel query see
whether they match and if so then you
admit it as the output all right it'll
be it'll be buffered as the output for
the next next tuple above so again the
parlance for outer versus inner is just
as it sounds the outer table is on the
outer for loop the inner table is on the
inner for loop and this would be
slightly confusing until what hash doing
this hash joins don't have Nesta for
this well what and we still refer to
this way again and in terms of how it
looks like in the end the actual query
plan it's it's usually designated as the
the right sorry the left operator going
into the join join query or join
operator the left input is the outer
table the right input is the inner table
all right so this is like the dumbest
thing to do to do a join why
absolutely correct so he says for every
single to point are we got to go scan s
and bring all that back into memory
every single time so we're not doing any
about locality we don't know anything
about pages or blocks at this point
we're literally just saying for every
single tuple my outer table let me go
fetch the page that has the the tuple
for my inner table so against it's super
dumb and super expensive right so the
cost for this using our variously
defined before is Big M plus little m
times n so Big M is the number of pages
in the outer table R so we have to read
every page right and then the this inner
part here is for every single tuple we
have in the outer table we have to go
then fetch every single page on the
inner table those little m times big n
so that's this sort of seems abstract
you guys because it's just much of
variables but let's actually put some
numbers into it and see how
this is okay so let's say our table our
has M page etcetera as M a thousand
pages with a total of a hundred thousand
tuples table s has 500 pages with a
total of forty thousand tuples so we
just plug and chug these these the the
the values for these variables we see
that for Big M plus little m times times
Big M we do 50 million iOS so say we
have a speedy SSD that can do an IO in
one tenth of a millisecond so roughly
100,000 to 200,000 nanoseconds per IO
which is about what a standard SSD can
do you could pay a little bit more money
and get get faster but in general that's
that's what consumer grade one can do so
now if you take this 0.1 milliseconds
times this it's one point three hours to
do that join right so all right what's
one optimization we can do to try to
speed this thing up I said before in the
beginning smaller table should be only
as the outer table so if we do that and
rerun that rerun the formula now we're
doing 1.1 hours now
you know not much better but you know it
is slightly faster so this is like this
is like super stupid this is the worst
case scenario because assume we're we're
doing four kilobyte pages then you just
do the math this to size these two
tables is six megabytes that can sit in
l3 cache so for something that can fit
on my CPU cache if I have to go get a
disco get it I'm doing one and taking
one hour right like you can do this in
memory you could do this join as two
nested for-loops in like microseconds or
nanosecond by microseconds all right it
should be super fast but if we have to
go to disk and we're not smart to how
we're going to disk then we're to pay a
huge penalty so one way to improve the
nested loop join the stupid one is to be
mindful that we have blocks we have
pages we can pack multiple tuples in our
pages so now if we just say we'll have
one block for the input
they started one block for the outer
table one block for the inner table then
for every block we fetch in the outer
table will fetch will scan through all
the tuples and for each block in the for
each tuple we'll go fetch it's right for
each block on the outer table we'll
fetch one block at a time for the inner
table and we do our join for every tuple
in the inner tape outer table block for
all the tuples in the inner table block
and we don't go to the next block in the
inner table till we have completed our
evaluation for all the tuples in the
outer block right so this is a little
bit better now so assuming that you know
again we have one block to the outer one
block to the inner never cost is Big M
plus Big M times n right before this was
little M because we were doing for every
single tuple in the outer table we were
fetching every single page in the inner
table but now for every single page in
the outer table we're fetching every
single page in the inner table so
there's a little bit better
and again what should be the outer table
the smaller one but in terms of pages
not tuples right it could be that we
have one has fewer tuples or more pages
than the other one we still always want
to base it on on
which one has the least number pages so
going back to our example we showed
beginning again plug and chug these
numbers now we can do our join in 50
seconds
still bad don't get no don't be the
wrong idea this is still terrible again
to join six megabytes should not take
fifty seconds but you know we're not one
hour we were before
so again just by being smart about
Evernote we're doing sequential access
we're reading a you know a single IO
we're getting multiple tuples just
making that simple change of our nested
loop algorithm we can cut it down to
being under a second so what if we can
generalize this right instead of having
one pay or what you know one block for
the out on Bluff in the inner what if we
have multiple blocks and so the way this
is gonna work is for the outer relation
we're gonna buffer as much as possible
in memory in B minus two blocks and then
we'll retain one block for the for the
inner relation and one block for the
output result and we can do it a little
bit better all right and again the
basically looks like this for B minus
two blocks and the interrelation then
I'll go fetch one block for the the for
B minus two blocks in the outer relation
I'll go fetch one block in the inner
relation do the to the scan across the
them and then when I'm done the inner
block go back to get the next one and
when I'm completed all the inner blocks
for my table go and get the next B minus
two blocks on the outer table so now
again plugging chugging the math instead
of having to do
mm reads and page reads only only on the
outer table its M divided by B minus two
and you take the ceiling of that because
that's tell me how many chunks of B
minus two blocks I can I can divide the
outer table into and you take the
ceiling because the last you know the
last segment of B minus two blocks may
not be exactly B minus two so you always
always round up all right so now what
happens though if the add a relation
fits entirely in main memory meaning the
size of the amount of buffers were
allowed to have is greater than n plus 2
again
- is one for the for the inner inner
interrelation or the inner table and one
for the for the output result so if we
can fit B - to all you know be mice -
Itza was exactly the size of the of the
interrelation sorry the outer relation
then we're golden because all we need to
do now is just go fetch the outer
relation once bring that into memory and
then just scan through the interrelation
once so then as M plus n so now I'm at
the I'm at 1500 I owe s and now I'm at
150 milliseconds that's starting to get
more realistic right so again this is
like the best-case scenario right if you
can fit the app if you have enough
memory to fit the ovulation of memory
you know the nested for-loops the nested
loop joint is probably gonna be good
okay for you of course now if your
database is like terabytes or petabytes
you can't do that all right
so in general why does this suck why
does the initial loop join suck well
because the word is basically a
brute-force search all we're doing is
sequential scans on the outer relation
and the inner relation we know nothing
about the locality the data we know
nothing about the data that we're
looking at right weird assuming it's
just we don't care we're blondie just
looking for for matches so if as we said
before sequential scans are always the
the fallback option for when we don't
have an index we don't can do can't do
anything smart but if we can be smarter
like if we know we have an index or as
we see in a second and the sort memories
join if we know what things are sorted
then we can make these sequential scans
be a bit bit smarter so then one of the
things that David system can do it can
recognize that if you have an index
based on the keys you want to join on
then Brittney's for the inner table then
you can use that as as part of the inner
loop instead of actually having to do
the sequential scan every single time so
there's two ways you could do this so
one is if you already have an index
available because that you know the
application created it for you then
you're golden because you just use that
again that's gonna be very common in old
tobe workloads because as we said if you
have foreign Keys B you have to have a
an index to enforce the foreign key
constraint so therefore you would use
that to find the thing you're looking
for some systems can build a an index on
the flawed essentially what a hash join
is going to be as we'll see later on but
in other systems like in sequel server
they can actually build a B+ tree on the
fly we call it a spooling index that
during the query then they run you know
run the query do the join using your
index and then when the query is done
they just throw it away again the idea
here is that the cost of doing some
punches can is so expensive that's
better off to build an index you know
and then ephemeral index right now to do
my query and then it'll throw it away
let's see how we do it in Ex nested loop
join so again all we're doing is that we
step through the sequential scan on the
outer relation again we can use use
additional buffers blocks to to not have
to go fetch you know have i/o for every
single tuple but in the inner part the
inner for loop we're now gonna do a
probe on the index and then if we find a
match we would then go check to see
whether we have a you know produced as
an output now the index does not need to
be exactly what we are join key is so
we're trying to say we join on column a
and column B if we have an index on a we
can still do that index probe to go
restrict now the number of tuples need
to evaluate just on that actuate a but
then now once we get the output we do
that additional match to see whether we
have whether B matches as well so the
index doesn't need to be an exact match
so now what's the cost of doing this
well it depends it depends on what the
index looks like so we're just going to
represent the cost of probing the index
with some constant C because again if
it's a hash table then it's you know
best-case scenario one if it's a B+ tree
then it's log n right but when you're
placed that that having to go access
every single page in the inter relation
that uppercase n with this constant and
that's in general that can be much
better much faster
so this is all you really need to know
about nested loop join like I said it's
the brute-force approach it's the most
simplest thing if any database system
says that you know a newer system says
they support joins it's more likely that
they're doing this because this is and
this is the easiest to implement so the
main things we need to mindful is that
again always pick the smaller table as
the outer relation we're gonna try to
put at the outer table as much as
possible in memory to reduce amount of
redundant IO we're doing on that and
then if possible if we have an index on
our inner table then we want to use that
otherwise we fall back to just doing a
scrunching scan okay all right so again
this is like the dumb thing we don't
know anything about the data we don't
anything about what the values look like
we just other than having an index we're
just always doing a brute-force search
so let's try to be a bit smarter and
this is what the sort merge-join tries
to do so as I said last class this is
super confusing because I'm gonna teach
you these sort merge-join
algorithm but in the sort face of the
certain version joint algorithm it can
use the external merge sort that we
talked about last time but in the
external merge sort it has his own birch
page which is different than this merge
phase so this is confusing but the only
give me mindful always like the sort
phase we just use the external merge
sort we did last class or quicksort if
it's a memory and then the merge process
will be different than what what they
did before again so two phases sort it
first spill to memory spill a disk if
necessary and then in the merge phase as
we'll see an example we're gonna walk
through the two sort of tables one by
one and do comparisons across them and
if we can see we have a match and in
some cases we may we never we only have
to look at each tuple once in the inner
relation we only always look at one
people to eat you but once in the our
relation but in the interrelation we may
also not have to go back track ever and
look at the same table multiple times
but we don't like to go jump at the very
beginning every single time the way you
have to do in a sequential scan and
that's the that's the advantage you get
by sorting ahead of time so this is a
approximation on the algorithm the basic
way it's gonna work is that after
sorting we're gonna have two cursors one
on the inner table one on the outer
table and they're going to walk
step-by-step down looking at tuples so
at each iteration if the
at a relationship cursor is pointing at
a tuple that has a value that's greater
than the inner one then we're going to
increment the inner cursor if the outer
is less than the inner then we implement
increment the outer if we have a match
we produce it as an output and then we
increment the inner so reading code like
this is difficult so let's do a visual
example so again we have two tables and
we're going to join our NS on on the odd
the ID column for both these tables so
in the very first step we're going to do
sorting and again this is just the
external merge sort or the quicksort
depending whether it fits a memory or
not so now our result is sorted and what
we're gonna want to do now is again have
a cursors walk through these two tables
so we're gonna start at the very
beginning here or maybe the cursor and
our cursor on s so the first thing we're
gonna do when they start they're gonna
go look at the the value that the
actuate their joining on the ID field in
this case here the the tuple that the
out of relation cursor is pointing to
the value is 100 and for the inner
relation cursor the value is 100 so
that's a match so we would produce that
combined tuple as our output for our for
our joining and then now at this point
we then increment the inner relation
cursor and move it down by one so now we
look at 100 again and again that matches
on this what we're pointing to here so
we produce another output and then be
incremented again and now it's 200 so
now this point 200 is greater than 100
so the we increment the outer relation
cursor so now look so so in this case
here we know that when we want to do
this evaluation between does 200 equals
200 which it does have a producer output
we don't need to go back and look at
anything else because we know at this
point the cursor is looking at 200 and
it's the first time I've seen this value
to hunter and thus up on the side of the
table so I know I don't need to look at
anything up above in the in the table so
if he were just doing a nested loop join
you don't know that you'd have to do the
scan all the way from the beginning but
because we pre sorted everything we can
say well everything above me in 200
doesn't need doesn't need to be examined
to do this joint so that's the advantage
that we're doing here
that that's the benefit we're getting a
resort merge over the nested loop join
so let's look at a case what we have to
do backtracking so the the add relation
is 200 the in relation is 200 we already
produced a match now we increment the
the interrelation and now it's 400 and
so now 400 is greater than 200
so we increment this side but now we
have 200 so if we just kept going down
and only going down down one by one we
would have missed the match between this
other 200 that we had up here so we have
to maintain some metadata on this side
to say oh I the last guy I just looked
at it looked at was 200 so as if I
increment this thing and it matches the
last one I just saw then I know I need
to go back to the very beginning when I
first saw that value on the on the
interrelation and then I can do my mash
and do my join them get the match but
then everything else just proceeds as
before
now increment back to 400 and then 400
once again is greater than 200 so if we
increment this guy so again the main the
main thing I'm stressing here is that we
may hit the backtrack on the
interrelation but you never backtrack on
the outer relation
we're only examining our relation once
so 300 is less than 400 they're not
equal so we increment the outer relation
now 400 because 400 that's a match
increment the inner relation for 500 is
greater than 400 that doesn't match and
that's that's in that's greater than the
best increment this then now we have 5 a
match 1 500 so now we increment this and
now we reach the end so we can't stop
here because again we don't know what's
coming down below us on the outer
relation and we may need to backtrack
because this next people might actually
be 500 and we'd have to go back up and
go back you know the starting point
where 500 is right but in this case here
for this example there is no match so we
keep going until eventually the both
curt retreats at the end and then the
join is complete yes
his question is going back here for this
backtrack part how would I keep track
that I I saw 200 before now I'm seeing
400 and then when this guy sees 200 I
know I need to backtrack you just say
here's here's the for the last value
that's different than the current value
I'm pointing at here's the starting
location so if you had a bunch of 200
here you know you have to jump that very
beginning right yes yes yes his point
he's correct is like if I'm down here I
finished my last one and now I'm off and
say well the last thing I saw with 500
so over here if I get to 600 I know that
600 is greater than 500 there can never
be anything below me that's going to be
matched with this so ever I could just
terminate here yes you could do that
okay so what's the cost of doing this
well the cert costs on the inner and the
outer table are just the the external
mergesort cost that we talked about
before right Suman we have to spilt a
desk so now but now the merge cost
roughly is M plus n right and the
best-case scenario I'm gonna read every
page and the outer table once and every
page on the inner table once after
they're sorted now I just showed in the
back Jackson case that's not exactly
true because if I go back here if say
four hundred five hundred one page but
then I got a backtrack to two hundred
that's on the previous page I gotta go
fetch that again but again we can't
compute that for our you know in this
example because we don't know what the
layout is of the data so we're just
gonna simplify it and just say that it's
it's it's M plus n again so the cost of
the total certain drawing on its cost
the sort phase which whatever sort our
when you want to use and the cost of
this merge phase which we approximate to
be M plus n so now if we say we have a
hundred buffer pages for our for our
simple example then we can sort R and s
in two passes again that's just using
the formula from from last class
so therefore the and then the merge cost
is just reading each 1,000 pages from
the inner I started thousand pages of
the outer the 500 pages is the inner
which is 1500 so you take the cost of
sorting our 3,000 sorting s 1350 and
then merge past 1500 you get 250 850 iOS
which is roughly zero point five nine
seconds five hundred five hundred ninety
milliseconds so again the the block
based nested loop join we can get down
to 50 seconds and now in this case here
we're now we're under a second now this
is starting to look reasonable right so
the worst case scenario for the certain
urge which is it which is rare but it
could happen is that you have every
single value on the outer table is
exactly the same as every single value
in the interval so like every every
value in the to pool and the tuples it's
just one right so sorting is just
wasting time because you're not sorting
you know you're not giving any been
from that because it's just gonna be the
same you know columns of ones all over
again and then now you're just paying
the the cost of walking through the you
know writing back to a nested we've
joined right but this is rare right this
is not like people people do stupid
things and databases but this one's
pretty stupid right and the databases we
could recognize oh I have only one one
value for this column
don't even bother doing the cert merge
just you know it's essentially calls
follows back to the Cartesian product
which is just two nested for-loops so in
that case when it's the sort merge join
actually useful well if the two tables
are already sorted on the join key then
we're golden because then we don't even
have a sort cost all right this is what
that clustered index stuff I've talked
about before if I have if I'm doing
joint on a tree and the ID attribute and
then I have a clustered index on my
table where it's sorted on the ID
attribute then I don't have a sort phase
I'm exactly where you know the data is
where I want to be and now I just have
my cursor just go through and lockstep
with each other it's also super helpful
is when the the if the query contains an
order by clause and the order by Clause
is the same you know what sort the table
or the start the result on the same keys
that you want to do a join on then I'm
getting a two for one because now I do
my cert more short merge join and then
the output is sorted in the same way
that the order by Clause wants it to be
sorted so I'm even have to do that order
by Clause so again the databases can
recognize that oh I my query looks like
this because again it's declarative I
you tell it how you want it to be sorted
and it can look at that and say oh well
you want to be sort of them as key and
you want to also join it on this key so
let me do the cert MERS join rather than
doing a nested loop join or hash joint
and then followed by an order by because
I just cut off that extra operator
entirely and that's gonna run way faster
so again it's all the same things we
talked about for in the last class if we
have an index that's already sorted in
the way we wanted to be and it's
clustered we can just use that otherwise
we fall back to the external merge sort
yes so this question is and we will talk
about this on on on Monday next week
this question is where is the output of
the of them sorting right is it cached
well so it's an inter Meera's alt for
the query ok so then it's what it's
backed by our buffer pool so the buffer
pool has this field about a disk because
our data set is too large we already can
handle that but that's why we picked me
Stern immerse or because that try to
maximize them in the mount of sequential
i/o that we're doing because we it could
be the case we have to spill a disk yeah
so it's cached and it's specific to the
one query that's running it and then we
can do the I think we talked about scan
sharing a little bit but like if we
recognize that two queries wanted to
sort the same data at the exact same
time the same way we could piggyback and
just do it once and share it across the
two of them right the high end systems
can do that I see compress cannot okay
so short merge is super super useful if
the Postgres supports this all of major
commercial maybe SS will support this
the sort of smaller newer embedded data
systems don't usually support this
they usually support nested loop join
and then if they're if they get their
together they can support hash join
I would but not everyone can do that
alright let's have a hash drawn again
this is gonna be the most important out
we're going to use to do joins because
this in general it's going to get the
best performance for a large large data
set this is this is pretty much always
what you're going to want to want to do
so the basic insight about how hash join
is gonna work is similar to how we were
doing that hash based aggregation at the
end of last class right our hash
function is deterministic meaning for
the same input the hash value will
always produce be the same thing so that
means that if we have values in the
outer table that hash to a certain thing
or certain value and then values in the
inner table that hash to the same thing
because they're equal then we can use
that to sort of partition and split
things up so that we only have the
examined things within the same hash
bucket again it's like a divide and
conquer approach alright so that's the
basic idea what we're gonna do that
we're gonna split the the our relation
up into partitions based on the hash key
and for this one
Oh we'll get to a second but this one if
it's in if it'll
if it's gonna be fit everything fits in
memory we can use a linear hash table
linear probing hash table we talked
about before like a static hash table if
we're gonna have to spilt a disk then we
can do that recursive partitioning on a
bucket chain hash table that we talked
about also before so again the idea is
that if we have two pools in the same
partition because the hash at the same
location then we only need to worry
about guys that are that are in my same
partition I don't to look across the
entire table again if the idea is we're
paying an upfront cost to split the data
up to make the search or probing process
one much faster so a basic hash joint
album has two phases in the first phase
the build phase you take the outer
relation you do a sequential scan on it
and then you're going to populate a hash
table and then in the second phase the
pro phase now you do a sequential scan
on the inner relation using the same
hash function you then probe into the
hash table you built in the first phase
and look to see whether you have a match
and if you do you produce produce it as
the output so at a hile it looks like
this right so again this what I'm saying
so about four about interest versus
outer tables so in this one we don't
really have a nested for loop we have a
for loop to build the hash table and a
for loop to do the probe but we still
were first referred to the the relation
we're going to build a hash table 1 as
the outer relation for you know just to
keep everything consistent so in the
first step the first phase we're going
to populate this hash table we're just
doing squinch will scan on this guy and
insert our big key but we want to put
into the hash table then in the second
phase we just do a sequential scan on
the interrelation probe inside this
doesn't you know it doesn't matter what
hash table implementation we're using
but we know how to always find an exact
match and if we find one then we produce
that as in our output right pretty
straightforward so the key again is just
whatever you're doing or join on the
value can depend on how you actually
want to implement your your your hash
table in your system right and as we
said before it can depend on what the
output is going to be or what the output
what the what information is needed up
above in the query plan that'll
determine what you actually want to
store so this is this classic trade-off
between storage
compute in computer science we could
store the full tuple because that's
everything we need to produce it the
output up above plus us everything we
need to do our join in our hash table
but of course now that that makes our
hash table much larger which means we
could have to spill to disk more but at
least computation entry faster to find
exactly what we want because we jump at
the hash table and we have everything we
need right there the other approach is
sort of do something like the late
materialization approach where we just
store the tuple identifier and when we
hash into the to the hash table we scan
till we find the key that the key that
we want but then we would see that we
have at this two point an affair that we
have to go fall along and get more
information that we need and so again
four column stores this approach is
usually better in general because the
hash table is much smaller
this won't be better for row stores
because it's it's you you're storing we
store all the data you need and you have
to go back and go fetch entire pages
that have the entire tuple all over
again huh so one simple optimization we
can do and this is the only sort of
other than spilling to disk this is the
only optimization we'll talk about for
joins today is for the probe side so in
the build phase as we built the hash
table we can also build an auxilary data
structure or a filter that can determine
how abouts determine whether the tuple
we're looking for is even going to be in
the hash table without actually having
to look inside of it so to do this we're
gonna we can build a bloom filter never
know what a blue throat there is who'd
who does not know what a blue filter is
okay I have backup slides for this for
this very reason I can't I I don't know
what people's background is for this
kind of stuff in algorithms so let me
teach it very quickly all right a bloom
footer is a super super useful data
structure you're gonna come across
throughout your entire life that's
awesome so it's built in the 1970s the
guide invented is named bloom and that's
why it's called that
right so it's a probabilistic data
structure that's a bitmap that can exist
that can answer set membership queries
or it set membership questions
so set membership question would be like
does this key exist in my set and I'll
come back and say yes or no it can't
tell you where to go find it it's not an
index it's a filter this tells you yes
or no but the interesting about it is
that it's a probabilistic data structure
or approximate data structure so could
give you actually false positives so
it'll never give you any false negatives
so he asked it does this key exists it
always says no then you know that's
actually true but if you ask the key
exists it may come out and say yes that
key does exist but actually may be lying
to you and then you gotta go actually
check something else I see whether
that's true or not right so it only has
two operations the basic bloom filter
can only do two things you can insert a
key and you go look up on key you can't
delete a key so here's how it works so
it's just a bitmap right so say this is
a really simple 8-bit bloom filter and
so when we want to insert a key like
Rizzo from the Mouton clan
we're gonna hash it multiple times and
then where the hash value would get out
we're gonna modify the number of bits we
have and that's gonna give us a location
in our bitmap so in this case here that
first hash mod 8 goes to 6 that goes to
that location and this mod mod egg goes
to 4 for this guy and that goes I'll a
cake that location and then all we do is
just flip that bit to 1 if it's 0 we set
it to 1 now we say we insert GZA same
thing he hash it and we get 3 for the
first hash function and we get 1 for the
second one say anything we jump into the
hash table we flip at the 1 this is
super fast we can do this extremely fast
cuz this all hang out in in CPU caches
so now we're going to do a lookup look
for Raekwon the chef right if we hash
this we get 5 and 3 great
it'll 5 points to this one it's 0 but
then it points to this one it's 1 so in
this case here because all the keys all
turn all the locations in our bitmap are
not 1 we know that this is just cannot
exist so we will get false and that's
correct and this way you never get a
false negative but we may look out for
odie beam and B hash 2 3 & 6
but now this hashes to these two
locations wet we'd bet repopulating
before
with Larissa and Jezza but we never
actually inserted ODB
so here's we're getting we're getting a
false positive right so this is bait the
blimp footers coming back and telling us
this key exists when it actually doesn't
okay balloon flows awesome again they're
super useful for a lot of things and
they're super stores like you know you
can take a billion key data set and put
it down to you know a couple couple
kilobytes or a bloom filter yes he says
can you delete a key no okay so what
would happen right so like say going
back to sorry right in this case here
right RZA went to six and four so we
flipped those bits and then just I went
to three and one there's been exam oh
but like we can have another key that
hashed me to one and two and now we want
to delete it we don't know whether that
one is from all right you know we're
we're whether we're the only one you
could turn this instead of it to a
bitmap into a counter then you can do
that but now that's getting larger we
want somebody needs something really
fast for us so that's not a blue dress
yes sirs question is how big do you
neutralize the blue filter to be
depending on the size of the data set
kilobytes if that like they don't need
to be very big and there's this and then
you can actually also vary the number of
hash functions you use and that'll
determine the number of be the your
false positive rate I the larger the
balloon close to the more hash function
you use the the bed of the false
positive rate you can get it down to
being you know I think like 1014 years
I'm gonna god it's like super small
these are gonna be used for you know all
other parts of data systems will come up
we can talk about later on but like for
our purpose here we're using them for
joins again and the different mean this
na index is that this is just telling
you what if something exists it doesn't
tell you where it exists where index
would tell you it exists and here's
where to go find it
I'm glad I included this slides because
I wasn't sure who who has seen blue
filters before
all right so the optimization we're
gonna do with our balloon filters is as
we're building our hash table which is
gonna be large and could spilt a disc
we'll also build a bloom filter for our
keys
we're just gonna be super small I can
fit in memory and so again as we
populate the hash table we build the
bloom filter and then now when we do our
probe we passed the bloom hooks are over
to this guy and before we probe the hash
table when you go probe the bloom filter
that's in memory that's super fast if
our key doesn't match anything in the
hash table and then the Blimpo that will
say you don't have a match and we stop
right there and we avoid having to do
that hash table lookup which could be
disk i/o so go jump to find the things
we want otherwise we come back to says
true then we have to go check the the
hash table because this my producing
might might have been telling us
something incorrect got false positive
yes so her question is for the bloom
filter how many hash functions you use
it depends on how you configure it my
exam oh you showed two other ones you
could have more depends how large you
make it to as well but in general I
actually I don't
yeah there's open source package sort of
lip butters I don't know the default is
I highlight for yes yes question is if
the filter his question is could be the
case that the bloom hunter has every bit
set and therefore everything values to
true yes that's where you get the size
it you know we do a certain amount so
like again we'll talk about query
planning in two weeks but like one of
things the optimizer can do is try to
estimate well here's the distribution
the values coming out of this guy right
and you need that to know how to how to
size your hash table anyway and you
would say all right well I think my key
division looks like this and therefore a
bloom filter of this size would be how I
want to you know how to size it avoid
that issue what everything set set the
one but even with a couple kilobytes
it's it's still gonna produce pretty
good results all right so this is
sometimes called highway highway
information passing the high-end systems
can do this kind of stuff and actually
well tell by distributing databases
later on in the semester but like you
can imagine now maybe a and B are on
different different machines or
different data centers
so that rather than me having to go send
messages over to the network to go do
probe in the hash join if I can just
send it over you know a couple kilobytes
or a bloom filter to the other machine
then I get what is even more filtering
on this side before I start going over
the network like this is a huge win for
that but this is this is and the reason
why is call it side by side weight
informations passing because this is
sort of breaking our model for how our
queries are gonna our query operators
execute whether they have you know these
these discrete channels are just sending
data up from from the child to the
parent and not between siblings and this
sort of violates that but it's it's a
big win so this is this is a good idea
okay so let's finish up talking about
what we have hash joints that don't fit
in memory so the if everything fits in
memory then we probably wanted to use
actually we do we just want to use a
linear probing hashing table right we
can approximate the size of the hash
table we need for depending what the
input data looks like and then that fits
in memory and that's gonna be really
fast the issue though now is if you have
to start spilling to disk now the hash
table is gonna be terrible for us
because now it's gonna be random i/o
because we're gonna take every single
key and we're gonna hash it to some slot
location in our hash table and for every
single key that could be another you
know cache miss and another to do
another page page lookup so what we're
going to want to do is we want to
convert that random access pattern and
our hash table which is the worst thing
for us in our database system and do
something that's more sequential I had
the same idea that we applied for this
the external merge sort same idea we did
for the hash based aggregation when we
spilt a disk so the technique we're
gonna use is called the grace hash join
sometimes it's called the partition hash
Doran I think the textbook refers it to
as the grace hash join but this is a
technique that's developed to do hash
joins when things don't fit in memory so
the term grace comes from this project
was academic project at the University
of Tokyo in the 1980s they built
something called a database because the
grace database machine that project
obviously doesn't exist anymore but they
had a paper that came out at the time as
part of this project that talked about
having to do a hash showing when things
don't fit in memory
then for whatever reason that term stuck
everyone refers to what I'm going to
describe here as the grace hash join who
here has ever heard of the term database
machine database appliance perfect okay
so a David as machine or Davis
appliances like specialized hardware
that you buy for a database system so
think about right you know right now
when you when you you want to run
Postgres what do you do you go spin up
an instance on ec2 you go download
Postgres and then you set up and
configure it for your instance sighs yes
you can get you know RDS it's hard to
pick configure but in general most
people are running you know deploying
these databases themselves on their own
hardware so the idea of a database
appliance is that you can by harbor from
a bender that's already been set up and
tune for a database system so you don't
worry about how to set anything up
yourself so all the high-end companies
will sell you very expensive very very
nice enterprise servers that are tuned
specifically for for our database system
so IBM has this thing called Netezza
which they they sort of killed off but
they would sell you a rack machine that
had mateesah already set up for you
clusters was a startup that came out of
a o L and then they got bought by
Percona
last year this year they should sell a
version of my sequel that would run on
our specialized program the most famous
one and probably most expensive one is
the Oracle Exadata
and this is everywhere this is like you
buy these huge rack machines that have
the Oracle data warehouse running it
inside it for you like like like we're
talking like millions and millions of
dollars and there's some places that
spend a hundred dollars a year on
running Exadata it's very expensive and
so a Database Machine is think of like
appliance that you know that's tuned
specifically for a database system but
then they add in special hardware like
custom a6 that are just for running your
database system so the grace database
machine that they built in the 1980s it
had special hardware to do hash joins
very efficiently so in this is this is
sort of how people built databases in
the 1980s and then that all sort of went
out of vogue everybody wants to run a
commodity Harbor now because by the time
it took for you to come up with your
custom hardware for your database system
and then actually you know favit and
actually produce it and manufacture it
tell or whoever came out with new chips
that also you know they're already ran
faster than what you started with and
you lost all benefits
eisah most database systems run on
custom hardware other than like this
super high-end stuff from Oracle there
are some newer startups that have come
out in the last year so this is this is
a slide from yellow brick this is a
newer database appliance vendor that
sells specialized flash controllers
running on you know running their
particular database system but most
people don't run this kind of stuff
unless you have a lot of money okay so
the hash the great hash join has two
parts in the build phase we're gonna
split up both tables now based on the
hash key and write the amounts of
partitions so the regular has joined we
only sorted hashed one side and build a
hash table for that and then we probed
on the other side now we're gonna do is
just split up into two separate hash
tables on both sides and then do a
nested loop join for the partitions that
match I'll show what that looks like in
the next slide so again on the outer
table we're gonna have a hash table for
it and we're just cash all our values
and populate this guy and so this won't
be a linear probe hash table this will
be a bucket chain hash table right
because we could have this we want to
have things that hash to the same
location all get mapped to the same
partition the same set of pages we don't
want something that hashed here landing
down here same thing now on the other
side right hash all the values produce a
hash table and now we're just gonna
number these these these levels as our
as our partitions right so now in the in
the probe phase when we do our join
right after getting the hash table we're
just gonna take all the the buckets
within one partition and now just do a
nested for loop right again the idea
here is that because we've already
partitioned them with the hash function
at the very beginning we know all the
data we could ever need to examine for a
tuple that exists and this side of the
of the the join and this bucket can only
exist in this side all right can't exist
anywhere down here so we don't need it
when we when we when we scan everything
here we don't need to look at anything
else
right it's sort of the same idea we did
and the sort Mary is doing because we
sort of think things ahead of time we
know what the boundaries are where there
could be possible you know matches for
tuples and on the outer table so if
everything fits in memory then this is
fantastic
right because member I should in the
very beginning when we tell me that you
look join if everything that's in memory
then this is the fastest way to do this
right there's no magic building hash
functions is wasted instructions all
you're doing is doing you know single
instruction or a small instruction to do
the comparison and there's doing fast
for loops to these things even the
compiler could start unrolling this loop
as well yes yeah yeah so he says
collisions can collisions can occur
right because two different values that
are couldn't hash to the same thing well
I can just remember human brute-force
search for the two the bucket in the
bucket in memory then who cares for
those collisions now if everything
collides to the same thing then this
starts spilling it yes then we have a
problem all right and we can handle that
through it's called recursive
partitioning and this is sort of them
later this is the technique I was
talking about last time with the hash
aggregation but we didn't go into
details of it but we can basically
recognize that if we start spilling the
buckets
within a given partition we start adding
more buckets and the chain keeps getting
longer and longer
because we have collisions then we can
just do another round of partitioning
and split up into even more buckets do
even more sub partitions and then that
way the idea is that when we do that
that that bad nested loop join
everything fits in memory question is do
1:1 mapping still haven't yes next slide
okay let's see how we do this so again
this this is on the outer table you run
the hash function and we get create a
bunch of bunch of buckets to be
partition so say this one the chain gets
super long we keep spilling out two new
more buckets so if we recognize that
there's some threshold to say well we've
gone past some water mark to say we've
spilled to too many pages
too many buckets we can then just run
the another hash function on this guy
and then split up the even more sub
pages
all right sub buckets so with all the
for the first hash function we have a
bunch of guys map to partition 1 and
then that overflowed so then for
position 1 we ran another hash function
again it's the same hash function just a
different seed value and then we split
out into more more buckets then now on
the when the we do the probe on the
interrelation if we hash to anything
that has not been split before so we'd
have some metadata to say well if you're
if you're going to hash you're going to
partition 0 or going to partition n the
first hash function is fine right so now
I can find exactly what I'm looking for
it would cross these pages here if
though if I hash to partition 1 then I
would recognize oh why I had to split
that on the build side for the adulation
so let me go ahead and run the second
hash function and then I'll find out
really where I really need to go and he
games key you keep doing this over and
over again until you get things to fit
in memory because worst case scenario
you know the the the column you're
joining on the actuaries you're joining
on only has one value it's always gonna
hash you the same thing
so therefore recursive partitioning is
this waste of time in that case you know
you just fall back to the nest loop join
because there's no joint algorithm that
can make that run faster simple and
again so we apply the same technique for
that the hash based aggregation we
talked about last time right if we our
buckets get too full then we just do
another round of partitioning so what's
the cost of this of doing this this
partition hash drawn well assuming there
we have enough buffers to fit everything
in memory to do the the join part across
partitions it's going to be 3 times n
plus n so the 3 comes from in the first
phase we do the partition it's one pass
through m and n the pages of the out of
the pages in the in relation one pass to
read and then another round of writes
rank is rich because what we're just for
every single page we read on the
interrelation we're running another page
on the adulation
then the second pass is now to do the
join part where we're just again just
doing a nested for loop join Nessa loop
join on the buckets within the same
partition and that's just one pass
through all the pages as well so the
again the partition phase is two times M
plus n prophase is does n plus N and
then we just put the the numbers to this
all right now we can do our join in 0.45
seconds
so the sort merge joined best-case
scenario was 0.59 590 milliseconds that
now we're down to four and a 50
milliseconds that's pretty good all
right and this is why the hash join is
always gonna be preferable any questions
okay
so just finish up as I said most of
times about today if we if the datum
knows something about what the what the
tables hash tables are to look like or
what the tables are I'm I'm reading into
or gonna look like then it can try to
size the the hash tables or the buffers
accordingly so everything fits in memory
a linear probe hash table is what we
want to use if we're at this filter disk
then we can use the partition approach
with a bucket hash table the if you
don't know the size then we could fall
back and use a dynamic hash table like
the the linear extendable or but those
perches are much more heavyweight to do
joins than the simple like bucket hash
table in a professional so in this case
here because we're we're going to do a
lot of probes and a lot of insertions
into our hash table you know it's as
simple as usually gonna be better for us
all right is to summarize the different
costs of the things we talked about
today right the stupid national OOP
joint could take one point three hours
if we had everything in we use a block
nest book join then we take 50 seconds
the index one depends on what the index
data structure we're using so we can't
actually give an exact cost for that but
then the server's join was zero point
five nine seconds and then the hash join
was was zero point four five
yes so it's questions what scenario
would I not know the size of of the
outer table so in this example other
thing I showed today was one query that
joins two tables and we said we were
doing a two-way joint operator so the
operator took two tables produce the
output right join them increase the
output what if I have three tables to
join so again if I'm doing a two-way
joint operator
I joined instead of tables a B and C I
want to join them I join a and B and
then the output of a and B is now joined
with C so unless I can have super
accurate estimations on what the output
is going to be on you know for the joint
when a B I may not know how to size
things up above now for us like it
depends on how you do query execution
the query processing we'll talk about
this on Monday but I could do a pipeline
approach where for every single to
polite output of an operator I then
immediately feeds up to the next
operator and do whatever it is I want to
do in that one so now that's the
streaming case sort of like you're I'm
incrementing building my hash table you
know in the second joint I want to do or
I could just say take the all the output
of my join put into a bunch of buffers
now I know these excise and then I can
size everything so in some cases you do
in some cases you don't furthermore the
further the more joints you have the
worse your estimations get because the
cost models are always terrible in query
optimizers yes as question is in yeah
and for this one it should this be a low
case and yes
I'll fix that thank you okay
so the main takeaway for you guys going
forth in the real world is that hash
join is always gonna be preferable to
everything else except if we if we went
things to be sorted as the output ahead
of them or things are already sorted for
us in which case the sort merge join is
gonna be preferable but nine times out
of ten if you take like Postgres or any
commercial database system from what
I've seen they've always pick a hash
drawn and this is what sort of separates
the high-end expensive or well-written
open-source databases
from the you know the the off-brand
things because they're to be able to do
both and reason about in the system
what's the right what's the right album
I want to use and then this is the
beauty of the relational model and
sequel at the same sequel query could
then choose either these other either
these algorithms we talked about today
and I don't have to go back and change
anything in my application to make that
work the data systems can do that for me
yes this question is yes question is are
all these things true that I'm talking
about here is that true if you're doing
outer joins or inequality joins or other
anti joints things like that for inner
versus outer join actually outer join I
don't think you can do actually outer
and I think you can do everything for
the for inequality joins arranged joins
you have to use sort merge because you
there's no locality to values in the
hash table right don't find me all the
keys that are less than this other key I
have to use a B+ tree I have to use a
the sort merge join for Auntie joins
voice if something doesn't equal
something hash drawings are usually
better I actually almost always better
okay
and actually another another extension
to your question is is this still true
on single node databases or distributing
databases yes well we'll cover that in
the end of semester but in general yes
because again instead of reading from
disk I'm reading from the network that's
even worse
so these to replace disk i/o from with
never connect iOS and it's still the
same yes
but if it's not skewed right
she actually should be uniform data if
it's uniformly distributed sorting Zrii
great for that if it's heavily skewed
then sorting is bad but you still have
the issue where everything's hashing to
the same thing okay so now Monday next
next the next week we will then now just
talk about how to compose all these
different operators we've talked about
and actually run them you know from end
n actually it'll execute queries so I've
alluded this multiple times while the
processing models of pushing data up to
from one opportu the next now we can
actually see how that's actually gonna
be implemented and then we're also
talked about how the student can be
architected to run queries in parallel
right I have multiple cores I have
multiple threads how am I going to
design a system to run multiple queries
at the same time and also take the same
query and split it up and run on
multiple threads at the same time right
and that'll segue into or that'll lead
into a discussion at the end of the
semester when we talk about distributing
databases because that's essentially
what you want to do as well when take a
single query and break it up across
multiple machines and run that in
parallel okay
all right so we're dumped today enjoy
the 88 degree weather outside or I don't
know what that is it's LCS
he's rich z19 my system I'm blessed
let's go get the next one get over there
will be Sun ricochet jelly hit the deli
for the boat one naturally bless ya what
rap is like the laser beam the fools in
the bush say nothing like a king wrap
the bottle of us a nice nifty go don't
feel like drinking a pony - you drunk
you can't cross the line and if the sake
don't know your phone can't a pancake