[Music]
all right right so so last lecture I
think Matt covered two-phase locking and
two-piece locking is a mechanism that
the database can use to essentially
generate serializable schedules at
runtime
and it relies on locks to be able to do
that today we're going to be talking
about is a collection of protocols that
don't rely on locks but instead rely on
on time stamps at a high level maybe
with a good way to think about this is
that two phase locking assumes that
there's gonna be a lot of contention
inside of the inside of the transactions
that are executing inside in the
database right so if there's a lot of
contention then it's obviously I've
edges to be defensive and take a lot of
locks so anytime you want to read or
write into into a database object you
acquire these locks so in that sense
it's quite pessimistic on the other hand
you can view time stamp ordering based
techniques as more optimistic right you
allowed the database to operate and read
and write data without actually
acquiring locks and at the end of the
day you sort of racket you're able to
correctly reconcile the correct
serializable schedule at the end of the
day and we'll talk about how this is
actually done inside inside of the
database there's actually going to be
two times time ordering protocols we're
going to talk about in this lecture one
of them is actually called time stamp
ordering or basic time stamp ordering
and another one is gonna be called the
optimistic concurrency control so it's a
little bit confusing because they're
both optimistic and they're both
timestamp ordering this is just the the
nomenclature that the community has come
up with alright so let get started the
basic idea for these timestamp based
protocols is that it's a mechanism that
the database can use to assign numeric
values to time stamps that predefined
the the commit order of these
transactions you can assume that there's
going to be a new function here called
TS that given a transaction gives you
the timestamp for that transaction and
so what the database tries to guarantee
is that if a transaction TI has a
timestamp that's less than the
transaction TJ then in the serial
schedule it's as if TI had occurred
before TJ inside of the database okay so
how is this done like what are these
timestamps look like the timestamps are
sort of unique fixed numeric values and
they have a couple of interesting
characteristics that characteristics
that the database has to maintain the
first one is that these timestamps have
to be monotonically increasing okay so
they have to always go forward in time
and increase in time the second thing is
that they have to be unique values right
so you can ever have two transactions
have the same timestamp because of this
monotonically increasing characteristic
so again assume that the database now
has this new function this TS function
that's able to take a transaction ID and
return to you the timestamp for that
transaction and these these different x
time protocols have different mechanisms
by which and time points at which they
actually assign these timestamps to the
transactions an important characteristic
is that these timestamps don't
necessarily have to correspond to the
wall clock time because they could be
assigned to the transaction at any point
during its execution not necessarily
when it enters the system not even
necessarily when it's about to commit
right so different protocols have
different mechanisms by which and time
points at which they actually assign
timestamps to transactions there's a
there's a few different ways on how you
actually source a timestamp for a
transaction okay and I've listed this a
few listed here the simplest thing you
could do is just ask the CPU okay what
is the current time right because time
is always increasing you can assume that
this kind of makes sense all right but
there's a there's a few drawbacks can
anybody think about a few drawbacks for
using wall clock time or a real time as
a timestamp yeah so that doesn't really
matter as long as you're going to the
same computer and as long as the time
the time is monotonically increasing
then you should be okay right so that's
a good point right so if you have
distributed disability-based and it's
difficult to keep these time points in
sync what's another problem with using
wall clock time
you can turn back the clock when would
you actually turn back the clock sure
yeah so there could be some skew in the
actual ganya granularity which you took
track time is there another and another
possible drawback yeah so you don't
actually have to keep duration of time
you just need like one point like this
is time point one time point two and
it's increasing so it's not necessarily
by duration is just about a point in
time okay so a clue is that it's gonna
happen this weekend yeah exactly yeah so
a day like say day that daylight savings
right so it could be the case that you
know you're operating on the weekend and
then at random at a at a random point
your clock back goes back an hour and
your your timestamps are pretty much
screwed okay
another option is actually to use these
logical counters right so you can think
of having just a register register and
the CPU dedicated to having a mono time
monotonically increasing 32-bit 64-bit
value are there any drawbacks or
potential downfalls for this approach
yeah yeah so the distribution aspect is
still an important factor but assume
that there's one counter for the CPU and
it's really fast to increment it without
at requiring locks like you can do an
atomic addition or something like that
are there any problems with using this
logical counter so I said
two bits or 64 bits what happens if you
run out of 32-bit values then you
saturate your Edition and you roll back
right so your counter is now going
backwards in time so that's one of the
problems with this approach
so most systems actually use this hybrid
approach which is like a physio
physiological thing and it sort of
matches both the physical counter and a
logical counter to make sure that
everything sort of works out so the
system clock one problem is you have
daylight savings times right so at a
point in time one day like say daylight
savings occurs your time you time move
backs or moves back an hour so now your
time is not monotonically increasing
it's not going back in time okay
right so just to give you an idea of
what the agenda is gonna be today so
we're gonna talk about something called
the basic time stamp ordering protocol
then we're going to talk about
optimistic concurrency protocol which is
also a timestamp based protocol and then
we're going to talk about a partition
based time stamp hoarding protocol which
alleviates some of the bottlenecks then
regular time snowboarding protocols have
and then we're going to talk about
isolation levels okay so let's get
started
so with these times time ordering
schemes the general idea is that you
want the transactions to proceed in the
system reading and writing objects
without actually acquiring locks okay to
make this possible you know you have to
add some extra metadata to all of the
database objects to make this possible
specifically you have to add two extra
timestamps to every single tuple in the
system you have to add a read time stamp
which represents them time stamp of the
transaction the most recent transaction
then read this item and a write time
stamp which is the time stamp of the
most recent transaction that wrote into
this this tuple and in the system and
then as the transaction is is is going
through its operations it's just going
to make sure that it can actually read
this tuple by leveraging the time stamps
that are associated with this tuple okay
now and I'll talk about how this is done
so for reads there's an invariant that
you have to make sure before you're
actually allowed to read a value from
the database system you have to ensure
that the time stamp so you read your own
time stamp for this transaction TI
you have to make sure that it's less
than the right time stamp for this tuple
in the system okay does that make sense
what does that mean that me that means
that's essentially making sure that
there's no other transaction that's
written into the system yeah there's no
other transaction in the system that's
wrote into the into this tuple that
should have read your but who's to say
you're not reading a value of the tuple
from the future right so there's a
transact transaction in the future
that's overwritten the database value
that you should now be reading that's
essentially but that's a problem and
when this happens you essentially have
to abort and when you abort you have to
make sure that you start with a newer
transaction a newer timestamp than the
one that you had when you initially
began the transaction does everybody
sort of understand why you need to
assign a newer timestamp what would
happen if you had the same timestamp you
had before exactly you'd run into the
same problem right you have to that's
because mod because you have to ensure
timestamps are monotonically increasing
you have to get a new timestamp to avoid
this problem yeah so if your timestamp
is the same as a right timestamp what
does that mean
exactly
you can read it you can read it right it
should be repeatable reads it's
perfectly fine yeah so in this scheme
other times times are assigned when you
begin that's when begin the transaction
okay so if this invariant is invalidated
you essentially have to abort but on the
other hand if you're actually allowed to
perform the read then you you modify the
read time stamp for that for this tuple
to take the maximum of whatever the read
time stamp is right now and what your
own time stamp is does anybody know why
you have to take the maximum
times have to be monotonically
increasing rate you could have a
transaction that's newer than you update
the read time stamp but you can't set
back the time stamp back to what you
were because you're older right time
times have to be monotonically
increasing so you have to take the
maximum or whatever it is right at this
point in time when you read it and
what's your time stamp is so this is
important okay so once you've updated
the time stamp you now have to make a
copy of this tuple into some local
private workspace that's only visible to
you so that you can ensure that you get
repeatable reads so there's a assume
that there's some there's some tuple
that you want to read right and the
right time stamp is from a transaction
that's newer than you that's in the
future right you shouldn't be able to
read that value right you should be
reading the value that existed before it
wrote before the new transaction wrote
it so that's why it hidden validates you
yep yep because you now appear in a
different order in the serial order
right you shouldn't because your time
stamp is newer than the one that wrote
to it before you logically appear after
this transaction in the serial order
yeah go ahead
so this is not I don't think it's
covered in the book but you have to make
sure that you have to make a local copy
so that you can issue repeatable reads
so you can imagine that at rent another
transaction comes in and updates the
system but you have to be able to read
the same value that you read initially
right but if you but if the if you allow
it another transaction to update the
value here then you would invalidate
this this this invariant top and you
wouldn't able to read it but you
actually should be able to read it right
because you wrote it you read it in a
transaction the consistent state yeah
that's a that's a very good point I
think you're alluding to the fact that
there could be starvation where you have
consistently consistent in boards that's
a that's a drawback of this approach and
we'll get sort of get to that later in
the presentation okay so this is just
for reads you have a similar similar
story for writes okay so if your
transaction I if your timestamp is less
than the the read time stamp of the the
object that you're trying to write into
that means it's a newer transaction that
read a stale value a value that you that
should have been coming from you as a
transaction but as is not anymore so
that's a violation of the of this time
step boarding protocol similarly if you
have a if your time stamp is less than
the right time stamp of another of the
of the object then again there's a new a
transaction that essentially overrode
your value and again that's a violation
and the idea is that if either of these
conditions are true you have to abort
and again start with a newer timestamp
value and begin the entire process again
if on the other hand these this is a
it's a valid right then you have to
update the right time stamp for the
tuple and and you're essentially you
essentially done you have to also make a
colloquial reads you you read your local
copy instead of going back to the in in
to the databases global stay
okay okay so let's walk through an
example hopefully this will clear things
up a little bit so we have two
transactions here and it's just assumed
that you can only execute one
transaction one operation at a time so
you can assume single core single thread
and in this database
we now have annotated all of the the
tuples we have all of the objects here
with the read time stamp and a write
time stamp okay so let's get started so
we have t1 and t2 when they entered the
system they were assigned a timestamp
assume that T 1 is assigned a timestamp
of 1 and T 2 is assigned a timestamp
book to write pretty simple then you do
the read so T 1 does a read of B you
look at the write time stamp for B it's
0 1 is greater than 0 so you update and
the read time stamp to 1 then we do a
contact switched into transaction 2 and
T 2 now wants to do a read of B if you
look at the write time stamp and you're
good to go so you update the read times
time to take the maximum of what it was
which is 1 and the new timestamp 2 and
you get 2 all right now you do a write
so T 2 wants to do a write of B you look
at the write time stamp and the real
time stamp your greater than both so you
update the write time stamp of B to 2
okay now you do a context switch back
into t1 t1 wants to do a read of a it
looks at the the write time stamp of a 1
is greater than 0 so you update the read
time stamp to be the maximum of 0 1 and
you're good to go
sorry yeah you update the read times
time to 1 now you come back over to
transaction 2 and 2 wants to do a read
of a you look at the write time stamp of
a 2 is greater than 0 you update the
real-time read time stamp to 2 now and
then finally t2 wants to do a read of a
so it looks at both the read time stamp
on the write time stamp of a it's
greater than both of them so that that's
for the right is valid and yeah so no
validations exist no no no violations
exists so both transactions are saying
and you can commit both of them alright
this is this clear okay good so let's
walk through another example so it's the
same setup here all the trends all the
initial timestamps are 0 T 1 and T 2
enter the system T 1 gets transact gets
a timestamp 1 T 2 gets x times 2 all
right so in this scenario T 1 wants to
do a read it's it's it's a it's a good
read so it updates the the read time
stamp do a context switch and now T 2
wants to do a write of a it checks the
write time stamp and the wait time stamp
it's valid so it updates the write time
stamp to 2t 1 now is trying to do a
write of a so checks the right times
time at 3 times 2m it's no longer valid
because you have it the time stamp of 1
which is 1 is less than the right time
stamp of a which is 2 this is a
violation so T 1 actually can't commit
it has to abort is that clear
you can think about this as like in the
serial order because T 1 has time stamp
1 and T 2 s times n 2 T 1 should appear
before T 1 and the serial order so this
is obviously going to be a violation
because this read here it's gonna be
aborted okay sorry so there's actually
an optimization that we can make here to
avoid aborting in this specific scenario
right you can think about it as in
physical time what's happening right T 2
is writing to something but then it's
being overwritten by T 1 so do we really
need this right no I think the
observation is you actually don't need
it what you could have is because we've
maintaining a local every transaction is
maintaining a local copy of the soup of
the tuples this right here can can
essentially be ignored by the system
right because externally this right is
what's valid and as long as this right
is externally valid then you don't
actually need this one externally within
the transaction you still need this
right because you have to be able to
read your own rights
so this
observation leads to an optimization
that you you can apply in these time
stamp based systems call the Thomas
Wright rule and the idea is that if
you're trying to write into an object X
as before if your time stamp is less
than the the read time stamp for that
object you still have to abort and start
with a newer trend a new a new a time
stamp but if the time stamp is less than
the write time stamp of the object which
means there's a newer transaction that
wrote into this object you can actually
just ignore ignore the right altogether
you have a local copy of the write that
you can now read but externally it's
okay to ignore this right yeah yeah yes
so this right is only important to t1
right so it's not it doesn't really I
don't actually have to propagate it back
to the database because it's gonna be
overwritten by this right because in the
serial order this happens first and then
this hip this happens okay because this
has a transaction time stamp of 1 this
has a time stamp of - right yeah so this
optimization and it's actually quite
useful in specifically this specific
scenario it allows you to have the
actually actually commit this this this
this schedule so this is the same
example as before t1 begins write reads
a updates 3 timestamp t2 begins does a
right now we recognize that this right
should normally be invalid we actually
but by applying the Thomas write rule we
don't actually update the write time
stamp or the value hey but we just
maintain this local copy we ignore it
and we allow T went to continue all
subsequent reads for this read all
subsequent reads of a in times in
transaction one occur in the local copy
with this value okay
yeah yeah so that's essentially basic
time stamp ordering like two phase
locking is up it's a mechanism for the
database to generate conflict
serializable schedules as long as you
don't apply this to this Thomas Wright
rule okay it does you can prevent it
deadlocks altogether because as you're
similar to how two phase locking works
for every operation you're performing on
the database you're making sure that
there's a this is a valid operation it's
sort of like deadlock prevention right
you're incrementally generating this
utilisation graph and as soon as you
detect and detect a cycle you
invalidated you aborted in two phase
locking here
you're incrementally checking for every
operation whether it's valid or not
based on these timestamps and then
aborting eagerly as eager as possible
okay one drawback to you which I think
one of the students led to is you could
have a possible you have the possibility
of starvation right you have it you can
think of a long transaction that's been
running for a long time and then you
have these short transactions that are
performing that exist for a very short
period of time update a few tuples and
then commit and leave these are
essentially going to invalidate all the
old transactions causing conflicts
causing a cyclical aborts okay so so
another thing that we should talk about
here is these these time step boarding
protocols they allow they permit
schedules that are not recoverable okay
so what is a recoverable schedule so a
schedule is recoverable if a transaction
only commits if all the previous
transactions that it relied on data for
from also have committed you can think
of it as like they like Casco Attucks
cascading abort
right you want to make sure that if you
read a value from it that's updated by
another transaction that that
transaction commits before you commit
basic time stamp ordering does not
guarantee this for you okay so I want to
talk about how this the specific recover
the specific characteristic is violated
by a basic time stamp ordering so
imagine
we have the same setup here we have two
transactions t1 and t2 t1 has time snap
1 T 2's times time 2
so t1 does a write of a t2 does a read
of a and then a write of B so in this
serial order
t1 occurs first and t2 occurs second so
this read can now read this right and
that's okay
it does some right of B which is OK in
commits right so t2 has committed at
this point but let's say later on in the
in the system this transaction has
aborted the problem is that we've now
notified the client we've notified
externally to the world that this
transaction is committed but it read a
value from a transaction that aborted
right so this is actually invalid not
it's not a it's not a recoverable
schedule because when the system comes
back we have to recognize that this is
aborted and that we should not apply
these rights okay so this is not a
recoverable schedule but it is permitted
by the basic time stamp order and
concurrency protocol all right yeah so
so t1 aborts after t2 is committed and
this this violates the recoverable
schedule requirement okay so I think a
lot of people are sort of picked up on
this but this this these basic time
stamp ordering that the protocol has a
lot of overhead right so every time you
do a write or read you need to now copy
it into your your local workspace so if
you're updating or reading and writing
billions of two poles you have to make
billions of billions of copies per
transaction in a local memory space
right and that's obviously a lot of
overhead
another thing that again was picked up
by one of the students is that you could
have starvation by from long load from
long running transactions by short
running transactions that quickly update
one or two tuples and then require the
long running the long running
transaction to abort and we start
so so what can we do if you think about
it right so two-phase locking and this
basic time stamp recording protocol that
I just talked about they're also
somewhat pessimistic right so in
two-phase locking as soon as you read
and write a value from the database you
have to acquire some block to protect
yourself from other transactions in the
system with basic timestamp order and
you're kind of doing the same thing
right every time you want to read and
write a tuple you have to make sure that
the timestamps align just right so that
you can perform the operation that you
want to perform right so they're both
assuming that there's a lot of
contention in the system and try to
prevent this from prevent something
wrong from happening but what if you
make a different assumption what if you
assume that there's not going to be a
lot of contention in the system what
different types of optimizations can you
apply assuming that there that
transactions are essentially a very
short-lived and are essentially conflict
free right can you be even more
optimistic than this stuff that we've
talked about so far and we'll talk about
one example one concurrency protocol
that makes this assumption and applies a
lot of different types of optimizations
okay and it's called as the name
suggests optimistic concurrency control
so it takes a very optimistic view of
how the transactions run in the system
so OCC optimistic concurrency control
was was written here at CMU by HT Cong
this he's no longer professor here I
think he said at Harvard but it's pretty
cool that one of the you know premier
concurrency control protocols was
actually written here at CMU okay oops
the the idea is as in the basics time
time time step boarding protocol every
operation you perform what you do is you
first make a you first make a local copy
of that data into a local thread local
private workspace okay any time you want
to read a copy any time you want to read
an element from the database you first
make a copy from it and then you're good
to go if you want to make an update to
it you first make a copy of it into your
local workspace and then you apply the
update to your local copy okay you don't
perform an in-place update anymore all
right
then once all of this work is done that
and you're ready to commit you have to
essentially make sure you have to
validate that all the changes you make
are transactionally consistent with the
rest of the transactions that are gone
running in the system concurrently with
you okay and I'll talk about how this is
done specifically in the workspace
in the following slides sorry
so after this validation step after the
database has Vallot has insured yeah hey
listen your transaction is good to go we
have to now install all the changes that
are in your private workspace into the
global database system and we have to do
this atomically okay and again I'll talk
about how this is done in the system
okay so the way the OCC works is that
it's split up into three phases the
first phase is called the read phase
then you have the validation phase which
is essentially gonna validate that this
transaction is actually still valid and
doesn't conflict with anything else and
once a validation phase is done then you
actually have to install your changes
from a private workspace into the global
database all right so the read phase is
a bit of a misnomer right you're
actually allowed to do both reading and
writing in it so I didn't want to make
sure that that gets across I actually
don't even like the phrase read phase I
actually prefer work phase where you're
doing the actual work for the
transaction okay so in the work phase
you're making your reads and writes
you're updating values you're reading
values all in a private workspace in the
validation phase when the interaction
the transaction is ready to commit the
database does a bunch of as you know
sanity checks to make sure that that's
true this is a valid transaction and
then in the write phase you atomically
install all your changes into the into
the global database okay so let's just
quickly walk through an example of how
this is going to work okay so the first
thing is that we have the same database
we had before but we've removed the
right time the read time stamp now we
just have a write time stamp the second
thing is we've now demarcated the
boundaries for all the phases we've
we've really just done this for
illustration they did the transaction is
not going to specifically say hey I want
to start my read phase I'm gonna start
my valid a phase and then the commit
phase this is it's going to be done it's
gonna be handled for you by the database
system itself much like how the two
phase locking protocol is implemented
for you by the database not by the
transaction right the transactions just
doing a bunch of reads
right okay so another thing I think I
want to point out is that unlike basic
time stamp or during the transaction
that time stamps aren't necessarily
assigned when the transaction entered
the system okay they're actually
deferred to a later point in time and
we'll get into how that's done okay so
we're ready to get started we begin
transaction t1 it now wants to a read of
a so it constructs a private workspace
that is essentially somewhat of a copy
of the database upon read it's going to
read or make a copy of a into its
private workspace along with the the
write time stamp for whatever it read
from the database system now t2 begins
and it begins its read phase when it
begins a read phase it has to construct
this private workspace for transaction
t2 it does a read of a into its private
work space along with the the the write
time stamp and then we're good to go so
now we get to the rally to the
validation phase so this is essentially
t2 saying to the database hey listen I'm
ready to commit what it does is the the
database will now enter the validation
phase 42 it's at this point that that
transact that the time stamp is assigned
to the to the transaction okay so so far
this transaction doesn't yet have a
timestamp you can assume that its
timestamp is infinity here when and when
t2 enters the validation phase it gets a
timestamp of one right so what does it
do it now it doesn't have to do any any
sort of validation because there's none
nothing to do B the validate it's a
read-only transaction so it begins the
write it falls into the write phase
there's nothing to write and then it
commits and everything is sort of done
okay that's a pretty simple example and
we do a context switch back into t1 t1
now wants to do a write so it makes a
modification to its local copy and it
assigns a time stamp of infinity okay
why does a time stamp have to be
infinity
does this transaction have a timestamp
yet it doesn't have a timestamp right
because it has an interval edition you
only get a timestamp when you enter a
location so if it doesn't have a
timestamp then it doesn't know what it's
types of time sampling is gonna be so it
assumes infinity right and it will fill
this in when it begins a validation
phase which is here so it now begins a
validation phase it gets a timestamp
assigned to it too and then when there's
no other concurrent transactions running
in the system so the validation phase
completes and in how now has to write
its local copy all of its local changes
into the global database space when it
does is copy it has to update the write
time stamp for this tuple a to the Trent
to the timestamp that it was assigned
when it began validation so - so writes
the write time stamp of 2 here ok this
is a pretty simple example it's like a
happy path example of how transactions
work ok so the work face is sort of
simple right anytime you want to read
and write a value you make a copy of it
into your local workspace and then you
modify the local work space alone once
you're done the work phase you've now
begin the validation phase the
validation phase is where the database
ensures that the schedule that it can
generate is serializable right it's
conflict serializable the way that it
does this is that for every transaction
it has to make sure that the the read
write set right so the set of things
that it has modified doesn't conflict
doesn't have a read write conflict or a
write write conflict with all other
concurrent transactions in the system
right and there's a mechanism for how to
do this
there's actually a couple of different
mechanisms when these slides are a
little bit out of order and the way that
you so the way that the database can
ensure that these transactions don't or
like the the sets are you know properly
serializable is that it needs to have a
global view of all active transactions
running in the system if you have a
global view of all transactions running
in the system you now have a global view
of all of the the modifications every
transaction has made in the system ok
and then you you use these readwrite
sets
as a mechanism to determine the ordering
of the transactions in the system so I
think I think one of the things that we
want to try to get across here to
simplify the the the entire protocol is
said the this validation and writing
happens see release eerily so the entire
system you can think about it as there's
a giant latch over the the validation
phase quote-unquote Kuala validation
phase to ensure that there's only one
transaction performing validation at a
time and this will simplify some of the
protocols we're gonna with this
simplified some of the details we're
talking about end up in the protocol a
little bit later on so yes when the read
phase as I mentioned before whenever
you're trying to read and write in a
value you make a local copy and you only
update that local copy to ensure
repeatable reads and then in the
validation phase is when you get is is
when you get a timestamp and then you
use this timestamp to look at all other
concurrent transaction the system to
make sure that you don't you don't
intercept your read and write sets to an
end to intersect to make sure that you
have a correct serial order so you look
at your you look at your timestamp which
are it's 40 I you find all other time a
transactions in the system that are
younger than you that are newer than you
and you have to make sure that a set of
conditions holds I mean the fact that
we're using newer transactions isn't
necessarily required you could also look
at all the transactions right there's no
reason why we're specifically looking
younger transactions but it simplifies
it makes things a little bit simpler but
I'll talk about another approach that we
can use that's slightly different than
this one so when you when you're ready
to validate you essentially invoke the
commit and then the database performs a
validation phase so it finds because it
has a global view of all the
transactions in the system we can find
all newer transactions and all the
transactions and make sure that
everything's sort of is a fits together
and there's two types of validations
that you can perform you can perform for
validation or bra or backwards
validation right so what are the what is
the difference between these two types
of validation techniques so in in in in
in backwards validation what you're
looking at is when a transaction is
ready to commit let's assume that
transaction t2 is ready to commit you
look at all the older transaction
in the system okay so t2 is ready to
commit its commit point is here and
you're doing backwards validation you
have to find all the transactions so
transit different transactions whose
time stamps are less than this one and
perform a validation right so we call
this the the scope of things that we
have to look at a validation scope so
this is the validation scope for t2 if
we're doing backwards validation because
t1 and t2 are running concurrently and
t1 committed before t2 so t1 is older
than t2 all right because it could be
the case that t1 made an update to
something that should have been read by
t2 but we didn't because T once changes
are made to a private copy alright so we
could be the case that we read something
new from the database system that we
should have been reading reading from t1
but we actually read from the main
database because the t1 is making
private changes to its own space so we
have to make sure that this this this
doesn't happen and if it does we have to
actually abort
t1 so this is backwards validation we're
looking backwards
correct yeah because this is already
committed right at this point we can't
do anything about - okay similarly
instead of going backwards you could
also look forwards so again we're trying
to do the the validation for t2 we find
all concurrently running transactions
that have not committed yet and we do a
validation against those so in this
specific scenario t3 is currently
running and we have to make sure that
this is transactionally safe because it
could be the case that I made an update
so t2 made an update into its local
private space but because it occurs
before t3 in the serial order this one
has read as stale value from the
database it should have read something
that I modified like a maybe I modified
it here and it hasn't read it here but
it actually read a stale value and if
that happens I have to abort myself
ok so these are just two techniques to
two mechanisms in which we perform the
validation what's really important here
is that they all that the entire date
that all transactions perform this
validation in the same direction you
can't have t1 performing forward
validation and t2 performing backwards
validation because that's going to mess
up the entire system yeah so if the
validation completes then you're
essentially committed you're ready to
write your changes out even like a
system goes down no yeah because the
validation validation is successful that
the database is saying that this is a
valid transaction it doesn't it doesn't
conflict with anything else so it's a it
should now be installed into the
internet into the system all right so
okay so for the rest of this lecture
let's just assume that we're always
doing forward validation so anytime you
want to validate a transaction you find
all newer transactions than you and you
perform the Vettes validation step okay
so there's a couple of different
scenarios that we have to cover okay the
first scenario is that if you find a
transaction TJ where all your phases
your read your would yes or your work
your that your validation in your right
steps happen before anything that TJ has
done all right this is sort of like the
simple happy path case here here so this
is an example you have t1 and t2 t1
completes all of its steps before t2 is
then anything okay so this is a really
simple example you could essentially
collapse this into one and now you have
a serial execution so you'd only have to
do anything all that interesting here
this is sort of given to you naturally
the second
the second scenario that we have to
handle is that if t1 completes before TJ
sorry TI completes before TJ begins its
right phase okay and we have to make
sure in this scenario that the stuff
that we write the the right set in our
transaction doesn't interact intersect
with the read set of the other
transaction so the other transaction
hasn't read anything that we're going to
that weird that we've written okay why
is this important
so let's walk through an example so in
this scenario we have two transactions
t1 is reading and writing a t2 is
reading a and doing nothing else so so
this is the state of the database so t1
has read a and written to it assume that
is writing the same value 1 2 3 and it's
timestamp is infinity T 2 is read a so
it has a timestamp of 0 there and it has
a local copy in its in its private
workspace and then you want to perform
the the validation here right so t1 has
to abort because it's read set so it has
it has a lower timestamp then then t2
because it begins validation first so
it's write set intersects with the read
set here all right so that bad that
violates the invariant that we had
before so we have to abort
this transaction okay in the serial
order t1 has to begin before t2 but t2
has read a stale value so we have to
abort that's that
I think it's a pretty simple example but
now let's that slightly tweak it and now
we'll have tea to begin validation
before t1 so in the serial order t2
happens before t1 what's gonna happen in
this in this case right so t1 reads a
begins validation it doesn't have a
right set so it doesn't it doesn't have
anything to intersect with this
transaction so so it commits t2 does the
same thing it's it's right set doesn't
intersect with the the read set of teeth
it doesn't intersect with any other
concurrent transaction because it's what
this one's all revela dated so another
thing at like nothing happens right so
when the serial order t2 happens before
t1 it reads the value of a that
initially existed before this
transaction is going to read the value
of a there make a local copy right to it
and everything's okay all right
questions yes so in this in this
scenario because T 2 begins validation
first it appears first in the serial
order yeah yeah
so T so T 1 has to abort because in the
serial order what should have happened
is that T 2 because it begins validation
first it's the first to recognize that
there's something wrong so it recognizes
something's wrong as soon as it begins a
validation because it gets assigned a
timestamp it sees a concurrent
transactions that's ready stale value so
it aborts well T 22 goes to validate T 1
note is no longer a valid transaction so
it won't see any concurrent transactions
there's nothing to intersect with also
it's a read-only transaction so there's
nothing to intersect with T 2 couldn't
no not until the stalls it's it's
changes because it's a private private
thing yeah yeah so when when this T 1
begins it's right back oh because the
validate face you don't get a timestamp
yeah I don't get I don't know 1 or 2 or
something but this T 2 doesn't have a
right timestamp yet yeah I mean it's
infinity it doesn't have any time stamp
because it hasn't begun validation yet
no no no so no no no no so the transact
the time stamp is at assigned to the
transaction it isn't assumed that it
doesn't take whatever times time
is from the the tuple yeah so that's
just a local copy okay yeah yeah are you
saying if t2 performs a right to this
object eh it'll get an it'll get a it'll
modify the bite time stamp of its local
copy to infinity yeah so if it makes a
right it will get a local time it'll get
a timestamp a validation and it'll
update the right time stamped there if
there's no conflicts if the no no you
have to you you have to have this right
be atomic so you write all all your
changes back into into the database in
this phase
that's just because of the schedule that
we have here so we have the device you
can think of it as like we begin the
validation we finish enemy do contact
switch here and now we begin the
validation in the right phase all right
so this is the second example there's
still one more to go
in this one the transaction you have to
ensure that the transaction TI completes
its read phase before transaction TJ
begins its read phase so we have to
ensure that the right set of my
transaction doesn't intersect with the
the read set and the right set of all
these of the transactions that fall into
this category or the read phases are
overlapping and this is another example
of how we can go through this so let's
see in this scenario t1 is reading and
writing a oops t2 is reading B and
reading a t1 baguettes and begin that
validation phase so it gets a time stamp
of 1 and now I can commit it because my
my right set doesn't intersect with the
read set of transaction t2 at this point
in time okay so I can install my changes
back into the into the database I update
4 5 6 or update a with value 4 5 6 and I
set my write time stamp to 1 which is
the time stamp that I was assigned at
validation phase okay then when we come
back down into we do a context switch
back into t2 t2 does a read of B or
sorry a read of a and now it can go back
to the main it goes to the to the main
database and does a local copy of the
updated value of a made by t1 and then
it can validate and write successfully
because there are no concurrent
transactions good
yeah so if you if you let's go back to
this example so when you want to perform
a right right you make a local copy of
the of the database object into your
local private workspace and then that's
when you set the time sent to infinity
you set it to infinity because you don't
know what your time stamp is going to be
because you haven't been assigned one
yet right it's it's zero here only for
mainly for illustrative purposes you can
think about like there was at some
trying some transaction with timestamps
arrow that bulk loaded all of these
objects into into the database so that's
why the right x times r0 when you read
it you read whatever it right whatever
timestamp is associate with associated
with the object at that point yeah so t2
does a read of a does a valid does a
validation does a right everything is
good because there's no concurrent
transactions yeah yeah these are all for
validation yeah correct yeah yeah you
still need to rely on the same time
stamps yeah so that was essentially the
I'm cup we've been kind of hind wavy on
a couple of things on how you actually
install the right Saitama Klee and how
you do the validations in a parallel way
because in a real system you have to do
this parallel parallel validation but I
think hopefully the the main idea has
gotten across right it's not too
complicated there are some there's
there's some trickeries here and there
but generally it's it's pretty intuitive
so there's a few observations that we
should we should try to make all of
these time supporting in optimistic
concurrency protocols sort of work well
when there's very little conflict right
because you allowed the transactions to
proceed without acquiring locks without
doing that anything heavyweight it
worked
and at the end you do a sort of
lightweight semi lightweight validation
to make sure that your transaction is
still valid so if you have very few very
few conflicts even better if all your
transactions are essentially just doing
read-only work and if the access
disjoint sets of data then this these
protocols work very well because they're
actually not doing much work at all
aside from doing some local data copying
right another way to think about this is
that if you have a very large workspace
and very small transactions and the
probability of these transactions
overlapping in the reader might set is
very low in this specific scenario these
optimistic concurrency protocols work
very well on the other hand in very
highly contentious workloads what ends
up happening is that you have
transactions consistently restarting
right so they do a lot of work in their
in their work phase assuming if there is
no there's there is no contention and
then and only at the very end do they
figure out oh crap all this work that
I've done is kind of useless after we
start right so you're kind of deferring
a lot of the the heavy lifting towards
the end assuming that there won't be a
lot of heavy lifting but in the
contentious work though there is heavy
lifting because your sense they have to
abort everything you've done so really I
think I think the the the research sort
of shows that in contentious workloads
both two-phase locking and exhausting
mystic concurrency protocols generally
don't work they're sort of like almost
equivalent so when two plu were simply
acquiring there's there's a lot of
contention on locks so you have
transactions waiting and these hot locks
here you have transactions that are
doing all their work almost wasteful
work and then aborting at the very end
so neither really work for contentious
workloads but if your workload is it has
very low contention then in general
these optimistic protocols work better
because they they have no overhead and
very very minimal override aside from
some local data copy okay whereas in the
two PL protocol you actually have to
acquire locks even if there's no logical
reason that you should be acquiring
these locks
so the time stamp the time stamps are
assigned at validation yeah I think what
you're describing is essentially basic
time stamp order right so in basic time
stamp ordering you assign the time
stamps when the transaction begins in
OCC chat the protocol dictates that you
assign the time stamps at validation
time because you want to defer the work
of doing the actual checking - when
you're ready to commit whereas basic
time step boredom is saying every
operation I'm going to perform I want to
do a check to make sure that this is a
valid operation so just how the protocol
works yeah you still need to make a
local copy even if you're reading to
ensure repeatable reads right so this
slide is essentially just saying that
for low contention workloads these
optimistic concurrency protocols work
very well because they have very little
overhead in comparison to two-phase
locking which you know even if you have
disjoint working sets between between
transactions you still have to have
transactions require locks whereas here
there's no locks at all
this guy yeah you're right
so you don't have to acquire like a
database of a lock you still have to
require latches you still have to make
sure the integrity of the data structure
is valid right
you can't just blindly overwrite stuff
in memory because there could be
concurrent access to these to these
structures so I think you're kind of
hitting on the point that we will talk
about it
I think in this slide yeah so there is a
little bit of work overhead in OCC right
because you have to maintain local
copies of everything that you want to
read and write so if you're updating a
billion two poles you have to make a
billion copies every transaction has to
make a billion copies and so there's a
lot of overhead here the other thing is
that the validation and the right phase
is they were happening serially right
the only one transaction can be
validating at a time
in reality you know in real systems you
have parallel validation in parallel
writing but again even those in those
scenarios these phases become a big
bottleneck and lastly because we're
being optimistic we're assuming that we
can perform all of the work with you
know safely without being interrupted by
there by them by other transactions but
in contentious workloads that's not this
that's not the case right that
assumption is invalidated
so in contentious workloads routing all
this work upfront and then we could find
out later that we actually have to abort
so all of this work is wasted
we're being optimistic and we're being
wrong about that optimism so when a
transaction commits they they they I
think that the student was was was
pointing this out correctly
even if these even if the transactions
logically don't overlap with each other
you still have to make sure that you
maintain the physical integrity of the
data structure you're gonna be looking
at so as part of the validation phase
you have to look at oh I have you know
all these other thousand Trent
transactions I have to look inside the
reads a read and write sets in a
consistent way I make this consistent by
by acquiring latches right so this latch
overhead it can actually play a big role
even if they're logically just disjoint
physically they're still contending on
the same data structures right there so
contending on the read and write data
sets even though logically they're
disconnected yes so when I'm doing my
validation right I have one transaction
and me I'm ready to validate I have to
go into his read and write transaction
set to make sure that we don't intersect
all right but he could be modifying it
because he's still running he or she's
still running right so I have to acquire
latch read a consistent view of it
perform the intersection to make sure
I'm okay and he and the this other
transaction can't modify that that said
while I'm reading it but I'm reading the
local copy I'm reading that transactions
local copy of the working set because
the table doesn't have all of the
updates that have been applied that this
transaction has read and has read and
written to write the transaction has a
local copy of Reason rights so to see if
this transaction has read a value that
I'm writing to I only know that by
looking at his we didn't write said I
don't know that by looking at the table
so I have to look at the local the world
the local working copies for all the two
are the other the other transactions as
part of my validation and I do that and
in order to do that in a consistent way
I have to acquire latches and this latch
is these latches can have some overhead
yeah yeah there's this yeah there's
there's a lot of techniques that you can
use to reduce the slash contention but
at the end of the day like if you even
if you have a parallel sighting there is
some overhead right so what if we take a
slightly different view right what if we
what if we partition the entire database
so that all of the stuff that one
transaction has to work on is only
within one transaction and then I can
remove all of my locks and latches
altogether is that even possible so it
turns out that this is a valid technique
and
it's called partition based timestamp
ordering
the idea is that I want to split up my
database into these horizontal
partitions right and then I want to be
able to use time stamps to order the
transactions on a partition in serial
order right so if I have transactions
executed executing serially then there's
no reason I'm sorry within a database
there's no reason to have locks and
latches at all because there's no
concurrent activity right if they're
operating single-threaded I don't need
lights
I don't need locks I don't need latches
and then it gets a little bit
complicated if you have to access
multiple of these database partitions
but if you're only accessing all the
data within one partition then then it
can be potentially really really fast
and this is sort of what partition based
time step ordering is trying to achieve
let's let's walk through an example so
imagine that I have this the schema that
represents some online store that I'm
running I have customers orders and the
the order items the items in the order
for this for for an order what I could
potentially do is because I have these
foreign key references I can store
within one partition of the day of the
table a set of customers all of their
orders and all of the items for their
orders by using this this this this
foreign key reference structure okay so
imagine that I have two databases now
where I have customers one through 1001
and 1002 2000 in a separate database and
I want to I don't know let's say I want
to update a customer's name I want to
add in order to one customer's order
right what do I do
so a transaction I have an application
here it begins a transaction and let's
say that it's trying to update customer
customer one it falls into this
partition here so okay it's missing
something
so assume that in this line there's a
there's an operation that says get me
the name of the customer whose ID is one
okay that's an operation that obviously
falls into this partition because this
customer belongs in this partition right
and then it does commit and it can
safely do that right because all of
these transactions get queued up and
operated in a single thread and this
transit in this database
there's no concurrent activity at all
similarly I can have another application
server that wants to update the customer
1004 that'll go here and these two
transactions are totally disjoint
they're operating on different customers
that's one way that we get parallelism
even though each database is operating
single threaded okay the finer grain
that we can have these customers we can
store these these database partitions
the more parallelism we can get and that
way each treats individual transaction
runs much faster because we don't have
to acquire locks and latches and we get
parallelism by having more of these
transactions when it concurrently on
disjoint sets of the data is that clear
all right so this turns out to be a very
popular protocol you still have to
assign transactions and ID and then you
queue them up bye-bye-bye these IDs and
the this type of partition based
protocol has been actually very very
very successful so Andy worked on this
system called a store which is a
commercial system that now get that got
commercialized into volt EB and they're
still using this this type of partition
based timestamp ordering Andy worked
with the someone called a professor
called Danny body who's at I think
Marilyn now who did some initial work on
a system called Calvin that's now been
commercialized into fauna that also uses
something very similar to this and
there's a system called K DB which is of
like a financial database and they also
use this technique and it's actually
pretty successful if you if your work
votes of supports this type of partition
based operation the way that you can
view this is that every single database
essentially has a giant lock or a latch
around it and when a transaction is
ready to commit it acquires this latch
and it begins execution within the
within the database fully single
threaded bare metal bare metal speed and
then as other transactions come up they
queue up on this latch and they
essentially get assigned a timestamp and
then as their timestamp gets gets ringed
up they begin execution into this
database
into this into this database partition
okay yeah so that's it
so four four four four reads the
database that the transactions can
essentially read whatever they want
right now safely without requiring
latches because they came Garon the
database system guarantees that there's
no other transaction running in the
system this is great if you only want to
read stuff within the within one
database partition it gets complicated
when you want to try to read rows that
exist across partitions so in the in the
application server we had before let's
say that you want to modify within one
transaction customers from two different
partitions that becomes complicated
because now I have to acquire the lock
for one partition and acquire a lock for
the other partition before I can do any
sort of operation okay and oftentimes
it's not even possible to know a priori
all of the partitions and have to touch
it so some systems what they actually do
is they'll run the system in sort of
like a like a speculative or like
reconnaissance mode to figure out all
the partitions I need to access and then
rollback acquire all the locks ahead of
time and then begin execution all right
yeah so that's essentially what this is
talking about if I have to access cross
partitions across partition rows I have
to abort and restart and acquire the new
locks the new set of locks that I've
discovered during execution and this can
be wasteful so if you you have to be
kind of careful about when you want to
apply partition based time step order so
in contrast to regular time step
ordering and OCC I can now apply all my
updates in place right so when oasis-c
and in basic timestamp ordering I had a
private workspace that or data plot that
I have to apply my updates so that I
don't conflict with other transactions
that are running concurrently that want
to read the same stuff that I'm writing
okay but here the goods the system
guarantees that there's only one
transaction running at a time I can
apply my updates in place and of course
I have some extra logic to ensure that
when I abort I undo those changes but I
can do this without making a local copy
so I've reduced the data copying
overhead that would normally exist in
OCC systems
and an ad as in the in the Greek case if
I try to modify a tuple that exists in a
different partition than when I'm
running on right now I'll abort restart
get a lock on both database systems or
database partitions and then begin my
execution yeah no no because every
database has only one transaction
actually execution thread every
partition has one transaction execution
thread right that's that's sort of one
reason why you want to do this because
you by having only one thread you don't
have to copy you don't have to have a
locks and latches yes yeah so I think
they're ways into the remedy this way as
you have if you if you have a
deterministic order that you acquire the
locks that's one way to alleviate this
problem but I think you're sort of
alluding to the fact that you could have
the case where you keep learning during
execution that you have that you're
touching different partitions so you do
a bit of work realize you have to
acquire it to a lock for a partition
that you don't have abort retry get
further in the execution realize you
have to acquire a different lock and a
different partition abort and then we
start and this you hope sort of
incrementally grow the set of locks that
you have to acquire because you don't
know a priori
yeah but you see so you solve that
problem by having that these
transactions acquire the locks in a
specific order in a deterministic order
so you have let's say a partition a and
B you have t1 t2 20 X s a and B they
realize that they need different
partitions then they restart the abort
and now they all acquire a and they all
acquire B and then they get queued up
and they get executed in that order all
right all right so that's essentially
partition based time step ordering this
is sort of a visual illustration of
what's going on let's say you have two
servers that are both trying to access
some customer data in this first
partition the issue a begin request they
get queued up in this transaction queue
they get assigned time stamps assume
that server one gets x times 100
servitude it gets timestamp 101 and
obviously the the database system will
take the transaction with the lowest
timestamp in this case the the one from
server one it begins execution acquired
by acquiring a lock on this on this
database partition it finishes its
execution it does it sorry it's doing a
bunch of work it's getting the customer
ID and it's updating the stuff the
animations are a little bit wonky but
then it does a commit it's safe because
nothing that nothing else is running at
the same time so now this this partition
can now move up this this request from
server 2 up in the queue begin execution
acquire the lock and then the whole
cycle continues all right
as we've sort of talked about a little
bit these systems obviously are not a
silver bullet right they have they have
some performance issues so these systems
are very fast if the database knows what
partitions the transaction needs before
even beginning execution that's not
really possible in a sort of an
interactive transaction protocol right
but you can remedy this by having stored
procedures right in store procedures you
declare everything on you you don't have
to do round trips back and forth and the
database runs everything on the server
side so can determine much quicker all
of the locks the system
before enduring execution and if the if
the transaction only touches one
partition then obviously it's gonna be
really fast but if it has to touch
multiple partitions and you have to do
some execution abort retry by acquiring
more locks and then continue execution
is again right so it becomes slower but
if your transaction only touches data
within one partition then you're
essentially running had bare-metal speed
because it's it's single threaded right
there's no locks no latches the other
drawback is that if you have this multi
partition setup you could have some
transact some partitions that are
essentially idle because you have one
hot one hot partition okay so that that
was essentially partition based time
stamp ordering try to get through this
as fast as possible so one of the
assumptions that we've been making
throughout this work is that the as
transactions execute they don't really
insert new data they only modify data
and they read data okay so when you now
add the requirement the data can it can
be inserted and updated and deleted and
inserted during execution it violates
some of the assumptions that we've been
there that we've made in our protocols
and we have to handle them okay and
specifically introduces an interesting
problem that's called the phantom
problem so imagine that we have the same
sequence of execution here but now I'm
using sequel statements instead of
regular read and write operations and we
have these two transactions t1 and t2
and we have the data this database here
of people that have you know name and a
H and some status so a transaction t1
that's performing that's getting the
maximum the the oldest person whose
status is lit ok so let's assume that it
runs and it figures out that the maximum
age is 72 and then we have this
transaction t2 that's essentially going
to enter it into the same database with
a new person whose age is 96 who also
happens to be lit all right and then we
get back here so it's the same t1 tries
to re-execute the same query and it gets
a different version it gets a different
result from this query so got 96 here
and it got 72 here today this is clearly
a problem
right kids can to phase locking solve
this assume tuple axis who said no why
do you say no yeah exactly that's it
that's exactly right right you can only
access locks on on tuples that that
exists so because because there was new
transaction that inserted a new tuple
they didn't even have something to
acquire a lock on right and that's
clearly a problem and how do we solve
this if I want to ensure it's a
realisability I have to ensure that I
can ensure I can ensure rpido reads so
if you saw this phantom problem okay so
what if instead of acquiring locks on
tuples I can acquire locks on abstract
objects what if I can acquire a lock on
an expression status Lit would that
solve the problem if I had a lock on all
tuples that satisfy the condition status
is equal to lid who says yes one person
who says no who says they don't know
okay so the answer is yes if you could
have a powerful a powerful enough
locking system that you can have an
ex-con an expression that says status is
equal to lid you can solve this problem
that would solve it for you all right
but the problem and that the term that
we're talking about here is called
predicate locking is that it's very very
expensive to be able to do this and in
fact I don't think any systems actually
do that type of really complex logic
because it's very complex right I gave
you one example of statuses equal to lid
but we're actually talking about it's a
multi-dimensional problem because you
could have any arbitrary complex
expression and you want to ensure that
the expression you're evaluating doesn't
intersect with this multi-dimensional
space so it's non-trivial to implement
so most systems don't do that yes
[Music]
yeah so you could acquire like a table
level lock or a page level lock yeah so
you could use these hierarchy locks
that's one way to definitely solve it
the other way to solve it is is this
predicate locking that I was talking
about which is more general-purpose and
there's another one called index locking
so if I have an index on the system
right let's say I have an index on this
on the status attribute what I could do
is take a lock on the slot in the index
where status is equal to lid so that any
new insertions have to go through the
index and I make an update they can't
acquire that lock okay so that's another
way to solve it if the status lit
doesn't even exist in the index what I
have to do is acquire what's called a
gap lock so a gap in the index I acquire
a lock on that gap so that if another
insertion comes in that tries to insert
statuses is equal to lid in that space
in the index it's not allowed to do that
okay so this that's that's two
essentially two ways to do it yeah so
this essentially goes back to the point
that was made earlier if you don't have
an index and you don't have predicate
locks you could do it by locking every
every page or you could do it by locking
the entire table or yeah hierarchical
locks
so I saw you know the last way to solve
this problem is through just by
repeating the scans by by the committing
sorry before committing so I think one
of the most popular systems that does
this is hecatomb which is from Microsoft
so essentially everything before you
commit you have to make sure that
everything you read before happens just
before you commit to make sure can see
you have consistent reads I think we're
at a time the last section was weaker
isolation levels maybe we'll cover that
in the next lecture all right all right
that's it
a machine on them it's a broken bar goes
in crushed up kids
let the cows in the demo I'll try it see
nights in my system I'm blessed
let's go get the next one good net will
be son ricochet jelly hit the deli for a
boat one naturally bless ya what rappers
like the laser beam the balls in the
bushes say nothing like a king wrap the
bottle of us a nice sympathy go don't
feel like drinking a pony - you drunk
you can't drop in at the stake don't
know your phone can tap a cake