[Music]
[Applause]
today's lecture is on databases that are
larger than the amount of memory that's
available to the database system so
again still in lockdown here in my house
the carrier's over there it's sort of
asking questions as we go along but it
hasn't been very good before so people
are complaining that like the chair
doesn't ask the questions that they want
to ask them it is one of this so before
we get into today's lecture material I
first wanted to do a quick overview on
what coming up for you for those of you
that are enrolled in the course this
semester like the upcoming deadlines and
dates so on Wednesday this week I will
be releasing the final exam it was
originally due a week from Wednesday so
next week I've now extended that to have
the final exam being due on the on the
13th so everyone's gonna have three
weeks now to actually complete it with
that ok the carriers question is can we
have a you know can the class have a
practice exam before I release this no
because you'll see that it's sort of a
long form question and based on the
material that we discussed this semester
and now that I'm giving you three weeks
to actually do it there's no point of
releasing a practice exam first the next
thing is that on Wednesday next week we
will have a hopefully the guest speaker
from Amazon come and give a talk for
this one because of Amazon restrictions
we're gonna have to make this a live
lecture that will only be accessible to
CMU students and so you'll need to come
at the time that it that that we
normally would have scheduled class
scheduled so be 12:00 12:00 p.m. Eastern
Standard Time because this will not be
recorded so now also in terms of project
3 the second round of reviews will be
due on May 4th and then we'll have now
our final presentations at our
originally scheduled final exam time on
May 5th at 5:30 p.m. and so again we'll
just go to the only zoom channel and
everyone will present as we've done with
the the status updates from before Hey
again and then the final exam will be
due on the 13th so the the main thing
I'll say about this so for the code
reviews Matt and I will go through this
week and give feedback on the first
round of code reviews and that prepare
you for the second round and the idea is
that you want to take all the
suggestions that the other team made
about your project from the first round
and actually apply them to the second
round I don't want to sort of hit make
the same mistakes all over again and
have them just repeating themselves okay
alright so as I said in the very
beginning of the semester which seems
like a long time uh-huh
now back in January was that this class
was focused on in memory databases and
that all of the algorithms and methods
and architectural decisions that we've
talked about this entire semester have
based based on this assumption that the
database resides entirely main memory
meaning we're not writing algorithms or
Rutte not already you know joint
algorithms that can maximize or minimize
the amount of disk i/o that they incur
words assuming that any time we follow a
pointer to a tuple or a buffer region
that that's gonna always be in memory
now the downside of this is like I said
I mean the upside is that as we've seen
throughout the entire semester this
allows you to implement things way more
efficiently because you don't have to
have this all these checks to account
for the fact that like in a disk or any
system anytime you go touch you know
piece of memory that it might actually
be in memory it's me on desk and you
have to get you know go through the
buffle minute ago and get it so we if we
you know we can write our system without
the assumption it's gonna go really fast
the downside is however and what the
in-memory marketplace has sort of shown
in our database marketplace has sort of
shown the last decade is that SSDs and
spinning discs are
drives still provide or still in terms
of price versus performance there's
still a you know still have provide
certain properties that would be
desirable in even from modern a previous
applications and this is because DRAM at
its core is expensive right and it's
expensive both to to buy relative to
DRAM and are sorry to SSDs and and
spinning gears hard drives so roughly in
2020 the price of per gigabyte for a
spinning disc hard drive is around two
to three cents for NAND flash it's it's
less than a dollar and a few years ago I
saw it being you know thirty cents per
gigabyte
whereas in DRAM it's gone down in recent
years because of some lawsuits which we
can take that offline but the it's
roughly maybe like around five to six
dollars per gigabyte
this is assume that you're buying in
bulk I guess I mean your manufacturer
not like you're going to Amazon and
buying you know Dan this for your
machines like you're you're a major
manufacturer they can buy this in bulk
so it's expensive to buy the other thing
we have really talked about too is that
it's expensive to maintain
meaning when I put it in my computer and
I'm on my server and I'm and I'm you
know plug the server in I'm actually
running it the percentage of the
electricity that's being used to power
that machine a sizable portion of it is
going to to be round now this is
ignoring like doing like Bitcoin mining
or you know no net training on GPUs
those things are definitely bigger power
hogs then then DRAM and so that those
are drawl draw most of the power in sort
of a database server that's not doing
stuff on the GPUs it's gonna be a
roughly about 40 percent this was a
survey that was done a few years ago
where they actually went and measured
how much memory was being drawn by the
DIMM slots and they showed it like on
average about was about forty percent so
it means like all the power that you're
paying for to run your machine 40
percent of that is going to
to D Ram so now that means if I'm
running an in-memory database when the
database has to fit entirely in DRAM the
larger my database the more dimalanta by
and then more pockets to use to maintain
him essentially what the motherboard is
doing is like every so often right I
thinks in every couple seconds it's
sending a charge to the dims so that
they can refresh the there's where
they're storing and of course this is
why you if you pull the pull the power
on them you can't do that refresh and
then you lose your data so given that we
spent the entire semester talking about
how to make a really fast in memory
database system it'd be nice if we could
bring back one of these slower
involvement non-volatile storage devices
NAND flash or spinning disk hard drive
and get the benefit of being able to
write out data to to those disks without
having to bring in all the architectural
components that we were avoiding and
algorithms that we were avoiding by
going you know from a disk or any
architecture and pulling that back into
an in-memory system so that we just end
up with that slower disk orient
architecture that we were trying to
avoid in the first place so that's what
the focus on today is so we'll first
talk in the background about the
different choices or we could have why
we want to do this for to support larger
than memory databases in an in-memory
database system then let's talk about
how you actually want to go to implement
this and then we'll finish up talking
about some real implementations of the
various techniques that what we will
talk about today so at a high level as
again I've already said this but just to
repeat it the goal of what we're
discussing today is enabling an
in-memory database minute system to be
able to store and access data that's
been written out the disk but without
having to bring back all of the slow
parts in particular the buffer pool
manager that we got rid of when we went
to an in-memory architecture right and
so another sort of engineering change we
want to try to achieve is that as we
bring back the disk
we don't want to have to go and touch
all our all our components in our
systems to now account for the fact that
data that it could be accessing is is
not an in-memory and it's on disk like
if we bring back a traditional Buffalo
manager this is somewhat the case
because anytime we go access a you know
location we need to know we would have
to know what page are blocking them it's
an univers ID then and go through a
before manager to do this for us so we'd
have to go modify the entire system to
now instead of just go reading a piece
of memory as we did before to now go
through the buffer pool manager and get
a page or get a block of memory that we
can then access and know the offset
within that that's gonna be slow the
algorithms that are designed to minimize
disk i/o there's really much slower than
the random access ones that we've been
talking about today so the the way we're
gonna have to do this or the way you
know though is that we need to be aware
of the the sort of fundamental
differences between the non-volatile
storage like a spinning disk hard drive
and man flash and in memory volatile
storage and the core difference is that
for in memory storage is going to be
tuple oriented essentially byte
addressable that I can go access to jump
to some memory location and that that's
where my tuple will reside in a disk or
any architecture in a disk storage model
it's gonna be block oriented or page
oriented meaning I can't jump to just a
single bytom and memory or in a page and
just get that data and bring it in into
memory
I gotta go fetch the entire four
kilobyte or a kilobyte page that my the
data that I wanted resides in even if I
don't want the other parts I only maybe
want one kilobyte at that for collide
page I'm bringing in the entire four
kilobyte pages right so this this is
what we have to deal with when we design
a capability that allows us to move data
in a disk in our a memory architecture
so the other important thing to discuss
is that the for the entire lecture we're
going to focus on all OLTP work
sooro LTP systems and we can do this in
the context of an H tap system where
we're running the OLAP systems that will
upload it to be workload at the same
time but for the OLAP lab queries there
really isn't gonna be anything special
or magical we can do in M every database
system to make the disk accesses that
they're going to incur go faster because
then in the day
oh that queries are going to do for the
most part large 2000 scans over or those
2000 stands over large segments of at
the table or they or maybe even the
entire table now may be accessing just a
subset of the columns and a column store
could could alleviate the issue of
bringing in data that you don't actually
need and we can do that but that's not
anything special because we're in memory
because the disk scorning the database
system can still be a column store and
still get that same benefit right so
again the main thing I'm trying to point
out here is that there's nothing really
we're gonna do because we ran a memory
system to make disk i/o and for OLAP
queries go better the only thing we can
really do is like say we have a column
that we know in our table that we want
to scan well we can compute a zone map
for it's like a pre computed aggregation
aggregates for the column like the min
the max you know all the things you
would run on want to run an aggregation
stuff on and keep that in memory at all
times and the the rest of the column the
actual data itself we shove out the disk
and so we can use this so map to try to
figure out what whether or not we need
actually need to access that column on
disk or not depending what query we're
trying to do and that's just the data
skipping technique we saw before when we
talked about doing compression in a data
system but again a disk learning system
can still use on maps and there's
nothing special because we're in memory
here so again for this reason there's
not much we can we can do from a good
lab stuff go away all the same
optimizations we would do in a
Discordian system in our buffer pool
like scan sharing or buffer pool bypass
we can still apply them here so the
reason why we're going to focus on the
LTP is because they're going to have
this
this is very common pattern where
there's gonna be this notion of hot data
and cold data in the database and the
idea is that we want to keep the hot
data in memory because that's the data
we're going to be updating or accessing
over and over again more often and then
the cold data we then shove out the disk
and the idea is that we still have a
we're still keeping track of that cold
data in memory so that we know it exists
and we don't have any false negatives
you know we do a lookup for a tuple and
it's on disk and say oh we don't know
anything about it like we're gonna void
that but we're just not gonna pay the
the storage penalty in memory to have
all that cold data around in memory even
though most of the time we're not gonna
need it so the example I always like the
use of understanding hot versus cold
data would be something like reddit for
hacker news right most people are going
to post comments on the latest articles
that been posted on reddit within the
last you know 24 hours or so many days
but few people are going back and
posting comments on you know articles
that were never never uploaded or posted
six months ago right and I actually I
don't think even read even let you do
comments on old articles so again the
ideas that the recent post we want to
keep in memory because those are the
ones everyone's reading and making
updates to the older stuff that you
shell out the disk if everybody comes
and goes looking for it we'll go fetch
it from disk and bring the memory and
serve it to them but most of the time we
don't need that and then the likelihood
that someone who's gonna read that same
article in a cold article immediately
after it was brought back and memory
from the disk it's actually very low so
we can go ahead and shove it back out
the disk later on I didn't save save
space so again some applications like I
said in reddit where they were actually
prevent you from posting on articles
that are that are you become a certain
age that mechanism is actually something
that the application does it's not
something that the data expander system
enforces as far as they know nobody no
database system actually says all right
this stuff is old you know we won't let
you modify because it
it doesn't know that you know you're not
you're inserting into a table like the
comments are giving certain to a
separate table home when the article
secretary post it so it doesn't know you
can't do that as far as I know no system
actually does those so again the purpose
what we're trying to do today is is this
piece here what we need the mechanism to
allow us to identify that we have this
cold data what it is where it is shove
it out the disk and then if never need
it again Brigham back in another way
conceptually think about this too is
that in what we're trying to do is push
cold data atom memory onto disk contrast
this with a disk or nyun system where
you pull hot data from disk and bring it
into memory so this seems like a sort of
semantic difference and hopefully as we
go along with this make more sense but
like the this system is being
architected as such that cold data is
moved out to disk whereas in a different
system hot data is pulled in alright so
let's look at a high-level example here
so we have now we have a database now
that can support writing out data to
cold data storage this is some some
spinning disk hard drive or NAND flash
or EBS whatever you want doesn't matter
for our purposes right now and then in
memory we still have our in memory index
and then we have our in memory table
heap for now assuming everything's fixed
fixed size and it all exists in in this
one space here so the say now we have a
mechanism to look at our tuples and
identify which ones are cold we have a
way to identify that these three tuples
here are haven't been access in in in
the recent recent time unlikely to be
access in the future again how exactly
we do that we'll cover in a second but
for whatever reason we think these three
are our candidates to be evicted so what
we're going to go ahead and do is we're
going to pull them out of our table heap
combine them into a page or a block that
we then write out to disk so this would
now be our victor tuple block there's
some header that's saying here's what
you know here's what's in here and then
we have our tuple data and for this
assume that we're organized as a row
store
store could essentially look the same
way because if you do a pax organized
block right this could be laid out and
in a common store within the page but
all the the values or all the attributes
for a given tuple can be found in this
in this block so now the first question
we have to deal with is what do we do
with the holes that we just made in our
table heap all right we have now empty
space that we could reuse what are we
actually gonna you know when do we
actually put stuff in there because the
issue is that the index now is because
everything is now in our database you
know you're having 64-bit pointers to
two other locations as a memory to
identify tuples it's not a you know page
ID and an offset as you would in a slot
number as you would in a discarding
system these pointers are now pointing
that are still in the index are still
pointing to these empty slots so now if
I could do a lookup and try to find this
tuple that that used to be here I'm
gonna land in you know look at some
empty space now because somebody else
could now be - yeah I could have put
another two boys in this space but now
let's say what this query comes along
and this query now wants to reference
one of the tuples that we just evicted
right so this is accessing tuple 1 but
now tube 1 is somewhere out on disk so
the question is we have to deal with is
well how are we actually gonna find it
how are we actually going to be able to
identify that Oh tuple 0 1 it's not in
memory anymore
right it's it's out on disk then say we
if we can actually identify that it is
on disk we need to bring it back into
memory and now the question is what do
we actually do because as I said the the
cold data storage on our disks is is
block oriented so I can't just go grab 2
+ 0 1 and just copy the the bytes
exactly for that tuple and bringing it
into my my table heap I gotta bring this
whole block in and so now I'm bringing
in tuple 1 also 3 & 4 but I didn't ask
for 3 & 4 I only wanted one so what I
actually do do I merge all three tuples
back in do I just hurt merge one tuple
in and then I'm gonna leave a hole out
on a disk so these are the questions
that were that we're trying to answer
today how we actually want to
orchestrate all of us so the issues we
have to deal with are the following and
again we're focusing on OTP systems
where we assume that actually turns out
you know transactions our query is good
or could try to actually not just access
but also update or modify to pools that
are data that's been shoved out to disk
so the first thing we had to deal with
is for the runtime operations is what
are we actually gonna do while the
transactional videos and runs queries
and transactions to keep track of
whether data is hot or cold like having
to keep track of it and identify oh when
it's time to evict or we wanna take some
data which tuples or which blocks
haven't been accessed in a while and
therefore we want to go ahead and dick
them the next is the eviction policy
this is when the the database system
recognizes that it's running out of
space or running out of memory so says
let's go ahead and let Vic some data so
the first question is when should it
actually fire off the eviction the next
is like what metadata we're going to
keep track of to to record that there
used to be data here in memory but it's
now out on disk and here's how to go
find where it's located on disk and we
need to do this because we need to avoid
false negatives we don't want to write
we only back here and write out tuple 1
to disk then this query comes along and
says oh I want to pull one but we only
consult this portion here of the table
heatman which doesn't have people
wanting more so it would come back and
say up I don't know anything about tuple
0 1 like you what you're asking for it
doesn't exist and therefore this thing
would return incorrect answer so we need
a way to identify that the in memory
that there used to be a tuple 0 1 here
and here's that here's here's the
information you know where to go to find
it on disk so that's the metadata which
kind of keep track out here
then now when we go and and recognize
that we actually do need data on disk
the question is how much data should we
actually bring in what do we actually do
with the query or transaction
that requested that data and where do we
actually put the data that that they've
requested right like where in memory the
table heap or maybe a private buffer I
will cover all of these did these
different design decisions and these all
come from a paper that we wrote in 2016
with one of my PhD students where we
were looking at this idea of again how
do you actually support larger memory
databases in memory database system so
what I'll say though this was based on a
system that I helped build in grad
school called a store which was then
commercialized in 2008 2009 as volte B
most of the mechanisms we'll talk about
here are going to be sort of tuple
oriented likes fine-grain eviction and
fine-grained identification of
individual tuples but the paper I had
you guys read lean store which came much
after this particular paper here was
doing this on at the page level so some
of the things we'll talk about here
don't make sense if you're trying to do
it at a page level because they have a
sort of more coarse graining view of
what data is hot and cold and how they
actually keep track of the metadata of
your when teams get evicted but it's
important to understand you know sort of
the fine grain approach and then you'll
hopefully then appreciate better why the
leads to our idea I actually think is
really good all right plan the first
thing you have to do with how to
identify with what data is called in our
database so the first choice is to do
what I'll call online identification
meaning as the database system is
executing transactions or executing
queries we are keeping track of what
tuples they're accessing what data
they're accessing and then we have to
then maintain some metadata directly in
the tuples of pages themselves that we
then update as our as our queries are
accessing them and the reason why you
want to embed it in the tuple itself is
because you don't want to maybe go then
consult a ugly data structure to say hey
by the way I've updated this tuple all
right if I made the tuple entry in my
tracking data and then up
because in your pain that the storage
penalty of having that extra extra data
structure and then you're also paying
the computational overhead of having to
update it every single time you access a
tubule so for when we did this in H
store the the we would store actually a
64-bit pointer of a tuple to that the
next most recently accessed tuple we
were essentially maintaining a an LRU
chain of all individual tuples so 64
bits per to pool is not ideal and so the
the the tuple is very large if it has a
lot of attributes then the overhead is
kind of small but if it only has like
two attributes like two 32-bit pointers
our sorry 32-bit integers has its
attributes then an additional 64-bit
pointer to keep track of the metadata
it's essentially doubling the size of
the tuple just to keep track of whether
it's hot or not the the second approach
is to go offline and what that means is
that the the database system will record
like an in-memory log of all the angel
accesses that the queries and
transactions make while they're running
but this is just sitting in getting
updated in a private buffer to the
thread doing the access so though
there's no contention on the global data
structure we're not storing for every
single tuple this metadata and payment
penalty as we saw up here so this is
just some some some additional tracking
we're doing that has low overhead at run
time for for queries as the access data
but then now periodically there'll be a
background thread that picks up and
looks at all this log information from
the different threads and then compute
some histograms to to figure out the
access frequencies of individual tuples
so this one is cooperative because all
the threads are sort of helping along
maintaining the metadata this one is is
this separate background thread to go
ahead and combine this information
together all right so the next thing to
do is have basically how to recognize
when the database system is
is running out of memory so a simple
approach is just to have a administrator
defined threshold that says when my
database systems a total memory usage
gets to be about 80% or 90% of the
amount of memory that's allocated to my
database system then I'll fire off my
eviction my fiction policy and go ahead
and start shoving things out the disk
right again in this case the data center
is responsible for removing this data
because there's nothing else that can
control this that's us managing our
memory and therefore we have to do this
we can't rely on the operating system
typically in database system I mean for
everyday pieces of meat whether it's in
memory or not the administrator the data
system has to be told by a human how
much memory they're allowed to use again
whether it's the buffer pool size for
disk warning system or just in memory
size of the heaps for a in-memory
database system it's sent again today
someone has to tell us how much memory
were allowed to use so we DS then set a
threshold and say when I forget to 85%
of that threshold that total upper bound
then I start a victim the other approach
is to do this on demand and this is
where if the database system recognizes
that it doesn't have any more memory to
bring in a new piece of data from disk
that it needs then it runs its
replacement policy which I'll talk about
in a second but I think it is LRU to
identify which pages are no longer
needed or unlikely to be be used in the
future and we can go ahead and shove
them out the disk then reclaim that
space for the new piece of data that we
want to bring in so in you could use LRU
or clock to approximate LRU lean store
uses an approximation of clock which
they call second chance and we'll see
what that looks like in a second all
right so now assuming that we have a way
to fire off the eviction to move data
out to disk we have a way to identify
what our cold data is and we need to
move out to disk now the question we
have to deal with is when it's been
written to disk what do we still
maintain and
to keep track of this data actually
there used to be two placenta that used
to be dated here in memory but if no
longer is and here's where to go find it
so the first approach is to use
tombstones and this is where we will
have a marker or our special kind of
tuple that we have in our table that
says this tuple you're looking for at
this address does not exist but here's
where to go find it here's the block ID
and all set in that block to go get the
data that you're looking for and anytime
that you see you know if you follow a
pointer doing a scan and come across
this tombstone pointer or tombstone a
tuple you could then say all right well
let me go talk to the cold data storage
layer and say go get this data that I'm
looking for so if you Victor tuple that
has showed us a disk and you replaced
with the tombstone then you have to go
update the index now for any or all any
index for that table that's pointing to
the old evicted tuple to now point to
the tombstone tuple writing in that way
there's no false negatives your data is
always there your data is always
identifiable the next approach is to use
bloom filters and this is where you
evict all the data out the disk Victo
clean of tuples at the disk but instead
of maintaining a tombstone
/ - puppets of dictum you just have of
this bloom filter
yeah an approximate data structure that
a set membership that says whether or
not there could exist they tuple for a
given key out on the cold data storage
and so what happens is I if I'm looking
for a particular key on a table I check
the real Mme index if it says is there
then I that's gonna have a pointer to
the real tuple so I'm done in memory if
it says not there then I go check this
bloom filter and if it says it's not
there that I know doesn't exist at all
because a bloom filter would never give
you false puppet false negatives could
give you false positives if it does say
the key exists and it's out and cold
data storage then I go fetch this on
disk index that I bring into memory and
then I find the real location on disk
for the two but I'm looking for
again I'll explain playing these two in
the next slide
the other two approaches are to do
either database system manage memory or
OS manage memory or virtual memory and
the for this one that's the database
system is going to keep track of on a
pad at a page level whether the page
actually exists in the memory or not or
the block level same kind of thing so I
can't tell you whether an image or tuple
exists but if I know that it would exist
in this block and that block have been
written to disk then I know the two
blood i1 is on disk so with OS virtual
memory it's gonna work in the same way
it's just in this case the OS is gonna
track what's in memory are you know what
did memory versus what's on disk and
this is the data systems gonna track it
so we're gonna focus on these two
because these are gonna be the you know
these are using like the fine grain to
pontification approach that we've talked
about we will discuss how to do this one
with least or and Umbra and then we will
see a technique from epfl of doing this
this OS managed memory and I'm using
ball TB and a few more slides well so
recover all of these but I'm gonna first
discuss and show you explicit examples
of these two here alright so again this
is our same setup we had before Mme
index in memory table heap and cold data
storage so again assuming we have some
way to look at how our tuples are being
accessed and we can computer histogram
that says here's the access frequency of
every single individual tuple we can use
this information to identify that these
three tuples here have been are the
least likely to be accessed again
because they didn't access the least
often in my last my you know the last
time I did this check so I'm gonna go
ahead and write those out to my cold
data storage so now in the the indexes
are still pointing to these old oh look
locations here so now what will happen
is if I go and use tombstones then I
will I will have a marker for every
single tuple that I removed with and
have a corresponding to new tuple that's
going to have the block ID and the
offset of where they exist on dead
so now and then I update my MMA index to
now instead of pointing with the old
locations and the table heap they now
point to the the tombstone tuples so if
a query comes along and looks up you
know key XYZ they follow the index and
get one of these pointers I check a flag
that says you're looking at a tombstone
pointer tombstone a tuple pointer or
sorry you're looking at a tombstone
tuple not amount of data to pool and
therefore I know that the my block ID
and offset will tell me where to go
fetch the data that I'm looking for own
desk in this example here I'm showing
the the the tombstone tuple is being
stored in the same data table as the as
the as the regular in-memory tuples in
actuality though you want to store these
as separate separate data tables we'd
have 1 / / you know regular table
because the schemas gonna be different
right in the in the red regular table
you know the the the the tuples can have
any arbitrary number of columns as
defined by the schema when you created
the table in the case of the tombstone
tuples these are gonna be stored these
are only stored storing two 32-bit
values the block ID and the offset
number so I wouldn't actually want to
store these in the same table he because
if I allocate the total amount of space
I would normally have for a regular
tuple for tomb certain people then I get
no benefit from this and I'm just
wasting space so all right so for that
reason that it's stored separately and
the reason why you want to have a
separate tombstone table per data table
instead of one giant tombstone table for
all tables in your database is because
when I do a sequential scan meaning I'm
not going through an index I'm just
scanning through one by one through
continues reaches the memory for my
table after I'm done scanning the
regular table heap the end memory tuples
then I need you started doing scans on
the tombstone tuples now I can't do any
predicate evaluations on on the
tombstones because there's no data in
there all the data is out here on disk
but there are some queries I could
potentially do like count queries where
I could I could you know just count the
number tuples that exist in the entire
table I could apply them on I can run
that kind of query on this and still
have the correct
the mountain without having to go down
or now if I'm also maintaining the a
memory zone map from what the values
actually exist in here and recording
that for a block of tombs from tubal's
I could then still do a scan on there
and be able to compute some answers for
some queries but anytime I need to
actually know what the exact value for
one individual tuple is for one give an
attribute within a tuple then I got to
go out the disk and get it another
optimization you can do with this but we
actually never implemented this in an H
store is that even though this is
Outland disk you could still maybe use
the index as a covering index like if I
know all the ash words that I need to
answer my query can be found in this
index I don't even have to go follow the
the pointers ago can get the data on
disk the index has everything I need
another thing we thought about we never
actually did would be say I have indexes
that for a table that have all the
attributes for my my table like I have
three attributes and there's an index
there's a separate index on each of
those three attributes so now my query
comes along does a lookup on one of
those attributes I would follow along
and then what this tombstone tuple here
but then rather than going up the disk
and getting it I can maybe do a reverse
search in my index and go find the
corresponding key that matches to my
value basically need to scan along the
leaf nodes like this and that actually
might end up being cheaper than having
to go fetch you know some block from
disk and bring it into memory because
this more than just the disk i/o I got
to go bring it into memory and
potentially update indexes as well so
one idea would be if I have enough if I
don't have a single index that could
cover my query but the combination of
them the intersection of them would it
might be cheaper to go back and do you
know do you leave no scans or depending
what data structure I'm using to find
the find all the values finding for the
matching matches for my given tombstone
but we never actually implanted
implemented that all right so the next
one is the the bloom filter approach and
so again the idea here is that we have a
bloom filter for every single index we
have in memory and then add on disk
for the ever every single for every
single block or comment a set of blocks
will have an on disk index just another
B+ treaty that we can use to identify
for the given key that we're looking for
where do we go find it the idea here is
that we want to reduce the size of this
index because in the tombstone case I
would still have all the keys for two
four tuples I've been evicted but with
the bloom filter any key that's been a
victor and the tuba that's been evicted
we removed those keys from the index and
now the index gets reduced in size so if
a query comes along that says does key X
exist
I always check the in memory index first
if it says it's there they don't have a
pointer to the tuple and I'm done if it
says it doesn't exist then I consult its
bloom filter and then again the same
thing the blue input says it doesn't
exist I'm done if it says it does exist
then I go to a lookup on the in memory
and the on disk index and that'll tell
me now where the location is the block
ID and the all set of where the tuple
that is that I'm looking for and then
I'd sort of have a copy back in okay so
now you depending on whether we're using
the tombstones or the bloom filter
approach or a West managed memory or
database system managed memory we now
got to bring bring our data back in so
then we can then have record a run on it
so the question you have to do is what
do we do with the tuples that we brought
in because again in an OTP environment
it's very likely that the for a given
block of data we're only going to need a
subset of the tuples for our query that
are in that block so do we do with all
that all the other ones so the first
choice is that we're just going to merge
all those tuples we find in the blog via
fetch from disk back into our table heap
but regardless of whether they're needed
or not and so what does that mean in the
case the bloom filter kate and bloom put
their arrangement or the the tubes are
tuples now we got to go update the
indexes to now point now to the tuples
we just merged in so if I needed one to
boil my block and my block has a million
tuples now I have to do a million
updates to my
next now to point to the 1 million
tuples that I just brought in and the
downside of this is that it's very
likely that tuples we just brought
brought in are gonna be evicted again so
we sort of have this ping-pong you're
thrashing effect where we're merging
data back and front index on our indexes
and back into our table heap from from
disk into memory and then we run our
diction algorithm and then they get
shoved out to disk right away because
they're cold all over again the other
approach is to only merge back the the
tuples that we need within the block and
so in this case here we identified just
what's the minimum amount we need we
bring that much our table heat we update
those indexes but now we have this
problem of the the disk page of the cold
data if we don't record that we have
evicted that data sorry then we move
that data back into memory and therefore
the the tuple shouldn't be existing on
that block anymore we could write out
the new block without that tuple in it
but that would be expensive because now
for every single read just to go access
a tuple I got to do one disk IO to read
it in I pull it out merge it back to the
table Eve and then another disk IO to
write it out and say the tuple doesn't
exist anymore so you have to maintain
some of there's some bookkeeping to keep
track of these holes and you probably
want to record them in a log rather than
in the in the addictive block itself and
then there's some background process you
could run to do compaction or coalescing
to combine a bunch of blocks that bunch
of holes together into a single block
the reason why you keep track of these
holes is because what would happen is if
I fetch a block get a tuple back have
merchantable back in and then now that
first block shouldn't have that tuple
but it's still physically there just but
I haven't recorded that it shouldn't be
there if that tuple get the victim again
now gets written to another block I
could have the same tuple duplicated
multiple times in the separate cold data
blocks and if I crash and come back and
now I don't know which one is actually
the the right one I should be I should
be merging in a bunch amount of work I
have to do in the recovery side to deal
with that
the right the second last issue is is
what is the threshold we're going to use
to determine whether to merge something
in a merger tuple back in so again with
least or we don't really have this issue
because everything is controlled by
pages that we can swap in and out of the
desk this is most thing and when you're
doing this is just neat if when you're
doing the fine-grained tuple based
identification and eviction so the
easiest proach is what I said before is
just always merge it whatever tuples I
decide I want to merge I'm just gonna
always put them back in the table heap
and update the indexes the next approach
is to only merge them when there's an
update this means is that if my query
just wants to read a tuple I will go
fetch the block that it met at once but
put it in a temporary buffer allow the
query to read it and then immediately
discard the buffer writes in this way I
don't want the updating in any indexes
if it is updated then I if the queries
trying to do an update then I'll go
ahead and merge it first then allow them
to do the update and then the last one
is that we can be a bit clever and
actually maintain the access frequency
of of evicted blocks but essentially how
often that be you know are they being
retrieved and if my access frequency
goes above some threshold then I've
decided that within my current time
window this block is being accessed all
the time so it's probably good idea for
me to keep this around so it's sort of
like in the same way we would keep track
of how two poles are being accessed our
pages are being accessed well 10 memory
we also can maintain information that
says how often a page is being accessed
you know from disk alright so the last
one I want to talk about is what do we
do with the query or transaction that
accessed cold data you know with how
should we respond to it so the easiest
thing to do is just abort the
transaction abort the query and restart
it and the idea here is that we go to
access a tuple that's not in memory we
record what tuple they wanted or what
data they actually wanted
and men we abort it a sever background
thread then kicks off and fetches the
data that they need that he wanted and
then merges it based on the policy that
we just talked about and when the data
is actually available we have a way of
either restarting the transaction like
if it's running as a store by seizure on
the server side
or we could potentially notify the
client said hey the data you want is
actually now available the that last one
nobody actually nobody actually supports
this right so it's basically you abort
the transaction and can send back an
exception over ODBC or JDBC and give a
error code to say the data you want
something memory please retry there's
similar once or deadlocks and things
like that so it's not unfeasible that
you couldn't do this but no system
actually does this explicitly for for
evicted data an in-memory database
system so the tricky thing what this is
going to be is that if I have a
transaction or a query that wants to run
with a strong isolation level like snaps
isolation or serialize legislation I had
to have multi-version concurrency tried
to use I can have multi versioning in
order to allow a transaction to get
restarted multiple times or sort of
paused and restarted and at least have a
consistent snapshot of the database so
with this one it's not really your
aborting you yes your aborting and
restarting it but when you come back the
second time your transaction ID was will
be still be the same and the idea here
is that this allows you again you have a
consistent snapshot of the table or
whatever you're trying to access even
though you may be running it at
different different invocations of the
query so the way to think about this is
say I have a query that wants to scan
the entire team but only half the table
can exist in memory at a given time what
would happen is what this approach is I
would query would start it was begin
scanning and get through the first half
of the table and then imma try to access
the next half
and then it would it would it would hit
up either a tombstone tuple or somehow
identify that the tuple that once is not
there then there's a it gets aborted the
background thread fetches the the
remaining data that actually needs by
victim the the first half of the table
and then my transaction of query can get
restarted but if I'm restarting from the
beginning then I'm gonna hit the same
issue where I the first thing I need to
go fetch is not memory and not to go
aboard it and now the first half gets
paid in the second half gets written out
I never can actually complete or at the
run with a consistent snapshot where
transactions could be updating the the
second half
while my waiting for a transaction get
me started or if I have a kiss isn't a
snapshot then I just should essentially
pause garbage garbage collection while I
go flush out the first half bring him
the second half and I come back and I
still have a consistent view or
consistent snapshot of the table as I
said nobody actually does this one that
I'm aware of you know for this reason
because it makes it tricky to guarantee
consistency the more common approach is
to do synchronous retrieval and the idea
here is that it's essentially what a
disk or native database does now when I
try to access something that's not in
memory my transaction gets pause or
stalled while another thread or my the
the disk controller or why that's a disk
manager it fetches the data that I need
and brings it into memory and once it's
in the memory then I'm allowed to
proceed and start running so there's
some games you can play with some of
these like I could try to let a query
keep running for long as it can
accessing evicted data and I just would
have to do like a Jedi mind trick that
says oh I want to read this tuple and
you pretend that it could actually read
it some queries can do this some other
queries can't and there's only when they
actually try to return results to the
application or do something with the
individual attributes on the evicted
data then you go ahead and pause it or
abort it the idea here is that you can
kind of let the query
as long as possible identify all the the
two poles are all the pages is gonna
access and then at some point you say
alright well I've seen enough let me go
fetch the big batch of things that you
need and so that way you're not like
this run stall run stall over and over
again you can maybe do a bunch of
sequential i/o fetch it all in and then
and let it run more quickly alright so
now I want to go through a bunch of
different implementations of systems
that support larger than memory
databases and the way this is gonna be
organized is that the first four here
we're all gonna be using the the sort of
fine-grain tuple based approach that we
talked about before we talked about so
far and then the these three million
systems are actually going to be page
based and at the high level they're all
going to achieve the same goal that we
can have a new memory database system
that can maintain and store databases
that are larger than the amount of
memory that's available to the system
without having to do any rewriting of
the application to some extent and the
spoiler that I'll say is that the the
page based approaches in particular from
lean store and Umbra I think are the
right way to go and these two base ones
are a little bit too fine grain and the
sort of stores and computational
overhead you pay or the pen or you pay
from being a little support this I think
is it's not worth it so again we'll go
through each of these one by one but I
think the leaves for umber one is is
probably the right way to go so as I
said before the the paper of all the
different implementation issues or
design decisions was based on a system
that I helped build when I was in grad
school called eight store that was then
commercialized as volt EP and over an
early prototype of of a store that
supported ready data out the disk was
this component we call it an T caching
and again the idea is like it's a
reverse of a cache instead of fetching
hot data from disk and pulling into
memory we push cold data out from from
memory onto disk so given all the
different design decisions we talked
a store here is gonna be doing online
identification it's gonna maintain an
LRU chain in the header every single
tuple we do sampling to make sure that
we're not updating it every single time
our transaction runs to avoid too much
overhead but it's still in 64 bits for
every single tuple it's gonna have
administrator defined threshold to
identify that the data that you need
when you're running out of space and go
ahead and kick off the eviction policy
we're going to use tombstone tuples
we're gonna do the board and restart
approach which we can do because all
transactions in an H store gonna run
have to run as store procedures it's
gonna do block level granularity of
merging and data and then in the
original implementation it would always
merge them right the original
implication couldn't decide oh this is
the data this data is being updated so
let me go ahead and emerge that just
that piece or have it the side buffer it
just always grab it over the block was
updated all the indexes that merge it in
so needless to say that this had a you
know quite a bit overhead to support
this the other sort of major
implementation around this time that
that supported larger than databases
came out of it was part of the the
Hecate on project again Hecate on was
the a memory storage or execution engine
that Microsoft build for sequel server I
think now and they're just called in
memory tables but the search hackaton
then it shows up so this was a side
project or a research project called
project Siberia that was again looking
at how to extend Hecate on to support
databases that exceed the amount of
memory that's available so the main
thing about this one was this is what
we're the bloom filter stuff that we
talked about came from and the idea is
that you do the offline identification
the same threshold as aged or with it
that's defined by the administrator well
we'll remove values or keys from evicted
tuples from the meat from the Mme
indexes but then update or maintain a
bloom filter to keep track of whether
the key actually could exist out on disk
and then when transactions try to access
that cold data we would actually pause
them or stall them and then go fetch it
and bring it in and they were always
doing this merging a tuple level
granularity and
like in a store they would always merge
everything so the best my knowledge all
the Siberia stuff from Microsoft never
actually made it to production never
actually made it into the real hackathon
system and I think a part of this was
just sort of the the engineering
complexity of sir maintaining the cold
data plus the hot data and the sort of
inconsistent performance you could get
from you know as sometimes your tuples
are in memories from them sometimes
they're not and you don't really know
that until you act upon them so for
these reasons I Hecate on never actually
got this this functionality and likewise
I don't think both TV ever got the the
antique ash and stuff that we were doing
at age 2 either another interesting
system is came from epfl and this was
developed by a Natasa alum aki and her
group in Switzerland the tossa used to
be the the database professor at CMU
before I showed up and she actually
taught the earlier versions of 7:21 13
years ago so what are they going to do
so they're gonna do offline
identification the same with that that
Siberia did but now they're gonna have
the OS manage memory and make decisions
of how to evict things out the disk but
they're gonna be clever about this
they're only gonna let the OS evict sort
of sort of the portions of the table
heap and they'll have a hot portion that
they maintain but that never gets
written out to disk and then we're gonna
move data to the cold cold portion of
the heap and let the OS patient's out as
needed so because it's doing it's using
em map and the assumed virtual memory
the OS is swapping things out it's gonna
do synchronous retrieval because the the
Dadaism doesn't know actually what's in
memory versus not remembering it's a new
page level granularity because that's
how that works and they're always gonna
merge things because again that's good
well the rest of the system doesn't know
that tuple has been evicted
he still has a pointer to the the cold
portion of the heap and then when it
goes try to access to then it gets then
it gets there's a page fault and it's
swapped him right so this is the key
part
that's different then then what we seen
before so let's see how this works so
here's our a memory table here's our
cold storage again this is being meant
this is just swap space that's being
managed by the operating system so the
good news is they're gonna divide the
memory heap into hot tuples and code
tuples and for the hot portion of the
heap they're gonna use em lock to pin
these pages in memory and this is the M
lock prevents the OS from from writing
this data out of the disk but the cold
tuple portion that's not locked or not
pinned so now that the operators can can
and any anytime decide to evict this
data out so let's say now we have this
offline identification that that the
database system is going to run
identifies that this data this tuple
here is cold so what we're gonna do is
copy it now into the cold tuple is
essentially a delete followed by an
insert like an internal transaction does
that delete an followed by an insert and
this will automatically update the index
is now to point to the new location for
this the physical location of this tuple
and then we can put whatever new data we
want here at some later point at the OS
decides that it's running out of memory
it can decide that go ahead and swap any
of the pages that are in the cold tuple
region but we have no way to determining
is this data in memory or not other than
asking the operating system I would
which would be a Cisco which are usually
a bad idea so the tricky thing we have
to make sure of course and is we want to
make sure that all our tuples are page
aligned because we don't have the issue
where the tube will may may be split
across multiple multiple pages and now
things are gonna be tricky to make sure
that we write out these pages in the
correct order to make sure that we don't
see one without the other right we won't
sort of do this at Tom okay which is not
something operating system can can
provide for us because and MF cannot be
atomic across multiple pages which now
means that we have to maintain a log
somewhere to keep track of what's
happening over here so so I think this
is an interesting idea because it's it's
using a map and a clever way for data
that is read mostly but to handle the
case for this
when there's updates you need a log to
keep track of what's happening here
all right the last tuple based approach
I want to talk about comes from Apache
geode so Apache geode was originally
this data system Ameri data system
called called gem fire long story short
gem fire was developed with another
company called gemstone and then pivotal
bought them excuse me and then VMware
bought them but then VMware decided they
didn't want to own database companies so
then they divested it and combined it
with AMC's greenplum and that became
pivotal and then I guess pivotal decided
they didn't want to you know sort of
actively maintain a gem fire or whatever
so then they dumped it off to the Apache
foundation so it's Apache geo so what
are they doing it's online
identification like an H door Dumanis
traitor defined threshold just like
before as far as I know they're using
tombstones to identify that tuples have
been removed from memory and now they
actually reside on HDFS but this is all
assuming that you run on HDFS they'll do
synchronous retrieval because the block
queries and bringing things in they'll
do it at a two-base granularity but the
interesting thing is that they're only
going to merge tuples and bring them
back into memory and discard the disk
based blocks whenever you do updates and
the reason why they do this is because
HDFS is append-only so it would be to be
kind of a pain for them to do in place
updates to a block that already exists
you'd have to either write a log message
from say this old block has been evicted
sorry it has been pulled back into
memory and it's no longer considered
sort of valid or up-to-date I you so in
their world to avoid that big penalty
and then also running things out to
dictator on they'd his update a log
message to say yes this thing's been
removed but they only want to do it on
on an update so as far as I know I mean
I'm sure people are using this but I
have not come across anybody in the wild
that has been using these these overflow
tables and apache geode
okay so now as I start alluded to so far
everything we've talked about at least
in the a store packet on volt EB and
Apache geode examples these are all
doing evictions based on a per tubule
basis right it means we have to keep
track of individual tuples how they're
being read how they're being updated and
then we make decisions about how to how
to evict them you know we're making
those decisions on a per pupil basis to
combine them into a page or block and
write them out to disk but with the
exception of a project Siberia all of
these wouldn't actually reduce the size
of indexes and furthermore none of them
can actually spill the index or write
portions of the index out the disk so
only project Siberia would pull the end
keys out of the index of reduce the size
of the index and then populate with the
bloom filter which is gonna be much
smaller than the than the had the keys
would have been if they existed in the
index but other than that they can't
identify oh well this portion of the
index of my index is there they're not
being updated or access very often so
let me go ahead and show up those things
out to disk and as we saw when we talked
about compression I showed at the end
when we talked about how to do index
compression for some Ultima databases
the size of the indexes can be quite
significant relative to the overall
overall size of the database right and
some examples who solved the indexes
were up to 60% of the total memory size
of a database so all the things we're
doing here are not actually targeting
for those applications are for those
databases what the bulk of the memory is
actually being used for so what we
really want is a unified approach and
unified model for evicting cold data out
the disk from either table or from
either indexes right we shouldn't have
to have seven policies a separate you
know separate mechanisms or both of
these it should just be a single
approach used across both types of data
so this is how we ended up with the the
paper I had you guys read on on leans to
and so lien store is a was a prototype
in memory storage manager that was
developed by the Germans Munich that
worked on the hyper system but to the
best of my knowledge this wasn't
actually part of the hyper project this
was a this is a standalone separate
thing and so it's really cool about lean
strong can do is again it's designed
from the ground up to evict pages and it
doesn't know and doesn't care whether
the pages belong to two parts for data
tables or they belong to indexes so the
way to think about what they're doing is
that lean store is provides a
decentralized buffer pool manager that
is based on a page hierarchy meaning
instead of having instead of having just
sort of like a regular page table just
an unordered list of pages it's going to
be organized as a tree structure the
idea is going to be that you can't evict
a the main idea is that you can't evict
a child page so you can Victorino its
child pages have been evicted to disk
either and then also now because they
are page based the overhead of tracking
how pages are access is gonna be much
less than having to do it on a on a per
pupil basis and in the other systems we
talked about here so but now the way
that you can view tracking is
interesting because they're actually not
going to track at all most of the time
and so the way they're going to decide
what to evict is that there's gonna
randomly select some pages and then if a
page is selected then they start
tracking whether how it's being accessed
or whether it's being accessed and then
at some point when we need to free up
space we go look at that tracking
information from the rim the last round
of randomly select the pages and we find
the ones that haven't been touched
Jordan been accessed let me go ahead and
Vic those right so you only turn on the
tracking identification the page is
notification when you randomly select a
page to be evicted so we'll go through
all these these policies in more detail
but the key thing they're gonna do
instead of using the tombstone instead
of using the bloom filter the key thing
they're gonna do to figure out whether a
block or page exists in memory is
through a technique called pointers
whistling so I don't think we've covered
points whizzing that much in the intro
class but so I'm gonna cover that now in
the advanced class
the idea of pointers whistling is that
we are going to switch the or sort of
flip the contents of a pointer that one
object has to another object based on
whether we know that whether that that
object that is being pointed to is in
memory or not so again the idea is that
and so to figure this out we only need
to use one bit in the pointer so we'll
use the first bit to say one that it's
that it's on disk zero if it's in memory
and then the rest of the 63 bits and our
64-bit pointers will actually be used
for the address that's actually not
entirely true either because on x86 the
current architecture only uses 48 bits
of a 64-bit address to define the memory
location of something in memory all
right so they can only actually store up
to 35 terabytes of memory Intel claims
they're eventually gonna use the whole
64 bits I was at a talk that Intel gave
three or four years ago where they said
hey don't store anything extra in the
remaining 16 bits of your pointers
because eventually Intel's gonna use it
but like I said that that hasn't
happened yet and as far as I know it's
still just 48 bits so you can use the
upper 16 bits to do whatever you want so
they say we have here we have two blocks
and block b1 has a pointer to block b2
so when the pointer is unsold meaning
it's pointing to something on disk then
the bit will be set that where the first
bit will be set the one saying that it's
on a Swizzle and then the then we'll
just have our page ID and offset like 32
bit page ID 32-bit offset but now if we
go invisibly 64 bits in total and now if
we go actually
Swizzle that address because we brought
in the block into memory will flip that
first bit to zero saying that what
you're looking at is a real in memory
address not a page ID and offset and
then the remaining bits would be used to
actually point to the memory location so
what happened is when you when you pass
a memory address you know in your
program to say go access the thing for
me to do a load you know this thing's
not used because this it's not part of
the 48 bits that the x86 cares about so
it is just ignored so we don't think we
do anything special when we do a memory
you just look up using these Quizlet
addresses the the harbor just takes care
of it for us right so the reason why you
want to do this is because this is gonna
allow us to have a decentralized way to
track whether a page is in memory or not
right this is what a page table would do
in a disk based system I be this this
giant map that says page ID 1 2 3 is is
in disk or owned a score in memory and
if it's in memory here's the address to
it the or the mapping table in the B+
tree or the B Doubletree was essentially
the same thing so rather than having a
centralized data structure if we ensure
that in our in our database system that
only one block will have a pointer to
another block then we know that there's
only one location where there's this
pointer to this other block so we just
can do a compare and swap on this to be
able to flip it to be Swizzle run
Swizzle because we don't have to worry
about trying to do atomic updates across
multiple pointers and so if we think now
in like a B+ tree I'd know if you ignore
it 7 pointers you're essentially gonna
get this for free because that's you
know it's a it's an acyclic graph I said
in others do you think interesting about
lynnster was again the eviction policy
was it maintaining LRU wasn't doing a
clock it was just randomly picking some
some blocks for eviction and then
figuring out whether they are gonna
actually be accessed so what's great
about this is that you don't have to
maintain any metadata as we did in in
the other approaches for hot data
because if it's hot then you don't track
any information but if it's if it's
potentially cold then you go ahead and
track this information so
what will happen is that I fixed them
some blocks I select some blocks to be
evicted and then I'm gonna maintain this
global hash table that's going to keep
track of of the tracking info how this
blocker is being accessed and then if I
if I determine that when it's time to go
free some memory I go check that that
that hash table and I see here's some
some blocks that haven't been accessed
then I know it's heading it's safe for
me to go ahead and evict them so again
what will happen is I randomly pick some
blocks I'm gonna unsmooth all their
pointers meaning it'll revert back to
the page ID and offset but the I'm not
actually going to evict the block still
gonna sit in memory and then what will
happen is if now a thread comes along or
query runs and if it comes across a
unsold pointer with the page ID and
offset I go check that global hash table
for the data and my cooling stage and if
it's in there then I know it's actually
still in memory and I go find out where
it is if it's not in there then I know
it actually is not remembering at all
and I go out to disk and get it and will
show an example what this looks like in
a second so the last thing that's
important about lean stores that is
again the block hierarchy again the
there's no centralized buffer pool table
so we need a way to and ensure that
there isn't more than one pointer to a
to a block in the database so that I can
just unlock a chanel that I or
switzerland's was the one location I
know that that's been covered everywhere
so they can organize this as a tree
hierarchy and so every parent can have a
pointer to a child and that parent is
the only one with that pointer to that
given block now so in indexes they're
already sort of managed like this if you
can or something pointers again for
table heaps you have to organize that as
a hierarchy and then do breadth-first
search to do scans and think in the lean
store case there was always index
organized tables and in the case of I'm
brother they're gonna do the same thing
so why do you want to do this well again
because I know that
if I want to Victor parent I can't evict
it to disk unless it children have been
evicted and this prevents me from having
the situation where I evict a parent but
it's children aren't still in memory
that parent gets written out the disc
and then now when it gets fetched back
in its gonna have you know when it was
written out it would have in memory
pointers to the children where they
existed before in memory but now I'm
gonna come back those memory dresses now
B might be pointing to frames my buffer
pool that now have different pages than
that will over in there before and so
now I'm pointing to garbage they're not
pointing they're things I should be
looking or should be pointing at
so by ensuring that the children
Victor's out first the children get
evicted I update the parent now to have
to unscrew so pointers to his children
so that when it gets written out to disk
and I bring it back in I can then use
those unsocial pointers to find the
pages that have the tools I'm looking
for so just in the same way I can't
fetch
I can't evict a parent before it's
children have been evicted
I can't fetch children until its parent
has been fetch which you would you
guarantee because everything is in this
tree hierarchy all right so let's look
an example so the way we're gonna
organize this again say we have a really
simple database that only has four pages
and so we're gonna break the the
hierarchy up into three stages so we
have the hot stage where everything is
in memory and you have a Swizzle
pointers then you have the cooling stage
where it still is this in memory but
you're gonna have unsocial pointers and
then you have the cold stage where it's
out on disk with unsocial pointers so
let's say that I run my eviction
algorithm that randomly picked some
blocks to be written out to disk and
let's say I pick b1 so I'm gonna move it
down now into the cooling stage and then
I'm going to add it into my hash table
over here that that's tracking again the
access patterns or how often this block
egg is being accessed
so this hash table is basically saying
for b1 here's where to go find it in
this in this eviction queue and then the
eviction queue would have the the actual
memory pointer to two-thirds block so
now what
happen is that if if and then of course
then I have to make sure I update the or
on so as the pointer from my parent
block again now if anybody comes along
and tries to access b1 they would have
to go through b0 that's in memory then
they would get this on swizzle pointer
but then I would always do a lookup in
my hash table and I would find ng for b1
find the location in the eviction queue
and that would give me the real memory
address so now you're paying a bit of
penalty now just as you would having an
indirection layer and a page table in a
disc or in a database system but it's
actually not that bad because again if
this was hot data then the first time
this would happen I would then bump it
back up to the hot stage remove it from
my eviction queue and then dispose of
the pointer and so only one query would
ever pay this penalty but if it actually
really was cold then nobody would
actually come across this I have to go
through this hash table and eventually
get around the disk and you know no harm
no foul so this is actually really
interesting right and the idea is also
to that this eviction cue is keeping
track of this is essentially is
naturally ordering the you know which
was what were the latest the oldest or
newest paid blocks attitude the queue so
now if I need to go fetch something
that's on the cold stage on disk and
bring it into memory I just go evict
whatever it is into the front of the
queue here shove it at the disk and then
use that space for the tuple or the
block that I'm that I need so there's
only one one latch you need in this
parka texture and that's when you
actually write things from the cooling
stage to the cold stage because they
just need to protect to make sure that
if you try to evict a page or victim
block the same time you're trying to
fetch that block back in you don't want
to have duplicates in it and get gif
fouled up so there's only one latch your
third use to protect for that concurrent
operation but that's pretty rare so like
I said this was a prototype system that
was developed by the Germans I think
they're continuing to work on it it's
separate from hyper and it's separate
from the from the Alma project which
we'll talk about next
right so Umbra is a a very new system
that the Germans have been building
think of this is like hyper 2.0 and they
are actually supporting the larger the
memory database that's a technique that
that lean store propose of having this
hierarchy with a randomized the
randomized eviction album but one of the
interesting things that there knew
differently is that they're going to
support variable sized pages so in the
case of a lean store and actually of all
that the architectures we shown before
the pages that were being organized in
memory the pages are getting written on
to disk we're always the same size in
Umbra what they're gonna do is they're
gonna they're gonna allow you to
allocate memory in the same way you
would in a slab allocator like and like
je malloc where you can allocate blocks
that are to be of different sizes
they're always exponential from the
previous size and then now you can then
address the entire block of a given size
rather than you know individual tuples
or individual offsets within within a
block and so the the advantage you're
gonna get for this is that for databases
that have large text fields or strings
or varchars or other internal data
structures like compression dictionaries
where you often can't store them in a
single page you can now avoid overhead
about having to copy those pages in
memory and reassemble them whenever you
go fetch things from disk so the number
people the Germans make actually a
really interesting design argument for
this system and they say that it's
better we want to support larger than
memory databases it's better just to
have a complex buffer pool manager like
in the case of a supporting a
variable-length one it's better to make
that be efficient have that be sort of a
more complex or difficult to engineer
component of the system because you only
have to implement that part once and now
the rest of the system that's going to
end up being easier to develop because
now you have this this flexibility in
this capability
the variable size buffle manager and
it's sort of what we said in the
beginning about how if you you don't
want to bring back the Buffalo manager
and then have to re-architect the entire
system to account for the fact that you
could be accessing data that's not on
disk in this same way here you can not
have to worry about your packing data in
all ways exactly into a page that you're
a fixed page size you can allocate the
right amount of memory that's needed for
whatever it is that you're doing and the
the algorithms of the data structures
are building on top of that that the
Buffalo manager don't have to worry
about the complexity of how that's all
managed so I think that's actually
really interesting and - that's my model
and knowledge this is the only data
system that's actually doing this which
is pretty exciting so just like in lean
store they're gonna store things as
hierarchy but all the tables are gonna
be all the relations are sorted index
organized table so basically all the
it's sort of like intimacy goes in a DB
where all the tuples are stored in the
leaf pages of a B+ tree so you get that
natural hierarchy that we needed in lean
store where every child only has there's
only one parent that has a pointer to
any one child
so this is just a high level overview of
what's going on in the various slides
buffer pool and again the way it's gonna
work is that it's like a slab allocator
will they'll have a bunch of frames in
the buffer pool for different size
classes and you'll have more frames for
the smaller size classes and fewer
frames for the larger ones because most
of the most of the chunks of memory
you're gonna allocate are gonna be quite
small so the the large size the small
side would be 64 kilobytes and that'll
go up to 512 kilobytes so the in the
buffer frames you would have just sort
of inactive and active pools everything
is gonna actually be managed using em
map use anatomize m map and that gives
you a virtual memory and so that means
that I can allocate reserve all this
space here but it's actually not backed
by physical memory until I go ahead and
access it all right so I can allocate
all the space I would need my buffer
pool frame for any for the total size
the database
but I only you know the OS actually only
gonna back it when it's actually needed
so they're also going to do pointers
whistling the same way you would in in
lean store and are in other systems but
what's interesting about it is in a lean
store case it was just if it's whistled
it's a memory dress and it's untwisted
here's the page ID in the offset in this
case here you don't have all sets
anymore in pages because you're having a
fine-grained pointer to the page that
has exactly the memory that you need you
know because it's the right size so if I
only need 64 kilobytes then I have a
pointer to those 64 kilobytes and
there's left to whoever is getting that
64 kilobytes to be able to interpret its
contents to get the data that is looking
for but I don't need to record that
offset in the unsocial pointer but I do
need to record what size classes in so
that when I go fetch that block I know
which category of the data I need to go
get it from and how big it actually is
going to be stored out some disk because
again the OS with virtual memory it
doesn't know that it's not going to
allow you to do with these memory
allocations or page allocations from
different sizes it's always going to be
whatever you know four kilobytes as the
default or you're using huge pages
whatever the two gigabyte ones it just
knows that you have some chunk of memory
so it's up for the the database system
to be able interpret you know how much
data do I actually need to read for a
given page size right and that's based
on a size class down here right so I
think this is actually they said I mean
this is really interesting this you know
this was the this paper came out only a
few months ago no other system as far as
I know actually implements this
so it's remains to be seen whether the
you know compared to something like lean
store that this is the the right
approach but I definitely it's very
promising and I think it's better than
the stuff that we were doing you know
years ago with with each store or the
project Siberia stuff and so actually
last thing to point out too is like
again these are still 64-bit pointers
the block ID is now 57 bits and then
this this size class is is just six bits
all right so the last approach I want to
talk about is mem sequel as I'm wearing
the the old school minima sequel sure so
traditionally what mem sequel you would
do is when they brought on the column
store even now today you can declare
that you want a table restore as a row
store and that resides in memory or you
can have a table exists or you declare a
table as a column store and that can
actually be backed by disk but there was
no way to declare a single logical table
that could have a but both types but
then in when they first came out with a
column store approach up up to 2017 they
were using em map to manage the pages
out to disk but they were so blinded is
using a map and you know it's not being
an anonymized memory memory virtual
memory allocation that Humber was doing
so they quickly found out this was
actually a bad idea and there's a blog
article that shows that they were sort
of abusing a map and getting bad
performance so then they built their own
buffer manager where they would take the
columns and split them up until one one
segment that had 1 million tuples and
knew how to fetch in this segments as
need him but they still had a separate
sort of separate row store for for
transactions or OTP workloads in a set
of is a separate column store for the
for analytics so what they then now
announced in 2019 is this that they call
a new single store architecture where
you it's like the hyper stuff or the
stuff we're doing in our own database
system where you can do transactions on
top of the on top of a column store
there's a this blog article makes a
bunch of claims about you know make a
sort of seem like that they're the first
to do this which is not really true and
then they have some optimizations to
deal with the large overhead of storing
nulls that we saw before in the row
stores when we talked about data types
but you know this is their sort of
getting away from having separate
different in memory roaster and sitter
separate calm store and now having a
single single columns for approach that
can you know have pages written out to
disk it's unclear how they're deciding
what pages get written out to disk I
suspect it's a basic LRU or clock
approach so now going back to our same
taxonomy to talk about four they don't
need any eviction metadata for this
could just keep me track what pages are
in and not meant memory or not memory
they're doing the singham's retrieval
and then he always has merged things
okay alright so that was a lot the as I
said the the what we talked about today
was just dealing with bringing back in
the the disk that's me block on in this
gonna be slow and trying to be clever
about it to avoid slowing down or in the
main architecture and as I said multiple
times
I think the block base or page brace
approach used in lean store Umbra is the
right way to go and the fine-grain to
pull stuff that we did in in those other
systems is is it's not the right
approach
now the other engine thing about this is
that everything I talk about here today
could eventually just all be made null
and void and and obsolete when we
actually finally achieve cheap and fast
byte addressable non-volatile memory so
that means that memory that goes in the
dim slot and then you can read and write
to it as if it's DRAM
but when you pull the power it persists
things like like like like an SSD so
that harbor actually exists we'll cover
that next week with like talking about
databases running a new hardware for now
SSDs or HBO's hard drives are all they
have for non-volatile storage but in the
future real persistent memory or real
non-volatile memory will make everything
we talked about today I think
unnecessary all right so next class
we're going to talk about sort of it
this is an additional topic that doesn't
fit exactly in with every we talked
about but it just
it's it's another way to get big
performance improvements in a database
system if you know what you're doing so
let's talk about a way to improve
performance and we'll see two approaches
from okay all right guys wash your hands
and what is this
[Music]